<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Hearings Before the Office</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter supplements the notice and hearing requirements of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Regulations issued by the Office of Administrative Hearings in <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the event of a conflict with <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>, the provisions set forth in this chapter control the conduct of a hearing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="22|06|06|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Hearings — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When Hearings Shall Be Held.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an applicant timely files a written request for a hearing, a hearing shall be held if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Board of Trustees denied the applicant a disability retirement allowance under <cite path="|22.06.05">COMAR 22.06.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The medical board rejected the disability forms submitted by a former member under <cite path="22.06.02.04">COMAR 22.06.02.04</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Disability Unit denied the disability claim of an applicant under <cite path="22.06.03.01|A.|(3)">COMAR 22.06.03.01A(3)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless the member waives the hearing in writing, a hearing shall be held if the Board of Trustees approves an application submitted by the Secretary of State Police on behalf of the member in accordance with <cite path="22.06.02.03|D.">COMAR 22.06.02.03D</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Date, Time, Place, and Notice of Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Retirement Agency shall coordinate with the applicant and the Office to schedule a hearing before a judge at the central office of the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The designation of a site for a hearing, other than the central office of the Office of Administrative Hearings, requires the Retirement Agency’s consent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Office shall issue a written hearing notice that conforms to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, within a reasonable time before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each party is required to provide every other party with a copy of any written communication with the Office or a judge, including but not limited to a request for postponement or a request for a subpoena.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Not less than 20 days prior to the hearing, each party shall provide written notification to every other party of the name and identify of each witness the party may call to testify at the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Conduct of the Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The burden of proof shall be on the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant may represent oneself at the hearing, or may be represented by an attorney who is licensed to practice law in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Official Record.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The judge shall prepare and submit to the Retirement Agency an official record of the hearing which shall include all orders, pleadings, exhibits, materials submitted in connection with any prehearing conference, other material filed in the proceeding, and any testimony transcribed according to <cite path="22|06|06|.02|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A party may request a transcript of the record of the proceedings. The cost of typewritten transcripts shall be paid by the party requesting the transcript.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Final Decision.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The judge shall prepare a summary of the testimony, comment on credibility and demeanor of the witnesses, and prepare written findings of fact and conclusions of law, and shall issue a final decision within 90 days after the completion of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The judge shall mail a copy of the decision to the parties and the Board Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Judicial Review.</heading>
    <text>A party who is aggrieved by a final decision of a judge is entitled to judicial review of the decision in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-222">State Government Article, §10-222, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Adjustment in Allowance.</heading>
    <text>The Retirement Agency shall adjust the allowance of a retiree who is subsequently granted an ordinary disability retirement or an accidental disability retirement retroactively to the effective date of retirement.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Effect of Death Before Final Decision.</heading>
    <text>If the applicant dies before the final decision on the applicant’s appeal for an ordinary disability retirement or an accidental disability retirement, or both, the claim shall terminate. Survivor benefits, if any, shall be paid in accordance with the selection made by the applicant for the retirement allowance granted and accepted before death.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-110">21-110</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|29-101">29-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|29-118">29-118</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1996 (22:26 Md. R. 2031)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective January 1, 1996, all of Title 22 was repealed and completely new regulations adopted. Codification and organization of the title were also completely changed. Consequently, the administrative histories of the revised Title 22 do not reflect regulatory activity before January 1, 1996. Refer to the old version of Title 22 or contact the Maryland State Archives for assistance.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|22|06|06|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1309)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|22|06|06|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, G amended effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-02-27"><cite path="|22|06|06|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite>, F, G amended effective February 27, 2006 (33:4 Md. R. 354)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|22|06|06|.02|H.">Regulation .02H</cite> repealed effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|22|06|06|.03">Regulation .03</cite> adopted effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|22|06|06|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|22|06|06|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
