<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>License Denial Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to all licenses the Commission is authorized to issue under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>E-05, Annotated Code of Maryland, to implement the State’s Sports Wagering Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The chapter explains the process by which a license application may be denied, and the process available to an applicant after the Commission determines that the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a sports wagering contractor or sports wagering employee license, does not meet the general requirements in <cite path="|36.10.02">COMAR 36.10.02</cite> and <cite path="|36.10.03">36.10.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a sports wagering facility, sports wagering facility operator license, mobile sports wagering license, or online sports wagering operator license, does not meet:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The general qualification requirements in <cite path="|36.10.02">COMAR 36.10.02</cite> and <cite path="|36.10.03">36.10.03</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specific license requirements; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Technical and operational standards; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Should be denied the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|07|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Sports Wagering Contractors and Sports Wagering Employees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, “application,” “applicant,” “license,” and “licensee” refer to an applicant for a sports wagering contractor or sports wagering employee license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Commission staff shall conduct the license application review and denial process in a manner consistent with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commission staff shall review a license application to determine whether it meets all the requirements of <cite path="|36.10.02">COMAR 36.10.02</cite> and <cite path="|36.10.03">36.10.03</cite> and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For an applicant for a sports wagering contractor license, the requirements in <cite path="36.10.06.04">COMAR 36.10.06.04</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For an applicant for a sports wagering employee license, the requirements in <cite path="36.10.06.05">COMAR 36.10.06.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After reviewing an application submitted for a license, staff may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue the license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recommend that the license not be issued to the applicant, and that the license application be denied.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If staff recommends denial of the license application, staff shall promptly provide the applicant with written notice of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommendation for denial;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basis for the recommendation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Applicant’s right to request a reconsideration meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An applicant may submit to the Commission a written request for a reconsideration meeting within 15 days of the date of the notice described under <cite path="36|10|07|.02|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If an applicant fails to timely submit a request under <cite path="36|10|07|.02|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the staff’s recommendation is the Commission’s final action on the license application.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|07|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Sports Wagering Facility License, Sports Wagering Facility Operator License, Mobile Sports Wagering License, or Online Sports Wagering Operator License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, “application”, “applicant”, “license”, and “licensee” refer to an applicant for a sports wagering facility, sports wagering facility operator, mobile sports wagering, or online sports wagering operator license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless the SWARC has first awarded the license, the Commission may not issue a license to an applicant for a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sports wagering facility license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Mobile sports wagering license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commission staff shall conduct the license application review and recommended denial process in a manner consistent with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After the SWARC has awarded a license to an applicant, Commission staff shall review the application and the applicant’s submissions to the Commission, and determine whether it meets all the requirements of <cite path="|36.10.02">COMAR 36.10.02</cite> and <cite path="|36.10.03">36.10.03</cite>, and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For an applicant for a sports wagering facility license, the requirements in <cite path="|36.10.04">COMAR 36.10.04</cite> that pertain to the license class;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For an applicant for a sports wagering facility operator license, the requirements in <cite path="36.10.06.03">COMAR 36.10.06.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For an applicant for a mobile sports wagering license, the requirements in <cite path="|36.10.05">COMAR 36.10.05</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For an applicant for an online sports wagering operator license, the requirements in <cite path="36.10.06.02">COMAR 36.10.06.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Staff’s review of applications for all licenses in this regulation shall include the requirements specified in the regulations for each license category, and also include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evaluating the applicant’s equipment, facility and data information center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conducting tests and controlled demonstrations,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reviewing the awardee’s operational and technical submissions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Determining whether the awardee is prepared to receive the public and to conduct safe and secure sports wagering.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Staff may not issue the license if it determines that the awardee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Does not meet the requirements in <cite path="36|10|07|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="36|10|07|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, the awardee is otherwise not prepared to conduct safe and secure sports wagering.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>After conducting the review described in §§D and E of this regulation, staff may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue the license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recommend that the Commission not issue the license, and deny the license application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If staff recommends the denial of an application under this regulation, staff shall promptly provide the applicant with written notice of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommendation for denial;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basis for the recommendation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Applicant’s right to request a reconsideration meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>An applicant may submit to the Commission a written request for a reconsideration meeting within 15 days of the date of the notice described <cite path="36|10|07|.03|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If an applicant fails to timely submit a request under <cite path="36|10|07|.03|I.">§I of this regulation</cite>, the staff’s recommendation is the Commission’s final action on the license application.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reconsideration Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Commission staff shall conduct the reconsideration process in a manner consistent with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an applicant timely submits a request under Regulation .02F or .03I of this chapter, staff shall notify the applicant of a date and time for the reconsideration meeting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A reconsideration meeting is not a hearing under <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>During a reconsideration meeting, the applicant or awardee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets with Commission staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May be represented by counsel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May present its views to staff as to why the license should be issued.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After the reconsideration meeting, the staff person who attended the reconsideration meeting shall issue a written notice to the applicant or awardee describing the result of the reconsideration meeting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the applicant or awardee is dissatisfied with the result of the reconsideration meeting, the applicant or awardee may submit a written request for a hearing to the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 15 days of the date of staff’s notice under <cite path="36|10|07|.04|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That states the applicant’s or awardee’s legal and factual bases for disagreeing with the result of the reconsideration meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the applicant or awardee fails to timely submit a written hearing request under <cite path="36|10|07|.04|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the staff’s determination is the Commission’s final action on the license application.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Hearings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a timely, written hearing request submitted under <cite path="|36|10|07|.04|F.">Regulation .04F of this chapter</cite>, the Commission shall provide the applicant a notice for a hearing held under <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Hearings Before the Commission. For any hearing under this regulation and held before the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Grant the license after determining that the applicant is qualified; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deny the license;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Commission denies the license, the Commission shall prepare an order stating its findings of fact, conclusions of law, and reasons why the denial is appropriate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall provide the applicant with written notification of the Commission’s final action on the license application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hearings Delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a hearing held under this regulation and delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings for a final action on the license pursuant to <cite path="36.01.02.06|O.">COMAR 36.01.02.06O</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The decision issued by Office of Administrative Hearings is the Commission’s final action on the license application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commission reserves the right to seek judicial review of the decision issued by Office of Administrative Hearings under <cite path="|36|10|07|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For any hearing delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings for a recommended decision under <cite path="36.01.02.06|O.">COMAR 36.01.02.06O</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Director may designate a staff member to review the recommended decision who has not been previously designated to review the license application under Regulations <cite path="|36|10|07|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|07|.04">.04</cite> of this chapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Director or the Director’s designee shall review the Administrative Law Judge’s Recommended Decision consistent with the terms of the delegation made and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provide the applicant and staff an opportunity to present exceptions under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-216">State Government Article, §10-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>After reviewing any exceptions filed by the applicant and staff, issue an order under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-220">State Government Article, §10-220, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that constitutes the Commission’s final action on the license application.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Petition for Judicial Review.</heading>
    <text>The Commission’s final action on a license application is subject to judicial review as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-01—9-1E-15, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|07|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
