<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Enforcement</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes a framework within which the Commission may take enforcement action against a licensee that results in a reprimand, penalty, or condition placed on a licensee, or a suspension or revocation of a license.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Violations.</heading>
    <text>A licensee may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Violate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A provision of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1E, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A regulation adopted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1E, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A directive of the Commission or the Director;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Take, or attempt to take, any action that is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cheating;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Influence the governing entity of a sporting event;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Influence any person or unit of government that is involved in implementing or enforcing <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1E, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Interfere with the regular operation of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A sports wagering platform or its software;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sports wagering equipment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A sports wagering website; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fail to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conform to the information contained in its license application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet a licensing requirement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Promptly submit to the Commission a change to the information contained in its license application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Adequately remedy a deficiency of which the licensee has received notice under <cite path="|36|10|08|.03">Regulation .03(B) of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintain a sports wagering employee license in good standing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notice of Violation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After receiving a report of a licensee’s alleged violation of <cite path="|36|10|08|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>, the Agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Investigate the report; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the licensee with written notice of the alleged violation, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Description of the law, regulation, condition, or directive allegedly violated: and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Staff recommendation for addressing the alleged violation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to require that the licensee receives an opportunity to meet with staff to discuss an informal settlement of a violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Agency may undertake a corrective action plan or attempt to reach a settlement with the licensee before the Director, or the Director’s designee, initiates proceedings for imposition of a sanction against a licensee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|08|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Corrective Action Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Director, or the Director’s designee, directs staff to implement a corrective action plan with a licensee, Agency staff shall give written notice to a licensee that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A description of the alleged violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the possible sanctions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The requirement for the licensee to submit a corrective action plan to the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Corrective Action Plan. A corrective action plan shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Periodic monitoring or progress reports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Timelines for completing corrective action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Implementation of measures to guard against recurrence of the alleged violation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other measures necessary to resolve the alleged violation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Time for Implementing a Corrective Action Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days of receipt of a notice under <cite path="36|10|08|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the licensee shall submit a corrective action plan to the Director, or the Director’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director, or the Director’s designee, shall review the corrective action plan and inform the licensee whether the corrective action plan is acceptable and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the corrective action plan is acceptable, the licensee shall execute it immediately; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the corrective action plan is not acceptable, the licensee shall submit a revised plan within 7 days of being notified by the Director or the Director’s designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the licensee fails to submit an acceptable corrective action plan within the time described under <cite path="36|10|08|.04|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Director, or the Director’s designee, may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide the licensee with additional time within which to submit a revised corrective action plan; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recommend the imposition of a sanction available in <cite path="|36|10|08|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> on the licensee in accordance with <cite path="|36|10|08|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Director, or the Director’s designee, provided a licensee with a notice under <cite path="36|10|08|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> and did not receive a timely written response, the Commission may adopt a recommendation made pursuant to §C(3)(b) as the final action by the Commission on the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Corrective Action Plan Outcome.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After a licensee has completed a corrective action plan, to the satisfaction of the Director or the Director’s designee, the alleged violation will be deemed resolved, except that the alleged violation may be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The basis of a subsequent corrective action plan, settlement, penalty, or sanction if a similar violation occurs; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Raised during a Commission hearing as part of the Agency’s enforcement record for the licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If at any time during the corrective action period the Director, or the Director’s designee, determines that the licensee has not made sufficient progress toward fulfilling a requirement of the corrective action plan, the Director may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For good cause, extend the time for completion of a corrective action plan; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recommend the imposition of a sanction on the licensee pursuant to <cite path="|36|10|08|.06|A.">Regulation .06A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If at the end of the corrective action period the licensee has failed to satisfactorily complete the corrective action plan, the Director, or the Director’s designee, may recommend the imposition of a sanction on the licensee under <cite path="|36|10|08|.06|A.">Regulation .06A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Settlement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may provide a licensee with the opportunity to discuss with staff a means of entering into a settlement agreement between the licensee and the Commission by which the violation is settled without a sanction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A settlement agreement:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be signed by an authorized representative of the licensee and the Director or the Director’s designee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be considered final and binding until approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a licensee violates a term of a settlement agreement, nothing in this regulation shall be construed to prevent the Commission from imposing a sanction against the licensee for violating a term of the agreement or the underlying violation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|08|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Recommended Sanction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. The Director or the Director’s designee may recommend the imposition of any sanction deemed appropriate against a licensee if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Violates a provision of <cite path="|36|10|08|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fails to timely or satisfactorily complete a corrective action plan required by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Violates a term of a settlement agreement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Engages in any conduct that exposes the State’s Sports Wagering Program to a serious and imminent risk of harm to its integrity, security, or profitability.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice of Recommended Sanction. The Director, or the Director’s designee shall provide the licensee written notice of a recommended sanction, including the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommended sanction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basis for the recommended sanction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Consequences of the recommended sanction if it becomes the Commission’s final action on the license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Licensee’s applicable hearing rights.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a licensee is dissatisfied with the recommended sanction, the applicant may submit a written request to the Commission to contest the recommended sanction:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 15 days of the date of the recommended sanction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That states the licensee’s legal and factual bases for contesting the sanction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a licensee fails to timely submit a written hearing request under <cite path="36|10|08|.06|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the recommended sanction:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Becomes final; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Constitutes the Commission’s final action on the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Emergency Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director may emergently suspend a license if the Director determines that suspension is necessary in order to protect the State’s Sports Wagering Program against a serious and imminent risk of harm to its integrity, security, or profitability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Emergency Suspension — Process. If the Director emergently suspends a license, the Director shall promptly schedule a hearing before the Commission in accordance with <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite> on the emergency suspension and provide the licensee with the written notice required under <cite path="|36|10|08|.06|A.">Regulation .06A of this chapter</cite>, along with notice directing the licensee that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee shall immediately cease performing operations under the license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with the Director’s directive to cease performing operations under the license constitutes a separate violation of <cite path="|36|10|08|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite> for which an additional sanction may be imposed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Hearings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall provide the applicant a hearing notice for a hearing held under <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a timely written hearing request submitted under <cite path="|36|10|08|.06|C.">Regulation .06C of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For hearings held under <cite path="|36|10|08|.07|B.">Regulation .07B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Hearings Before the Commission. For any hearing under this regulation held before the Commission, the Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine if the licensee is subject to sanction pursuant to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice of recommended sanction issued under <cite path="|36|10|08|.06|B.">Regulation .06B of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notice of emergency suspension issued under <cite path="|36|10|08|.07|B.">Regulation .07B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Impose the sanction the Commission deems appropriate, if the Commission determines that a licensee is subject to sanction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a sanction is imposed, prepare an order stating the Commission’s findings of fact, conclusions of law, and basis for the sanction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide the licensee with written notification of the sanction as the Commission’s final action on the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hearings Delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For any hearing held under this regulation and delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings for a final action on the license under <cite path="36.01.02.06|O.">COMAR 36.01.02.06O</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The decision issued by Office of Administrative Hearings is the Commission’s final action on the license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commission reserves the right to seek judicial review of the decision issued by Office of Administrative Hearings under <cite path="|36|10|08|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For any hearing delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings for a recommended decision under <cite path="36.01.02.06|O.">COMAR 36.01.02.06O</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Director may designate a staff member to review the recommended decision who has not reviewed the license under Regulations <cite path="|36|10|08|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|08|.06">.06</cite> of this chapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Director or the Director’s designee shall review the Administrative Law Judge’s recommended decision consistent with the terms of the delegation made and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provide the applicant and staff an opportunity to present exceptions pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-216">State Government Article §10-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>After reviewing any exceptions filed by the applicant and staff, issue an order pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-220">State Government Article §10-220, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that constitutes the Commission’s final action on the license.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Petition for Judicial Review.</heading>
    <text>The Commission’s final action on a license is subject to judicial review as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|08|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Imposition of Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Permissible Sanctions. The Commission may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Impose a penalty on the licensee not exceeding $5,000 for each day and each violation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to any penalty assessed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Revoke the licensee’s license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Suspend the licensee’s license for a period of time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reprimand the licensee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Impose conditions upon the licensee that must be met within a specified time as to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Training;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Staffing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supervision;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Compliance with internal controls;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Probationary periods; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Any other directive to address the violation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Penalty — Required Considerations. To determine the amount of a penalty to impose on a licensee, the Commission shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The seriousness of the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The harm caused by the violation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the person who committed the violation acted in good faith.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sanction — Considerations. To determine the appropriate sanction to impose on a licensee, the Commission may consider the factors in <cite path="36|10|08|.10|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether a violation was willful;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the licensee had, or should have had, control of the situation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the violation may have occurred in connection with unclear or insufficient:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Communication; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Requirements;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any extraordinary circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prior disciplinary history with the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Profit that resulted, or may have resulted, from the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Harm that resulted, or may have resulted, from the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>How the violation was detected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Action taken by the licensee to prevent recurrence of the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Action taken by the Commission to address similar violations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Any other information that the Commission finds relevant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Ignorance No Defense. A licensee is presumed to be familiar with applicable statutes and regulations governing the State’s Sports Wagering Program, and a claim of ignorance of the statutes and regulations may not be used as a defense to a finding of a violation or to the imposition of a sanction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Imposition of Sanction. A separate sanction may be imposed for each violation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Commission Action.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee whose license has been suspended or revoked by the Commission’s final action on the license shall immediately cease sports wagering activity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee against whom the Commission imposed a penalty shall remit to the Commission payment in full of the penalty within 30 calendar days.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|20">20</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|25">25</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-01—9-1E-15, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|08|.11">.11</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
