<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Enforcement of Voluntary Exclusion Program</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|10|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition. Unless context dictates otherwise, for purposes of this chapter, “sports wagering licensee” includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sports wagering facility licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Mobile sports wagering licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sports wagering facility operator licensee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Online sports wagering operator license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall notify sports wagering licensees that an individual has been placed on the voluntary exclusion list established in <cite path="|36.01.03">COMAR 36.01.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may disclose information about an individual on the voluntary exclusion list to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The licensee’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Managers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Security department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Surveillance department; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Employees who are directly responsible for excluding unauthorized individuals from sports wagering; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the sports wagering licensee pursues criminal charges against an individual on the voluntary exclusion list who is suspected of trespassing on the premises of a sports wagering facility licensee, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A law enforcement officer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person who is legally authorized to be involved in the criminal prosecution of an individual on the voluntary exclusion list who is suspected of trespassing on a sports wagering licensee’s property.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a sports wagering licensee uses technology for the purpose of complying with this regulation, the sports wagering licensee shall ensure that the technology:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complies with all applicable State and local requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is designed to prevent unauthorized access to confidential records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an individual on the voluntary exclusion list is found on the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted, the sports wagering licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall immediately notify the Commission in person or via email; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May pursue criminal charges against the individual such as trespassing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permit an individual on the voluntary exclusion list to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enter the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Participate in sports wagering;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Knowingly fail to exclude from the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted an individual on the voluntary exclusion list; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Disclose information about an individual on the voluntary exclusion list beyond the disclosures that are authorized under <cite path="36|10|10|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unless excluded by operation of another directive or order outside the Commission, an individual who has been placed on a voluntary exclusion list of the Commission that is not under this subtitle may engage in sports wagering.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|10|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Responsible Gaming Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall establish a responsible gaming plan that sets forth its plan for addressing problem gambling that shall include at least the following elements of the plan:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures and deadlines for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Procedures for retrieving and securely maintaining the voluntary exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures for notifying the Commission of an unauthorized access to the list within twelve hours of the unauthorized access;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Identification of a sports wagering licensee’s personnel responsible for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities of a sports wagering licensee’s personnel identified as responsible for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Training for a sports wagering licensee’s personnel on problem gambling and voluntary exclusion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Means of controlling access to records pertaining to voluntary exclusion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Means of educating bettors about:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Problem gambling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Problem gambling treatment resources, including treatment and prevention programs established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Voluntary exclusion;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Placement of responsible gambling awareness information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the premises of a sports wagering facility licensee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a sports wagering licensee’s sports wagering platform;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Ensuring that an individual on the voluntary exclusion list is not permitted to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enter the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Participate in sports wagering; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Claim winnings;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee’s response to the discovery of an individual who is enrolled in the voluntary exclusion list in the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted, which may include pursuing criminal charges against the individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee’s response to the discovery of a bettor who is enrolled in the voluntary exclusion list using a sports wagering platform, which may include an action up to and including permanent suspension of the bettor’s account;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee’s procedures for returning to a bettor the funds in the bettor’s account that were placed by the bettor prior to the bettor’s application for voluntary exclusion, including the requirement that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Funds be returned as soon as practicable after the time the bettor is placed on the voluntary exclusion list; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The sports wagering licensee return the funds to the bettor within 7 days of the bettor’s placement on the voluntary exclusion list, by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Crediting the bettor’s personal bank account; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Paying the bettor by check; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Any other element required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall submit to the Commission the responsible gaming plan required under <cite path="36|10|10|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> at least 60 days before sports wagering operations are to commence or within a time-period approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall submit any amendments to its responsible gaming plan to the Commission prior to implementation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall annually submit to the Commission its responsible gaming plan.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Advertisement” means any material that is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Disseminated to the public through broadcasting, publication, mail, or any other means; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Intended to encourage sports wagering.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Billboard advertisement” means a roadside sign, aviation banner, or event banner that is intended to encourage sports wagering.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Gambling assistance message” means a phrase approved by the Commission to encourage responsible play.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>“Printed advertisement” means an advertisement that appears in or on a sign, direct mailing, poster, brochure or other written material and is intended to encourage sports wagering.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>“Responsible gambling awareness materials” means a sticker, a brochure, a wallet card, or other material that conveys only problem gambling resource information.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>“Underage warning message” means the phrase: No bettor under the age of 21 is permitted to participate in sports wagering.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Post signage approved by the Commission that prominently bears the gambling assistance message and the underage warning message at each customer entrance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include banners or other notifications on the sports wagering websites that bear the gambling assistance message and the underage warning message;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include the gambling assistance message on an advertisement that is intended to encourage sports wagering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a printed advertisement bears the gambling assistance message and meets requirements of <cite path="36.10.13.43">COMAR 36.10.13.43</cite> and <cite path="36.03.03.08">36.03.03.08</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a billboard bearing a printed advertisement bears the gambling assistance message and meets requirements of <cite path="36.10.13.43">COMAR 36.10.13.43</cite> and <cite path="36.03.03.08">36.03.03.08</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a radio, television, video, online, or social media advertisement bears the gambling assistance message and meets requirements of <cite path="36.10.13.43">COMAR 36.10.13.43</cite> and <cite path="36.03.03.08">36.03.03.08</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the gambling assistance message is printed on a paper product that is associated with bettor consumption of food or beverage if the paper product is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Special ordered; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Branded with the sports wagering licensees logo;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the gambling assistance message is printed on a sports wagering ticket or sports wagering voucher;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Place in the sports wagering facility and sports wagering platform responsible gambling awareness information according to its responsible gaming plan required under <cite path="36.10.10.02">COMAR 36.10.10.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the gambling assistance message is conspicuous and readable; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Ensure that an advertisement for sports wagering, video lottery terminal, or table game play does not include language that suggests an outcome is guaranteed or without risk.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|24">24</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-01—9-1E-15, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|10|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|10|.03">.03</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|10|10|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
