<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Mandatory Exclusion</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definition.</heading>
    <text>Unless context dictates otherwise, for purposes of this chapter, “sports wagering licensee” includes:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Sports wagering facility licensee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Mobile sports wagering licensee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Sports wagering facility operator licensee; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>Online sports wagering operator licensee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes a mechanism by which the Commission:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maintains a list of individuals who shall be mandatorily:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excluded from participating in sports wagering; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Excluded or ejected from the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establishes standards that require a sports wagering licensee to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exclude an individual from participating in sports wagering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exclude or eject an individual from the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensure that an individual under the age of 21 does not participate in sports wagering and are not allowed in the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted including the platform of a sports wagering licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual who has been placed on the Commission’s mandatory exclusion list from sports wagering under this chapter may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Engage in sports wagering; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be on the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless excluded by operation of another directive or order outside the Commission, an individual who has been placed on a voluntary or mandatory exclusion list of the Commission that is not under this subtitle may engage in sports wagering.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|11|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Mandatory Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall establish a mandatory exclusion list for the Sports Wagering Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may place on the mandatory exclusion list an individual who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a career offender as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has been convicted of a criminal offense under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States that is a criminal offense involving moral turpitude or a gambling or sports wagering offense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Would adversely affect the interests of the State, the licensee, or the individual if that individual were to participate in sports wagering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is the subject of any administrative or judicial order directing the individual to cease participating in sports wagering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Presents a threat to the safety of any individual on the premises of a wagering facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Engages in, or has a documented history of engaging in, disruption of sports wagering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee has a reasonable belief has cheated, or attempted to cheat; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Engages in any conduct that may adversely affect public confidence in, or perception of, the State’s Sports Wagering Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In evaluating whether to place an individual on the mandatory exclusion list, the Director may consider monetary amounts and circumstances, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The nature of the incident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual was a sports wagering employee at the time of the incident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the individual was a sports wagering employee while the individual engaged in conduct described in <cite path="36|10|11|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the incident directly impacts:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sports wagering operations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A bettor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A licensee;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The amount or type of loss to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The sports wagering licensee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sports wagering operations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A bettor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A licensee;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual made restitution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual was involved in a prior incident that meets the criteria of <cite path="36|10|11|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Whether a sports wagering licensee has other information the Director finds relevant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other information the Director finds relevant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission’s entry of an individual on the mandatory exclusion list shall include sufficient information to identify the excluded individual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The information used to identify an excluded individual may include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The individual’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and any nickname or alias;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Residential address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Telephone numbers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Gender;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Physical description, including any birthmarks, scars, or tattoos;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Race or ethnic origin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>For non-United States citizens, country of origin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Photograph; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Social security number or other government issued identification number;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of placement on the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Brief statement of the basis for placing the individual on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other information the Commission requires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The mandatory exclusion list and related records are public records under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|11|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Inclusion on Mandatory Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of information that reasonably indicates an individual meets any criteria under <cite path="|36|10|11|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>, and after making any determination under <cite path="|36|10|11|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, the Director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evaluate the information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the information required under <cite path="|36|10|11|.04|E.">Regulation .04E of this chapter</cite> sufficiently identifies the individual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Decide whether to place the individual on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prior to placing an individual on the mandatory exclusion list, the Director or the Director’s designee may provide a sports wagering licensee with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Information used to identify an individual who may be excluded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The factual basis for placing an individual on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An opportunity to provide the Director with additional information identified in <cite path="|36|10|11|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Director decides to place an individual on the mandatory exclusion list, staff shall deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a written notice explaining:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The factual basis for placing the individual on the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The availability of a reconsideration meeting with the Director or the Director’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The requirements for submitting a request for a reconsideration meeting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That, if a timely request for a reconsideration meeting is not submitted, the placement of the individual’s name on a mandatory exclusion list and the distribution of the individual’s name to all sports wagering licensees in the State is available to the public; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>That the excluded individual shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prohibited from the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted and from participating in sports wagering;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Subject to criminal charges for trespassing or any other appropriate criminal charge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Required to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Redeem or liquidate unredeemed items that the individual has received since being placed on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Surrender to the Problem Gambling Fund established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland, any unredeemed items in the possession of the individual or received by the individual while participating in sports wagering after placement on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reconsideration Meeting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may submit to the Director a written request for a reconsideration meeting within 15 days of the date of the individual’s receipt of the notice described in <cite path="36|10|11|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an individual fails to timely submit a request under <cite path="36|10|11|.05|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A reconsideration meeting may be held by the Director or the Director’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>During a reconsideration meeting, an individual may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be represented by counsel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Present evidence as to why the individual does not meet the criteria under <cite path="|36|10|11|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Director or the Director’s designee shall deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a written notice of the decision following the reconsideration meeting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual dissatisfied with the result of a reconsideration meeting may submit a written request to the Commission for an appeal hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The request for an appeal hearing shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted within 15 days of the date of the individual’s receipt of the written notice of the decision following the reconsideration meeting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describe the individual’s legal and factual bases for disagreeing with placement on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If an individual fails to timely submit a written request for an appeal hearing under <cite path="36|10|11|.05|D.|(7)">§D(7) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a timely written request for an appeal hearing, the Director or the Director’s designee shall provide the individual with a notice for the appeal hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Appeal Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If after an appeal hearing the Commission decides that the excluded individual does not meet any criteria under <cite path="|36|10|11|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>, the individual’s name may not be placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If after an appeal hearing the Commission decides that the excluded individual meets any criteria under <cite path="|36|10|11|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual’s name shall remain on the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commission shall notify all sports wagering licensees in the State of the individual’s addition to the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The individual may seek judicial review of the Commission’s decision; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The individual may request to be removed from the mandatory exclusion list only as provided in <cite path="|36|10|11|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|11|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Removal from Mandatory Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After an excluded individual has been on the mandatory exclusion list for at least 5 years, the individual may request removal from the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An excluded individual’s request under <cite path="36|10|11|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be submitted to the Director in writing and shall include a detailed statement about why there is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Good cause for removal of the individual from the list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A material change in the individual’s circumstances since the individual’s name was placed on the list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Director or the Director’s designee shall investigate the request and make a recommendation to the Commission whether to grant or deny the request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Director or the Director’s designee recommends removing the individual from the list, the Commission may approve the recommendation without a hearing, and staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Remove the individual from the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a notice of removal from the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notify the State’s sports wagering licensees of the individual’s removal from the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the Director or the Director’s designee recommends continued inclusion on the mandatory exclusion list, the excluded individual may submit a written request for an appeal hearing to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Appeal Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The request for an appeal hearing shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted within 15 days of the date of the individual’s receipt of the written notice of the recommendation of the Director or the Director’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describe the individual’s legal and factual bases for disagreeing with the recommendation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an individual fails to timely submit a written request for an appeal hearing under <cite path="36|10|11|.06|F.|(1)|(a)">§F(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall remain on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a timely written request for an appeal hearing, the Director shall provide the individual with a hearing notice for a hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If after a hearing the Commission denies the individual’s request for removal, it shall deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a notice that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request was denied; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individual shall remain on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Separate from the individual’s ability to request removal under <cite path="36|10|11|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Director shall periodically review the mandatory exclusion list and may consider the following in order to determine if an individual should be removed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual is living;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether there are changed circumstances; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether removal is warranted due to any other relevant information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Judicial Review.</heading>
    <text>The Commission’s decision under Regulations .05E(2) and .06G of this chapter may be subject to judicial review.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <text>A sports wagering licensee may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Knowingly fail to exclude or eject an excluded individual from the property of a sports wagering licensee for which it is licensed or authorized to operate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fail to notify the Commission if an excluded individual is prohibited from entering any sports wagering facility;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fail to notify the Commission if an excluded individual is prohibited from participating in sports wagering through a sports wagering licensee including through a sports wagering platform;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Permit an individual younger than 21 years old to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Participate in sports wagering; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enter the part of the premises of a sports wagering facility it is licensed or authorized to operate where sports wagering is conducted;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Knowingly allow to collect winnings an:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excluded individual; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individual younger than 21 years old; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Fail to obtain any unredeemed items in the possession of an excluded individual and transfer them to the Problem Gambling Fund established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|11|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Sports Wagering Licensee’s Mandatory Exclusion Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall establish a plan for identifying and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excluding or ejecting excluded individuals from a sports wagering facility or from participating in sports wagering; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensuring that excluded individuals and individuals younger than 21 years old are not allowed to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Participate in sports wagering; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Enter the part of the premises of a sports wagering licensee where sports wagering is conducted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The plan required under <cite path="36|10|11|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures and deadlines for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identification of facility personnel responsible for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities of sports wagering licensee’s personnel identified as responsible for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Training for sports wagering licensee’s personnel on the requirements of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Regular monitoring of the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Prompt reports to the Commission about the presence at a wagering facility of an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is included on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is required to be prevented from participating in sports wagering;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Prompt reports to the Commission about an individual who is permanently excluded from participating in sports wagering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee’s response to the discovery of an individual who is on the mandatory exclusion list at the property of a sports wagering licensee or participating in sports wagering, which may include pursuing criminal charges against the individual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Any other element required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall submit to the Commission for its approval:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 60 days before sports wagering operations are to commence, the mandatory exclusion plan required under <cite path="36|10|11|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any amendments to a sports wagering licensee’s mandatory exclusion plan prior to implementation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An annual report describing the operation of the sports wagering licensee’s mandatory exclusion plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|24">24</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-01—9-1E-15, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|11|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|11|.09">.09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
