<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Collection of Taxes, Fees, and Penalties</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the manner and method by which the Commission may collect from an applicant or licensee a tax, fee or civil penalty established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1E, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the manner by which a sports wagering licensee may reconcile proceeds under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>E-07, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Fee” means an amount established by the Commission that an applicant or licensee is required to pay and includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application or renewal fee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A fee associated with an applicant’s criminal history records check.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Proceeds” has the meaning stated in State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-12, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|12|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Obligation to Pay.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A tax that is due and payable shall be paid by an applicant or licensee and collected in accordance with State and federal law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall submit monthly sports wagering tax returns to the Commission by the 5th day of the following month.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If monthly sports wagering taxes are due, the licensee shall pay them to the Commission by wire transfer by the 5th day of the following month.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If, by the seventh calendar day of the month, a sports wagering licensee fails to submit a properly completed sports wagering tax return and all taxes due to the Commission, the sports wagering license shall be automatically suspended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a sports wagering license is suspended under of this regulation, the Commission may lift the license suspension after the licensee submits the tax return and the tax payment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>For a fee or penalty:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall issue an invoice or other order to pay; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant or licensee shall remit payment to the Commission within 30 days after the date of the invoice or order to pay.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Reconciliation of Gross Sports Wagering Receipts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a sports wagering licensee returns to successful bettors more than the amount of money wagered on a sporting event, the sports wagering licensee may subtract the difference between the amount wagered and the amount returned to bettors from its proceeds of up to 3 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sports wagering licensee may not subtract losses under <cite path="36|10|12|.03|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite> for more than 3 consecutive months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|12|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Collection and Deposit of Payments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant or licensee shall pay a fee or civil penalty by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wire transfer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Money order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certified check made payable to the “State of Maryland”; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other manner designated by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall deposit payment of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application, license, renewal, or other fee into a bank account that the State Treasurer designates to the credit of the State Lottery and Gaming Control Agency Fund and distribute the funds as described under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>E-07, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>E-12, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Expired winnings into the Problem Gambling Fund established in the Maryland Department of Health under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Funds surrendered under <cite path="|03.10.10">COMAR 03.10.10</cite> or <cite path="|03.10.11">COMAR 03.10.11</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission may recover from an applicant or licensee whose payment of a fee or penalty is overdue:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The unpaid amount of the fee or penalty;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Revenues lost to the State as the result of the nonpayment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Attorney’s fees; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other penalty, interest, cost, and expense allowable by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The failure of a licensee to timely pay a fee or penalty is a violation of an order of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission’s election to seek recovery under <cite path="36|10|12|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> for a licensee’s failure to pay a fee or penalty does not preclude the Commission or the State from enforcing other rights, or seeking other remedies, for the same failure to pay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall account for collection of a fee or penalty in accordance with applicable law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|33">33</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-01—9-1E-15, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|12|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|12|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-25"><cite path="|36|10|12|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 26, 2022 (49:5 Md. R. 364); amended permanently effective July 25, 2022 (49:15 Md. R. 740)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
