<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Sports Wagering Requirements and Limitations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Authorized Wagers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition. Unless context or the individual regulation dictates otherwise, for purposes of this regulation, “sports wagering licensee” includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sports wagering facility licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Mobile sports wagering licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sports wagering facility operator licensee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Online sports wagering operator licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Type of Event.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A sports wagering licensee shall submit to the Commission for approval the events and types of wagers it proposes offering to bettors prior to accepting a sports wagering bet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may authorize a sports wagering licensee to offer wagering on a sporting event as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>E-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Verifiable Outcome.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this section, “official league data” means statistics, results, outcomes, and other data relating to a sporting event obtained by a sports wagering licensee under an agreement with a governing entity or an entity expressly authorized by a governing entity for determining the outcome of a wager placed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sports wagering licensee may use any Commission approved data source for determining the results of sports wagers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Wager Limits. The maximum wager that may be accepted by any sports wagering licensee from a patron on any one sporting event shall be limited to $5,000,000.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|14|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Commission Approval of Specific Bet Types.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall submit to the Commission for approval the events and types of wagers it proposes offering to bettors prior to accepting any sports wagering bets.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may permit a sports wagering licensee to offer wagering on any approved sporting event.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission may permit a sports wagering licensee to offer any of the following types of wagers on the events contained in <cite path="36|10|14|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exchange wagers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In-game wagers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Parlay wagers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Proposition wagers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Straight wagers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Pools; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Other types of wagers as approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall make available to bettors a clear explanation of all types of wagers permitted by the Commission and events on which those wagers are permitted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may place a layoff wager with another sports wagering licensee or located in the State for the purpose of offsetting bettor wagers provided that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee placing the layoff wager discloses its identity to the sports wagering licensee receiving the layoff wager; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The receiving sports wagering licensee agrees to accept the layoff wager after receiving notification of the identity of the sports wagering licensee placing the layoff wager.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|14|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Wagers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Sports wagering activity may not involve:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wagering on a high school athletic event governed by the Maryland Interscholastic Athletic Association, Maryland Public Secondary Schools Athletic Association, or a similar sports governing entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for an amateur athletic event specifically approved by the Commission, wagering on an amateur athletic event; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other wagering activity that is prohibited by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may not accept a wager that the licensee knew or should have known:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Involves cheating;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Was made by an athlete on an athletic event governed by the same governing entity under which the athlete competes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Was made by a person who holds a position of authority or influence over the participants in a sporting event or is professionally connected to an athletic event or governing entity, including a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Referee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Official;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Coach;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manager;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Handler;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Trainer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Medical professional; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Person with access to non-public information about a sporting event that is overseen by the governing entity;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Was made by an independent evaluator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Was made by a person who is placing a wager on behalf, or for the benefit, of a person that is prohibited from participating in sports wagering under applicable law or regulation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Encourages or instructs a bettor to structure a wager to circumvent applicable law or regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless it immediately issues a sports wagering ticket detailing the wager after accepting money to fund the wager, accept or hold cash or a cash equivalent to fund a wager that will be placed if a specified future contingency occurs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accept a wager that is not authorized by the Commission; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accept a wager on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Injuries;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Penalties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Player disciplinary rulings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Replay reviews; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any other types or forms of wagering that are contrary to public policy or unfair to bettors.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may not accept or facilitate a wager:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On a sporting event not approved by the Commission under this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From an excluded individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>From a person who is placing the wager in violation of applicable law or regulation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>From any employee of a sports wagering licensee or sports wagering operator, on the premises or platform of the employee's employer, that may not participate in sports wagering because the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is licensed by the Commission under State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitles 9-1A or 9-1E, Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is an affiliate or agent of a sports wagering licensee or online sports wagering operator.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The prohibition under <cite path="36|10|14|.03|D.|(4)">§D(4) of this regulation</cite> is not applicable to persons who are registered or certified as a vendor under <cite path="36.10.06.11">COMAR 36.10.06.11</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|14|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Limits on Accepting Wagers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering platform shall be capable of allowing a registered bettor to establish the following responsible wagering limits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A deposit limit on a daily, weekly and monthly basis that specifies the maximum amount of money a registered bettor may deposit into their sports wagering account during a particular period of time;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A limit on the amount wagered or money lost within a daily, weekly or monthly basis that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Renders the registered bettor unable to place an additional wager for the remainder of the time selected once the registered bettor reaches the loss limit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not allow a wager placed prior to reaching the loss limit to be cancelled or refunded;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A limit on the amount of money wagered within a daily, weekly or monthly basis that renders the registered bettor unable to place an additional wager for the remainder of the time selected once the registered bettor reaches the wager limit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A limit on the maximum amount of a single wager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A time-based limit that specifies the maximum amount of time, measured hourly from the registered bettor’s login to log off, in which a registered bettor may engage in sports wagering on a daily basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A temporary suspension of sports wagering through the sports wagering account for the number of days selected by the registered bettor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A mechanism by which a registered bettor may change the limits of §A(1)—(6) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provision in this section, the registered bettor may not change wagering limits while a sports wagering account is suspended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An increase to financial limits in <cite path="36|10|14|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may not become effective until after the time period of the previous limit has expired.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A decrease to the chronological limits in <cite path="36|10|14|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may not be effective later than the registered bettor’s next login.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A self-imposed limitation established by a bettor may not replace or override a more restrictive limitation imposed by a licensee or these regulations.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Funding Wagers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A bettor’s sports wagering account may be funded by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A cash deposit made directly with a sports wagering licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A cash equivalent, personal check, or wire transfer made directly or mailed to the sports wagering licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A bettor’s debit card or prepaid card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A bettor’s deposit of a winning sports wagering ticket at a sports wagering facility approved by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A cash complimentary, promotional credit, or bonus credit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If there is documented notification to the bettor, an adjustment made by a sports wagering licensee following the resolution of a dispute; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any other means as approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>ACH Transfer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a sports wagering licensee has security measures and controls approved by the Commission to prevent and detect fraud, it may accept an ACH transfer to fund a wager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a bettor has successfully deposited funds through an ACH transfer on a previous occasion with no outstanding chargebacks, a sports wagering licensee is not required to consider one failed ACH deposit attempt as fraudulent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a sports wagering licensee suspects fraud after a bettor’s multiple failed ACH deposit attempts, the sports wagering licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May temporarily freeze or suspend the bettor’s account to investigate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the sports wagering licensee determines that fraud has been attempted or occurred, suspend the bettor’s account.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Extend credit to a bettor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Allow the deposit of funds into a sports wagering account that are derived from the extension of credit by an affiliate or agent of the sports wagering licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A bettor’s sports wagering account:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not have a negative account balance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not accept a wager if the account does not have funds sufficient to pay for the wager.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The sports wagering licensee shall update bettor account balances after each bet settles to reflect the funds available for any future wagers the bettor may choose to place.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Adjustment to a sports wagering account for an amount of $500 or under shall be periodically reviewed by supervisory personnel as set forth in the sports wagering licensee’s internal controls.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Supervisory personnel shall authorize an adjustment for an amount above $500 before the adjustment may be entered into the bettors’ account.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|14|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reserve.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall maintain a reserve in cash, cash equivalents, irrevocable letter of credit, surety bond set forth in <cite path="36|10|14|.06|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, or a combination thereof in an amount approved by the Commission to cover the outstanding liability of the sports wagering licensee to bettors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee may not remove, release, or withdraw funds from its reserve without the written approval of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The amount in the reserve shall be at least $500,000 and equal or exceed the aggregate sum of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total amount of funds to cover the potential liability for all wagers accepted by the sports wagering licensee on sporting events with outcomes that have not been determined; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Money owed but unpaid by the sports wagering licensee to bettors on winning wagers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall ensure that the reserve is held:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By a financial institution insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and licensed to transact business in the State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For sports wagering facility licensee, in cash held on facility premises.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A sports wagering licensee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Calculate its reserve requirements each day; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the sports wagering licensee determines its reserve is insufficient to cover the requirement of this regulation, notify the Commission in writing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 24 hours of the deficiency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The steps to be taken to remedy the deficiency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Surety Bonds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee may obtain a single surety bond or multiple bonds to be used as a cash reserve to pay the current outstanding liability of all winnings and awards offered to a winning bettor as set forth in this regulation and <cite path="36.10.13.40">COMAR 36.10.13.40</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A surety bond shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be in a form approved by the Agency and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identify the sports wagering licensee or applicant as the principal of the surety bond;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Indicate what license type and class the sports wagering licensee or applicant offers or intends to offer in the State of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Provide that the surety bond is protected against claims by creditors of the principal, including the patrons for whose benefit and protection the reserve account is established;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Allow the Director of the Agency or the Director’s designee to make demand upon the surety for the payment of valid winning amounts not paid by the principal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Require the sports wagering licensee to provide an updated listing of winning wagers that form the basis of the reserve to the Agency within 72 hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Include a statement that within 24 hours of receiving the updated listing of winning wagers that form the basis of the reserve that the Agency will commence review of the list of outstanding patron accounts;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Include a statement that within 10 business days of the demand made by the Director or the Director’s designee the processing of the payment will commence;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Include a statement that within 60 days of the demand made by the Director or the Director’s designee issuance of the payment shall occur; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Include a statement that if the surety provides written notice of withdrawal, the withdrawal is not effective until 60 days have elapsed after receipt of the notice.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be by and between the sports wagering licensee or applicant and the surety company;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify the Agency as the obligee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Specify that it guarantees the portion of the sports wagering licensee’s reserve that is not covered by a cash reserve; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Specify that the surety bond is valid for at least the 5-year license term.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The sports wagering licensee or applicant shall provide the original surety bond to the Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Agency staff may not issue a sports wagering license unless the applicant or awardee has provided Agency staff with a copy of any surety bond that comprises any portion of the reserve the sports wagering licensee is required to hold.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|14|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Complaint by an Interested Party.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Interested party” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A sports wagering licensee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A professional sports team, or its:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>League;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Association; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Governing entity; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An institution of higher education.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Public hearing” means the portion of a Commission meeting during which the Commission will consider an interested party’s complaint about a matter described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government, §9-1</cite>E-11(e)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complaint.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An interested party may submit a complaint to the Commission requesting the Commission to prohibit a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type or form of sports wagering; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Category of individuals wagering on a sporting event.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Time for Submission.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The complaint shall be submitted at least 15 days before commencement of the wagering activity that is the subject of the complaint.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except for recurring events, the Commission shall immediately dismiss, and may not consider, a complaint that is submitted less than 15 days before commencement of the wagering activity that is the subject of the complaint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The complaint shall be in writing, and specifically describe the type, form, or category of wager, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of the sporting event for which the wager is offered, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Time;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Place; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Participants in the sporting event;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The name and contact information for the licensee or person offering the wager;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The specific reasons why the complainant believes that the type, form, or category of wager:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is contrary to public policy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is unfair to consumers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Affects the integrity of a particular sport; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Affects the integrity of the sports wagering industry; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other information the Commission requires.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Review of Complaint.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commission staff shall review the complaint for compliance with <cite path="36|10|14|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Missing Information.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Commission staff shall notify the complainant if the complaint is missing information required in <cite path="36|10|14|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, or if additional information is required to review the complaint.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The complainant shall provide Commission staff with any missing or required information within 5 days of the notice in <cite path="36|10|14|.07|C.|(2)|(a)">§C(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Commission staff shall dismiss the complaint if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The complainant fails to timely provide information as required in <cite path="36|10|14|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person that is allegedly conducting the wagering activity that is the subject of the complaint is not a licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The wagering activity is a prohibited wager under <cite path="|36.10.14">COMAR 36.10.14</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The wagering activity occurs before the next scheduled Commission meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Public Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The portion of the Commission meeting pertaining to the agenda item of the complaint shall be conducted as part of a Commission open meeting under <cite path="36.01.02.03">COMAR 36.01.02.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A public hearing on the complaint of an interested party is not a hearing under <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the complaint has not been dismissed under <cite path="36|10|14|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, Commission staff:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall place the complaint on the agenda item of the next Commission meeting and post notice of the meeting in the ordinary course of business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall attempt to contact the complainant and the licensee or person offering the wager of the meeting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>May notify any interested party of the complaint and meeting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual who wishes to speak during the portion of the Commission meeting pertaining to the agenda item of the complaint:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is encouraged to contact the Commission staff who notified the individual of the meeting to advise, in advance of the meeting, whether they plan to attend; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is limited to the time limit established by the Chair.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the Commission meeting will be held virtually:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual shall contact the Commission staff who notified the individual of the meeting to advise, in advance of the meeting, the telephone number, or other means acceptable to the Commission, by which they will join the virtual meeting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual who has not contacted Commission staff as required in <cite path="36|10|14|.07|E.|(5)|(a)">§E(5)(a) of this regulation</cite> may not participate in the meeting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>During discussion of the agenda item pertaining to the complaint, the Commission shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Receive a report from Commission staff;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hear the views if interested parties, or individuals who have arranged to join the meeting under <cite path="36|10|14|.07|E.|(5)|(a)">§E(5)(a) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Decide whether good cause is shown to prohibit the wagering activity that is the subject of the complaint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If good cause is shown, the Commission shall notify the complainant and licensee of the decision and take appropriate action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If good cause is not shown, the Commission shall notify the complainant and licensee of the decision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission’s decision on a complaint under this regulation does not give rise to an appeal right under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite>—9-1E-15, and 9-1E-17, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|14|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|14|.07">.07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-25"><cite path="|36|10|14|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 26, 2022 (49:5 Md. R. 364); amended permanently effective July 25, 2022 (49:15 Md. R. 740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-25"><cite path="|36|10|14|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 26, 2022 (49:5 Md. R. 364); amended permanently effective July 25, 2022 (49:15 Md. R. 740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|10|14|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|10|14|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|10|14|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); adopted permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
