<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>Sports Wagering Licensee Facility Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies only to sports wagering facilities.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Hours of Operation.</heading>
    <text>A facility may operate during the hours approved by the Commission.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Facility Design Standards.</heading>
    <text>The awardee of a Class A or Class B license shall, at its own expense, construct its facility in accordance with requirements established by the Commission, including:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For any sports wagering licensee that does not currently hold a video lottery facility operator’s license, at least 100 square feet of office space or an amount approved by Agency staff that is available for use by the Agency staff and equipped with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Partitioned workspace, telephones, all-in-one printer, and office supplies sufficient to meet the Commission staffs operational needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A secure high-speed wireless internet connection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Computer terminals permitting read only access by authorized Commission staff to any sports wagering platform, promotional play system, point of sale system, or surveillance system used by the sports wagering licensee;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A surveillance system approved in writing by [the Commission] Agency staff that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is configured to provide surveillance of all sports wagering related activities within the facility in accordance with standards established by the Commission or Agency staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is enabled with digital video recording capabilities in accordance with standards established by the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provides Agency staff with timely and unfettered access to its surveillance system;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An alarm system connected to all emergency exits from the facility which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Produces a distinguishable warning sound that is discernible in the vicinity of an exit when the emergency door is opened; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requires deactivation and reset by means of a key or alternative locking mechanism maintained and controlled by the security department;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any signage required by Agency staff;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Communication systems capable of effecting timely communication between the facility and the Commission, law enforcement exercising proper jurisdiction over the facility, and emergency first responders; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Any other equipment or design feature required by the Commission or Agency staff.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|10|15|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Sports Wagering Facility Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation is only applicable to the awardee of a sports wagering facility license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least 60 days before sports wagering operations are to commence, a licensee shall submit a floor plan depicting its facility and all restricted areas to Agency staff for review and written approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An awardee may not commence operations until its facility plan is approved in writing by Agency staff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility plan that an awardee or licensee submits to Agency staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be drawn to 1/8-inch scale, unless another scale is approved by Agency staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Depict the facility with a notation as to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Total square feet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Perimeter of the facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each ATM and bill breaker, ticket redemption unit and kiosk; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each security department zone, including a notation as to whether it is a fixed or roving post;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Depict any restricted areas within the facility with a notation identifying:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cashiers cage, any satellite cashiers cage, and ancillary offices, inclusive of each cashiers cage window location and location number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Count rooms and any trolley storage areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Information technology department computer rooms;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Surveillance equipment room;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Vault and armored car bay facilities, if applicable; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any area designated as restricted by the awardee or licensee in its approved internal controls;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Depict each surveillance camera with a notation as to camera type and location number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Depict each automated teller machine installed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any other equipment or design feature required by Agency staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a facility includes an outdoor area, in addition to the requirements of <cite path="36|10|15|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a licensee shall submit to Agency staff a facility plan that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amenities that the licensee intends to offer in the outdoor area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An affidavit from the licensees chief executive officer attesting that the outdoor area and its intended use meet all applicable local and State requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A plan for bettor and equipment safety during inclement weather.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensee may not implement any change to its approved wagering facility plan without the prior written approval of Agency staff.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite>—9-1E-15, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|10|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|10|15|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); adopted permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|10|15|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|10|15|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
