<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Open Meetings</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. "Board" means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Advisory Board for Juvenile Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any other board, commission, or entity of the Department that is a public body, as that term is defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-502">State Government Article, §10-502, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Public Attendance and Observance Allowed.</heading>
    <text>At any open session of a board, the general public is invited to attend and observe.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Public Participation Limited.</heading>
    <text>A member of the public attending an open session may not participate in the session except to the extent:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board expressly invites or allows public testimony, questions, comments, or other forms of public participation; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person is entitled by law to participate.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="16|03|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Disruptive Conduct Prohibited.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General. A person attending an open session of a board may not engage in any conduct, including visual demonstrations such as the waving of placards, signs, or banners, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Disrupts the session; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interferes with the public's right to attend and observe the session.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Enforcement. If any person persists in conduct prohibited by <cite path="16|03|07|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> or violates any other regulation concerning the conduct of the open session, the presiding officer may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Order the person to be removed from the session;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Request police assistance to restore order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Recess the session until order is restored.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Recording, Photographing, or Broadcasting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Authorized Generally. A member of the public, including a representative of the news media, may record, photograph, videotape, broadcast, or televise the proceedings of an open session by means of a tape recorder, camera, or other device or equipment, if the device or equipment:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is operated without excessively bright artificial light that disturbs board members or other individuals attending the session;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not create an excessive noise that disturbs board members or other individuals attending the session; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not otherwise:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Disrupt the session; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Interfere with the public's right to attend and observe the session.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Restricted Movement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If necessary to maintain the orderly conduct of the session, the presiding officer may restrict the movement of the person who is using a recording device, a camera, or broadcasting or televising equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the person refuses to comply or otherwise persists in conduct prohibited by this regulation or any other regulation concerning the conduct of the open session, the presiding officer may take action as authorized in <cite path="|16|03|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Recordings Not Part of Record.</heading>
    <text>Neither a recording of an open session made by a member of the public nor a transcript derived from this recording is considered a part of the record of any proceeding of the board.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|9-204">Human Services Article, §9-204</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-507">State Government Article, §10-507(b)</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-06-18">Effective date: June 18, 2007 (34:12 Md. R. 1067)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
