<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Scope and Definitions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided, all regulations and policies of the Commission apply to both credit courses and programs and continuing education noncredit courses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This subtitle applies to the Baltimore City Community College except for the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.02.02B;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.02.03B(1) and (2);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.02.03C(1), D, E, and F;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.02.04C;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.02.06;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.03; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>COMAR 13B.07.04.01, .03, .04, .05, and .06.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board of trustees of a college" means the governing board of a college or system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>College.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"College" means a public community college or regional community college authorized to operate in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"College" includes Baltimore City Community College, except as provided in <cite path="|13B|07|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Continuing education course" means a course for which academic credit is not awarded.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Contract amount" means the total amount received by a college from a local, State, or federal contract, plus any other federal or State revenue related to the contract, excluding full-time equivalent student (FTE) State support.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"County" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A political subdivision of the State that supports a community college under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|16-201">Education Article, §16-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The total of all counties that support a regional community college under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|16-302">Education Article, §16-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"County resident" means a student who has maintained a domicile in the county or region served by the college for at least 3 months before the date of enrollment at a college.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Direct Costs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Direct costs" means expenditures that are clearly incurred by the college in the fulfillment of a federal, State, or local contract or grant, and are explicitly related to the performance or fulfillment of the contract or grant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Direct costs" includes salaries, wages, benefits, services, materials, and equipment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Domicile" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A student's permanent place of abode, where physical presence and possessions are maintained with the intention of remaining indefinitely; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The permanent place of abode of any person or persons contributing more than 1/2 of the student's financial support during the most recently completed year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Dual enrollment student" means a secondary student who is enrolled in college courses and receives both high school and college credit for the courses completed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Electronic" means relating to technology having electrical, digital, magnetic, wireless, optical, electromagnetic, or similar capabilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Electronic signature" means an electronic sound, symbol, or process that is a protected entity, attached to or logically associated with a record, and executed or adopted by a person with the intent to sign the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Eligible employee" means a full-time, nontemporary employee of the college who is entitled to receive full employment benefits at the college.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Equated credit" means contact hours divided by 15.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Full-time day equivalent (FTDE)" means the total number of credit hours taught on campus between 8 a.m. and 5 p.m., divided by 15 credit hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Full-time equivalent faculty (FTEF)" means the number of full-time faculty plus the number of course credit hours eligible for State aid and taught by part-time faculty during a given fiscal year, divided by 30.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Full-time equivalent student" means the quotient of the number of student credit hours produced in the fiscal year which is 2 years before the fiscal year for which the State share is calculated, divided by 30.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Gifted and talented" means an elementary or secondary school student who is identified by professionally qualified individuals as having outstanding abilities in one or more of the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>General intellectual capabilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specific academic aptitudes; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Creative, visual, or performing arts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Indirect costs" means the number of full-time equivalent (FTE) students taught under a training contract multiplied by the budgeted current year net cost per FTE for that college per the Annual Budget Report (form MHEC-CC-5), multiplied by the percentage of the adjusted current unrestricted expenditures in all functions other than instruction as reported in the current Annual Budget Report (form MHEC-CC-5) for that college.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Maryland resident" means a student who has maintained a domicile in Maryland for at least 3 months before the date of enrollment at a college.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"PlanMaryland” means the State Development Plan prepared by the Maryland Department of Planning and filed with the Secretary of State on December 16, 2011.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Protected entity" means a process for verifying that an electronic signature is that of a specific person to whom the electronic signature is being attributed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Record" means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium retrievable in a perceivable form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Higher Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>Standardized Test.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Standardized test" means a test distributed by external agencies for determining academic equivalence of knowledge or skills, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Standardized test" does not include departmental or other examinations developed and administered by the college.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">Education Article, §11-105, </cite>and Title 16, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-01-26">Effective date: January 26, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 77)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-31"><cite path="|13B|07|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1622); June 23, 2003 (30:12 Md. R. 791); March 31, 2014 (41:6 Md. R. 380)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
