<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Workforce Readiness Grant Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>The criteria and procedures in this chapter apply to the Workforce Readiness Grant Program provided for by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|16-321">Education Article, §16-321, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as enacted by Ch. 457, Acts of 2019.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“College” means any public community college authorized to operate in the State and includes Baltimore City Community College.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Designated time period” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>July 1, 2019, to June 30, 2021; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>July 1, 2021, to June 30, 2023.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Eligible contribution” means the total amount or fair market value of monetary or equipment contributions pledged by an eligible donor to an eligible institution, and received by the college, that are specifically designated by the donor to improve the college’s technology, during a designated time period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Eligible donor” means any individual, corporation, partnership, organization, or other form of business organization, public or private foundation, or other nonprofit organization, other than a local, state, federal, or foreign government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Eligible institution” means each campus of each college and does not include any foundation affiliated with the college or campus.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Technology” means any technology that will improve the college’s career and workforce instruction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|07|06|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reporting to Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>No later than 60 days after the end of a designated time period, a college requesting matching funds from the State under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|16-321">Education Article, §16-321, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall provide to the Commission, for each eligible institution, a report containing the information set forth in <cite path="13B|07|06|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For each eligible donor, the college shall provide, in a format specified by the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An itemized list of all monetary and equipment donations made during the designated time period that includes a description of the purpose for which the eligible contribution was or will be used; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation, from the donor, of each monetary or equipment donation made during the designated time period showing that the donation was specifically designated to improve the college’s technology.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A college shall provide additional or alternate documentation to the Commission upon the Commission’s request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a college requesting matching funds does not already provide a copy of its annual audit and management report to the Commission, it shall submit one within 90 days of the close of each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>On or before August 1, 2022, and on or before August 1, 2024, a college shall provide to the Commission, for each eligible institution, a report specifying how all eligible contributions and State matching funds granted under this program were used.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Record-Keeping Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Colleges shall maintain all records that document or support the information provided to the Commission under <cite path="|13B|07|06|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, including documentation showing the use of all eligible contributions and State matching funds granted under this program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Records specific to this program shall be maintained separately from other donation records and provided to the State upon request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All records relating to this program shall be kept through June 30, 2029, or until audited, whichever is earlier.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Reporting to Governor.</heading>
    <text>On or before October 1, 2021, and on or before October 1, 2023, the Commission shall provide to the Governor a list of the total eligible contributions made to each eligible institution during the preceding designated time period.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite>(u) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|16-321">16-321</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 457, Acts of 2019</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-24">Effective date: February 24, 2020 (47:4 Md. R. 263)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
