<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Sexual Assault Victims’ Rights — Disposal of Rape Kit Evidence and Notification</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter is intended to promote uniform statewide implementation of the disposal of rape kit evidence and sexual assault victim notification requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-926">Criminal Procedure Article, §11-926, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Child advocacy center” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-296">Criminal Procedure Article, §11-296(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Hospital” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-296">Criminal Procedure Article, §11-296(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Information Provided to Victims.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A health care provider that performs a sexual assault evidence collection kit exam on a victim of sexual assault shall provide the victim with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If known, contact information for the investigating law enforcement agency that the victim may contact about the status and results of the kit analysis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Written information describing the laws and policies governing the testing, preservation, and disposal of a sexual assault evidence collection kit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice of the right to request an independent review of a law enforcement agency’s decision not to test a sexual assault evidence collection kit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An investigating law enforcement agency that receives a sexual assault evidence collection kit, within 30 days after a request by the victim from whom the evidence was collected, shall provide the victim with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The law enforcement agency’s decision regarding whether to send the sexual assault evidence collection kit to a forensic laboratory for analysis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The law enforcement agency’s decision regarding whether to send the sexual assault evidence collection kit to a forensic laboratory for analysis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All available results of the kit analysis except results that would impede or compromise an ongoing investigation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|08|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Transfer and Destruction of Kits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Kit Transfers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A sexual assault evidence collection kit shall be transferred to a law enforcement agency:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By a hospital or a child advocacy center within 30 days after the exam is performed; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By a government agency in possession of a kit, unless the agency is otherwise required to retain the kit by law or court rule.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A hospital or child advocacy center shall cause a sexual assault evidence collection kit to be transferred by notifying the appropriate law enforcement agency as set forth in §A(4) and (5) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon notification, the law enforcement agency shall promptly send a representative to retrieve the kit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sexual assault evidence collection kits transferred pursuant to <cite path="02|08|01|.04|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be given to the law enforcement agency responsible for investigating the crime associated with the kit, if known.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the law enforcement agency responsible for investigating the crime associated with the kit is unknown, the kit shall be given to a law enforcement agency in the county:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Where the hospital, child advocacy center, or government agency is located; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Where the alleged sexual assault occurred.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="02|08|01|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, within 20 years after the evidence is collected, a law enforcement agency may not destroy or dispose of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A sexual assault evidence collection kit; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other crime scene evidence relating to a sexual assault that has been identified by the State’s Attorney as relevant to prosecution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A law enforcement agency is not required to comply with the requirements in <cite path="02|08|01|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The case for which the evidence was collected resulted in a conviction and the sentence has been completed; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All suspects identified by testing a sexual assault evidence collection kit are deceased.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>On written request by the victim from whom the evidence was collected, a law enforcement agency with custody of a sexual assault evidence collection kit or other crime scene evidence relating to a sexual assault shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the victim no later than 60 days before the date of the intended destruction or disposal of the evidence; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Retain the evidence for 12 months longer than the period specified in <cite path="02|08|01|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> or for a time period agreed to by the victim and the law enforcement agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-926">Criminal Procedure Article, §11-926(e), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-08">Effective date: October 8, 2018 (45:20 Md. R. 917)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-04"><cite path="|02|08|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective May 4, 2020 (47:9 Md. R. 476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-04"><cite path="|02|08|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective May 4, 2020 (47:9 Md. R. 476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-04"><cite path="|02|08|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> repealed effective May 4, 2020 (47:9 Md. R. 476)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
