<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Sexual Assault Evidence Collection Kits — Analysis</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Criteria for Analysis.</heading>
    <text>A sexual assault evidence collection kit shall be submitted to a forensic laboratory for analysis unless:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is clear evidence disproving the allegation of sexual assault;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The facts alleged, if true, could not be interpreted to violate a provision of Criminal Law Article, Title 3, Subtitle 2, 3, or 6, or Title 11, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The victim from whom the evidence was collected declines to give consent for analysis; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The suspect’s profile has been collected for entry as a convicted offender for a qualifying offense in the Combined DNA Index System (CODIS) maintained by the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the suspect has pleaded guilty to the offense that led to the sexual assault evidence collection kit.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Anonymous Kits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a victim of sexual assault wishes to remain anonymous and not file a criminal complaint, the victim shall be informed that the victim may file a criminal complaint at a future time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a provision of <cite path="|02|08|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> is determined to be satisfied after the submission of the victim’s sexual assault evidence collection kit for analysis, testing may be terminated or not initiated.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|08|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Submission to Forensic Laboratories.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|02|08|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, an investigating law enforcement agency that receives a sexual assault evidence collection kit shall submit the kit and all requested associated reference standards to a forensic laboratory for analysis within 30 days of receipt of the kit and all requested associated reference standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Testing by Forensic Laboratories.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A forensic laboratory that receives a sexual assault evidence collection kit and all requested associated reference standards for analysis shall determine suitability and complete screening, testing, and analysis in a timely manner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to complete the screening, testing, and analysis in a timely manner as required in <cite path="02|08|02|.03|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> may not constitute the basis for excluding the analysis or results as evidence in a criminal proceeding.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Use of Victim Services Organizations.</heading>
    <text>A law enforcement agency that receives a sexual assault evidence collection kit shall make use of certified sexual assault crisis programs or other qualified community-based sexual assault victim service organizations that can provide services and support to survivors of sexual assault.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>CODIS.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The eligible results of an analysis of a sexual assault evidence collection kit shall be entered into CODIS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The DNA collected from a victim under this chapter may not be used for any purpose except as authorized by this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-926">Criminal Procedure Article, §11-926(e), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-04">Effective date: May 4, 2020 (47:9 Md. R. 476)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
