<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Reporting</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Reporting by Law Enforcement Agencies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A law enforcement agency shall submit a copy of its written policies demonstrating compliance with this subtitle to the Office of the Attorney General within 90 days of the date this regulation goes into effect.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On or before September 1, 2021, and every year thereafter, a law enforcement agency shall submit the following information to the Office of the Attorney General:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The number of sexual assault evidence collection kits in its possession as of June 30 of that calendar year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of untested sexual assault evidence collection kits in its possession as of June 30 of that calendar year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date each sexual assault evidence collection kit in its possession was received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The number of sexual assault evidence collection kits tested during the prior year as of June 30 of that calendar year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of sexual assault evidence collection kits not tested during the prior year as of June 30 of that calendar year pursuant to <cite path="02.08.02.01|A.">COMAR 02.08.02.01A</cite>, B, C, or D;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The number of any other kits not tested and an explanation of why the kit was not tested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>For untested kit reviews:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The number of untested kit reviews requested during the prior year as of June 30 of that calendar year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The written recommendation resulting from each of the untested kit reviews conducted during the prior year as of June 30 of that calendar year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The number sexual assault evidence collections kits tested at the recommendation of an untested kit review;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>For sexual assault evidence collection kits destroyed during the prior year as of June 30 of that calendar year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The number of sexual assault evidence collection kits destroyed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date each sexual assault evidence collection kit was collected;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The date each sexual assault evidence collection kit was destroyed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The reason for the destruction; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The number of written requests received pursuant to <cite path="02.08.01.04|D.">COMAR 02.08.01.04D</cite> during the prior year as of June 30 of that calendar year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Reporting by Forensic Laboratories.</heading>
    <text>On or before September 1, 2021, and every year thereafter, a forensic laboratory shall submit the following information to the Office of the Attorney General:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The number of sexual assault evidence collection kits tested within the prior completed fiscal year;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The date each sexual assault evidence collection kit tested was received from a law enforcement agency; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The date on which a report summarizing the results of the test was prepared for each sexual assault evidence collection kit.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Criminal Procedure Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-926">11-926</cite>(e) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-927">11-927</cite>(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-04">Effective date: May 4, 2020 (47:9 Md. R. 476)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
