<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This subtitle applies to electronic gaming devices regulated by the Commission under Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-308">12-308</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This subtitle applies to all electronic gaming devices, regardless of whether the device delivers a game through the Internet or offers Internet or other services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This subtitle does not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Slot machines that are subject to regulation by the Comptroller under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-304">Criminal Law Article, §12-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lottery devices used by the Agency or, under the authority of the Agency, by a licensed retailer under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Video lottery terminals or tables games permitted and licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Paper tip jar gaming where authorized; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Skills-based amusement devices that award prizes and are operated in compliance with <cite path="|36.08">COMAR 36.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Antique electronic gaming device” means an electronic gaming device that is at least 25 years old.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Electronic gaming device” means an electronic machine, apparatus, or device that can be configured to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Operate by inserting, depositing, or placing with another person money, a token, or another object; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Through a preponderance of the element of chance, the reading of a game of chance, the delivery of a game of chance, or any other outcome unpredictable by the user, award the user anything of value other than an award of free play or the right to receive anything of value other than an award of free play.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Counties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review a county’s licensing and regulatory process for electronic gaming devices; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determine upon review that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The county’s licensing and regulatory process for electronic gaming devices is equivalent to a license from the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A county license for owning, operating, or manufacturing an electronic gaming device in the county is equivalent to a State license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A decision of the Commission on the equivalency of a county’s licensing and regulatory process for electronic gaming devices under this regulation is final and not appealable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Baltimore City and Baltimore County. Operators of amusement games in Baltimore City or Baltimore County shall be required to be licensed by the jurisdiction in which they are located.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Section 6, Chapter 603, Acts of 2012</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2017 (43:23 Md. R. 1281)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
