<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Service Credit for Officers of Employee Organizations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. “Employee organization” means an organization designated as the exclusive representative under a public bargaining law or the State affiliate of an organization so designated.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Grant of Eligibility and Creditable Service Credit.</heading>
    <text>A member who is elected to serve as a full-time executive officer of an employee organization may receive eligibility and creditable service for the period the member serves as such officer if, during that period:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>the member remits member contributions, if any; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>the participating employer remits employer contributions payable with respect to the member’s earnable compensation as provided in the member’s State system. The employee organization may not remit payments of member or employer contributions to the Retirement Agency.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Limits on Service Credit.</heading>
    <text>If the member elected as an officer of the employee organization becomes eligible to receive a retirement benefit of any type from the employee organization, the member shall notify the Retirement Agency and is subject to the following limitations with respect to his retirement benefit from the State system:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The member may only receive a maximum of 5 years eligibility and creditable service; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The member must have 5 years of eligibility or creditable service with one or more participating employers before receiving eligibility or creditable service for time spent as an officer of an employee organization.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-110">21-110</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13">Effective date: June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 707)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
