<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Screening and Assessment for Mental Health, Substance Abuse, and Mental Retardation</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs the requirements for a Department of Juvenile Services intake officer to disseminate information regarding screening and assessment for mental health, substance abuse, and mental retardation.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Referral for Screening.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a complaint concerning a child, and in no event not later than 25 days after receipt of a complaint, an intake officer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Discuss with the child and the child's parent or guardian information regarding a screening for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mental illness;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Substance abuse; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mental retardation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Document the discussion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Obtain written verification from the child and the child's parent or guardian acknowledging receipt of information regarding screening for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mental illness;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Substance abuse; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mental retardation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 15 days after the discussion with the child and the child's parent or guardian, the intake officer shall document whether the child's parent or guardian made an appointment for a screening.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Screening and Assessment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The screening and assessment authorized by this chapter shall be conducted by an individual who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has been selected by the child's parent or guardian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has been approved, as appropriate, by the State public mental health system or the child's health insurance carrier, if any; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A qualified health, mental health, or substance abuse professional; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Staff trained by a qualified health, mental health, or substance abuse professional.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A child may consent to advice, consultation, diagnosis, and treatment as provided in Health-General Article, Title 20, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Confidentiality.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Information received by the Department of Juvenile Services or the Maryland Department of Health relating to a specific screening or assessment for mental health, substance abuse, or mental retardation conducted under this chapter is confidential and may not be disclosed to any person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise prohibited by law, the Department of Juvenile Services and the Maryland Department of Health may make public non-identifying information concerning screenings or assessments for mental health, substance abuse, or mental retardation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Amendments to Regulations.</heading>
    <text>This chapter may not be amended unless the amendment is approved by both the Secretary of Juvenile Services and the Secretary of Health.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Courts and Judicial Proceedings, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-8">3-8</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|04">04</cite>—3-8A-17.12, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-06-11">Effective date: June 11, 2001 (28:11 Md. R. 1054)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|16.03.02">COMAR 16.03.02</cite> to <cite path="|16.16.02">COMAR 16.16.02</cite> in June, 2007</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
