<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Limits on Use of Restraints and Seclusion; Prohibition of Abuse</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Abuse.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Abuse" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The physical injury of a youth by any employee under circumstances that indicate the youth's health or welfare is significantly harmed or at risk of being significantly harmed; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Sexual abuse of a youth, whether or not physical injuries are sustained.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Abuse" does not include providing a youth with nonmedical religious remedial care and treatment recognized by State law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Juvenile Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Duty officer" means the individual designated by the superintendent to make decisions during the superintendent's absence or when the superintendent is unavailable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Employee" means any Department employee or any volunteer providing direct or indirect services to a youth in a facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Facility" means a residential program operated and managed by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Locked door seclusion" means the placement of a youth in a locked individual room, separate from the youth's room, where a youth is kept for a period of time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Restraint" means a mechanical device or a chemical agent which, when used, limits movement of a youth's body or temporarily disables the youth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Sexual abuse" means any act that involves sexual molestation or exploitation of a youth by an employee and includes incest, rape, or a sexual offense in any degree, sodomy, and unnatural or perverted sexual practices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Superintendent" means the individual who manages a facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Youth" means any individual under care in a facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibition of Abuse.</heading>
    <text>Acts of abuse at a facility are prohibited.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Use of Locked Door Seclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility employee may not place a youth in locked door seclusion as punishment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility employee may place a youth in locked door seclusion only:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When it is clearly necessary to protect the youth or other individuals or to prevent escape; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After less restrictive methods have been tried or cannot reasonably be tried.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Time Limitations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A youth may not remain in locked door seclusion more than 24 hours without the review and approval of the superintendent or the duty officer, who shall provide a written explanation for the decision. If one of these administrators was involved in the incident, the other one makes the determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After the decision has been made to keep a youth in locked door seclusion for more than 24 hours, the youth shall be seen by the superintendent or the duty officer at least once during each 12-hour period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The maximum stay in seclusion as a result of a single incident may not exceed 72 hours, unless a declared written emergency is issued by the superintendent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Release. A youth shall be released from locked door seclusion when the youth no longer fits the criteria for placement in locked door seclusion.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Use of Restraints.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility employee may not apply any restraint to a youth as punishment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility employee may apply restraints to a youth only for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The protection of the youth or other individuals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Secure transportation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The prevention of escape.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Facility Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Use by an employee of locked door seclusion or restraint is governed by the policy applicable to the facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility's policy shall address a youth's right to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hearing before an impartial hearing officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advance written notice of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date, time, and location of the hearing, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Availability and name of a child advocate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be heard and present witnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Confront adverse witnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Appeal the decision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Expungement of the records from the youth's file if the youth prevails at the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility's policy, based upon the facility's physical structure and personnel, shall describe:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The permissible locations for locked door seclusion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The supervision that shall be provided when locked door seclusion or restraints are used;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The services or treatment considered appropriate as a result of a youth's conduct; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A process for releasing a youth from locked door seclusion or restraints.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Human Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|9-226">9-226</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|9-229">9-229</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-22">Effective date: June 22, 1992 (19:12 Md. R. 1136)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-06-18">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|16.05.02">COMAR 16.05.02</cite> to <cite path="|16.18.02">COMAR 16.18.02</cite> effective June 18, 2007 (34:12 Md. R. 1067)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
