<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>In-Home Family Services</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|02|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Goals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of In-Home Family Services is to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Promote the safety and well-being of children and their families;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Preserve family unity where children's safety can be supported;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain permanency for children; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Empower families to achieve or sustain independence and self-sufficiency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The goals of In-Home Family Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enhancing the parents' ability to create a safe, stable, and nurturing home environment that promotes healthy child development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Preventing out-of-home placement of children when safety can be promoted to a sufficient proportion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Providing, referring to, and coordinating services needed to achieve or maintain family safety, stability, independence, and unity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department provides a continuum of service programs designed to achieve the purposes and goals of In-Home Family Services and meet the needs of individual families. The programs include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services to Families with Children—Central Intake (SFC-I) or Family Support Services (FSS), as described in <cite path="|07|02|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services to Families with Children—Continuing (SFC-C), as described in <cite path="|07|02|01|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Intensive Family Services (IFS), as described in <cite path="|07|02|01|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Families Now, as described in <cite path="|07|02|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Continuing Protective Services, as described in <cite path="|07|02|01|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Consolidated Family Services, as described in <cite path="|07|02|01|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In each program specified in <cite path="07|02|01|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, services shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Child safety based;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Family focused;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dedicated to work with families as partners;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Built on respect of the family;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Designed to build on family strengths and unity within the context of the family's culture and community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Dedicated to prevent, reduce, or eliminate behaviors, institutional practices, and community conditions that may place a child, family, or community at risk of maltreatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Primarily provided in the home or community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Flexible and based on the changing needs of families and children at various times in their lives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Timely; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Designed to achieve measurable outcomes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The local department may terminate services with the family at any time during the course of the intervention when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The goals have been met and the safety issues have been resolved;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There has been a referral to another unit or agency for service; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The family declines or fails to accept service, safety is not an issue, and other intervention is not warranted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Abuse" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-701">Family Law Article, §5-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="07.02.11.03|B.">COMAR 07.02.11.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Acceptance date" means the day the local department determines that the family is in need of a specific service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Adjudication hearing" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-801">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-801(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Applicant" means an individual who applies for service under the program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Child" has the meaning stated in <cite path="07.02.11.03|B.">COMAR 07.02.11.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Child In Need of Assistance (CINA)" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-801">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-801(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Client Information System (CIS)" means the automated electronic system that maintains data related to services provided by the local department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Custody and guardianship" means court-assigned physical custody, authority, and responsibility for a child for the purpose of providing for the child's physical, social, and emotional needs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Family" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One or more parents and children related by blood, marriage, or adoption, and residing in the same household; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A parent substitute, such as a related or unrelated caregiver or legal guardian, who has responsibility for the 24-hour care and supervision of a child.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Family Support Services—Central Intake" means the centralized services that provide services to families with minor children living in Baltimore City who request those services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Family Support Services (FSS)" means supportive services provided to families with minor children living within the Family Investment Centers catchment areas in Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Flex funds" means those discretionary funds available to a local department in each of the In-Home Family Services programs to purchase goods and services to support a family's service plan when no other resource is available.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Foster care" has the meaning stated in <cite path="07.02.11.03|B.">COMAR 07.02.11.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Imminent risk of out-of-home placement" means that individual who, without specific and timely intervention, will need to be placed in a setting outside of the primary living situation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Income eligibility requirement" means that a family's monthly gross income does not exceed 80 percent of the State's median income, adjusted for family size, according to Schedule A under <cite path="07.02.04.11">COMAR 07.02.04.11</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Indicated" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-701">Family Law Article, §5-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|07.02.07">COMAR 07.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Intensive Family Services (IFS)" means a highly intensive short-term program for children who are at risk of being removed from their homes, which is provided by a team consisting of a social worker and a case associate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Local department" means the local department of social services in a county or Baltimore City, or the Montgomery County Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Maltreatment" means any type of child abuse or child neglect as defined in <cite path="07.02.07.02">COMAR 07.02.07.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Mental injury" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-701">Family Law Article, §5-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|07.02.07">COMAR 07.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Neglect" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-701">Family Law Article, §5-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|07.02.07">COMAR 07.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Out-of-home placement" means the removal of a child from the child's primary home by a representative of the local department for placement in foster care or kinship care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Order of protective supervision" means an order by a court exercising juvenile jurisdiction:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directing the local department to assure that a remedial program is carried out; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Authorizing supervision of the child in the child's own home.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Preplacement prevention service" means those services offered to a family in order to reduce or eliminate the need to place a child in foster care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Record" means the original or a copy of any documentary material, including referral information, formal and informal assessments, recommendations, and closing material, while a family is receiving a particular service within a local department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Ruled out" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-701">Family Law Article, §5-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|07.02.07">COMAR 07.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Return home" has the meaning stated in <cite path="07.02.11.03|B.">COMAR 07.02.11.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"Reunification" has the meaning stated in <cite path="07.02.11.03|B.">COMAR 07.02.11.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Services to Families with Children—Continuing (SFC-C)" means a means test-based program where a family has been assessed by SFC-I and is in need of more extensive service to work toward the efforts of safety, stability, and health of the family.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Services to Families with Children—Central Intake (SFC-I)" means a short-term assessment service for families that are identified as in crisis and at risk of their home dissolving.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"SSA" means the Social Services Administration of the Department of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>"Supportive services" means purchased, provided, or referred assistance to clients that are being served by In-Home Family Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>"Unsubstantiated" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-701">Family Law Article, §5-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|07.02.07">COMAR 07.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>"Voluntary placement" means the temporary placement of a child outside of the primary home by the parent or primary caretaker, in which child and family shall meet the criteria for voluntary placement in <cite path="07.02.11.06">COMAR 07.02.11.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>"Voluntary Placement Agreement (VPA)" means a bonding written agreement between the local department and the parent or guardian.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Scope of Services.</heading>
    <text>In order to achieve family unity within a safe environment for all family members, each In-Home Family Services program can provide, coordinate, or refer families to services including but not limited to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Family, couple, and individual counseling or therapy for assistance in resolving family or parent-child relationship problems;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Substance abuse counseling and referral to substance abuse treatment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Medical evaluations and treatment of a household member;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Child development and parenting skills training;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Family planning counseling;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Health care services or information, such as Early and Periodic Screening, Diagnosis and Treatment (EPSDT);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Support in acquiring proper registration, testing, and appropriate educational services;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Employment counseling;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Vocational training;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Skills building assistance surrounding child care, normal childhood development, age appropriate disciplinary practices, parenting skills, and conflict resolution;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Assistance and support to enhance the likelihood of positive family responsibility and self-sufficiency;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Formal education or educational degree equivalent programs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Housekeeping and home management skills training;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Housing information and assistance;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Emergency financial assistance through flex funds or other available monetary resources;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Budgeting assistance and management training;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Parent-aide or in-home aide services;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Day care assistance;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Respite care;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Transportation assistance;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Assistance with and connection to both formal and informal support systems and resources;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>Skills training in advocating for support and services for self and family;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>W.</num>
      <text>Court involvement;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>X.</num>
      <text>Other services identified for the promotion of family safety and self-sufficiency; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Y.</num>
      <text>When applicable, referrals to other service units, such as Child Protective Services, Family Services, and out-of-home voluntary and involuntary placements.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|02|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Services to Families with Children — Central Intake (SFC-I) or Family Support Services (FSS).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Description.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services to Families with Children—Central Intake or Family Support Services is a voluntary assessment and service provision program for families requesting assistance by preventing further breakdown in family functioning which, if not addressed, might require either Child Protective Services intervention, out-of-home placement, or dissolving of the family unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Use of an approved family assessment designed to identify both the needs, risks, and safety issues of all household members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A mutually agreed upon combination of assistance to help resolve the identified problems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any of the services identified in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Referrals for services to outside vendors in conjunction with Regulation 03 of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A family is eligible for SFC-I or FSS:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Without regard to income;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Who is experiencing a situational crisis brought on by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Catastrophe such as fire, flood, or storm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Loss of income;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Lack of shelter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Domestic violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Physical or mental illness;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Death of or desertion by a significant other, including incarceration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Breakdown in relationship between adult caregivers, which if not addressed could lead to out-of-home placement of the children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Breakdown in the parent-child relationship; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Substance abuse or emotional disturbance of a child or adult household member; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Who is not currently involved with Child Protective Services or LDSS because of alleged or indicated child abuse or neglect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A family who is experiencing barriers in obtaining benefits under the Family Investment Administration's services shall focus on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employment, education, training, family responsibility, and self-sufficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtaining preventive health care for children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Regularly sending school age children to school; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any or all of the services listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Application Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A referral for service can be initiated by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The customer/applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Another agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Another local department or program with a screening and assignment policy in place; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A Family Investment Administration (FIA) supervisor or worker.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 5 working days of receipt of the referral from the Family Investment Administration, the family shall be assigned a worker.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within 7 calendar days of receipt of the referral from the customer/applicant, another agency, local department, or program, a determination shall be made to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accept and initiate service for the family;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contact the family or referring source to discuss:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The immediacy of the need for service;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any delay in implementation of service due to restraints of the Department, such as staff shortage or excessive referrals; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Alternative or intermediate service resources available within the community until such time that the local department can offer service to the family; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Decline the offer for services and notify the referring source.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Within 7 calendar days of the acceptance date, a meeting between the caseworker and family shall take place during which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall complete and sign an application form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The worker and the primary caretaker for the child shall complete and sign a preliminary service agreement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The worker and applicant/customer shall initiate the safety assessment or take appropriate action to ensure safety, if warranted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the customer is unavailable during this time, there shall be clearly recorded documentation with an explanation and new meeting date within the next 7 calendar days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If there are a minimum of three attempted contacts through a combination of on-site visits and certified letters, the local department shall document the attempts and close the case with no further action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Provision of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 7 working days of case acceptance, the worker shall complete the safety assessment for every child.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within the 30 calendar days of service, the worker shall complete a family assessment for all household members, including a sanctioned Maryland Risk Assessment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within the 30 calendar days of service, the caseworker may provide, coordinate, or refer families for any of the services identified in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If continued services are necessary beyond 30 days, and in order to stabilize the family and fulfill the goals of the service agreement, the caseworker shall make the appropriate transfer of service through a locally identified protocol.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At any point within the 30 calendar days, services may be terminated and referred to another unit within the local department, including Child Protective Services or other In-Home Family Service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Duration of Services to Families—Central Intake.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services may continue for up to 30 calendar days from the acceptance date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In order to avoid the transfer to another local department unit and before the 30th calendar day, a worker may formally request up to an additional 15 calendar days through the local department's director or director's designee to finalize the service goals and make referrals to external resources.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Case Disposition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The worker, on or before the 30th calendar day, shall take one of the following actions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Close the case when no other services are required;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide assistance, refer to outside resources, and close;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Formally request an extension;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Refer to continuing SFC-C, after it is determined that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>More extensive services are warranted;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The family wants the service; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The family meets the income eligibility requirement specified in <cite path="07.02.04.03">COMAR 07.02.04.03</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Refer to another local department program by following the appropriate protocol.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The worker shall refer back to the Family Investment Administration once barriers have been eliminated or a determination has been made that services are ineffective in removing barriers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Case Closing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services shall be discontinued and the case closed before the time limits specified in <cite path="07|02|01|.04|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The family declines to accept this voluntary service and there are no safety issues regarding the children in the home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least three documented attempts have been made to contact the family, which includes regular or certified mail, and there has been no response;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Service objectives in the written service agreement have been achieved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The family is not actively progressing toward meeting the objectives of the service agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The family cannot be located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The family moves to another jurisdiction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The family circumstances have changed and there are safety issues and risk factors concerning the children in the home and an appropriate referral has been made to assure safety and reduce risk; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The family has met the service objectives mutually agreed upon, further services are needed to stabilize the family, and the appropriate referral is made.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Before closure, the worker shall offer the family the opportunity to discuss:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for closing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The family's progress;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The need to continue providing services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any referrals made or to be made to other programs or resources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other resources and options available to the family if another crisis should occur in the future.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|02|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Service to Families—Continuing (SF-C).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Description.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services to Families—Continuing is a voluntary, means based, service program for families who have had an initial assessment and it has been determined that additional assistance is needed to prevent further breakdown in family functioning and stability.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services include those identified in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Services to Families with Children— Continuing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To qualify for SFC-C:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A family shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Have had an initial assessment and been determined to be in need of additional support, information, and services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Agree that services are needed and are voluntarily willing to accept and work actively to meet mutually agreed upon goals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Meet the income eligibility requirement specified in <cite path="07.02.04.03">COMAR 07.02.04.03</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Have been experiencing one or more of the conditions or circumstances in <cite path="|07|02|01|.04|B.|(2)">Regulation .04B(2) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>There are no child maltreatment or child safety issues involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When existing barriers to independent living have been identified by the Family Investment Administration for case management services, they may be rectified through Family Services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A family may be referred by local department staff after being assessed to be in need of a more long-term supportive service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A family may be referred by another local department, after agreeing that services are warranted and available for the family.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Referral Process.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A review of the record will be completed to determine the appropriateness of the family for this particular service within 7 calendar days of the date in which the family was referred.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 10 calendar days of the referral for service, a supervisor or the assigned worker shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reviewed the record;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Made contact with the primary caretaker of the family; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identified a date to see all family members, or clearly documented why the meeting could not be accomplished and a new meeting date established within the next 7 calendar days, if the customer is unavailable during this time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the first meeting between the worker and applicant, the worker shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Review what was accomplished with the previous service, to include corresponding plans for family members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Discuss the need for additional service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify preliminary goals, tasks, and a time frame for completion not to exceed 3 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Complete and sign a preliminary service agreement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Complete a safety assessment for each child.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Scope of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The caseworker shall develop and implement a comprehensive service plan to include all other involved agencies or services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Depending upon the family's needs, goals, and progress, there shall be a minimum of three face-to-face contacts per month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any of the services listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite> may be provided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Every 3 months, there shall be a formal reevaluation of service needs with the family including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An updated assessment of risk for all household members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An updated safety assessment for every child in the household; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An alteration of the service and safety plans, as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A redetermination of income eligibility shall be completed every 6 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Services provided shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child safety focused;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Support based;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mutually agreed upon;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Goal oriented;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Developed to build on family and community strengths;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Culturally sensitive; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Provided directly or purchased with flex funds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Duration and Reconsideration of SFC-C. SFC-C may be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provided for up to 6 months after acceptance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extended for 6 months with written authorization of the local department director or the director's designee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Extended for a third 6-month increment of service with written authorization from the local department director, the SSA program manager, or their designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Case Closure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On or before 180th day, the worker shall take the following action:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Close when no other services are needed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide assistance as appropriate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Refer to outside resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Refer to another services program by following the appropriate referral procedures for that program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Request an extension for service of not more than another 6 months in order to accomplish the identified goals made with the family.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services shall be discontinued and the case closed before the time limits specified in <cite path="07|02|01|.05|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Service objectives have been achieved and no safety issues are present;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The family no longer wants this voluntary service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family is not actively progressing toward meeting the objectives of the service agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The family cannot be located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The family moves to another jurisdiction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The family is no longer eligible; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A change in the family's circumstances requires referral to another service program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the plan is to close the case, the worker shall offer the family an interview to discuss:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for the closing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The family's progress;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Continuing or further needs or concerns;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Referrals made or to be made to other programs or resources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other resources and options available to the family if, in the future, the family has a need.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|02|01|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Intensive Family Services (IFS).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Description. IFS is a short-term, highly intensive, non-entitlement in-home service for families whose children:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Are at imminent or high risk of out-of-home placement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have been emergently placed outside of the home within 7 days of service, with the intent of reunification when service is initiated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>IFS uses a social worker, or social worker and parent aide team approach that is most effective when a caseload of six families is maintained per worker or team to provide assistance after a mutually agreed upon service agreement has been developed between the family and the local department team.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Families are served without regard to income.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Families are eligible for services when they:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Are facing crises or problems that will affect the well-being of their children and the stability of the family without assistance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have children:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In the home that may or may not have been determined to be at significant risk of maltreatment; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In voluntary out-of-home placements needing assistance returning home;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Are likely to benefit from a short-term, highly intensive in-home service to avert an out-of-home placement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Are likely to benefit by achieving reunification before the adjudication hearing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Are actively willing to accept assistance to reduce the identified risk or safety factors, or have at least one caretaker who is willing to actively work toward mutually agreed upon goals in an effort to reduce the identified risk factors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Have been assessed by a previous unit or agency to be eligible for the service, with an appropriate safety plan in place for all children determined to be at risk of maltreatment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Have not been served for the same presenting problems within the past 18 months by the local department or a vendor associated with the local department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Application Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Families are eligible for IFS only after an initial assessment has been completed and the eligibility criteria are met.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 24 hours of the referral for service:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The case shall be reviewed by a locally sanctioned, formal review system to determine eligibility and appropriateness of the family for IFS, another In-Home Family Service Program, or service either within the local department or another outside agency resource; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A screener shall assign or transfer the referral for service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within 24 hours of a family's assignment to a worker or team, and not longer than 48 hours from the initial referral:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One or more members of the team shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Review the referral information, including the previous service provision and plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Visit the family's home;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Interview the family members;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Reevaluate all children for risk and safety within their environment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Identify with the family the length of service being provided;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Mutually assess the most immediate service needs; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Initiate a preliminary written and signed service agreement; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the family is not available at the time of the home visit, a team member shall fully document the attempt to make the home visit or the reason why this effort was not made.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At the first meeting, the family shall sign a preliminary service agreement to acknowledge acceptance of service and a willingness to actively participate in working towards safety, stability, and health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Within 7 working days of case assignment, the team and the family members shall negotiate and execute a short term, individualized service plan/agreement to include obtainable goals, tasks, and expected dates of accomplishment within the 90 day service duration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Scope of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>IFS is most effective when the team maintains a small caseload of a maximum of 6 families.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Depending upon the family's individual needs and progress in the treatment process, there shall be up to 20 hours per week of face-to-face contact with a family.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any of the services listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite> may be provided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Services provided directly by the IFS team shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Safety focused;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Support based;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Accessible 24 hours a day, 7 days a week by either direct service staff or a local departmentally sanctioned after-hours caseworker;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Available to all family members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Designed to include the family as team members in planning, developing, implementing, and monitoring the service agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Intensive;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Goal-oriented;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Developed to build on family and community strengths;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Culturally sensitive; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Provided directly through a vendor-supported provider or purchased with flex funds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Duration of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>IFS may be provided for up to 90 calendar days from the date of the family's acceptance for service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services may be extended a maximum of 90 additional days only upon:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Written request by the team, which shall include the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Reason for the extension;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Specific goals and tasks to be identified for both the team and the family members; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Estimated length of time needed to address each additional goal;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Formal review of the request by an endorsed panel within the local department or the director or director's designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Written approval of the extension and length of time approved for continued service from the director of the local department or director's designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Case Closure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services shall be discontinued and the case closed before the time limits specified in <cite path="07|02|01|.06|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The safety of the children is assured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The service objectives have been achieved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family no longer wants this voluntary service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The family cannot be located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The family moves to another jurisdiction; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A change in the family's circumstances requires a referral to another service program such as Continuing Protective Service or Out-of-Home Placement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the plan is to close the case, the worker shall offer the family a face-to-face contact to discuss:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for the closing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A review of the family's progress;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Continuing or further needs or concerns;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Referrals made or to be made to other programs or resources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other resources and options available to the family if, in the future, the family has a need.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Families Now.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Families Now is a voluntary non-entitlement program to families whose children are at risk of removal from their primary home, or have recently been removed from the home and the plan is rapid reunification. Families Now Levels I, II, III, and IV are developed as separate service provision units with varying degrees of intensity and time allotments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Scope of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services provided in any of the Families Now support programs include those listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services shall meet the standards listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.06|E.|(4)">Regulation .06E(4) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Services may be continued beyond the maximum times specified only upon written authorization of the director of the local department or director's designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Families are referred to Families Now by another unit within the local department or another agency that has been providing service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 24 hours of the referral to Families Now, at least one member of the unit shall review the referral and collateral information to determine the appropriateness of the program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An initial, face-to-face contact with the family shall be made within the following time frames:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>24 hours from the receipt of the referral in Level I; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>5 working days from receipt of the referral in Levels II, III, and IV.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If both the caregivers and the children are not available for face-to-face contact, written documentation of all efforts within the required time frame shall be maintained in the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Each child shall be assessed individually for safety during the initial visit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>During the initial contact, the family shall be actively involved in the assessment of both strengths and needs, and shall begin negotiation of the initial service agreement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>By the end of the second face-to-face contact, the local department and the family shall have negotiated and executed a short-term, individualized service plan/agreement to cover a period of not more than 3 months. The agreement shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reviewed, amended, modified, or updated if necessary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Signed by the worker, associate, family, and supervisor every 30 days until service termination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completed and maintained according to specific program regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Families Now—Levels I, II, and III.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Level I is the most intensive service level in the Families Now Program. It is most effective when a small caseload of a maximum of six families is maintained and is designed to assist families in which a child is at imminent risk of out-of-home placement or has been placed out-of-home within the past 7 days, with the intent to reunify at the time service begins. This is offered to families who would benefit from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A short-term, intensive, interactive service for up to a maximum of 90 days; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Up to 20 hours per week of face-to-face contact with the local department staff.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Level II is designed to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Serve families whose children are at imminent or high risk of out-of-home placement or have been placed out-of-home within the past 7 days;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Offer a moderate intensity of service of 1 to 2 visits per week; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide service to a family for up to a maximum of 6 months.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Level III is designed to serve families:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whose children are at high risk of out-of-home placement or have been placed out-of-home within the past 7 days;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Who would benefit from long-term intervention of not more than 1 year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Who can sustain a moderate intensity of 3 to 4 visits per month;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Where there is some resistance to service on the part of one or more household members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Who may be involved with the court as a result of abuse or neglect issues; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Who may have been served in a short-term, intensive voluntary program with limited success.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Families Now—Level IV/Out-of-Home.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Families Now—Level IV/Out-of-Home is designed to serve parents and children while the children are in out-of-home placement in order to expedite reunification or an alternate permanency plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Families are eligible for service if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Their children have been in out-of-home placement for less than 6 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The primary permanency plan at the time of the referral to Families Now is reunification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reunification is expected to occur within 6 months of the referral;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>None of the circumstances detailed in <cite path="07.02.11.16">COMAR 07.02.11.16</cite> exists which would indicate a permanency plan other than reunification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>There are indications that intensive family preservation services would reduce the child's length of stay in out-of-home placement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>There is information to believe that there is willingness on the part of the family to actively work towards reunification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Services may be provided for up to 9 months from the date that the case is accepted for service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All services provided in Families Now—Level IV are regulated under <cite path="07.02.11.03|B.|(46)">COMAR 07.02.11.03B(46)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Redetermination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All families in the Families Now program shall be formally reassessed at the end of each 90 days of service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The review requirements of <cite path="07.02.11.18">COMAR 07.02.11.18</cite> apply to families and children served in Level IV.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When it is jointly determined between the social worker and supervisor that an extension for service is warranted, a formal, written request shall be made to the director or director's designee at least 14 days before the determined closure date. Each request shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A review of why the family is receiving the present service including issues of safety for all children in the home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A review of service provided and justification why all goals were not met; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A new service plan identifying goals, the services to be provided, and the estimated length of time needed in order to complete the service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Written authorization by the director or director's designee shall be provided in order for the family to receive service beyond the mandated time frames designated in <cite path="|07|02|01|.05|D.">Regulation .05D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The maximum time limit for any Families Now service is 1 calendar year within a 3-year period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If further service beyond a maximum of 1 calendar year is determined to be essential, a referral to another unit within the Department shall be made.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Case Closure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services shall be discontinued and the case closed before the time limits specified in this regulation when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Safety of the children is assured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Service objectives have been achieved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family no longer wants the service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The family is not actively progressing toward meeting the objectives of the service agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Agency related court involvement has been terminated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The family cannot be located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The family has moved to another jurisdiction, and the local department refers them for service or closes the case with no further follow-up; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>A change in the family's circumstances requires referral to another service program such as Continuing Protective Services or Out-of-Home Placement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the plan is to close the case, the worker shall offer the family an interview to discuss:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for the closing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A review of any safety planning made for the child;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A review of the family's progress;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Continuing or any other further needs or concerns;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Referrals made or to be made to other programs or resources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other resources and options available to the family if, in the future, the family has a need.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Continuing Protective Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Continuing Protective Services is a non-entitlement specialized, time limited, goal-oriented service designed to develop positive, nurturing parent-child relationships for families when children remain at home, when there has been a determination that risk for further maltreatment is significant. This population has either previously been served in another In-Home Family Services program, a similar program outside of the local department, or a program ordered by the court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The purpose of Continuing Protective Services is to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide protection to children, while providing services to their families;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reduce the degree of risk of maltreatment, while children remain safely in their homes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop a safety plan for children with other family or household members, when parents or other caretakers are unwilling or unable to change; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Remove children from the home, when it is determined that safety will not or cannot be provided, and the child is at imminent risk of harm or has incurred further harm by a family or household member.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Families are served without regard to income.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The court may order services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Families are eligible when other in-home family services have been offered and the family declines the service, and the local department determines that services are necessary to reduce risk factors associated with the care of the child.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Families may be referred by another in-home family service after support has either been offered or provided and the children residing in the home remain at risk of maltreatment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Families may be referred directly from Child Protective Services-Investigations when risk factors remain, in order to assure safety of the children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Families may be served when children are determined to be at risk of maltreatment, families are resistant to service, and court intervention is not appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Families shall be served when the court has intervened and determined that services are essential.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Application Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Referrals can be made directly by Child Protective Services Investigations, any other In-Home Family Service, another local department, or the court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the time of transfer, the following information shall be available to the supervisor and assigned worker:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Documentation showing the initial reason for intervention by the local department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of any assessment of the family, to include past services provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A recently completed risk assessment and corresponding safety plan detailing the action taken to stabilize the family and protect the children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documentation to indicate the need for Continuing Protective Services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Documentation of face-to-face contact with the family within 7 calendar days of the closing and transfer from the previous service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Initial Contact</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contact shall be made with a family member within 5 working days or 9 calendar days of the transfer to Continuing Protective Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When possible, a joint transfer visit shall be made with the family by the investigating caseworker and continuing caseworker.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the first visit, a service plan/agreement shall also be initiated with the family.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Provision and Scope of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For the first 30 days, there shall be contact with the family at least once a week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After the first 30 days, the local department shall have at least 2 contacts per month with each family member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>During each contact, all children shall be seen individually and separately from the caregiver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The continuing caseworker shall review, clarify, and make appropriate modifications to the safety plan with the family during this time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At the end of each contact, the worker shall document the ongoing assessment for the safety of each child.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Within 45 calendar days from the acceptance date, the worker and the family shall have completed and signed a service plan/agreement to cover a period not longer than 6 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any of the services listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> may be provided either directly, through a referral to another agency, or contractually through flex funds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Services shall meet the standards listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.04|A.|(2)">Regulation .04A(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The local department may petition the court at any time during the course of service when the safety of the children cannot be assured or the caretaker is not actively working toward a resolution of the problem, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>If the court is involved with the family at the time service is initiated, periodic status reports and an agency court appearance is warranted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The local department may remove a child from the home at any time when reasonable efforts had been made to assure child safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Duration of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Continuing Protective Services are to be provided until:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any concerns for safety have been satisfied and the risk of maltreatment minimized;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The child is removed from the home by either a court order or voluntarily, and the child is safe from harm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family refuses services, the degree of risk is minimal, and the court has declined to accept involvement with the local department or sanctioned service; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The child becomes 18 years old.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the end of every 3 months of service, the supervisor and caseworker shall formally review the safety, progress, and service plan for the family and make appropriate changes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Service shall be provided to the family for up to 12 calendar months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Extension.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the family is determined to need service beyond 12 months, an administrative review shall be requested for an extension at least 30 days before the predetermined closure date.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A written request shall be made by the caseworker to the director or director's designee and include the reason for need, a plan of action, and an estimated time for closure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The case shall remain open only upon written approval by the director or the director's designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The written approval shall provide the conditions and time frame for the extended service time to the family.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A copy of the extension request shall be maintained in the record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Case Closing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At any point, Continuing Protective Services may be terminated when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Risk of maltreatment has been reduced and safety has been assured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The family is functioning marginally, but the risks to the child are insufficient to justify court action and the family refuses to utilize services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>There is sufficient reason to remove the child from the home and to place the child in an environment that can assure safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If, during the course of service, the family relocates outside of the jurisdiction of the LDSS, and it is determined that continued intervention is necessary, the local department where the family has relocated shall be notified immediately both by telephone and written communication to request service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the plan is to close the case, the caseworker shall meet with the family to discuss the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for closing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The safety plan that has been established for the child;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family's progress and any further concerns; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The resources and options available to the family within their community.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Consolidated Family Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Consolidated Family Services is the blending of Families Now, Intensive Family Services, and Continuing Protective Services to achieve a seamless continuum of services in an effort to better service families whose children are at risk of out-of-home placement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Families are served without regard to income.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The court may order services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Families may be referred by another service after support has either been offered or provided and the children residing in the home remain at risk of maltreatment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Families may be served when children are determined to be at risk of maltreatment, families are resistant to service, and court intervention is not appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Families shall be served when the court has intervened and determined that services are essential.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Referrals can be made directly by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child Protective Services Investigations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any other In Home Family Service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Another department of social services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the time of transfer, the following information shall be available to the supervisor and assigned worker:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Documentation showing the initial reason for intervention by the local department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of any assessment of the family, to include past services provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A recently completed risk assessment and corresponding safety plan, detailing the action taken to stabilize the family and protect the children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documentation to indicate the need for services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Documentation of face-to-face contact with the family within 7 calendar days of the closing and transfer from the previous service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Initial Contact.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contact shall be made with family members within 5 working days or 9 calendar days of the transfer to Consolidated Family Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When possible, a joint transfer visit shall be made with the family by the investigating caseworker and continuing caseworker.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the first visit, a service plan/agreement shall also be initiated with the family.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Provision and Scope of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For the first 30 days, there shall be contact with the family at least once per week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After the first 30 days, the local department shall have at least two contacts a month with each family member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>During each contact all children shall be seen individually and separately from the caregiver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The continuing caseworker shall review, clarify, and make appropriate modifications to the safety plan with the family during this time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At the end of each contact, the worker shall document the ongoing assessment for the safety of each child.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Within 45 calendar days from the acceptance date, the worker and the family shall have completed and signed a service plan/agreement to cover a period not longer than 3 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any of the services listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> may be provided either directly, through a referral to another agency, or contractually through flex funds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Services shall meet the standards listed in <cite path="|07|02|01|.04|A.|(2)">Regulation .04A(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The local department may petition the court at any time during the course of service when the safety of the children cannot be assured or the caretaker is not actively working toward a resolution of the problem, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>If the court is involved with the family at the time service is initiated, periodic status reports and agency court appearances are warranted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The local department may remove a child from the home at any time when reasonable efforts have been made to assure the child's safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Duration of Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services are to be provided until:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Concerns for safety have been satisfied and the risk of maltreatment minimized;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The child is removed from the home by either court order or voluntarily, and the child is safe from harm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family refuses services, the degree of risk is minimal, and the court has declined to accept involvement with the local department or sanctioned service; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The child becomes 18 years old.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the end of every 3 months of service, the supervisor and caseworker shall formally review the safety, progress, and service plan for the family and make appropriate changes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Service shall be provided to the family for up to 6 calendar months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Extension.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the family is determined to need service for longer than 6 months, an administrative review shall be requested for an extension at least 30 days before the predetermined closure date.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A written request shall be made by the caseworker to the director or director's designee to include the reason for need, a plan of action, and an estimated time for closure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The case shall remain open only upon written approval by the director or director's designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The written approval shall provide the conditions and time frame for the extended service time to the family.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A copy of the extension request shall be maintained in the record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Case Closing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At any point, services may be terminated when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The risk of maltreatment has been reduced and safety has been assured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The family is functioning marginally, but the risks to the child are insufficient to justify court action and the family refuses to utilize services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>There is sufficient reason to remove the child from the home and be placed in an environment that can assure safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If, during the course of service, the family relocates outside of the jurisdiction of the local department, and it is determined that continued intervention is necessary, that local department where the family has relocated shall be notified immediately both by telephone and written communication to request service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the plan is to close the case, the caseworker shall meet with the family to discuss the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for closing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The safety plan that has been established for the child;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The family's progress and any further concerns; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The resources and options available to the family within their community.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Flex Funds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To access flex funds on behalf of a family, the worker shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine that the goods or services to be purchased cannot be obtained without cost to the local department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Document in the case record how the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Goods or services to be purchased support the service plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Family meets the eligibility criteria and is active in the family service program to which the expenditure is being charged;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Family will benefit from the specified purchase; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Specified purchase will directly contribute to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The child's health and welfare;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Preventing the child's out-of-home placement; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Reunifying the child who has been placed out-of-home.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Families shall be encouraged to contribute toward the cost of purchased items to the extent possible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approval of Expenditures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The supervisor and the local department director or director's designee may approve all expenditures of flex funds after reviewing the documentation and verifying the appropriateness of the expenditure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Flex fund expenditures exceeding $1,000 per item require the local department director's or director's designee's signature.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All purchases require the local department to comply with <cite path="|21.05.07">COMAR 21.05.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Documentation of the appropriateness of the expenditure shall include written verification of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Delivery of the item by the vendor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Receipt of the item by the family.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Flex funds may be used to purchase goods and services including, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Parenting education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Psychiatric or psychological evaluation, testing, and treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Drug or alcohol rehabilitation services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vocational training and employment counseling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Clinical consultation for staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Therapeutic family recreation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Assistance in developing a support network for the family;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Assistance in locating and obtaining housing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Reimbursement for reasonable transportation costs for family visits, treatment, or employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Special educational services such as tutoring, G.E.D. classes, tuition, and standardized test preparation fees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Personal care supplies, such as clothing and personal hygiene items;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Day care services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Security deposits and rental assistance on housing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Deposits or emergency grants to avoid utility terminations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Medical services or equipment not covered by medical assistance or other resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Learning aids such as flash cards, books, games, and computers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Respite care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Automobile operating or maintenance costs to enable employment, treatment, or family visitation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Essential household items such as sheets, blankets, furniture such as beds, tables, and chairs, and appliances such as a stove or refrigerator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Essential household supplies such as brooms, mops, and cleaning supplies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>Employment tools and equipment, uniforms, and footwear; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>Other items determined to be essential in maintaining the safety and welfare of the family.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Items such as beds or clothing purchased with flex funds for a child who is temporarily residing outside of the primary home are considered the child's possessions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>When multiple purchases of similar items whose individual cost exceeds $250 per unit are expected to exceed $5,000 in aggregate cost during the fiscal year, the local department shall solicit competitive bids and enter into written contracts with selected vendors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The maximum annual expenditure of flex funds per family may not exceed 80 percent of the average cost of foster care placement for each at-risk child in the family.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The local department shall submit reports of expenditures of flex funds to SSA within 20 days of the close of each quarter of the fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Appeal Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Decisions of the local department with respect to In-Home Family Services Programs may be appealed as specified in the fair hearing provisions of <cite path="|07.02.02">COMAR 07.02.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The local department shall give written and oral notification of the right to and the methods of requesting and obtaining a fair hearing to each applicant for and to each recipient of In-Home Family Services:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the time of application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whenever the local department notifies the applicant or recipient of any pending action that may deny, suspend, reduce, or terminate the service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A fair hearing need not be held on any decision which has been, or may only be, determined by a court.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-801">3-801</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-820">3-820</cite>; Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-524">5-524</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-525">5-525</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-704">5-704</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-709">5-709</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-713">5-713</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference: 42 U.S.C. §620 et seq.; 45 CFR 1355—1357</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-05-04">Effective date: May 4, 1979 (6:9 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1986-10-06">Regulations .06E and .07 amended effective October 6, 1986 (13:20 Md. R. 2207)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-01-08" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|07|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|02|01|.09">.09</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|07|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|02|01|.07">.07</cite> adopted effective January 8, 1990 (16:26 Md. R. 2787)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-02" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|07|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|02|01|.07">.07</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|07|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|02|01|.11">.11</cite> adopted effective September 2, 2002 (29:17 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01"><cite path="|07|02|01|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
