<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>22</num>
  <heading>Family Support Center Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of a family support center program is to provide parents and their children with a hospitable and constructive environment to provide or coordinate services which:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Improve parenting skills;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Develop the family as a functioning unit; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Promote the growth and development of their children.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Social Services Administration of the Department of Human Services as staff to the Subcabinet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Applicant" means a parent who has applied to receive services from one of the family support centers in the network.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Center" means a family support center operated by a provider under a contract with the Intermediary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Intermediary" means the agency that provides management for the operation of the State's network of community-based family support centers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Parent" means the mother or father of a child and includes a single youth who is at risk of early or unplanned parenthood.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Provider" means an agency or individual who contracts with the Intermediary to operate a center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Subcabinet" means the Subcabinet for Children, Youth and Families established under Article 49D, §4.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Temporary Cash Assistance (TCA)" means a form of cash assistance provided to assistance units that are technically and financially eligible.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility for the Program.</heading>
    <text>Any parent may use the center.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Delivery of Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A center shall provide directly, by purchase or other arrangement, services to include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Parenting skills, parent education classes, and other activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Health care counselling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Diagnostic and assessment services to identify developmental problems of the young parent and of the child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Child care as necessary to allow participation in the Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Peer support activities, including recreational and social activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Educational services such as GED and post-high school classes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Pre-employment counselling and skill development, to assist the parent in securing and maintaining employment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The center shall plan and provide services to both parents, their children, grandparents, and other family members, to the extent possible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The center may provide other services when approved by the Intermediary.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Requirements for a Center.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before operating a center, the provider shall submit to the Intermediary a program plan which describes the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services to be provided;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Manner in which the services are provided;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Staff to carry out the program and training plans for the staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The provider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall employ staff of the type and qualifications as required by the program plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May use volunteers in the program and train and supervise them as required by the program plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall operate the center during the day, evenings, and weekends as necessary to meet the parents' needs according to the program plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The program plan shall describe the methods to be used to refer parents to other agencies that provide services not available at the center.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Records and Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The center shall maintain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A record of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Attendance at the center,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Expenditures to be reimbursed by the designated State fiscal agent,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Services provided; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other records as required by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Intermediary shall send to the Administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A written monthly report of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Center attendance, including number of TCA customers serviced,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Expenditures to be reimbursed by the designated State fiscal agent,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Types of services provided; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Copies of reports made by the center to other agencies or organizations, including private foundations and the Maryland Legislature.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The provider shall maintain the records and reports of grievance decisions for inspection by the Intermediary and Administration.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Grievance Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The provider shall include in the program plan a description of the grievance system in each center available to parents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The grievance system shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A written decision to parents by the provider resolving the grievance, and the procedures for appealing to the Intermediary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written decision to parents by the Intermediary reviewing the decision of the provider, and the procedures for appealing to the Office of Administrative Hearings; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A written communication to the Administration containing the results of the grievance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant for services may appeal to the Office of Administrative Hearings for a fair hearing in the following situations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant's complaint is not resolved by the provider's grievance system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant is denied services; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant disagrees with the manner or form of the provisions of service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Office of Administrative Hearings fair hearing process shall conform to the procedures in <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Article 88A, §§3 and 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-04-06">Effective date: April 6, 1987 (14:7 Md. R. 829)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|07|02|22|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|07|02|22|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective December 26, 1988 (15:26 Md. R. 2981); October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|07|02|22|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|07|02|22|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|07|02|22|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
