<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Legislative Branch Buildings and Grounds in Annapolis</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>These regulations are in addition to <cite path="|04.05.01">COMAR 04.05.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>These regulations apply only to the buildings, improvements, and grounds of the Legislative Branch in Annapolis under the jurisdiction of the Department of General Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following areas are further subject to the procedural rules of the Senate and House of Delegates:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chambers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lounges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lobbies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Committee rooms;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Joint Hearing Room; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Appurtenant areas.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="04|05|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Demonstrations and Rallies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to the conditions below, demonstrations, rallies, and solicitation, whether or not by permit, may be held during regular business hours, but may not be scheduled to start after 8 p.m., or finish after 9 p.m., except when sessions of the Senate or House of Delegates run beyond 9 p.m.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Demonstrations and rallies may be conducted at Lawyers’ Mall in front of the State House between the Legislative Services Building and Government House. The areas posted as fire lanes may not be obstructed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In case of preemption or conflicting scheduling of Lawyers’ Mall, demonstrations may be conducted in other nearby outdoor areas if agreeable with the applicant for the demonstration permit and the Secretary or the Chief of the Maryland Capitol Police.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Demonstrations or rallies outside State property may require separate approval of the Mayor of Annapolis through the Annapolis Police Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Groups of 15 or more persons wishing to hold demonstrations or rallies or engage in solicitation should apply in writing at least 2 days in advance to the superintendent or manager for a permit, unless extraordinary circumstances prevent the applications. Groups of less than 15 persons may hold demonstrations or rallies or engage in solicitation without a permit, space permitting, subject to the same conditions in this regulation, but an individual or group holding a permit will have priority over an individual or group without a permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Permits shall be issued at no cost to the applicant on a first-come, first-served basis. The Secretary or the Chief of the Maryland Capitol Police may not refuse to issue a permit based on the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject matter of the demonstration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applicant; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lateness of the permit application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Subject to <cite path="04|05|02|.02|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, and except as provided elsewhere in this Title, the following activities are not prohibited at Lawyers’ Mall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Distribution of literature, materials, and merchandise for the exposition of ideas and opinions in the exercise of freedom of speech, association, assembly, and religion, but excluding purely commercial materials; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Solicitation of funds for lawful, non-commercial purposes or the collection of petition signatures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall indicate whether solicitation for charitable contributions will occur and, if so, indicate whether the applicant is properly registered under the Maryland Solicitation Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or exempt from registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The applicant or any participant engaging in solicitation of funds shall inform donors whether the contribution is tax deductible, a contribution under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|1-101">§1-101(o) of the Election Law Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a gift.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Secretary or the Chief of the Maryland Capitol Police shall have discretion only as to matters of scheduling, safety, security, and traffic.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The applicant should designate, by name, at least one individual to be present at the demonstration who will wear an armband or other identifying insignia and be responsible for advising the demonstrators on compliance with applicable laws and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Battery operated sound systems may be used, but the State may not provide extra electricity or lighting. Signs and placards are permitted, but signs and placards mounted on sticks and poles are not permitted. Applicants must comply with all local noise ordinances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>An individual may not possess a firearm within 1,000 feet of a demonstration on the property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>The following activities are prohibited at Lawyers’ Mall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Erecting any structures including tents, canopies, or structures; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Climbing on, removing, or damaging any memorial, statue, architectural feature, tree, or landscaping.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Interference with Legislative Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual or group may not willfully disrupt or interfere with, or attempt to disrupt or interfere with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A session of the General Assembly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Senate or the House of Delegates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any of the Senate's or House of Delegates' committees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An officer, employee, or staff member of the General Assembly; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A member of the Senate or House of Delegates in the member's performance of any official function.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual may not willfully picket in a building where:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Senate or House of Delegates has a chamber;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A member of the General Assembly has an office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A committee of the General Assembly or the House of Delegates has an office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Communications with General Assembly Members.</heading>
    <text>Nothing in this or other regulations shall prohibit citizens and small groups of citizens from communicating with the General Assembly in a reasonable and orderly manner, including delivery of handbills, pamphlets, letters, and small symbolic objects to members or members' offices.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">United States Constitution, Amendments 1 and 14; Maryland Constitution, Declaration of Rights, Article 13;<br/>Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|4-208">4-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|6-409">6-409</cite>; State Finance and Procurement Article, §§4-604(6) and (7) and 4-607(a) and (c);<br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1702">State Government Article, §2-1702</cite>;  Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-10-10">Effective date: October 10, 1994 (21:20 Md. R. 1731)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|04|05|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 25, 2019 (46:4 Md. R. 190); April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
