<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>State Depository of Plans</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following words have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Area plan" means the approved, officially adopted statement of a legislative body, chief executive, or regional council that sets forth major policies concerning future physical development for a planning area smaller than the jurisdiction as a whole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Planning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Depository" means the State Depository of Plans established by the Department in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|5-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §5-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Functional Plan.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Functional plan" means the approved, officially adopted statement of a legislative body, chief executive, or regional council that sets forth major policies concerning one specific aspect of future physical development, generally on a jurisdiction-wide basis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Functional plan" may address governmental services, such as sewerage and water, fire and police stations, education, or parks and recreation, or it may address development issues, such as historic and agricultural preservation, housing, economic development, community renewal, transportation, or water quality.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Functional plan" has a physical dimension. It does not consist solely of service provision programs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>General Plan.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"General plan" means the approved, officially adopted statement of a legislative body, chief executive, or regional council that sets forth major policies concerning future physical development for the entire geographic area of the jurisdiction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"General plan" includes the following primary elements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Land use element;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Transportation element; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Community facilities element.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"General plan" is based on demographic, economic, and physical surveys and projections that are integral to, but may not be included in, the plan document itself.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The term "general plan" does not include legal and programmatic documents, such as subdivision regulations, zoning ordinances, and capital improvement programs. However, these documents are based on the general plan, are guided by it, and are the basic tools to implement it. Thus, these documents are integral parts of the jurisdiction's physical development process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Purpose of Depository.</heading>
    <text>The Depository is a resource center, not only for the Department, but for all State, interstate, regional, and local government agencies, as well as for citizens, interest groups, government consultants, and others. Plans and supporting documentation are available at the Depository for reference and study. The Depository offers a unique opportunity to review at one location collected government planning documents for the State or any portion of the State.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Location of and Access to Depository.</heading>
    <text>The Depository is located in the central office of the Department. The contents of the Depository are available, during regular office hours, for examination and use by individuals and representatives of government agencies and private organizations. Information concerning the Depository may be obtained from the Librarian, Department of Planning, Room 1101, 301 West Preston Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21201.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Submission of Material to Depository.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General, Area, and Functional Plans. The agency charged with responsibility for issuing any general, area, or functional plan shall submit a copy of the plan, and a copy of any amendment or revision to the plan, to the Depository.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Implementing Regulations, Ordinances, and Programs. The agency responsible for issuing any regulations, ordinance, or program to implement a general, area, or functional plan shall submit a copy of the regulations, ordinance, or program, and a copy of any amendment or revision, to the Depository.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Time for Submission. An agency shall submit material described in §A or B of this regulation as the material is adopted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Number of Copies. Unless the Department asks for two copies, the submitting agency shall submit one copy. If the Department asks for two copies, the submitting agency shall submit two copies. The submitting agency need not submit more than two copies of any material.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Address for Submission. An agency shall submit material described in §§A and B of this regulation to the following address: State Depository of Plans, Department of Planning, 301 West Preston Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21201.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Publications Contact Person. Each agency that is required to submit material to the Depository shall designate a publications contact person and provide the name, address, and telephone number of that person to the Depository. In the case of a State agency, this person may, but need not, be the same person designated as the agency publications contact person under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|23-303">Education Article, §23-303(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of Depository.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice to Submitting Agencies. The Depository shall send a notice at least annually to submitting agencies, informing them of the requirements stated in Regulation .04.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>List of Materials Received.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least monthly, the Depository shall issue a list of all materials that it has received.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Single copies of the list will be distributed on request, free of charge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Depository may establish a subscription service for the list. The Department may charge subscribers a reasonable fee to cover the costs of postage and handling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Retention Policy. The Depository shall retain all materials received under this chapter for at least 5 years, unless the materials are clearly superseded by later editions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Time of Availability. The Depository shall make materials received under this chapter available within 30 days after receipt.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|5-502">State Finance and Procurement Article, §5-502, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-30">Effective date: December 30, 1977 (4:27 Md. R. 2108)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|16.00.05">COMAR 16.00.05</cite> to <cite path="|16.01.02">COMAR 16.01.02</cite></annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-11-30">Chapter revised effective November 30, 1987 (14:24 Md. R. 2557)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|16.01.02">COMAR 16.01.02</cite> to <cite path="|14.24.02">COMAR 14.24.02</cite> in July 1, 1989</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-10" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|14.24.02">COMAR 14.24.02</cite> to <cite path="|34.01.03">COMAR 34.01.03</cite> effective March 10, 2009</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
