<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following activities are exempt from regulation under this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appearances as part of the official duties of an elected or appointed official or employee of the State, a political subdivision of the State, or the United States, to the extent that the appearance is not on behalf of another entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Actions of a member of the news media, to the extent the actions are in the ordinary course of gathering and disseminating news or making editorial comment to the general public;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Representation of a bona fide religious organization to the extent the representation is for the purpose of protecting the right of its members to practice the doctrine of the organization;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Appearances as part of the official duties of an officer, director, member, or employee of an association engaged exclusively in representing counties or municipal corporations, to the extent that the appearance is not on behalf of another entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Actions as part of the official duties of a trustee, an administrator, or a faculty member of a nonprofit independent college or university in the State, if the official duties of the individual do not consist primarily of attempting to influence legislative action or executive action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Activities by attorneys who are not employed by an organized bar as regulated lobbyists, in the course of serving as an officer, committee or section chair, or representative designated to represent a section, committee, or an organized bar at large, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Testimony before either the Senate or the House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Testimony before a committee or subcommittee of the Senate or the House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Communication with an official or employee of the Legislative Branch or Executive Branch in the presence of that official or employee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Communication with an official or employee of the Legislative Branch or Executive Branch not in the presence of that official or employee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following activities are exempt from regulation under this chapter if the person engages in no other acts for an employer during the reporting period that require registration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appearances before a legislative committee at the specific request of a regulated lobbyist, if the witness notifies the committee that the witness is testifying at the request of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appearances before an executive unit at the specific request of a regulated lobbyist, if the witness notifies the executive unit that the witness is testifying at the request of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An elementary, secondary, or postsecondary school student or student organization that communicates as part of a course or student activity based solely on the expense threshold in <cite path="|19A|07|01|.02|A.|(1)">Regulation .02A(1) of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Professional services in drafting bills or in advising clients on the construction or effect of proposed or pending legislation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Appearances before the entire General Assembly, or any committee or subcommittee of the General Assembly, at the specific request of the body involved; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Appearances before an executive unit at the specific request of the executive unit involved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person that compensates one or more regulated lobbyists for the purpose of lobbying is exempt from the registration and reporting requirements of this chapter if the person:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Engages in no other act that requires registration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reasonably believes that all expenditures requiring registration will be reported by the regulated lobbyist or lobbyists.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Registration Required.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Persons engaged in the following activities shall register with the Ethics Commission and are regulated lobbyists for the purposes of this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attempting to influence legislative action, or executive action related to the development or adoption of regulations or the development or issuance of an executive order by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Communicating with an official or employee of the Legislative Branch or Executive Branch in the presence of that official or employee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exclusive of the personal travel or subsistence expenses of the entity or a representative of the entity, incurring expenses of at least $500, calculated per employer, or earning at least $2,500, from all employers cumulatively, as compensation for the communication, and activities relating to the communication, during the reporting period;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attempting to influence legislative action, or executive action related to the development or adoption of regulations or the development or issuance of an executive order by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Communicating with an official or employee of the Legislative Branch or Executive Branch; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Earning at least $5,000 from all employers cumulatively, as compensation for the communication, and activities relating to the communication, during the reporting period;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In connection with or for the purpose of influencing any executive action, spending a cumulative value of at least $100 for gifts to one or more officials or employees of the Executive Branch, including gifts for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Beverages; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Special events;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Receiving compensation to influence executive action on a procurement contract that exceeds $100,000, unless the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is a bona fide salesperson or commercial selling agency employed or maintained by an employer for the purposes of soliciting or securing a procurement contract; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has not engaged in acts during the reporting period that require registration under this subtitle;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Receiving compensation from a business entity to influence executive action to secure from the State a business grant or loan with a value of more than $100,000 for the business entity unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person has engaged in no other acts during the reporting period that require registration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The person:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is a bona fide full-time official or employee of a business entity seeking to secure a business grant or loan; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Seeks to secure a business grant or loan for the purpose of locating, relocating, or expanding a business in or into the State;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Spending at least $2,000 for the express purpose of soliciting others to communicate with an official to influence legislative action or executive action, including expenditures for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Salaries;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contractual employees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Postage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Telecommunications services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Electronic services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Advertising;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Printing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Delivery services; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Spending at least $2,500 to provide compensation to one or more persons required to register under this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a regulated lobbyist compensated by an employer that is exempt under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.01|C.">Regulation .01C of this chapter</cite> fails to report the information required by this chapter, the employer immediately shall be subject to the registration and reporting requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Authority to Lobby.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A regulated lobbyist engaged by an entity for the purpose of lobbying shall certify under oath or affirmation that the regulated lobbyist is authorized to engage in lobbying for the entity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The certification of authorization to act under <cite path="19A|07|01|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The full legal name and business address of the entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, contact information and the official title of the representative of the entity who authorized the regulated lobbyist to engage in lobbying for the entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The full legal name and business address of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Subject to subsequent modification, the period during which the regulated lobbyist is authorized to act; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The proposal or subject on which the regulated lobbyist represents the entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Registration with Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each regulated lobbyist shall register with the Ethics Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Separately for each employer that has engaged the regulated lobbyist for lobbying purposes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using the electronic registration system provided by the Ethics Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each registration shall include, if applicable:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The regulated lobbyist's name and permanent address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name and permanent address of each other regulated lobbyist that will be lobbying on the regulated lobbyist's behalf;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and nature of business of the employer that has engaged the regulated lobbyist for lobbying purposes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A statement indicating if, because of the filing and reporting of the regulated lobbyist, the compensating entity is exempt from registration under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.01|C.">Regulation .01C of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The identity of any other person that the regulated lobbyist will represent regarding the matters covered by the registration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The specific identification, by issue including bill number, regulation number, State contract, or other matter, if known, of the matters on which the regulated lobbyist expects to perform acts, or to engage another regulated lobbyist to perform acts, that require registration under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If applicable, each registration shall include the certification required by <cite path="|19A|07|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A regulated lobbyist shall register with the Ethics Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 days after first performing an act that requires registration under this chapter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On or before November 1 of each year if on that date the lobbyist has not yet submitted a new registration and the lobbyist is engaged in lobbying activity which will continue in the upcoming lobbying reporting period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each registration shall be accompanied by a fee in the amount established by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-704">General Provisions Article, §5-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The fee shall be credited to the Lobbyist Registration Fund.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Termination of Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each registration shall terminate on the earlier of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>October 31 following the filing of the registration; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An earlier termination date specified in the lobbyist registration form.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A regulated lobbyist may terminate the registration before the date specified in <cite path="19A|07|01|.04|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite> by notifying the Ethics Commission that the regulated lobbyist has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ceased all activity that requires registration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Filed a notice of termination with the Ethics Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Filed all reports required by this subtitle within 30 days after the filing of the notice of termination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Registration — Lobbyists Serving on Boards and Commissions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="19A|07|01|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, if a regulated lobbyist becomes an official or State employee, the regulated lobbyist shall immediately terminate the registration in accordance with <cite path="|19A|07|01|.04|F.">Regulation .04F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Section A of this regulation does not apply to a regulated lobbyist who becomes a public official solely by the regulated lobbyist's appointment to a board or commission subject to the jurisdiction of the Ethics Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Lobbyist Disclosure — Boards and Commissions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the time a regulated lobbyist is appointed to serve on a board or commission subject to the jurisdiction of the Ethics Commission, or at the time a board or commission member becomes subject to the lobbying regulations, the regulated lobbyist shall file a report:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar days of the dual status measured from later of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date of registration as a lobbyist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date of oath of office as a member of the board or commission; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If no oath of office is required, the date of official notification of appointment by the appointing authority;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using the electronic registration system provided by the Ethics Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Under penalty of perjury;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>With a copy sent to the Appointing Authority; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Providing the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For any current representation of a person for compensation before a State governmental unit, except in a judicial or quasi-judicial proceeding:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The person or entity represented for compensation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The name of the State agency;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The services performed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The monetary consideration;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For any current representation of a State agency for compensation, any contractual relationship with State government, or any transaction with State government for monetary consideration:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The name of the agency or governmental unit with which the regulated lobbyist has a financial relationship; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The services performed or details of any contractual relationship or the transaction entered into;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For any current interest held by the regulated lobbyist, the regulated lobbyist’s spouse or dependent children, together or separately having either 10 percent or more of the capital stock, or stock worth $35,000 or more, in a corporation subject to regulation by or doing business with the board or commission, or any interest in a partnership, limited liability partnership, or limited liability company subject to regulation by or doing business with the board or commission:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The name of the immediate family member and relationship for any interest held together or separately;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The name of the corporation, partnership, limited liability partnership, or limited liability company; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The nature of the interest held;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The primary employer of the spouse of the regulated lobbyist; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The name of any business entity from which the regulated lobbyist or the spouse of the regulated lobbyist receives earned income as a result of an ownership interest in the business.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The regulated lobbyist shall update the information required by <cite path="19A|07|01|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> as required to reflect the regulated lobbyist's current registrations throughout each reporting period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Whenever an issue arises within the board or commission related to the information disclosed in accordance with <cite path="19A|07|01|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the regulated lobbyist member shall submit a statement of recusal from discussion of, voting on, or any other action required by the circumstances concerning the issue:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On a form provided by the Ethics Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To the board or commission for inclusion in the minutes of the meeting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The subject area of the conflict; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The reason for the recusal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to the disclosure requirements set forth in this regulation, regulated lobbyists who are public officials solely because of their participation on boards or commissions are subject to the conflict of interest requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Lobbying Activity Reporting Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Activity Reports Required.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A regulated lobbyist shall file with the Ethics Commission a separate report for each registration disclosing the regulated lobbyist's lobbying activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A regulated lobbyist who has no lobbying activity related to an employer specified on a registration during a reporting period shall file a report with the Commission disclosing the lack of activity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each report shall be filed electronically and shall be made by verifiable electronic signature in the report and made expressly under penalty of perjury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each report shall be filed by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May 31 of each year, to cover the period from November 1 of the previous year through April 30 of the current year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>November 30 of each year, to cover the period from May 1 through October 31 of that year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each lobbying activity report required by this section shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A complete, current statement of the information required under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Total expenditures in connection with influencing executive action or legislative action in each of the following categories:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Total individual regulated lobbyist's compensation, excluding the expenses reported in §B(2)(b)—(l) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Office expenses of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Professional and technical research and assistance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Publications that expressly encourage communication with one or more officials or employees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Witnesses, including the name of each and the fees and expenses paid to each;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Meals and beverages for officials, employees, or members of the immediate families of officials or employees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If a full and final accounting has not been provided in accordance with <cite path="|19A|07|01|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> in the post-event report, an accurate and final report of food, beverages, and incidental expenses spent on behalf of officials of the Legislative Branch for meals and receptions to which all members of any legislative unit were invited, including the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Location; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Total expense of the regulated lobbyist for each meal, reception, event, or meeting;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Food and beverages for members of the General Assembly at the respective times and geographic locations of meetings of legislative organizations, to which meetings those members' attendance at State expense has been approved by the appropriate presiding officer, including the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Location; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Total expense for the regulated lobbyist for each meeting;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Food, lodging, and scheduled entertainment for officials and employees at meetings at which the officials and employees were scheduled speakers or scheduled panel participants, including the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Location; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Total expense for the regulated lobbyist for each meeting;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Tickets and free admission extended to members of the General Assembly as a courtesy or ceremony to the office to attend charitable, cultural, and political events sponsored or conducted by the reporting entity and to each of which all members of the legislative unit were invited, including the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Location; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Total expense of the regulated lobbyist for each event;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Other gifts to or for officials, employees, or members of the immediate families of officials or employees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Salaries and other expenses paid to staff who were not required to register independently; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Other expenses.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the regulated lobbyist is not an individual, an authorized officer or agent of the regulated lobbyist shall submit the report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a prorated amount is reported as compensation, it shall be labeled as prorated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Additional Required Information and Exceptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A report required under this section also shall include the name of each official, employee, or member of the immediate family of an official or employee who has benefited from one or more gifts with a cumulative value of $75 during the reporting period from the regulated lobbyist, regardless of whether the gift:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is attributable to more than one entity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Was given in connection with lobbying activity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following gifts need not be allocated to individual recipients and reported by name:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Gifts reported under §B(2)(g) and (h) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Gifts reported under <cite path="19A|07|01|.07|B.|(2)|(i)">§B(2)(i) of this regulation</cite> with a value of $200 or less; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Gifts reported under <cite path="19A|07|01|.07|B.|(2)|(j)">§B(2)(j) of this regulation</cite>, unless the recipient received from the regulated lobbyist during the reporting period two or more of these gifts with a cumulative value of $100 or more.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Additional Reports from Employers and Regulated Lobbyists, Other Than an Individual.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the employer or regulated lobbyist, other than an individual, is organized and operated for the primary purpose of attempting to influence legislative action or executive action, the employer or regulated lobbyist shall report the name and permanent address of each person that provided at least 5 percent of the regulated lobbyist's total receipts during the preceding 12 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of the reporting and registration requirements of this chapter, receipts of the employer or regulated lobbyist subject to this chapter include funds spent on the employer's or regulated lobbyist's behalf, at its direction, or in its name.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Meals or Beverages — Executive Branch Activity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each regulated lobbyist shall file a separate report disclosing the name of any State official of the Executive Branch or member of the immediate family of a State official of the Executive Branch who has benefited during the reporting period from gifts of meals or beverages provided by the regulated lobbyist, whether or not in connection with lobbying activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Gifts reported by name of recipient under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|B.|(2)|(i)">Regulation .07B(2)(i) of this chapter</cite> need not be included on this report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The report shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Filed electronically at the time and in the manner for reports filed under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Filed by May 31 of each year, to cover the period from November 1 of the previous year through April 30 of the current year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Filed by November 30 of each year, to cover the period from May 1 through October 31 of that year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The report shall contain the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name and business address of the regulated lobbyist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name of each recipient of a gift of a meal or beverages;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Date and value of each gift of a meal or beverages, and the identity of the entity or entities to which the gift is attributable; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Total cumulative value of gifts of meals or beverages, calculated as to each recipient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The report may include an explanation of the circumstances under which the gift of a meal or beverages was given.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a regulated lobbyist reports gifts of meals or beverages in accordance with this regulation, the regulated lobbyist need not count or report them under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|E.">Regulation .07E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Business Transactions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This regulation applies to an individual regulated lobbyist who lobbies the Executive or Legislative Branch.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This regulation does not apply to an entity that employs an individual regulated lobbyist.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual regulated lobbyist shall file, with the report required by <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, a report that discloses any business transaction or series of business transactions that the individual regulated lobbyist had with an individual or business entity listed in <cite path="19A|07|01|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> that occurred in the previous 6 months and involved the exchange of value of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>$1,000 or more for a single transaction; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>$5,000 or more for a series of transactions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual regulated lobbyist is subject to the reporting requirements of <cite path="19A|07|01|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> if the individual regulated lobbyist engaged in a business transaction with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A member of the General Assembly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Governor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Lieutenant Governor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Attorney General;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Comptroller of the Treasury;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The State Treasurer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The secretary of any principal State department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The spouse of an individual listed in §C(1)—(8) of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A business entity in which an individual listed in §C(1)—(9) of this regulation participates as a proprietor or partner; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>A business entity in which an individual listed in §C(1)—(9) of this regulation has an ownership interest of at least 30 percent in the entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The report shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date of the business transaction or dates of each of the series of transactions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name and title of the official listed in <cite path="19A|07|01|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> who was involved in each business transaction or series of transactions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Nature and value of anything exchanged.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The report shall be filed electronically at the time and in the manner for reports filed under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Contributions for Benefit of Certain Officials or Candidates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual regulated lobbyist shall file with the Commission a separate report disclosing any political contributions made:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Directly or indirectly by the individual regulated lobbyist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During the reporting period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel">Election Law Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For the benefit of the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Attorney General, Comptroller, a member of the General Assembly, or a candidate for election to any of those offices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The report shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of each official or candidate for whose benefit a contribution was made; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Total contributions for the benefit of that official or candidate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The report shall be filed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Electronically at the time and in the manner for reports filed under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By May 31 of each year, to cover the period from November 1 of the previous year through April 30 of the current year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>By November 30 of each year, to cover the period from May 1 through October 31 of that year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Legislative Unit Meal or Reception; Registration Report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Legislative Unit Registration Requirement. A regulated lobbyist who invites all members of a legislative unit to a meal or reception shall, at least 5 days before the date of the meal or reception:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Extend a written invitation to all members of the legislative unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Register each meal or reception with the Department of Legislative Service by submitting a notice of invitation electronically to the Ethics Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include in the notice of invitation the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date and location of the meal or reception; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Legislative unit invited.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disclosure Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A regulated lobbyist who is required to register under <cite path="19A|07|01|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall submit a post-event report, providing the total cost of the meal or reception, including the identity of any sponsor who contributes to the cost and the amount of the contribution, to the Ethics Commission:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 14 days after the date of the meal or reception;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Electronically; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If any information required in the post-event report is not known within 14 days after the date of the meal or reception, the nature and estimate of the amount of each item which is not known.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If all of the information required in <cite path="19A|07|01|.11|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> is reported accurately and completely in the post-event report, the regulated lobbyist is not required to report the cost of the meal or reception in the Lobbying Activity Report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Post-event reports shall be available for public inspection on the public access section of the Ethics Commission’s website.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Filing and Public Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Electronic Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With the exception of the statement of recusal under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.06|C.">Regulation .06C of this chapter</cite>, the reports required by this chapter shall be filed electronically, and the oath shall be made by an electronic signature made expressly under the penalties for perjury in the report. The electronically signed reports are subject to the same penalties for perjury as those made under an oath or affirmation before an individual authorized to administer oaths.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>With the exception of the registration under <cite path="|19A|07|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, which is not considered filed until approved by the Ethics Commission and payment is received by the Ethics Commission, electronic documents are considered filed when the complete and accurate document is submitted electronically.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Ethics Commission shall make all lobbying reports available for public inspection on the public access section of the Ethics Commission’s website.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Gifts to Family Members.</heading>
    <text>A regulated lobbyist need not disclose on any report required by this chapter any gift to a member of the regulated lobbyist's immediate family, if the gift is:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purely personal and private in nature and not related to the regulated lobbyist's lobbying activities; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>From the regulated lobbyist's personal funds and not attributable to any other entity or entities.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Additional Reports.</heading>
    <text>The Ethics Commission may require regulated lobbyists to file any additional reports it determines to be necessary in the manner prescribed by the Ethics Commission.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Disclosure of Statistics; Notice to Official Named in Report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After each reporting period, the Ethics Commission shall compute and make available:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For each of the categories of expenses set forth in <cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|B.|(2)">Regulation .07B(2) of this chapter</cite>, a total of the expenditures reported by all regulated lobbyists in that category;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the categories of expenses required to be reported by Regulation .07B(2)(e)—(g) of this chapter, a combined total of the expenditures reported by all regulated lobbyists; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total of the reported expenditures by all regulated lobbyists for lobbying activities during the reporting period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a report required by Regulation .07 or .08 of this chapter contains the name of an official or employee in the Executive or Legislative Branch or the name of a member of the official's or employee's immediate family, the Ethics Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the official or employee within 30 days of receipt of the report by the Ethics Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the official or employee 30 days after receiving the notice to submit a written exception to the inclusion in the report of the name of the official, employee, or member of the official's or employee's immediate family; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Keep the report confidential for 60 days after its receipt.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions.</heading>
    <text>A regulated lobbyist may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be engaged for lobbying purposes for compensation that is dependent in any manner on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The enactment or defeat of legislation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The outcome of any executive action relating to the solicitation or securing of a procurement contract; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other contingency related to executive action or legislative action;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Initiate or encourage the introduction of legislation for the purpose of opposing the legislation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Knowingly counsel any person to violate any provisions of this title or any other State or federal law;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Engage in or counsel any person to engage in fraudulent conduct;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>While engaging in lobbying activities, knowingly make to an official or employee a statement of material fact relating to lobbying activity that the regulated lobbyist knows to be false;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Engage in lobbying without being properly registered as a regulated lobbyist in accordance with <cite path="|19A|07|01|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Request an official or employee to recommend to a potential client the lobbying services of the regulated lobbyist or any other regulated lobbyist;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Make a gift, directly or indirectly, to an official or employee if the regulated lobbyist knows or has reason to know that the gift is in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-505">General Provisions Article, §5-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Make a gift directly or indirectly as a result of a solicitation or facilitation, which the regulated lobbyist knows or has reason to know is prohibited under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-505">General Provisions Article, §5-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If the regulated lobbyist is an individual, engage in any charitable fund-raising activity at the request of an official or employee, including soliciting, transmitting the solicitation of, or transmitting a charitable contribution;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Unless in the ordinary course of business of the regulated lobbyist, make or facilitate the making of any loan of money, goods, or services to an official or employee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>While engaging in lobbying activities on behalf of an entity, knowingly conceal from an official or employee the identify of the entity;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Commit a criminal offense arising from lobbying activity;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>If serving on the State or a local central committee of a political party, participate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As an officer of the central committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In fund-raising activity on behalf of the political party; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In actions relating to filling a vacancy in a public office; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>While engaging in lobbying, unlawfully harass or discriminate against, based on any characteristic protected by law:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An official or employee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An intern, a page, or a fellow in any branch of State government;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual regulated lobbyist; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A credentialed member of the press.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Restriction on Campaign Contributions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies only to a regulated lobbyist described in Regulation .02A(1)—(5) of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The restrictions in this regulation apply from the starting date of the regulated lobbyist's registration to the end of the calendar year in which the registration period ends.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A regulated lobbyist or a person acting on behalf of the regulated lobbyist may not, for the benefit of the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Attorney General, Comptroller, a member of the General Assembly, or a candidate for election to the office of Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Attorney General, Comptroller, or a member of the General Assembly, engage in the following activities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Solicit or transmit a political contribution from any person, including a political committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Serve on a fund-raising committee or a political committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Act as a treasurer for a candidate or official or as treasurer or chairman of a political committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Organize or establish a political committee for the purpose of soliciting or transmitting contributions from any person; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Forward tickets for fund-raising activities, or other solicitations for political contributions, to a potential contributor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A regulated lobbyist may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make a personal political contribution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inform any entity of a position taken by a candidate or official; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Engage in other activities not specifically prohibited in this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a regulated lobbyist who is a candidate with respect to the regulated lobbyist's own campaign.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|07|01|.18">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Ethics Training Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies to an individual regulated lobbyist described in <cite path="|19A|07|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual regulated lobbyist shall complete the lobbyist training course required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-205">General Provisions Article, §5-205(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 6 months of the individual regulated lobbyist’s initial registration with the Ethics Commission; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the initial registration is terminated in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-704">General Provisions Article, §5-704(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, earlier than 6 months after the date of registration, before any subsequent registration with the Ethics Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On completion of the initial training course under <cite path="19A|07|01|.18|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, an individual regulated lobbyist shall complete the training course required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-205">General Provisions Article, §5-205(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, within the 2-year period following the date of the most recently completed training course.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-206">General Provisions Article, §5-206 </cite>and Title 5, Subtitle 7, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20">Regulations <cite path="|19A|07|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|19A|07|01|.17">.17</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 31, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1584); adopted permanently effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 27)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-25"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective May 25, 2015 (42:10 Md. R. 685)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-25"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective May 25, 2015 (42:10 Md. R. 685)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, E amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-11-23"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12); November 23, 2017 (44:23 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, C amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1309)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.08|F.">Regulation .08F</cite> amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> adopted effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.16|M.">Regulation .16M</cite>, N amended effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.16|O.">Regulation .16O</cite> adopted effective May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-25"><cite path="|19A|07|01|.18">Regulation .18</cite> adopted effective May 25, 2015 (42:10 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
