<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Declaratory Ruling</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Declaratory ruling" means a ruling made by a promulgating authority with respect to the manner in which the promulgating authority would apply a regulation or order of the promulgating authority, or a statute that the promulgating authority enforces, to a person or a property based on a given set of facts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Aging.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Person" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual, receiver, trustee, guardian, personal representative, fiduciary, or representative of any kind;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A partnership, firm, association, corporation, or other entity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A political subdivision of the State or an instrumentality of a political subdivision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Promulgating authority" means the promulgating authority's designee or an officer or unit of the Department that is authorized by law to adopt regulations subject to State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-101">10-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-139">10-139</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, or adjudicate contested cases subject to State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">10-226</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Petition for Declaratory Ruling.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An interested person may file with the promulgating authority a petition for a declaratory ruling.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The petition for a declaratory ruling shall be filed in writing and shall describe in detail:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The interest of the petitioner in making the request;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The issues involved;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A detailed statement of the facts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A list of documents or statements the petitioner believes should be considered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A sworn statement by the petitioner that the facts contained in the petition are true to the best of the person's knowledge and belief.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Consideration and Disposition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The promulgating authority:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall consider the petition and may issue the declaratory ruling requested; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall notify the petitioner in writing of the action decided upon and state the reasons for the decision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Publication and Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The promulgating authority shall keep a record of each declaratory ruling issued and index all declaratory rulings issued by reference to statutes or regulations involved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The promulgating authority may publish declaratory rulings of general interest subject to the mandates of the Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-601">State Government Article, §10-601 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland, and allow inspection of the declaratory rulings subject to the Public Information Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Appeal.</heading>
    <text>A declaratory ruling is subject to judicial review as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-305">State Government Article, §10-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-301">10-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-305">10-305</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-27">Effective date: August 27, 2007 (34:17 Md. R. 1510)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
