<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Maryland Tort Claims Act—Coverage and Limits</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Commercial Insurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within budgetary appropriations and market availability, the Treasurer, in the Treasurer's sole discretion, may purchase commercial insurance to provide coverage, in whole or in part, under the Maryland Tort Claims Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Treasurer elects to purchase commercial insurance under §A, above, the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Policy limits, terms, and conditions of the commercial insurance shall determine coverage and establish the limitation of State liability; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment limits, terms, and conditions applicable to the Treasurer's self-insurance program under this chapter shall determine the coverage and establish the limitation of State liability for purposes of the State's deductible or self-insured retention, if any, under this commercial insurance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="25|02|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Self-Insurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. Within budgetary appropriations, the Treasurer may provide self-insurance to provide coverage under the Maryland Tort Claims Act for those incidents not covered by purchased commercial insurance obtained pursuant to Regulation .01.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Coverage. Subject to §A, above, self-insurance shall provide coverage for a tortious act or omission of State personnel that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is within the scope of public duties of the State personnel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No element of which constitutes malice or gross negligence.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exclusions and Limitations. The Treasurer may not provide self-insurance coverage for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Punitive damages;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interest before judgment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A claim that arises from the combatant activities of the State militia during a state of emergency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A tortious act or omission of State personnel:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That is not within the scope of the public duties of the State personnel, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An element of which constitutes malice or gross negligence; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A cause of action that law specifically prohibits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Limits of Liability. Within total budgeted funds available for self-insurance coverage of tort claims, the limits of State liability shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to <cite path="25|02|02|.02|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, $200,000 per claimant for all injury, loss, and damage to person and property arising from a single incident. For the purpose of determining the limits of liability under this subsection, all persons claiming damages resulting from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bodily injury to, or the death of, any one person shall be considered to be one claimant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Damage to or destruction of a single item of property shall be considered to be one claimant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Such greater, lesser, or additional limits as otherwise may be established by the annual State Budget for incidents occurring during that fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>No Waiver of Immunity. The sovereign immunity of the State is not waived for claims in excess of the limits set forth in <cite path="25|02|02|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="25|02|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Discretionary Payments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within budgetary appropriations, the Treasurer may pay from the State Insurance Trust Fund all or part of that portion of a claim that exceeds the limits of purchased commercial insurance coverage obtained pursuant to <cite path="|25|02|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The claim is consistent with the provisions of Regulation .02B and C of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A judgment or settlement has been entered granting the claimant damages greater than the limits of the purchased commercial insurance obtained pursuant to <cite path="|25|02|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A request for a discretionary payment is submitted to the Treasurer within 60 days of entry of the settlement or judgment described in <cite path="25|02|02|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board of Public Works, with the advice and counsel of the Office of the Attorney General, has approved the discretionary payment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A discretionary payment of part of a settlement or judgment pursuant to <cite path="25|02|02|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Does not abrogate the sovereign immunity of the State beyond the waiver provided in <cite path="|25|02|02|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is subject to the monetary limits of <cite path="|25|02|02|.02|D.">Regulation .02D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|12-501">State Government Article, §12-501(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a decision of the Board of Public Works under <cite path="25|02|02|.03|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite> is not subject to judicial review.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|9-104">9-104</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|9-105">9-105</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|12-101">State Government Article, §12-101 </cite>et seq; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-07-02">Effective date: July 2, 1984 (11:13 Md. R. 1178)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-04">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|25.02.01">COMAR 25.02.01</cite> to <cite path="|25.02.02">25.02.02</cite> effective as an emergency provision July 17, 1985 (12:16 Md. R. 1603); emergency status extended at 12:22 Md. R. 2102); adopted permanently effective November 4, 1985 (12:22 Md. R. 2109)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-04-16">Chapter, State Insurance Trust Fund, repealed effective April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-04-16" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|25|02|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|25|02|02|.03">.03</cite>, Maryland Tort Claims Act, adopted effective April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-26"><cite path="|25|02|02|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective January 12, 1998 (25:1 Md. R. 17); June 26, 2000 (27:12 Md. R. 1142)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
