<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Maryland Tort Claims Act—Inmate Claims</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to tort claims filed with the Treasurer pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|12-107">State Government Article, §12-107, </cite>by inmates who are confined in an institution within the Division of Correction or the Patuxent Institution.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When an inmate files a claim with the Treasurer, the Treasurer may suspend claims processing pending receipt of the decision of the Inmate Grievance Commission issued pursuant to <cite path="|12.07.01">COMAR 12.07.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Treasurer elects to suspend claims processing pursuant to §A, above, the Treasurer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Direct the inmate to file a complaint with the Inmate Grievance Commission, including with that complaint a copy of the Treasurer's notification requiring the inmate to file the complaint with the Inmate Grievance Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify the inmate that processing of the claim filed with the Treasurer shall be stayed pending the Treasurer's receipt of the Inmate Grievance Commission's decision on the inmate's complaint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Treasurer may, in the Treasurer's discretion, waive the provisions of §§A and B, above, and process the claim in accordance with <cite path="|25.02.03">COMAR 25.02.03</cite> without awaiting the decision of the Inmate Grievance Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Inmate Grievance Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Inmate Grievance Commission dismisses the inmate's complaint as wholly lacking in merit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Inmate Grievance Commission shall notify the Treasurer of its decision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of notification of the Inmate Grievance Commission's decision, the Treasurer then shall process the inmate's claim in accordance with <cite path="|25.02.03">COMAR 25.02.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Inmate Grievance Commission recommends to the Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services that the inmate be awarded monetary damages pursuant to <cite path="12.07.01.06">COMAR 12.07.01.06</cite>, and the Secretary affirms the Inmate Grievance Commission's recommendation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services shall notify the Treasurer of the Secretary's decision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the Secretary's decision and subject to §B(3), below, the Treasurer then shall process the inmate's claim in accordance with <cite path="|25.02.03">COMAR 25.02.03</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In processing the inmate's claim, the Treasurer may rely on fact-finding undertaken by the Inmate Grievance Commission in its review of the inmate's complaint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Payment of any award, compromise, or settlement of the inmate's tort claim pursuant to <cite path="25.02.03.07">COMAR 25.02.03.07</cite> shall be made through the State Insurance Trust Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Treasurer shall notify the Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services of the Treasurer's approval or denial of the inmate's tort claim.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|9-104">9-104</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|9-105">9-105</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|12-101">State Government Article, §12-101 </cite>et seq; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-04-16">Effective date: April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
