<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>General Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A skills-based amusement device is not legally operated if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless authorized under <cite path="|36.08.03">COMAR 36.08.03</cite>, the merchandise, prizes, tickets, tokens, or other objects awarded per play exceeds minimal value;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The device awards a cash prize or a prize that is readily convertible to cash;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The outcome of the game is based on a preponderance of chance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The ability of any player to succeed at the game is impacted by the number or ratio of prior wins to prior losses of that device;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The outcome of the game can be controlled by a source other than the player of the game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The success of any player is or may be determined by a chance event which cannot be altered by player actions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The ability of a player to succeed at the game is impacted by game features not visible or known to a reasonable player; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The ability of a player to succeed at the game is impacted by the exercise of skill that no reasonable player could exercise.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The merchandise, prizes, tickets, tokens or other objects that are awarded by a skills-based amusement device may be accumulated and exchanged for non-cash merchandise or prizes of value that is similar to the cumulative value of the items exchanged.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Testing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may require testing of a prototype of a skills-based amusement device for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Overall operational integrity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Compliance with this subtitle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other function that the Commission determines may be necessary to validate the proper functionality and performance of the device.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may accept testing by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commission staff; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A testing facility recognized by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The costs of testing required under this chapter shall be the responsibility of the licensee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2017 (43:23 Md. R. 1281)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
