<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Instant Bingo Facility Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Hours of Operation.</heading>
    <text>A facility operator shall submit its proposed hours of operation to the Commission for written approval.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Facility Design Standards.</heading>
    <text>A facility operator shall, at its own expense, construct its facility in accordance with specifications established by the Commission, including:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Computer space for the instant bingo validation and accounting server that is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Equipped with heating, ventilation, and air conditioning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Supplied with power including an uninterruptible back-up power supply;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Secured with a key or alternative locking mechanism; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Covered by a surveillance system enabled to record all entry and exit to the computer space and activity in the area;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A surveillance system approved in writing by the Commission that is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Configured to provide surveillance of all instant bingo machines and related activities within the facility in accordance with standards established by the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enabled with a digital video recording format in accordance with standards established by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An alarm system connected to all emergency exits from the gaming floor that produces a distinguishable warning sound discernible in the vicinity of an exit when the emergency door is opened;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any signage required by the Commission;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Communication systems capable of effecting timely communication between the facility, law enforcement exercising proper jurisdiction over the facility, emergency first responders; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Any other equipment or design feature required by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Gaming Floor Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit a floor plan depicting its gaming floor and all restricted areas to the Commission for review and written approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not commence operations until its gaming floor plan is approved in writing by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A gaming floor plan that a facility operator submits to the Commission shall depict:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The gaming floor with a notation as to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Total square feet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Total square feet utilized for the placement of instant bingo machines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The location of each instant bingo machine;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All restricted areas within the facility with a notation as to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Locations for redemption of instant bingo tickets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Location for the counting of currency from instant bingo machines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Locations for the storage of currency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Computer space allocated to the instant bingo validation and accounting system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An area designated for the storage or repair of instant bingo machines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Surveillance monitoring room; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Locations for the storage of instant bingo tickets.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each surveillance camera; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each automated teller machine.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not implement any change to its approved gaming floor plan without the prior written approval of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-110">State Government Article, §9-110</cite>; Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>.1 and 12-308; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-12">Regulations <cite path="|36|07|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|07|03|.03">.03</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 26, 2013 (40:20 Md. R. 1650); adopted permanently effective December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2019)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
