<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>General Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Compliance with Federal Law.</heading>
    <text>A person who transports an instant bingo machine shall comply with applicable provisions of 15 U.S.C. §§1171—1178, commonly known as the Johnson Act.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|07|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Transportation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise directed by the Commission, a person shall submit a written notice to the Commission prior to transporting an instant bingo machine.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For each instant bingo machine to be transported, a person proposing to transport the machine shall submit to the Commission a written notice containing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and address of person initiating transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The method of transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name of and address of the carrier;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The anticipated beginning and end dates of transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the destination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The manufacturer's serial number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The model number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A description of the instant bingo machine to be transported; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person proposing to transport or transporting an instant bingo machine shall promptly submit to the Commission written notice of any changes to the information already submitted as required under <cite path="36|07|05|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person transporting an instant bingo machine shall plainly and clearly label the package so that the name and address of the shipper and recipient, and the contents of the package, may be readily ascertained during an inspection of the outside of the package.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After delivery of an instant bingo machine, the facility to which the machine is delivered shall promptly submit to the Commission written notice that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date instant bingo machine was received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date instant bingo machine will be placed into operation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Storage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an instant bingo machine will not be placed into operation upon delivery to a facility, the facility shall provide the Commission with written notice that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A precise identification of the instant bingo machine;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The reason for storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The storage facility’s location; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility may store an instant bingo machine only in a manner that the Commission has approved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall maintain a register of each instant bingo machine placed in operation in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For each instant bingo machine placed into operation, the Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assign an instant bingo machine certification control number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Affix a Commission certification tag.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An instant bingo machine may not be transported out of the State unless the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approves the action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Removes the certification tag.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Testing.</heading>
    <text>The Commission may test instant bingo machines and associated equipment for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Accuracy; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any other function that the Commission determines may be necessary to validate the proper functionality and performance of the machines and equipment.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|07|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Request for Authorization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility shall obtain prior written Commission authorization before taking any of the following actions with respect to an instant bingo machine or associated equipment in its facility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Placing a machine into operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Changing percentage payout;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Changing software or hardware that has been tested by the Commission’s independent test laboratory; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Performing any other action that materially alters or interrupts the operation of a machine.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before the Commission may authorize an action described in <cite path="36|07|05|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, a facility shall provide the Commission with written notice of the request that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A description of proposed action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The location of action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The start and end dates and times;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The estimated ”go live” date for the machine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Documentation demonstrating the approval of the manufacturer of the affected instant bingo machine; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice of Changes.  A facility shall submit to the Commission written notice of any changes to the information already submitted under §A or B of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Commission Response to Request for Authorization.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may impose additional requirements on the facility or the manufacturer before authorizing the action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may deny approval of the action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A facility shall notify the Commission if the action is not completed as approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-110">State Government Article, §9-110</cite>; Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>.1 and 12-308; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-12">Regulations <cite path="|36|07|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|07|05|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 26, 2013 (40:20 Md. R. 1650); adopted permanently effective December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2019)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
