<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the terms defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-101">State Government Article, §9-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and in <cite path="36.01.01.01">COMAR 36.01.01.01</cite>, which have the same meanings in this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Activate” means to make a book of instant tickets ready for sale.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Announced end of game” means the date determined and announced by the Agency after which retailers may not activate instant ticket game books.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Bonus drawing” means a game the Agency designates as a bonus drawing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Bonus game” means a game the Agency designates as a bonus game or bonus drawing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Cash.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Cash” means coins, U.S. currency, money orders, debit cards, and checks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Cash” does not include credit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Claim form” means a paper or computer-generated document that identifies a prize claimant, prize amount, game and ticket characteristics.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Coupon” means an instrument that a player may use to obtain a lottery ticket at reduced or no cost.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Daily game” means a draw game for which the Agency offers a drawing every day.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Designated cutoff time” means the time after which a ticket may no longer be purchased for the next drawing of a specified lottery game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Draw Game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Draw game” means a lottery game:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Sold and redeemed through a subscription or a computer network at retailer locations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For which tickets are generated by a terminal and are a record of a transaction for a draw game.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Draw game” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A jackpot game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A nonjackpot game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A monitor game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A multi-jurisdictional game played with draw game tickets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Any other Agency-issued game played as described in this section.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Draw ticket” or “Draw game ticket” means a ticket purchased from a terminal or through a subscription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Drawing” means a random selection event used for determining winning numbers of certain lottery games.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Drawing date” means the day, days of the week, or times of day on which the winning numbers for the lottery games are selected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“ePlayslip” means an electronically-generated game play selection process using an official web or mobile application issued by the Agency that is used by a player to select the purchaser’s playable numbers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Fast Play Game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Fast Play game” means a game produced by a lottery terminal where predetermined game results are obtained from a finite pool of randomly generated results for that specific game and are printed on a ticket.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Fast Play game” does not include games where players select their numbers or symbols and there is a drawing to determine a winning number or symbol.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Instant game” or “instant ticket game” means a lottery game where tickets have an area that the player exposes in accordance with the game instructions, and includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Scratch-off tickets; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Tickets using other methods of revealing a hidden area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Instant ticket” or “instant game ticket” means an authorized lottery game ticket issued in an instant game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Instant ticket pack” or “instant ticket book” means a group of sequential instant tickets that are in an individual bundle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Jackpot game” means a lottery game where the top prize amount varies depending on amounts wagered and on whether the top prize was won in the preceding drawing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Lottery game” means a game, activity, or other enterprise offered by the Agency for consideration to win a prize by random chance and, unless specified by the Director, does not include a promotional game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Monitor” means a television screen or similar type of screen used to display draw game results.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Monitor game” means a draw game where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tickets are generated by an Agency vendor’s computer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An Agency vendor’s computer generates results of the draw game; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Drawing results may be graphically displayed on a monitor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Multi-jurisdictional game” means a lottery game offered by the Agency and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any other political entity outside Maryland or outside the United States;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any private licensee of a state or a foreign nation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Nonjackpot game” means a lottery game where the top prize remains constant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Number” means any item or symbol used to play to win a lottery game, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Numerals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Letters; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Icons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Odds” means the long run ratio of the number of times a win does not occur to the number of times a win does occur.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Pari-mutuel” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The total number of winning matches per prize level, divided equally into the dollar value of the prize pool for the specific prize level; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The total number of winning matches in the designated prize levels, divided equally into the dollar value of the prize pool for the designated prize levels.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Player-Activated Terminal or PAT.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Player-activated terminal” or “PAT” means a machine through which a player may purchase Agency tickets or claim a prize without action by a licensed retailer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Player-activated terminal” or “PAT” does not mean a machine that dispenses cash.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>“Playslip” means a card issued by the Agency and used by a player to select the purchaser’s playable numbers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>“Probability” means the long-run ratio of the number of times a win occurs to the number of times that game’s drawings are held.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>“Progressive jackpot” means a jackpot offered by a lottery game that may increase uniformly in value based on sales of that game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>“Promotion” or “promotional game” means an activity or game offered by the Agency to advertise the Agency and its products and services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>“Retailer” means a person licensed by the Agency to sell lottery tickets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>“Subscription” means a method of playing a lottery game which provides the ability to play a specific number of games using the same numbers for a period of consecutive drawings as specified on the subscription membership card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>“Terminal” means a computerized unit specifically designed for issuing and processing tickets and for printing special reports.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>“Validate” or “validation” means the process of determining that a ticket is the rightful winner so that the claimant may be paid the prize.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>“Vendor” or “Agency vendor” means a person under contract to the Agency to provide services that support lottery games.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-103">9-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-104">9-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-109">9-109</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-111">9-111</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-122">9-122</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 2013 (40:9 Md. R. 790)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-12-02"><cite path="|36|02|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-21"><cite path="|36|02|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597); January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13); September 21, 2020 (47:19 Md. R. 850)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
