<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Retailer Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Lottery Laws and Regulations. A retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with all lottery laws and regulations of the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be aware of all lottery laws and regulations pertaining to the duties and responsibilities of a retailer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inform the Director of an act or omission that the retailer knows or should know constitutes a violation of lottery laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Services. A retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide specified services for the Agency, including the sale, cashing, and issuance of lottery tickets as directed by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sell a lottery ticket for cash only;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sell lottery tickets only at the location specified on the retailer’s license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Exercise courteous and fair treatment to lottery ticket purchasers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Sell all games as directed by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Except for those requiring submission of a claim form to the Agency, pay every winning ticket upon validation under <cite path="|36.02.06">COMAR 36.02.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Report, as required by the Internal Revenue Service or the Agency, income tax information relating to holders of winning lottery tickets;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Charge no fee for the issuance or cashing of checks for lottery winnings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Display the retailer’s license in a prominent location;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Keep playslips in stock and available to players;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Not sell any lottery ticket or lottery-style ticket other than those made available for sale by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Obtain prior Agency approval for any advertising of a permanent or semi-permanent nature such as signs and billboards, other than advertising located on the licensed premises; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Prominently post point-of-sale and other promotional/consumer materials supplied by the Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Care of Terminals. A retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Place terminals within the retailer’s premises only on a site approved by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide sufficient space for the proper operation of the terminal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide all electrical requirements as prescribed in the vendor pre-site form, before the installation of the terminal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Participate in training approved by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Replace lottery ticket stock when necessary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Provide reasonable care and security for lottery ticket stock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Exercise due diligence in the operation, security, and care of the terminal as specified in the retailer’s operating manual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Perform no mechanical or electrical maintenance on the terminal except as directed by the Agency or an Agency vendor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>As directed by the Agency, immediately notify the technical support operations center in the event of any terminal malfunction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Make the terminal available for the sale and cashing of lottery tickets as directed by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Except for materials that are provided by the Agency and are specifically authorized to be placed on a terminal, keep all surfaces of the terminal free and clear;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Pay all electrical utility charges in connection with the operation of the terminal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Assume the cost of any repairs to the terminal arising out of or related to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unauthorized attempts to modify or repair the terminal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unauthorized attempts to move or relocate the terminal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Intentional damage to the terminal or defacement of the terminal surface or repeated or continuing negligence which results in damage to the terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall hold the Agency and the State of Maryland and their officials and employees harmless from any liability arising in connection with operating and conducting lottery ticket sales.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall notify the Agency at least 14 days before the retailer temporarily or permanently ceases the operation of the retailer’s business.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a person ceases to be a retailer, the person shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Surrender, or allow an Agency vendor to remove, any materials or equipment that were provided by the Agency or a vendor of the Agency; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assume the cost of any repairs to the retailer’s location arising from the removal of the Agency’s equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Sale of Lottery Tickets — Instant Ticket Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Retailers shall activate an instant ticket pack before selling an instant ticket from that pack.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Instant tickets that a retailer activates before a ticket’s announced end of game may be sold by the retailer after the ticket’s announced end of game and until the last date to claim a prize for that game.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Sale of Lottery Tickets — Draw Game Ticket Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Playslip or ePlayslip Purchase Procedure. If a player wishes to purchase a ticket using a playslip or an ePlayslip:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A player shall complete a playslip and give it to the retailer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The retailer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Process the playslip or ePlayslip through the ticket terminal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Issue to the player the specified draw game ticket for the game being played.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Vocalized Purchase Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Randomly Selected Numbers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a player wishes to have playable numbers randomly generated for a draw game ticket, a retailer shall enter the game type and the dollar amount the player wants to wager.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The retailer shall deliver to the player the ticket issued by the terminal with the randomly generated numbers for the game printed on the ticket.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Player Selected Numbers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the player wishes to provide playable numbers, a retailer may allow a player to vocalize the numbers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The retailer shall enter the information provided by the player, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The game type;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The dollar amount the player wants to wager;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The numbers the player selects;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The number of games the player wishes to play; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Any other information required by the Agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Player Activated Terminal.  If a player wishes to purchase a ticket using a PAT, the player may purchase the ticket using any method offered on the PAT.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Sale of Lottery Tickets — Fast Play Game Ticket Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Retailer Assisted Purchase Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a player wishes to purchase a Fast Play game ticket, the player shall indicate to the retailer the name of the Fast Play game desired.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The retailer shall make the selection and issue the ticket through the terminal and deliver it to the player.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Player-Activated Terminal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a player wishes to purchase a ticket using a PAT, the player may purchase the ticket by selecting the icon for the desired Fast Play game on the terminal screen.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The PAT shall generate and dispense the ticket.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Lost, Stolen, or Missing Tickets.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a ticket is lost, stolen, or missing from a retailer, the Director may reimburse the retailer for the ticket.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may require the party responsible for a lost, stolen, or missing ticket to reimburse the Agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Agency is not liable to a retailer or player for a lost or stolen ticket.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A ticket is void if it:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is mutilated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is altered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is irregular;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is expired;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Fails to meet validation standards; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Fails to meet security requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a retailer is reimbursed for a lost, stolen, or missing ticket, the retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hold the Agency harmless; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the Director with as much information considered necessary to process the claim.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A retailer may not seek indemnification from another source if reimbursed by the Director for a lost, stolen, or missing ticket.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Posting of Winning Numbers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As soon as practical after each drawing, a retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Post in a prominent and conspicuous location within the retailer’s business location the winning number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Keep the winning number posted until the next drawing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall display active winning numbers as requested by the Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Agency is not responsible for a retailer’s failure to post or properly post current official winning numbers.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Payment of Prizes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall pay the holder of a winning lottery ticket up to $600 upon submission and validation of the ticket.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall pay the holder of a valid winning ticket regardless of whether the retailer sold the ticket.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless the retailer is a participant in the Expanded Cashing Authority Program under <cite path="|36|02|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, if the winning ticket entitles the holder to a prize that is more than $600, the retailer shall instruct the ticket holder to seek payment from the Agency or a retailer participating in the Expanded Cashing Authority Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Multiple Claims. A retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except in those cases of multiple claims totaling over $600 by the same person, pay all claims in cash; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For multiple claims totaling over $600, pay a minimum of $500 in cash toward the claims, and issue checks or money orders for the balance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Validated and Paid Tickets. Unless a ticket is cashed at a PAT, after a ticket is validated and paid, the retailer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not return the ticket to the winner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall secure the ticket.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Cashing Period. A retailer or Agency claim center may not cash or otherwise process a winning ticket more than 182 days after the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Draw date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of sale of a Fast Play game ticket; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Announced end of the game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Expanded Cashing Authority Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director may establish an Expanded Cashing Authority Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Retailers selected by the Director may pay cash prizes up to $5,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Participation. Before authorizing a retailer to participate in the Expanded Cashing Authority Program, the Director shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The length of time the retailer has been licensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The financial record and responsibility of the retailer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The retailer’s compliance with the requirements of this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The need for expanded cashing authority within a specific geographical location;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of existing retailers with expanded cashing authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The overall performance of the retailer since the license was issued; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any other factor deemed relevant by the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Retailer Requirements. A retailer in the Expanded Cashing Authority Program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain a separate bank account solely for lottery monies to the credit of the State Lottery Fund;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure the confidential handling of personal information from players and winners by not disclosing any personal information to anyone other than the Agency or as required by law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Report income tax information relating to holders of winning lottery tickets to the Agency as required by the Internal Revenue Service or the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For prizes over $600, utilize the lottery terminal to determine, whether a holder of a winning lottery ticket:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owes a State obligation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is on the Voluntary Exclusion list described in <cite path="|36.01.03">COMAR 36.01.03</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Deny payment of a prize to the holder of a winning lottery ticket if the Agency has notified the retailer that the holder may not be paid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Recertification for the Program.  The Director may establish a periodic recertification process for retailers in the Expanded Cashing Authority Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Removal from the Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A retailer participating in the Expanded Cashing Authority Program may be removed from the Program at any time by the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Removal from the program does not automatically otherwise terminate a retailer’s license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director's decision to remove a retailer from the program is final and not subject to appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Payments to Agency.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be financially responsible to the Agency for all:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Revenues derived from the sale of lottery tickets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lottery tickets in the possession of the retailer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Except for tickets cashed through a PAT, tickets that the retailer cashed or cancelled which are later submitted to the Agency for payment;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make regular weekly settlement and payment remittance in the manner, in the place, and on the day of the week specified by the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make more frequent settlement and payment remittances when required by the Director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pay a service charge to the Agency for any dishonored check or electronic transfer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Promptly pay a bonding fee in such amount as the Director determines, when required; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Promptly pay any fees under this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any payment due to the Agency not made within 10 days after the due date shall be charged interest until paid.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Agency may refer delinquent accounts to the Central Collection Unit of the Department of Budget and Management.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Delinquent accounts shall be increased by any additional fees authorized by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|3-304">State Finance and Procurement Article, §3-304(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Americans with Disabilities Act.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“ADA” means the certain law commonly known as the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“ADA retailer compliance form” means a form prepared by the Agency and used to inspect a retailer’s location in connection with this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Disability” means the term as defined in the ADA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Compliance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A retailer shall, at its expense:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Comply with federal, State, and local laws prohibiting discrimination against individuals with disabilities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain a business location that is accessible to individuals with disabilities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Make available at the retailer’s location all lottery-related goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, and accommodations to any individual with a disability.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Agency shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Inspect the site of a new retailer for compliance with this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Inspect the site of a change of ownership retailer for compliance with this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If necessary, provide the retailer with a corrective action plan on the ADA retailer compliance form.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Changes in Ownership.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A change in ownership of a retailer’s business:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Automatically voids the existing retailer license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requires an application for a new license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a retailer is a corporation, partnership, or LLC, a transfer of ownership includes a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Merger;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Consolidation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Share exchange of a majority of stock;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Transfer of a majority of assets or transfer of stock of the majority shareholder; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Transfer of a majority partner's interest, or transfer of member’s or principal’s interest.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A transfer of interest to a spouse currently identified as an owner on the retailer’s license by gift or through operation of law is not a transfer of ownership.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A retailer who transfers ownership remains responsible for all tickets and lottery sales up to the date of final accounting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A retailer shall pay all outstanding funds due to the Agency upon change of ownership.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The purchaser of a business where a lottery terminal is installed shall apply for continuation of the existing license at least 30 days before the transfer of ownership.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval Process for Change of Ownership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Require that a new application for a lottery retailer license be completed when a retailer notifies the Agency of a change in ownership; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Review the existing location and the applications on file for that trading area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the application of the proposed new owner meets all lottery requirements to become a licensed retailer, preference will be given to retaining the license at the existing location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director may reasonably determine that circumstances and conditions exist that do not warrant the approval of a license at that location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Director's decision to approve or deny the application of the proposed new owner at the existing location shall be in writing and state the reasons for the decision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The decision to deny the application of the proposed new owner shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be treated in the same manner as a denial of an application for a retailer license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Create the same rights of review and appeal as the denial of an application for a retailer license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Acts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prevent a person from giving a lottery ticket to another as a gift; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prohibit the purchase of a ticket for the purpose of making a gift to a person younger than 18 years old.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>No person other than a licensed lottery retailer or the retailer’s employee or the Agency may sell a lottery ticket or a lottery subscription.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A retailer shall require all lottery tickets to be paid for by the purchaser at the time of purchase.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A retailer may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sell a ticket at any price other than that established by the Director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sell to or cash a lottery ticket for a person younger than 18 years old;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Allow an employee younger than 18 years old to sell or cash a lottery ticket or operate lottery equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Extend credit in any manner for the sale of lottery tickets;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Offer customers alcoholic beverages to induce them to purchase or redeem a lottery ticket; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>.1, 12-304, and 12-308, Annotated Code of Maryland, have on its premises an illegal gaming device or a slot machine as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">Criminal Law Article, §12-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Games of Chance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This section does not apply to a game of chance offered legally by a retailer that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A video lottery facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal operator of an electronic gaming device that is licensed as an amusement game in Baltimore City or Baltimore County under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">Criminal Law Article, §12-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Subject to regulation by the Comptroller under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-304">Criminal Law Article, §12-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A legal operator of instant bingo under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-308">Criminal Law Article, §12-308, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Authorized to offer paper tip jar gaming under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr">Criminal Law Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for a lottery game or promotion, a retailer may not offer a game of chance on the retailer’s premises.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in these regulations or with the approval of the Director, a retailer may not cancel or accept ticket returns for draw games.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>All instant ticket and Fast Play game ticket sales are final and may not be cancelled once sold.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Void Ticket.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A ticket may not be sold for a drawing after that drawing has occurred; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A ticket sold for a drawing after that drawing has occurred is void.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">Criminal Law Article, §12-301</cite>.1; State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-103">9-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-104">9-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-109">9-109</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-113">9-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-115">9-115</cite>,<br/>9-117, 9-119, 9-122, and 9-124, Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 603, §6, Acts of 2012</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 2013 (40:9 Md. R. 790)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|02|03|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-12-02" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-21"><cite path="|36|02|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 21, 2020 (47:19 Md. R. 850)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-09"><cite path="|36|02|03|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective March 9, 2020 (47:5 Md. R. 313)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
