<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Common Provisions for All Lottery Games</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Governing Law and Rules.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>By purchasing a game ticket, a player agrees to comply with and abide by all:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applicable laws and regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures implemented by the Director for conducting a lottery game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Rules for that lottery game; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Decisions of the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A multi-jurisdictional game shall be governed by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applicable law and regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rules, procedures, and other documents concerning that game as agreed to by the jurisdictions offering that game; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Agency provisions regarding the purchase and claiming of a ticket.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All decisions made by the Director shall be final and binding on all players and on all persons making claims with respect to them.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Ticket Purchaser Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the time of purchase, the purchaser of a lottery ticket is responsible for verifying that the information printed on the ticket accurately reflects:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The numbers, or other symbols by which winning is determined, that the purchaser wants to play if the purchaser is permitted to select their own numbers and has chosen to do so;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The drawing date; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the correct ticket was purchased.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The sole remedy for an inaccurate ticket shall be cancellation of that ticket, if permitted, as set forth in <cite path="|36|02|04|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To receive a prize, a person holding a winning ticket shall submit to an authorized claiming location the ticket and all necessary documentation for claiming within 182 days after the date of the drawing, the date of sale of a Fast Play game ticket, or the announced end of an instant ticket game.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Methods of Purchase.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Playslips and ePlayslips.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following are not valid as a receipt to claim a prize or proof of purchase of a ticket:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A playslip; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An ePlayslip.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a playslip or an ePlayslip may be used to play a draw game, the playslip or ePlayslip shall be available at no cost to the purchaser and may be used by the purchaser for selection of numbers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A playslip shall include instructions on how to complete the playslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except for monitor games, if game play by playslip or ePlayslip is authorized and a playslip or an ePlayslip is unavailable, the retailer shall manually enter into the ticket terminal the numbers selected by the player.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For monitor games, a retailer may require players to use a playslip or an ePlayslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Agency or a retailer may seize and destroy an invalid playslip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Purchase by Playslip Through Retailer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a game may be played using a playslip and the player chooses to play by playslip, the purchaser shall present a completed playslip to the retailer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A player may play as many panels or play areas as are available on the playslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A player shall mark all necessary areas on the playslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a player does not mark all necessary areas, the retailer shall return the playslip to the player or the terminal may select numbers necessary to complete the playslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A playslip shall be manually marked and may not be marked by an electromechanical, electronic printing, or automated device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A playslip marked by a method other than a method authorized by this section shall be invalid.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A ticket produced by an invalid playslip is invalid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Purchase by ePlayslip Through Retailer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a game may be played using an ePlayslip and the player chooses to play by ePlayslip, the purchaser shall present a completed ePlayslip to the retailer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A player may play as many panels or play areas as are available on the ePlayslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A player shall select all necessary areas on the ePlayslip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a player does not select all necessary areas, the retailer shall return the ePlayslip to the player.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A ticket produced by an invalid ePlayslip is invalid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Purchase Using a Player-activated Terminal. If a game may be played using a player-activated terminal, the player shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enter selections from the choices provided by the device; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Insert a playslip or scan an ePlayslip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Purchase by Subscription.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subscription Plans.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Lottery may offer subscription plans.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Director shall determine the price of a subscription plan.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Director may reduce the price of a subscription plan for a specified period under a special purchase option.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subscription Applications.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A purchaser of a Lottery subscription shall be a resident of Maryland or use a Maryland address for the subscription application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a game may be purchased by subscription, a subscription application form shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identify the game being played; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Require the purchaser to supply identifying information as determined by the Agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A subscription application form shall allow the purchaser to designate:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The number of drawings or games to be played, or the length of the subscription; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If a game allows a player to select numbers, the player’s decision to supply particular numbers or to allow the Agency vendor’s computer to select random numbers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A subscription application may require the player to provide any other information the Agency requires.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Group Subscription Applications.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application for a subscription in the name of more than one person:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is a group subscription;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Shall designate a single group member to be the group manager;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The group manager shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A Maryland resident or have a Maryland mailing address; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Authorized to be the sole recipient of prizes up to an amount determined by the Director.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An application for a group subscription shall include identifying information for each group member, as determined by the Agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The application for a group will only be completed if the application form is fully completed and all requested information is provided about each group member.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Subscription Email.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Agency shall provide a subscription purchaser or, if a group purchaser, the group’s representative, a subscription confirmation email.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A subscription confirmation email shall include information identifying the subscription, as determined by the Agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Subscription Play and Winning.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A subscription player shall be automatically entered in each drawing or game during the period when the subscription is active.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Agency shall monitor each subscription.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Payment of subscription prizes shall be made as provided for in <cite path="|36.02.06">COMAR 36.02.06</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A subscription may be renewed as allowed by the Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Cancellation of Tickets.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Draw Games.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless cancellation is authorized by this regulation or the rules governing that ticket, a sale of a draw game ticket is final.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A multi-jurisdictional game played with a draw game ticket may be cancelled only if authorized by the rules governing that game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A ticket purchased at a player-activated terminal may not be cancelled at the PAT, but an eligible ticket may be canceled at a non-PAT terminal at the retailer where the ticket was purchased.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Director may determine during certain promotions that tickets may not be cancelled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A draw game ticket may be cancelled only:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By the same retailer from which the ticket was purchased;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On the day of purchase;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Before the designated cutoff time for the first drawing on the ticket; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If allowed by the game.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Canceling a draw game ticket:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Voids the ticket;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Removes the ticket from the pool of tickets eligible for the drawing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Results in the ticket being invalid and not eligible to win a prize.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A retailer presented with a draw game ticket for cancellation shall cancel the ticket as authorized by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>When a retailer cancels a draw game ticket in accordance with this regulation, the retailer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensure that the terminal issues a refund receipt in the amount of the purchase price of the ticket;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Keep the refund slip; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pay the player a refund equal to the purchase price of the ticket.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The Agency is not obligated to pay a prize to the holder of a cancelled ticket, even if the ticket was cancelled in error.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Instant Ticket Games. Unless the Director determines otherwise, an instant game ticket may not be cancelled.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fast Play Games.  A Fast Play game ticket may not be cancelled.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Game Liability Limit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term Defined. “Game liability limit” means the dollar amount at which winning tickets, if paid, would exceed the amount the Director deems to be in the Agency’s best interests.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may establish a game liability limit for each drawing of a game and for each game.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A lottery ticket may not be issued if the ticket, if won, would exceed the game liability limit established by the Director for that drawing or game.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Agency Not Liable.</heading>
    <text>The Agency is not responsible or liable for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A ticket or entry that is lost, stolen, damaged, or destroyed;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A ticket redeemed by a retailer in error;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A winning number repeated, reported, or displayed in error, including by television, media, or by any other form of communication;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An outdated or incorrect playslip, ePlayslip, or consumer game information;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A claim, liability, injury, or property loss of any kind arising out of a player’s, winner’s, guest’s, traveler’s, or any other person’s participation in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A lottery game of any kind;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A promotion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A drawing or a related event or occurrence; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The award, receipt, possession, use, misuse, or acceptance of a prize;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Negligence or breach of obligation of a person other than the Agency, its employees, officials, or members; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Payment of a ticket not in accordance with this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>No Endorsement.</heading>
    <text>By providing a prize or any portion of a prize from a company or other person, the Agency has not endorsed the company or other person.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Reporting Death or Prize.</heading>
    <text>The Agency may report to the Comptroller of Maryland and the Internal Revenue Service a lottery winner’s name, win, winning amount, death, or any other permissible information.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-103">9-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-104">9-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-109">9-109</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-111">9-111</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-122">9-122</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-124">9-124</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 2013 (40:9 Md. R. 790)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|02|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-12-02"><cite path="|36|02|04|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|02|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597); January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|02|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-12-02"><cite path="|36|02|04|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> adopted effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|02|04|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|02|04|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
