<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Unclaimed Lottery Prizes</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Prize Claiming Period.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unclaimed Monetary Award.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall retain an unclaimed monetary award for 182 days after the date of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Drawing in which the prize was won;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Date the Fast Play game ticket was sold; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Announced end of game for an instant ticket.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If no claim for a monetary award is made within 182 days, the Director shall transfer the monetary award to an unclaimed prize fund.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unclaimed Merchandise or Experiential Award.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall designate the time period for retaining unclaimed merchandise or an experiential award.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If no claim is made for merchandise or an experiential award within the time period designated by the Director, the Director shall designate how the Agency will handle the merchandise or experiential award consistent with any Agency contract or license agreement for the merchandise or experiential award.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If no time period has been designated by the Director for retaining unclaimed merchandise or an experiential award, the period for claiming the award may not exceed 182 days.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unclaimed Prizes Held Other Than 182 Days. The Director may hold a prize in a game or drawing for a period of time other than 182 days if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The game is not a weekly or daily lottery drawing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director designated the game as a bonus game or drawing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director designates the claiming period to be a time other than 182 days.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Unclaimed Prize Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prize money on winning tickets that have not been claimed within the claiming period for that game shall accrue to the unclaimed prize fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may institute bonus prizes using funds from the unclaimed prize fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The bonus prizes shall be determined by the Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director may change the number of bonus prize categories and the allocation of prize money among the prize categories.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Agency shall announce any change to the number of bonus prize categories and to the allocation of prize money among the prize categories.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-103">9-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-104">9-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-109">9-109</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-111">9-111</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-122">9-122</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 2013 (40:9 Md. R. 790)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-12-02"><cite path="|36|02|07|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|02|07|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite>, E amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
