<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Special Operation Licenses for Instant Ticket Lottery Machines</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to a retailer that is a veterans’ services organization and applies for and sells tickets under a special operation license for instant ticket lottery machines.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of this chapter, a veterans’ services organization licensed to sell tickets from an instant ticket lottery machine shall meet the requirements of this subtitle for a retailer licensed by the Agency.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Cashout voucher” means a printed slip of paper with a code indicating the amount of money payable to the individual who presents the ticket to an operation licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Contractor” or “Agency’s contractor” means a company selected by the Agency for the design, development, installation, implementation, operation, and maintenance of the Agency’s Instant Ticket Lottery Machine system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Facility” means the building where an operation licensee places instant ticket lottery machines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Instant ticket” means a preprinted ticket purchased from an instant ticket lottery machine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Instant ticket lottery machine” means a machine or other device provided to a retailer through the Agency’s contractor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Operation licensee” means the holder of a special operation license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Special operation license” or “operation license” means permission granted by the Agency under this chapter to sell instant tickets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Veterans’ services organization” means an organization that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tax exempt and organized as a veterans’ organization under §501(c)(19) or §501(c)(4) of the United States Internal Revenue Code; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Located in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Allegany County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Anne Arundel County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Baltimore City;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Baltimore County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Calvert County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Carroll County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Charles County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Frederick County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Garrett County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Harford County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Howard County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Montgomery County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Prince George’s County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>Saint Mary’s County; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Washington County.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Operation Licensee Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A veterans’ services organization may not operate instant ticket lottery machines without a special operation license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A veterans’ services organization may apply for a special operation license to operate up to 5 instant ticket lottery machines.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An operation licensee may be required by the Agency to qualify for and become authorized to operate under the Expanded Cashing Authority Program as set forth in <cite path="36.02.03.06">COMAR 36.02.03.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An operation licensee shall locate the licensed instant ticket lottery machines in its primary meeting hall.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Agency may restrict the permissible location within a facility of instant ticket lottery machines.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An operation licensee shall enter into an agreement with the Agency regarding the instant ticket lottery machine program that provides for the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Payment of rent for the instant ticket lottery machines;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Power, utility, security, and HVAC needs of the instant ticket lottery machines; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Operation, maintenance, ticket retention, record keeping, and reporting requirements of the instant ticket lottery machines.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Sales of Instant Tickets.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An operation licensee may sell an instant ticket only to an individual who is 18 years old or older.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An operation licensee shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Knowledgeable about the games available in the instant ticket lottery machine; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Able to show players how to access help screens in the instant ticket lottery machine.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The purchase of an instant ticket may not be cancelled.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Payment of Prizes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A cashout voucher may be presented for payment only to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The operation licensee where the voucher was printed; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An Agency claim center as defined in <cite path="36.02.06.01|B.|(1)">COMAR 36.02.06.01B(1)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Only a player who is an individual may present a cashout voucher for payment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="36.02.06.15">COMAR 36.02.06.15</cite> and <cite path="36.02.06.16">COMAR 36.02.06.16</cite> do not apply to claims for payment of a prize from an instant ticket lottery machine.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §§A—C of this regulation, an operation licensee shall pay the individual holder of a cashout voucher in accordance with the claims procedures described in <cite path="|36.02.06">COMAR 36.02.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-112">State Government Article, §9-112, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-13">Regulations <cite path="|36|02|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|02|09|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 12, 2014 (41:18 Md. R. 1008); adopted permanently effective October 13, 2014 (41:20 Md. R. 1115)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
