<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Procedure for Hearings in Contested Cases</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter contains procedures for administrative hearings in contested cases. These procedures are required by the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Contested case" means a proceeding to determine:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A right, duty, statutory entitlement, or privilege of a person that is required by statute or constitution to be determined only after an opportunity for an agency hearing; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The grant, denial, renewal, revocation, suspension, or amendment of a license that is required by statute or constitution to be determined only after an opportunity for an agency hearing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Decision maker" means the person or persons with authority to decide a contested case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Commerce.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Party" means one whose legal rights, duties, statutory entitlements, or privileges will be affected by the outcome of a contested case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notice and Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In a contested case all parties shall be afforded an opportunity for hearing after reasonable notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The notice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State the time, place, and nature of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the legal authority under which the hearing is to be held;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cite the particular sections of the statutes and regulations, including procedural regulations, that are pertinent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>State concisely and simply:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The facts that are asserted; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the facts cannot be stated in detail when the notice is given, the issues that are involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Hearing Officer.</heading>
    <text>The decision maker may request that the Office of Administrative Hearings designate an administrative law judge who shall conduct the hearing and submit in writing to the decision maker proposed findings of fact and proposed conclusions of law.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Representation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A party may appear in proper person or be represented by counsel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A corporation may be represented by an officer, agent, or attorney.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Parties and their attorneys shall give written notice to the hearing officer of their names and addresses in advance of the hearing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Evidence.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Probative evidence that reasonable and prudent individuals commonly accept in the conduct of their affairs may be admitted at a hearing and given probative effect.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Incompetent, irrelevant, immaterial, or unduly repetitious evidence may be excluded.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Documentary evidence may be submitted by parties before and at the hearings and for the period of time that the administrative law judge may designate the record to remain open after the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>On a genuine issue in a contested case, a party may call witnesses and cross-examine opposing witnesses.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The hearing shall be open to the public, unless otherwise provided by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon written notice 7 days before a hearing and upon payment of costs, a party may request that a hearing be transcribed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="24|01|04|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Ex Parte Communications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Persons other than advisory staff may not communicate ex parte with the administrative law judge or decision maker.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ex parte communications received in violation of <cite path="24|01|04|.08|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be placed in the record and disclosed to all parties, who shall then have 10 days within which to rebut them.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Record.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In the determination of a contested case, the decision maker may consider only evidence that is in the record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The record in a contested case shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pleadings and motions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentary evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Statements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Transcripts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Staff memoranda, unless privileged;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Proposed findings of fact, proposed conclusions of law, and exceptions to them;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Preliminary and final decisions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Other writing germane to the case and not otherwise privileged.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Decision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The decision maker may adopt, modify, or rewrite the administrative law judge's proposed findings of fact and proposed conclusions of law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a decision maker, or a majority of decision makers, has not heard the evidence, a proposed decision, including findings of fact and conclusions of law, shall be served on each party. Parties adversely affected by the proposed decision shall be afforded the opportunity, within 10 days after receipt of the proposed decision, to file exceptions and present argument to the decision maker or the majority of decision makers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Copies of the final decision and findings of fact and conclusions of law shall be delivered or mailed promptly to all parties or their attorneys.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Instead of a decision, a contested case may be disposed of by agreed settlement, consent order, or default.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Time Periods.</heading>
    <text>For good cause, the administrative law judge or decision maker may extend or waive time periods provided in these regulations.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Appeal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon issuance of a final decision, an aggrieved party may proceed to exhaust any remaining administrative remedies or seek judicial review in accordance with applicable law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon notice of appeal, the record shall be transmitted promptly to the appropriate appellate tribunal, but within the time period prescribed in the Maryland Rules of Procedure governing appeals from administrative agencies.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Interpretation.</heading>
    <text>These regulations are meant to complement the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act. In the event of conflict, the Act takes precedence over them.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|2-108">Economic Development Article, §2-108</cite>; State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-12-07">Effective date: December 7, 2006 (33:24 Md. R. 1907)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
