<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Open Meetings</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter contains procedures regarding the conduct of persons attending open meetings, and the recording and broadcasting of open meetings.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Commerce, and all boards, commissions, authorities, and councils within the Department, except for the Board of Appeals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Open session" means any meeting of the Department required to be open to the public by State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-501">10-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-512">10-512</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Public Attendance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At any open session of the Department, the general public is invited to attend and observe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except in instances when the Department expressly invites public testimony, questions, comments, or other forms of public participation, or when public participation is otherwise authorized by law, a member of the public attending an open session may not participate in the session.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="24|01|05|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Disruptive Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual attending an open session of the Department may not engage in any conduct, including visual demonstrations such as the waving of placards, signs, or banners, that disrupts the session or that interferes with the right of members of the public to attend and observe the session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The presiding officer may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Order an individual who engages in conduct prohibited by <cite path="24|01|05|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> or who violates any other regulation concerning the conduct of the open session to be removed from the session;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Request police or other assistance to restore order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Recess the session while order is restored.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Recording, Photographing, and Broadcasting of Open Sessions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A member of the public, including any representative of the news media, may record discussions of the Department at an open session by means of a tape recorder or other recording device if the device does not create noise that disturbs members of the Department or others attending the sessions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A member of the public, including any representative of the news media, may photograph or videotape the proceedings of the Department at an open session if the camera:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is operated without excessively bright artificial light that disturbs members of the Department or others attending the session; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not create noise that disturbs members of the Department or others attending the session.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A representative of the news media may broadcast or televise the proceedings of the Department at an open session if the equipment used:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is operated without excessively bright artificial light that disturbs members of the Department or others attending the session; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not create noise that disturbs members of the Department or others attending the session.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The presiding officer may restrict the movement of an individual who is using a recording device, camera, or broadcasting or televising equipment if this restriction is necessary to maintain the orderly conduct of the session.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Recordings Not Part of Record.</heading>
    <text>A recording of an open session made by a member of the public, or any transcript derived from this recording, is not considered a part of the record of any proceeding of the Department.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|2-108">Economic Development Article, §2-108</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-507">State Government Article, §10-507</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-12-07">Effective date: December 7, 1992 (19:24 Md. R. 2127)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
