<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Information Provided by the Department</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Information Provided.</heading>
    <text>The Department will provide the following information:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In answer to written or telephoned requests, the Department will provide free of charge the following information for domestic corporations, limited partnerships, limited liability partnerships, limited liability companies, and any other organization which is required to file its original organizational document or trade name with the Department:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Address of principal office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of incorporation or date of filing the certificate of limited partnership, the certificate of limited liability partnership, the articles of organization of a limited liability company, any other original organizational document, or the trade name certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Resident agent for service, or for business entities that have filed a trade name certificate, the names and addresses of the principal or owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In answer to written or telephoned requests, the Department will provide free of charge the following information for foreign corporations, limited partnerships, limited liability partnerships, limited liability companies, and other foreign organizations which are required to qualify or register with the Department:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Address of principal office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of qualification or registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Resident agent for service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In answer to written requests, the Department will provide free of charge information as to availability of trade names and names for corporations, limited partnerships, limited liability partnerships, and limited liability companies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>On written request and accompanied by a fee, the Department will prepare and forward an abstract comprising the items listed above, and, in addition:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The names of corporate officers and directors as listed on the most recent report filed with the Department, if available;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the corporation is delinquent as to filing required reports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether a domestic corporation has had its charter forfeited, or whether a foreign corporation has had its qualification or registration withdrawn or forfeited, and the dates of these proceedings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether a domestic corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or other domestic organization which is required to file its original organizational document with the Department, has been dissolved, has had its certificate withdrawn or has merged into another organization, and the dates of these proceedings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Whether a foreign corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or other foreign organization which is required to qualify or register with the Department, has had its qualification or registration withdrawn or cancelled or has been merged into another organization, and the dates of these proceedings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Certificates and Certified Copies.</heading>
    <text>When the Department provides certificates or certified copies, the signature of the custodian or other person authorized to make certification for the Department and the Department's official seal may be originally produced on a computer-generated printed form approved by the Department.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|2-201">Tax-Property Article, §2-201</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|1-406">Corporations and Associations Article, §1-406</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-01-07">Effective date: January 7, 1982 (8:26 Md. R. 2106)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-09-21"><cite path="|18|04|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 7, 1983 (10:22 Md. R. 1968); August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1320); September 21, 1998 (25:19 Md. R. 1496)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-06-04"><cite path="|18|04|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective June 4, 1999 (26:12 Md. R. 926)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
