<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Key Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to all real property owned or occupied by a unit which is secured by a lock needing a key to gain access.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Key" includes electronic card keys and similar devices that perform locking or unlocking functions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"State" means the State of Maryland or any unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"State real property" means any land or improvements, structures, or fixtures on land leased or owned by the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Unit" means a department, agency, board, commission, university, college, or other entity of State government.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Unit" does not mean political subdivisions and units of political subdivisions of the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities for Authorizing Manufacture, Duplication, and Distribution of Keys.</heading>
    <text>Every unit shall appoint an employee who shall be responsible for authorizing the manufacture, duplication, distribution, and possession of keys capable of locking and unlocking doors, gates, or barriers in or on State real property used by the unit.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="04|04|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Maintenance of a List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each unit shall keep current lists of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All State real property owned, controlled, or used by the unit for which keys are used to gain access;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All employees who have been authorized to be given keys to the property; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All employees given keys to the property.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each unit shall provide current copies of the lists in <cite path="04|04|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> to the chief law enforcement or security officer of that unit, or if the unit has none, to the Assistant Secretary for Facilities Operations and Maintenance of the Department of General Services.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Markings.</heading>
    <text>Any key capable of being used in locks on State real property shall be clearly marked with the words "DO NOT DUPLICATE" or "UNLAWFUL TO DUPLICATE" and shall bear symbology indicating ownership by the State.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Use and Possession of Keys.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any key subject to these regulations may be used, distributed, maintained, or duplicated only with the written permission of a person identified in <cite path="|04|04|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person, firm, or organization may not use, distribute, manufacture, duplicate, or possess keys capable of being used in locks in or on State real property unless the use, distribution, manufacture, duplication, or possession is in accordance with Regulations <cite path="|04|04|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|04|04|01|.06">.06</cite> of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <text>As provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|7-204">Criminal Law Article, §7-204, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, any person, firm, or organization found guilty of violating these regulations shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction shall pay a fine of not more than $500 for each offense.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|7-204">Criminal Law Article, §7-204, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2003-05-12">Effective date: May 12, 2003 (30:9 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
