<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Security Cards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>These regulations are applicable to all State real property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>It is the intent of these regulations to ensure the safety of all persons working, visiting, conducting business, or otherwise lawfully in, on, or about State real property.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Department of General Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Maryland Capitol Police (MCP)” means the Department of General Services Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Prox privileges” means privileges associated with a proximity card, integrated with the security card, and used for access control applications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of General Services or the Secretary's designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Security card” means a State of Maryland employee security card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“State” means the State of Maryland or any unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“State real property” means any land or improvements, structures, or fixtures on land leased or owned by the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Unit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Unit” means a department, agency, board, commission, university, college, or other entity of State government.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Unit” does not mean a political subdivision or a unit of a political subdivision of the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Issuance of Security Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In accordance with this chapter, the Secretary shall issue a security card to each State employee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may issue a security card to an individual other than a State employee, including but not limited to a contractor, lobbyist, media personnel, local government official, or volunteer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any duties assigned by this chapter to the Secretary may be delegated by the Secretary to the MCP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All prox privileges associated with a security card shall be subject to criteria established by MCP as approved by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may authorize and the MCP shall conduct a security clearance investigation prior to issuance of a security card to an individual other than a State employee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Surrender of Security Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A security card is the property of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A security card issued to a State employee shall be surrendered upon:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The employee's separation from State employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demand by the employee's supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Demand by the Secretary; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Demand by the MCP.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Surrender Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon separation from State employment or upon a demand under this regulation, a State employee shall surrender the employee’s security card to the personnel division of the employee’s unit or MCP as the case may be.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon the employee’s surrender of the security card, the personnel division of the unit or MCP shall issue a receipt to the employee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The personnel division shall return the surrendered security card to the MCP within 10 days after the employee’s surrender of the card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon notification by the employee’s personnel division, any prox privileges associated with the surrendered security card shall be cancelled by MCP.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon the failure of a State employee or former State employee to surrender the employee's security card under this regulation, the Secretary may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Place or cause to be placed a hold on the payment of any separation benefits, including but not limited to severance pay and retirement benefits, until the employee surrenders the employee's security card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Withhold a reasonable fee from any wages or other monies to be paid to the employee, if the employee notifies the Secretary that the security card has been lost; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refer the matter for criminal prosecution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A security card issued to an individual other than a State employee shall be surrendered to the MCP upon demand by the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Secretary; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>MCP.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upon the failure of an individual other than a State employee to surrender the individual's security card under this regulation, the Secretary may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Place or cause to be placed a hold on any monies due the individual until such time as the individual surrenders the individual's security card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Withhold a reasonable fee from any monies due the individual, if the individual notifies the Secretary that the security card has been lost; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refer the matter for criminal prosecution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notification to the Department of Employee Separation from the Service.</heading>
    <text>The personnel division of the employee’s unit shall notify the MCP within 30 days upon the separation of service of any employee with security card privileges and shall provide the name of the affected employee.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of Holders of Security Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to be issued a security card, an individual shall complete and submit a security card application, including written authorization to withhold the employee's wages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The security card application shall be in a form prescribed by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall review and may approve or deny a security card application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A holder of a security card shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the MCP in writing within 30 days of any changes to the information entered into the security card application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Immediately report a lost or stolen security card to the employee’s supervisor, if a State employee, and the MCP; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When on State real property:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Display the security card:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On the outermost garment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In the area of the upper chest; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>So as to be visible at all times; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Produce the security card upon demand by a member of MCP, a police officer, or authorized security personnel.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A holder of security card may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Place the security card in a holder or cover the security card in a manner that impacts the viewing and examination of the security card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Loan or allow the security card to be used by another individual for any reason;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Alter, copy, photograph, or reproduce the security card, or allow the security card to be altered, copied, photographed, or reproduced; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Grant entry, exit, or other prox privileges on any State real property to anyone but the security card holder.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="04|04|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="04|04|02|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Secretary may charge a fee for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The replacement of a lost security card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The failure of a State employee to surrender the employee's security card upon separation from State employment or demand under <cite path="|04|04|02|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The failure of an individual other than a State employee to surrender the individual's security card upon demand under <cite path="|04|04|02|.04|E.">Regulation .04E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fees established for security cards are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Lobbyist — $50;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contractor — $50; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Replacement fees as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>First loss — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Second loss — $100; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each successive loss — $250 subject to authorization from DGSP.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may not charge a fee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To replace a damaged security card, if the damage was unintentional and the security card is surrendered; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To issue a security card with updated personal or employment information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Deduct from the wages due a State employee any fee that may be owed under this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deduct from any monies due an individual other than a State employee any fee that may be charged under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The violation by a State employee of any regulation under this chapter may result in the revocation of the employee's security card and any associated privileges as well as criminal prosecution as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|9-704">Criminal Law Article, §9-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The violation by an individual other than a State employee of any regulation under this chapter may result in the revocation of the individual's security card and any associated privileges as well as criminal prosecution as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|9-704">Criminal Law Article, §9-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|9-704">Criminal Law Article, §9-704</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|3-503">Labor and Employment Article, §3-503(4)</cite>;<br/>State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-604">4-604</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-607">4-607</cite>(a);  Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-21">Effective date: April 21, 2008 (35:8 Md. R. 804)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|04|04|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|04|04|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite>—E amended effective April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|04|04|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|04|04|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|04|04|02|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
