<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Enforcement Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <text>The enforcement provisions of this chapter apply to alleged violations of the Public Ethics Law by any:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Official or employee of the Executive Branch;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Public official or employee of the Legislative or Judicial Branch;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Member of the General Assembly as to matters concerning the financial disclosure requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Person or entity subject to the lobbying provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 7, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Candidate for office as a State official, who is required to file financial disclosure pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Constitutional officer-elect in an executive agency;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Former employee subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-504">General Provisions Article, §5-504, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Other person or entity identified by State law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Hearing" means a hearing conducted by the Commission pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-404">General Provisions Article, §5-404, </cite>and the Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Party" includes only the respondent and the staff counsel or other counsel designated by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Preliminary Inquiry.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Preliminary inquiry" means the process by which a matter may be presented to the Commission for preliminary review to determine whether the matter should be processed as a complaint in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-401">General Provisions Article, §5-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Preliminary inquiry" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Investigation and review of the matter by Commission staff or other individual designated by the Commission; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Consideration of the matter by the Commission.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Preliminary investigation" means the investigation conducted by the staff counsel or other investigator identified by the Commission, after a complaint has been accepted or issued and been referred by the Commission pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-403">General Provisions Article, §5-403, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Respondent" includes, when appropriate to the context of this chapter, counsel speaking or acting on the respondent's behalf in connection with an enforcement matter subject to this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Staff counsel" includes, when appropriate to the context of this chapter, any other person designated by the Commission to perform the functions of the staff counsel in accordance with this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Confidentiality.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General Rules.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as set forth in §B(2)—(4) of this regulation, during the pendency of any preliminary inquiry by Commission staff pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> or following the filing of a complaint, the proceedings, meetings, and activities of the Commission and its employees in connection with the complaint shall be conducted in a confidential manner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except as set forth in §B(2)—(4) of this regulation, the Commission, its staff, the complainant, and the respondent may not disclose any information relating to the complaint, including the identity of the complainant and the respondent.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exceptions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Commission may release information at any time if the respondent has agreed in writing to the release.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The identity of the complainant shall be disclosed to the respondent at any time in response to a written request from the respondent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Information may be disclosed by the Commission or the Commission's staff as necessary to conduct a preliminary inquiry, investigation, or hearing, or to issue subpoenas at the request of the respondent pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-404">General Provisions Article, §5-404, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Confidentiality does not apply to referral or release of information to a prosecuting authority pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-408">General Provisions Article, §5-408, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Confidentiality may be waived by the respondent, and information disclosed accordingly as part of a cure, settlement, or other prehearing resolution of an enforcement proceeding pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Information Provided to a Complainant.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A complainant shall be provided information regarding the status of an enforcement matter as set forth in §B(3)(b) and (c) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The staff counsel shall notify the complainant that evidence is being referred to the Commission for preliminary disposition, at least 15 days before referring the evidence to the Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The complainant shall be provided with a copy of a signed order of the Commission dismissing a complaint if after:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Preliminary consideration of the evidence, it is determined that the evidence does not merit further proceedings and that dismissal is not contrary to the purposes of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Consideration of the evidence at a hearing, it is determined that the respondent has not violated any of the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Confidentiality after Hearing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The confidentiality requirements apply, as set forth in §B(4)(b)—(c) of this regulation, to written reports setting forth findings of fact and conclusions of law required after a hearing by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-405">General Provisions Article, §5-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|19A|01|03|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When there is a finding that there was no violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the requirements of <cite path="19A|01|03|.02|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> apply, and there may not be disclosure of information.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When there is a finding of violation as to any allegation of the complaint, the written report of the Commission shall be a public record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Subpoena Powers and Oaths.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The staff counsel of the Commission may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Administer oaths and affirmations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Subject to the supervision of the Executive Director, issue subpoenas to compel the attendance and testimony of witnesses or for the production of books, papers, records, documents, or other tangible objects.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On its own or through its designee, administer oaths and affirmations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On its own motion, issue subpoenas to compel the attendance and testimony of witnesses or for the production of books, papers, records, documents, or other tangible objects.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The respondent may, as set forth in §C(4)—(6) of this regulation, use the subpoena power of the Commission in preparation for any hearing to be held in accordance with this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Respondent subpoenas pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.02|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite> shall be issued only in response to a written request by or on behalf of the respondent received by the Commission not later than 10 working days before the date set for the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Respondent subpoenas pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.02|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite> may be issued by the Commission or by the Commission Chairman acting on behalf of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Service and enforcement of any respondent subpoena issued pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.02|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite> is the responsibility of the respondent or other person acting on respondent's behalf, not of the Commission or its staff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Subpoenas issued pursuant to this section and General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-207">5-207</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-404">5-404</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, are judicially enforceable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Referral.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If, while an enforcement matter is being considered, it is determined that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the respondent may have committed a criminal offense, the Commission or the Commission's staff, upon direction from the Commission or the Chairman, shall refer the matter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Promptly to an appropriate prosecuting authority for an evaluation of whether criminal prosecution is appropriate; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Directly to the appropriate prosecuting authority for prosecution.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When an enforcement matter is referred to a prosecuting authority for evaluation or prosecution, the Commission may suspend action by the Commission or the Commission's staff on the matter pending completion of action by the prosecuting authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When an enforcement matter is referred to a prosecuting authority for evaluation or prosecution, the Commission shall make available to the prosecuting authority all pertinent evidence under the Commission's control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Commission staff may consult with a prosecuting authority in connection with the possible referral of a matter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Counsel. The respondent in an enforcement matter conducted pursuant to this chapter is entitled to be represented by counsel for any purpose, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Representation in connection with interviews of the respondent by the staff counsel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submission of any written or other materials on respondent's behalf in connection with the investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Personal appearance on respondent's behalf at any stage of the matter where respondent's appearance before the Commission is permitted or required.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Service.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="19A|01|03|.02|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>, service of any document required to be served by this chapter shall be by regular mail, postage prepaid, to the respondent or other addressee at their last known address.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instead of service by mail, the hearing notice may be served by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Personal service by an individual over 18 years old, as evidenced by an affidavit of personal service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Service by the Sheriff of the county of the addressee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Registered or certified mail, restricted delivery, return receipt requested.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If required service is to a person represented by an attorney, mail or delivery to the attorney's last known business address is considered satisfactory service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Appointment of Interpreter. If a party or witness cannot readily hear, speak, understand, or communicate the spoken English language, the Commission may, of its own volition, or shall, upon written application of the party or witness, appoint a qualified interpreter to provide assistance during the hearing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Preliminary Inquiry.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may consider as a preliminary inquiry any matter that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Arises from any source, including the consideration of an advisory opinion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Involves past or ongoing conduct; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Presents a possible violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The staff counsel shall, upon the direction of the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collect and review information pertaining to a preliminary inquiry; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Present this information to the Commission for its consideration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission may close a preliminary inquiry without issuing a complaint if the Commission determines that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The matter is not within the jurisdiction of the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The information presented does not support the filing of a complaint; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Based on all the circumstances presented, further enforcement proceedings would not serve the purposes of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A preliminary inquiry may also be closed by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Docketing the matter for consideration as an advisory opinion pursuant to COMAR 19A.01.02;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Letter or other informal advice; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other resolution agreed to by the subject.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Complaints.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complaints from a Person.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may file a complaint with the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A complaint filed by a person pursuant to this section shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be written, signed, and under oath;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Allege a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, by an official, employee, or any other person subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contain sufficient facts to permit a preliminary investigation to be undertaken.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall accept for further proceedings any complaint filed by a person pursuant to this section unless the complaint:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is plainly frivolous; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not comply with the requirements of this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complaints by the Commission.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may issue a complaint on its own motion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may issue a complaint pursuant to this section when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A preliminary inquiry pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> results in sufficient evidence to believe a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may have occurred; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Informal review in connection with an advisory opinion request under COMAR 19A.01.02 discloses information suggesting that past or continuing conduct of an official, employee, or other person subject to General Provisions Article, Title 5, may constitute a violation of General Provisions Article, Title 5.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Commission complaint shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Signed on the Commission's behalf by the Chairman or another member as authorized by the Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Otherwise in the same format as a complaint from any other person as set forth in <cite path="19A|01|03|.04|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Issued pursuant to action by the Commission taken consistent with the procedures set forth in COMAR 19A.01.01.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Amended Complaints.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consistent with the requirements of <cite path="19A|01|03|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Commission may on its own motion issue an amended complaint in any complaint either accepted or issued pursuant to §A or B of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An amended complaint may be issued based on additional information submitted by a complainant or on information available to the Commission as a result of a preliminary investigation and review as set forth in Regulations .05 and .06 of this chapter, and may either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Add or delete allegations as justified by the information; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Clarify the allegations of the original complaint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An amended complaint is subject to the same investigatory, review, and notice procedures as the original complaint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A copy of any complaint or amended complaint accepted or issued by the Commission pursuant to §§A—C of this regulation shall be served on the respondent as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Preliminary Staff Investigation and Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complaints issued by the Commission or filed and accepted by the Commission pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> shall be referred to the staff counsel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Collection of Evidence.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The staff counsel shall collect evidence relating to the allegations of the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evidence may be collected by personal interview, interrogatory, deposition, review of documents, or any other usual investigatory method.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In the collection of evidence pursuant to this section, the subpoena power of <cite path="|19A|01|03|.01|C.|(1)">Regulation .01C(1) of this chapter</cite> may be relied upon to compel the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of books, papers, records, documents, or other tangible objects.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notification and Respondent Action.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The staff counsel shall notify the complainant and the respondent of the anticipated presentation of the evidence to the Commission at least 15 days before presenting the evidence to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The respondent may take action to cure all alleged violations within 15 days of receipt of the notification provided in accordance with <cite path="19A|01|03|.05|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, and advise the staff counsel of this action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In response to the notification of <cite path="19A|01|03|.05|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, the respondent may also submit materials or other proposed resolution for consideration by or negotiation with the staff counsel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staff Counsel Preliminary Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The staff counsel shall provide the Commission with a preliminary report including all evidence collected relating to the allegations of the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The preliminary report to the Commission shall include any evidence of cure action taken by the respondent, any resolution of the complaint proposed by the respondent, and any other agreement or proposed resolution of the complaint agreed to by respondent and staff counsel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The preliminary report may include a recommended disposition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A proposed disposition or proposed resolution agreed to by staff counsel and the respondent is a recommendation only, and may not be binding on the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Commission Preliminary Consideration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall consider the preliminary report submitted by the staff counsel pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall dismiss the complaint if it determines that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The report contains evidence of a cure of all violations, and dismissal would not be contrary to the purposes of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The evidence does not raise sufficient likelihood of a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to merit further proceedings; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A proposed resolution agreed to by the staff counsel and the respondent is accepted and supports a conclusion that the matter does not merit further proceedings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Dismissal of a complaint pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By written order signed by the Chairman or other designated member on behalf of the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Served on the respondent as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a complaint filed by a person other than the Commission is dismissed pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the complainant shall be advised of the fact of the dismissal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If, after preliminary consideration by the Commission, a complaint is not dismissed pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Commission shall issue a hearing notice as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Hearing Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a complaint is not dismissed by preliminary Commission determination, a hearing shall be scheduled and a hearing notice shall be issued by the Chairman or other designated member acting on the Commission's behalf.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A hearing notice shall include a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Statement of the time, place, and nature of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Statement of the legal authority and jurisdiction under which the hearing is to be held;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reference to the relevant sections of the statutes, regulations, and rules of procedure involved;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Short and simple statement of the matters asserted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Statement that failure to appear for the scheduled hearing may result in adverse action against the respondent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Statement that the respondent may agree to the evidence and waive the right to appear at the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Statement of the respondent's right to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Call witnesses and submit documents or other evidence as provided in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Use the subpoena power of the Commission as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|C.">Regulation .02C of this chapter</cite>,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Receive a copy of the Commission's enforcement procedures found in this chapter if not otherwise provided, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Be represented by counsel in the hearing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If, in a hearing notice issued pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Commission is unable to state the matters in detail at the time the hearing notice is served, the initial notice may be limited to a statement of issues involved. Thereafter, upon application, a more definite and detailed statement shall be furnished.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A hearing notice issued pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be served on the respondent as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Settlements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At any time after a matter is initiated and before a final determination by the Commission, the staff counsel and respondent may develop a proposed settlement of the matter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A proposed settlement may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be based on admissions or stipulations of fact or law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recite actions taken or agreed to be taken by the parties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include any sanction, penalty, or action agreed to be imposed or taken as a result of Commission acceptance of the proposed settlement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Include any other provisions allowable by law that would define the framework for resolution of the matter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A proposed settlement shall be in writing, agreed to by the staff counsel and the respondent, and may be by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Stipulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consent order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Waiver of hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Settlement agreement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other appropriate format.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A proposed settlement agreed to by the staff counsel and the respondent shall be presented to the Commission for consideration by joint motion of the parties and may be the basis for a joint request for postponement of a scheduled hearing on the complaint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Commission Action.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may not be bound by a proposed settlement or other resolution reached by the staff counsel and the respondent, and may accept or reject the proposed resolution as the purposes of the Ethics Law may require.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A settlement accepted by the Commission may form the basis for final action by the Commission to be reflected in a final order issued pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Offers of settlement or compromise which are not accepted by the Commission may not be made a part of the case record or otherwise admitted into evidence in the hearing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Prehearing Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Discovery and Disclosure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The respondent has the right to inspect and to copy any document that is accessible under the Maryland Public Information Act, General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">4-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-601">4-601</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, as set forth in COMAR 19A.01.01.04.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a prehearing conference is not held, the respondent and the staff counsel shall submit to the general counsel, at least 10 working days before the scheduled date of the hearing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A proposed list of their witnesses and possible documentary evidence to be introduced at the hearing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An estimate of the anticipated length of the presentation of their case.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Chairman may prohibit the introduction of documentary or testimonial evidence not disclosed before the hearing as provided in <cite path="19A|01|03|.09|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prehearing Conferences.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In its discretion, the Commission may direct the Chairman or another designated member to conduct a prehearing conference in any matter scheduled for a hearing pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, either on the initiative of the Commission or at the request of the staff counsel or the respondent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notice shall be provided to the staff counsel and respondent of the date, time, and place of a prehearing conference called pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.09|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>, as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A prehearing conference shall be designed to simplify the hearing by resolving preliminary matters, and may address the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issuance of respondent subpoenas or other matters pertaining to discovery or disclosure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The possibility of obtaining stipulations, admissions, agreements on documents, understandings on matters already of record or judicially noticeable, or similar agreement that will avoid unnecessary proof;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identification of witnesses or documentary evidence, and consideration of limiting the number of expert witnesses or the presentation of similar cumulative evidence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The order of presentation and scheduling of the hearing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Preliminary motions presented by either party; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other matters that will simplify or clarify the issues or otherwise promote the orderly and prompt conduct of the hearing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The proceedings at a prehearing conference shall be recorded.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Chairman or other member may issue a prehearing order that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recites the results of the preliminary conference;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Includes any rulings on motions considered at the prehearing conference;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Clarifies any scheduling or related issues; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sets forth any other actions taken, or to be taken, with regard to any matter addressed at the prehearing conference.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Comments on or disagreement by the staff counsel or respondent with the prehearing order shall be filed with the Chairman or other member not later than 5 working days after service of the prehearing order. A dispute shall be ruled upon by the Chairman or other member before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A prehearing order issued pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.09|B.|(6)">§B(6) of this regulation</cite> is a part of the complaint record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Motions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for extraordinary situations or as otherwise provided in these regulations, preliminary matters requiring a formal ruling shall be raised by motions at either the prehearing conference or at least 15 working days before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Motions shall be in writing and state briefly the relief applied for and the grounds for the motion and, when appropriate, be supported by a memorandum of points and authorities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A response to a motion shall be filed with the Commission within 10 working days after receiving the initial motion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A motion or response shall be served on the opposing party as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Chairman may rule on the motion at any time before, during, or after the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Postponement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon request from the staff counsel or the respondent, the Chairman may grant a postponement of the hearing for good cause as set forth in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requests for postponement shall be confirmed in writing, served on the opposing party as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>, and shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The reason for the request; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When appropriate, a list of at least three dates within the 60-day period following the day on which the hearing was originally scheduled on which the party would be available for a hearing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Requests for postponement shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except in extraordinary circumstances or when requested in connection with a settlement proposal, be denied if made after a prehearing conference; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be granted only if the party requesting the postponement clearly demonstrates that the request is made in good faith and that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Hardship will result from its denial, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Postponement is required as part of a settlement consideration.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whenever feasible, a postponed hearing that is to be held shall be rescheduled within 60 days of the date the hearing was originally scheduled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="19A|01|03|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Failure to Attend Hearing, and Default.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If after receiving proper notice a party fails to attend or participate in the hearing, the party shall be considered in default and the hearing may be conducted and the issues finally determined in the party's absence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days after mailing of a final decision following a default, the party may file a written request that the decision be vacated, stating the reasons relied upon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The final decision may be vacated by the Commission if it is found that there is an:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Actual controversy in the matter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equitable excuse for the default.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conduct of the Hearing by the Chairman or Designee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Commission hearing conducted pursuant to this chapter shall be conducted by the Chairman or another member designated by the Commission. The member so designated may exercise all powers assigned to the Chairman by this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chairman shall convene the hearing and shall place the complaint, hearing notices, and other appropriate documents in the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Chairman has the power to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Conduct a fair and impartial hearing, take action to avoid unnecessary delay in the disposition of proceedings, and maintain order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Rule on offers of proof and receipt of evidence in accordance with the general principles set forth in <cite path="19A|01|03|.10|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consider and rule upon all motions appropriate to the proceedings; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Recess the hearing for any reasonable purpose, for example:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In response to requests of the parties,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>To allow the parties to prepare final argument, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>To enable the Commission to consider action on motions or undertake preliminary consideration of the case.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Rights of Parties. Each party to the hearing has the right to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Present opening and closing statements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Call witnesses and present evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cross-examine every witness called by the Commission or any other party;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Impeach any witness regardless of which party first called the witness to testify; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Rebut all evidence presented.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Ex Parte Communications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission staff counsel shall be responsible for presenting evidence to the Commission in connection with a complaint proceeding subject to a hearing under this regulation, and may not be part of the decisional process in connection with a complaint. The general counsel of the Commission, or other individual designated by the Commission, shall be the legal advisor to the Commission regarding complaint proceedings and in that capacity is considered to be part of the decisional process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The staff counsel, the Executive Director, respondent, respondent's counsel, and any other individual not involved in the decisional process may not communicate ex parte with any member of the Commission or with the general counsel regarding any issue of fact or law in connection with a complaint being heard pursuant to this regulation. The Commission may communicate with members of an advisory staff, including the general counsel, who participate as part of the decisional process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ex parte communications received in violation of <cite path="19A|01|03|.10|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be placed in the record and disclosed to all parties, who shall then have 10 days within which to rebut them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The general counsel or any member of the Commission may, if he or she considers it necessary to eliminate the effect of a prohibited ex parte communication, disqualify himself or herself from further participation in the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Presentation of Evidence.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evidence shall be presented by the parties at the hearing consistent with terms agreed to in a prehearing conference or as set forth in any schedules previously exchanged by the parties in anticipation of the hearing, unless a deviation from the agreed upon process is expressly allowed by the Chairman.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The staff counsel shall present to the Commission evidence collected in the investigation relating to the complaint that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Relevant to the matters at issue as set forth in the hearing notice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Set forth in any preliminary agreement by the parties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consistent with a prehearing order issued by the Chairman or the Chairman's designee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Otherwise allowed by the Chairman.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The respondent may present evidence either through counsel or on the respondent's own behalf that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Relevant to the matters at issue as set forth in the hearing notice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Set forth in any preliminary agreement by the parties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consistent with a prehearing order issued by the Chairman or the Chairman's designee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Otherwise allowed by the Chairman.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Evidence shall be received by the Commission in accordance with the following principles:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The hearing need not be conducted according to the technical rules of evidence, and any relevant evidence, including hearsay of probative value, is admissible.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Oral evidence shall be taken only on oath or affirmation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Evidence which possesses probative value commonly accepted by reasonable and prudent persons in the conduct of their affairs may be admitted and given probative value. The rules of privilege shall be given effect, and incompetent, immaterial, and unduly repetitious evidence may be excluded.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Except as set forth in §E(4)(e) and (f) of this regulation, all evidence, including records and documents in the possession of the Commission, of which the Commission desires to avail itself, shall be offered and made a part of the record in the case. Other factual information or evidence may not be considered in the determination of the case. Documentary evidence may be received in the form of copies or excerpts, or by incorporation by reference.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Commission may take notice of judicially cognizable facts or general, technical, or scientific facts within their specialized knowledge, as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-213">State Government Article, §10-213, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. Commission members may use their experience, technical competence, and specialized knowledge in the evaluation of evidence presented to them. The parties shall be advised of any fact officially noticed pursuant to this paragraph and be given an opportunity to contest the fact.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The existence of offers of settlement or compromise considered in the preliminary enforcement process are considered privileged communications and may not be admitted into evidence at the hearing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>At the completion of the hearing the Chairman may, in the Chairman's own discretion or at the request of the parties, declare the record to be open for a specified period to enable the parties to submit written arguments or other documents that are relevant to the issues presented in the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Hearing Record.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verbatim Record.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="19A|01|03|.10|G.|(1)|(b)">§G(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>, a verbatim record shall be taken of the entire hearing. In addition to the stenographic or recorded record of testimony in the case, a verbatim record shall include motions by the parties and rulings by the Chairman, the opening and closing arguments of the parties, and any oral decisions of the Commission that are made in the context of the hearing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unless requested by the respondent in writing, or otherwise at the discretion of the Commission, hearings on financial disclosure complaints under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may be conducted without a verbatim record.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When a verbatim record is not kept, minutes of the proceedings shall be kept which shall, at a minimum, identify the witnesses, list all exhibits, and record all rulings by the Chairman, as well as any preliminary or final Commission determination.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A stenographic or recorded verbatim record, or the minutes of a hearing, need not be transcribed unless requested by a party or the Commission. The party requesting the transcript shall pay for the cost of transcription.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An official record of the hearing shall be developed, including the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All pleadings, motions, and intermediate and final rulings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentary evidence received or considered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any statement of matters officially noticed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any questions and offers of proof, objections, and rulings on them;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any proposed findings and exceptions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any written arguments or documents submitted by a party after the hearing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Copies of testimony or minutes transcribed pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.10|G.|(1)|(c)">§G(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The decision of the Commission issued pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Any memoranda of ex parte communications submitted pursuant to <cite path="19A|01|03|.10|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Commission Decision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Commission decision following a hearing shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Made in accordance with its regular procedures as set forth in COMAR 19A.01.01; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Based on a preponderance of the evidence presented at the hearing as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.10|E.">Regulation .10E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If, after a hearing, the Commission finds that a respondent has violated <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Commission shall issue a written report that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Includes findings of facts and conclusions of law for each of the violations alleged in the hearing notice; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disposes of all disputed issues referenced in the hearing notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Commission finds that the respondent has not violated any of the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as alleged in the hearing notice, the Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue an order dismissing the complaint; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promptly send a copy of the order to the complainant and the respondent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Sanctions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Commission finds that the respondent has violated any of the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Commission may take any action authorized in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-405">General Provisions Article, §5-405 </cite>or Title 5, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In determining the sanctions to impose in a matter involving a finding of a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 7, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Commission may consider all relevant factors, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The extent to which the respondent derived financial benefit from the prohibited conduct;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The willfulness of the prohibited conduct;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any history of violations of the Public Ethics Law by the respondent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The severity of the violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The cost of investigating and prosecuting the case against the respondent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The necessity to protect the public interest and the integrity of the governmental process; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Any conviction of the individual regulated lobbyist of bribery, theft, or other crime involving moral turpitude based on acts arising from lobbying activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the Commission finds that the respondent has violated the financial disclosure or lobbying reporting provisions of General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitles 6 and 7, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Commission shall impose late fees as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-405">General Provisions Article, §5-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An order issued by the Commission pursuant to this regulation shall be served on the parties as set forth in <cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|F.">Regulation .02F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A final default order issued pursuant to <cite path="|19A|01|03|.10|A.">Regulation .10A of this chapter</cite> shall be issued as a final decision consistent with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Commission may seek judicial enforcement of any order issued pursuant to this regulation, or any other relief as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Judicial Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If aggrieved by a final order of the Commission, the respondent may request judicial review in accordance with the provisions of the Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-222">State Government Article, §10-222, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The final order of the Commission shall be stayed automatically until the time for seeking judicial review has expired.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a timely appeal for judicial review is filed, action to implement the final order shall be stayed until the final disposition of the matter by the court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may take action to seek judicial imposition of fines as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-902">General Provisions Article, §5-902, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, Title 5, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-03-20">Effective date: March 20, 1981 (8:6 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-26">Regulations <cite path="|19A|01|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|19A|01|03|.08">.08</cite> under chapter "Complaint Procedures" repealed effective September 26, 1994 (21:19 Md. R. 1635)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-26" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|19A|01|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|19A|01|03|.12">.12</cite> under chapter "Enforcement Procedures" adopted effective September 26, 1994 (21:19 Md. R. 1635)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|19A|01|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|19A|01|03|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite>, C amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|19A|01|03|.10|G.">Regulation .10G</cite> amended effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-25"><cite path="|19A|01|03|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective August 8, 2011 (38:16 Md. R. 946); May 25, 2015 (42:10 Md. R. 685)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
