<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Certification Standards and Procedures for Emergency Services Instructors</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>NFPA 1041 Standard for Fire and Emergency Services Instructor Professional Qualifications (National Fire Protection Association, 2019 Edition) is incorporated by reference.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Application process” means the date the Application for State Emergency Services Instructor Certification or Recertification is received from the sponsoring agency by the MICRB.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Approval" means approval as statutorily applied to the Maryland Fire-Rescue Education and Training Commission (MFRETC) as an agency of the Maryland Higher Education Commission (MHEC), under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">Education Article, §11-105, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, before a postsecondary institution can award a certificate, diploma, or degree to an individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Certification" means to verify that an individual has met the requirements of these standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Emergency services" means fire, rescue, and emergency medical services, with emergency medical services also meaning "emergency care" as related to training.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Field evolutions" means a structured training exercise designed to complete a specific training objective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Local emergency services instructor" means an individual who is designated to instruct by the local jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Local jurisdiction" means any city, county, municipal, or State government, public fire-rescue or emergency medical services department, State-approved public school, or postsecondary institution providing emergency services training or education, and other institutions as approved by the Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board (MICRB).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board (MICRB)" means an independent five-member board created as a unit within the University System of Maryland which is responsible for the administration of the Emergency Services Instructor Certification Program and the issuance of certificates under that program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Sponsoring agency" means a local jurisdiction submitting a candidate for certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"State emergency services instructor" means an individual who is certified to be an emergency services instructor by the MICRB.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Supporting services" means nonteaching support rendered in the emergency services area, usually in an administrative or communication capacity in the career or volunteer service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Training supervisor" means an individual who is a MICRB certified State emergency services instructor and who directly supervises certified State emergency services instructors on a full-time basis.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|03|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>State Emergency Services Instructor Certification Standard.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The objective of this certification system is to provide the emergency services of the State with a competent instructor. When certified, the instructor shall provide instruction and training in one or more of the emergency services disciplines.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Advanced life support program coordinators and medical directors functioning under <cite path="|30.04">COMAR 30.04</cite> shall ensure that individuals providing instruction as faculty have appropriate educational credentials in addition to subject matter expertise. In addition, the Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems (MIEMSS) shall ensure that educational program faculty qualifications are consistently applied Statewide via the Advanced Life Support Educational Program approval process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Instructor certification is granted by the Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The State emergency services instructor standards apply to faculty employed by a public or private postsecondary institution, including degree-granting institutions teaching credit courses in emergency services programs whose students are to be qualified as emergency services personnel serving the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Six Sequential Stages of Instructor Candidate System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Expression of Interest.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>This first stage identifies emergency service personnel who meet specific entry level criteria and indicate their interest in the program to a sponsoring agency as defined in <cite path="|13B|03|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The candidate shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Be 21 years old or older;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Have a high school diploma or general education diploma (GED) verified by the sponsoring agency;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Have 3 years of experience in the emergency services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Possess the ability to perform all tasks required for the teaching; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Complete an approved training program in the area of instruction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Selection Process. The MICRB recognizes the need for a candidate selection process. The sponsoring agency is encouraged to use the means it considers appropriate in assessing candidate eligibility. While the development and use of a screening mechanism is the responsibility of the sponsoring agency, it is suggested that the process provide a means of assessing the candidate's field knowledge, reading comprehension, verbal ability, mathematical ability, and mechanical aptitude.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Instructor Training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The approved instructor training program consists of sequential instruction and is designed to impart knowledge and skills necessary for the candidate to perform duties as an instructor. The scope of the training shall include instructor roles and responsibilities, lesson planning, domains of learning, learning styles, goals and objectives, communication skills, diversity, legal issues, student evaluation, and basic course designs. Evaluation shall be accomplished by written examinations and instructor performance evaluations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The instructor training program shall fulfill the professional requirements and qualifications in <cite path="|13B|03|01|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>, as taught by an instructor trainer approved by the MICRB. The course shall also include an examination at the end of each course, performance evaluations, and performance testing items to be completed before the end of the course. The MICRB may consider credentials of a degreed applicant verified by a sponsoring agency as having completed this requirement. Evidence of academic achievement in the field of education (adult education preferred) shall be submitted to the MICRB.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The instructor candidate may fulfill the instructor training requirement by completing a nationally recognized instructor training course approved by the MICRB.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An Instructor I training program shall be taught by an MICRB-approved State emergency services instructor approved as an instructor evaluator or instructor trainer. An Instructor II training program shall be taught by an MICRB-approved State emergency services instructor trainer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Skills Development.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When a candidate successfully completes instructor training, the sponsoring agency shall conduct a skills development program. A date, place, and time shall be planned and a program shall be coordinated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This program shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Be at least 12 hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Be designed to unite practical instruction to specific field evolutions; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Afford an opportunity to demonstrate performance instruction techniques.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The instructional period shall be planned and supervised by certified instructors who may be primarily responsible for the particular discipline or specialty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The training is to be specialized.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Performance evaluations are to be conducted and provided to the instructor candidate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>In lieu of the prescribed skills development program, the MICRB may consider credentials, experience, or another such program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Practice Teaching.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The candidate, after successful completion of skills development, is required to practice teach a minimum of two 3-hour sessions or classes which include one cognitive information session and one practical skill session, and shall receive a satisfactory evaluation for each class. The teaching shall be performed under the continuous direct supervision of a certified State emergency services instructor. A certified State emergency services instructor approved as an evaluator shall perform the evaluation of this training.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Practice teaching provides the instructor candidate with an opportunity to teach, following instructor training, under actual conditions. This on-the-job instruction consists of two 3-hour segments as described in <cite path="13B|03|01|.03|E.|(5)|(a)">§E(5)(a) of this regulation</cite> and shall be evaluated by an approved MICRB evaluator pursuant to <cite path="|13B|03|01|.09|B.">Regulation .09B of this chapter</cite>. To ensure that the practice instruction is of the highest possible quality and is meeting the lesson objectives, a three-step process shall be used for evaluation purposes, which consists of observation, written evaluation, and a supervisory conference.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Interim Student Teaching.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Interim student teaching provides the instructor candidate an opportunity to teach a complete course of instruction with some supervision. During this stage, two evaluations shall be made by MICRB-approved evaluators or instructor trainers approved by the MICRB. The completed evaluations shall become part of the total certification requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The candidate shall teach a minimum of 60 clock hours and receive two consecutive satisfactory evaluations from two different MICRB-approved evaluators or instructor trainers approved by the MICRB. Each evaluator shall be from a local jurisdiction or sponsoring agency different from the other.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Application for Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After the teaching assignment is completed, each candidate's file shall be reviewed by the sponsoring agency representative, who shall make appropriate recommendations based upon the evaluation of the completion of the six stages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Application Process.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To be considered for certification, the candidate shall submit an application for certification through the sponsoring agency to the MICRB on the form prescribed by the MICRB.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A candidate shall complete the application process within 5 years of completion of an MICRB-approved instructor training course.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If a candidate has completed the instructor training course between 5 and 10 years before beginning the application process, the candidate shall, in addition to the prescribed initial certification requirements, complete within 3 years of submitting their application 12 hours of approved instructor methodology as a corequisite to the initial completion process.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If a candidate has completed the instructor training course more than 10 years before beginning the application process, the candidate shall be required to successfully complete:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A current, MICRB-approved instructor training program; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The Instructor Training Course Challenge process, as outlined in MICRBs policy on Instructor Training Course Challenge Criteria.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Term of Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State emergency services instructor certificates are valid for a period of 3 years from the date of approval by the MICRB.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The sponsoring agency or employer, or both, shall determine what subject matter the State emergency services instructor is qualified to teach.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Recertification Process. The following process is to ensure that instructors continue to use up-to-date methods and information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recertification shall be based on a 3-year cycle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The instructor shall teach a minimum of 60 hours during the 3-year period, or if a training supervisor, teach a minimum of 3 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The instructor or training supervisor shall receive a satisfactory teaching evaluation and no subsequent unsatisfactory evaluation from an approved MICRB evaluator during the 3-year period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The instructor or training supervisor shall successfully complete 12 hours of professional development or continuing education in instructional methodology or training safety. A maximum of 6 hours of approved professional development can be in the area of training safety within the 3-year period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Procedure for Reentering after Failing to Recertify.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following procedures are required for an individual who fails to recertify and wishes to reenter the teaching program within 3 years of the expiration of the individual's certification:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The candidate shall submit correspondence to the sponsoring agency asking to reenter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a minimum, the candidate shall have successfully completed all the requirements as listed in <cite path="13B|03|01|.03|H.|(2)|(4)">§H(2)(4) of this regulation</cite> within 3 years before the date of the application for reentry and shall receive a satisfactory teaching evaluation before the application may be submitted to the MICRB; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The sponsoring agency shall submit a recommendation with the application to reenter, and the MICRB shall review the information submitted by the sponsoring agency and take appropriate action.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual who has a certification lapse in excess of 3 years is required to meet initial certification requirements, beginning at the instructor training course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Certification Standard Instructor Trainer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The candidate shall document instructional experience and formal education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Educational Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To become certified as an emergency service instructor trainer in Maryland, an individual shall have completed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A baccalaureate or graduate degree in education or a related field from an accredited college or university; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>3 years of teaching experience, which shall be documented as evidence of competence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within the degree, or in addition to the degree, courses that cover the following topics are required:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Methods of Teaching: using various teaching methodologies to enhance the classroom environment, such as lecture, case studies, technology, demonstration, group activities, and interactive discussions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Classroom Management: organizing the learning environment; maintaining motivation, interest, and discipline; attending to administrative detail, such as record keeping and scheduling; demonstrating leadership skills;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Instructional Media: developing, selecting, and using training audio-visual aids and instructional technology appropriately;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Speech and Communication: choosing, using, and defining terminology correctly, speaking from notes and extemporaneously, assuring understanding of explanations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Evaluation and Measurement: assigning scores and grades, using current technology to determine measures of central tendency and statistical results, interpreting results, revisions of exam questions as needed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Course Design and Lesson Planning: performing needs assessments and task analyses; creating instructional objectives; creating lesson plans and teaching materials that enhance student learning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Education Psychology and Learning Theories: identifying learning characteristics and learning styles; adjusting instruction to meet the social, psychological, and physiological needs of adult learners;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Counseling and Guidance: counseling students first through informal steps (discussion and suggestions for correcting the problem) and formal steps (explanation of corrective steps and penalties or results for failure to comply accompanied by written notification to the student, student's supervisor, and the class file);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Research and Administration or Training Administration: planning course schedules, instructor assignments, and faculty and equipment use, performing administrative tasks including managing and maintaining program schedules, instructor assignments, and records and reports, including course and student data, instructor support, and facility and equipment use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Instructor Management: performing instructor management tasks such as identifying instructor (personnel) needs, recruiting, selecting, and training or orienting, and evaluating instructors; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Design of Evaluation Tools or Principles of Teaching and Evaluation: using various written and skill testing instruments based on learning performance objectives.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Certification Criteria. A certificate for an individual approved as an instructor trainer is valid for 3 years after the date of approval by the MICRB, if the candidate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements as specified;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has evidence of academic achievement to meet these requirements documented by an official transcript from the college or university and has the institution send it to the MICRB;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has at least two satisfactory evaluations by a certified instructor trainer or individual designated by the MICRB before the evaluation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is recommended by the employing agency or agency having jurisdiction within the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the instructor trainer candidate is currently certified as a State emergency services instructor at the time of the candidate's initial certification as an instructor trainer, the instructor trainer certification will run concurrently with the State emergency services instructor certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To retain approval, an instructor trainer shall teach at least 60 hours in a 3-year certification cycle, 30 of which shall be in instructor training, have at least one successful evaluation in the 3-year certification period by an approved instructor trainer, and complete one of the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successfully complete a 3 credit-hour course in educational methodology, or the equivalent of 3 credit hours on in-service professional development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Successfully complete 12 hours of continuing education in an approved professional development seminar for instructors; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Research, develop, and teach a professional development seminar for instructors of at least 3 hours in length.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An instructor trainer who does not meet currency requirements may reapply after satisfactory completion of §C(1), (2), or (3) of this regulation and be recommended by the sponsoring agency. The MICRB shall review the entire file and may require the applicant to complete other certification requirements.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Higher Education Commission, through the Maryland Fire-Rescue Education and Training Commission, has established, under its authority, standards for certification of emergency services instructors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The process for issuing certificates under these standards is the responsibility of the Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board (MICRB).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The MICRB is a unit within the University System of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The MICRB consists of five members appointed, effective July 1, for a 2-year term by the Chancellor of the University System of Maryland as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In even numbered years, one member recommended by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland Fire-Rescue Education and Training Commission, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In odd numbered years, one member recommended by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland Council of Fire and Rescue Academies,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland Fire and Rescue Institute, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland State Firemen's Association.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Members appointed to the MICRB shall serve until such time as a successor has been appointed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Chancellor of the University System of Maryland shall designate the chairman from among the appointees to the MICRB. The chairman shall serve at the pleasure of the Chancellor of the University System of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Each constituent organization shall also recommend an alternate representative to be appointed by the Chancellor of the University System of Maryland to serve in the absence of the regular member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The MICRB, through the Chancellor of the University System of Maryland, shall report to the MFRETC and the MHEC at least annually on the status of the instructor certification system.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General administration of the MICRB is vested in the Chancellor of the University System of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall act within the provisions of the Maryland instructor certification standards established for all State emergency services instructor, instructor evaluators, and instructor trainer certification candidates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Certificates shall bear the seal of the University System of Maryland and be signed by the Chancellor, the chairman of the MICRB, and the chief officer of the agency or organization proposing the certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall approve all evaluators. Sponsoring agencies may submit candidates for consideration as evaluators. All evaluator candidates submitted by their sponsoring agency shall have successfully completed a MICRB-approved evaluator workshop prior to their recommendation and approval as an instructor evaluator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall set the term of an evaluator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The term of State emergency services instructors approved as evaluators shall be concurrent with their State emergency service instructor certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An MICRB-approved instructor evaluator must administer at least one evaluation during the appointment period as a condition of reappointment as an instructor evaluator. An instructor evaluator not meeting this requirement must successfully complete an MICRB-approved evaluator workshop prior to being recommended and approved for reappointment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An instructor receiving initial certification as an MICRB-approved State emergency services instructor may not be approved as an instructor evaluator. An instructor must complete at least one certification cycle and successfully complete an MICRB-approved instructor evaluator workshop before becoming eligible for recommendation and approval as an instructor evaluator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The MICRB is the final authority in issuing, renewing, or revoking certificates.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board Meetings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall meet at least four times during the calendar year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Representation from three of the organizations shall constitute a quorum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the absence of the chairman, another regular member shall act as chairman.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall prepare the minutes of all meetings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The member representatives shall be the five individuals designated by the recommending organizations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The designated alternate shall vote only in the absence of a member.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board Operations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall maintain a current file of all MICRB certified instructors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall maintain a roster of certified State emergency services instructors currently approved by the MICRB as evaluators. The organizations represented on the MICRB may recommend evaluators. The MICRB shall approve evaluators who have been recommended and who have completed an MICRB endorsed evaluator workshop. Only MICRB approved evaluators may carry out required evaluations of student teaching activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>MICRB shall make available current lists of certified instructors, instructor trainers, and approved evaluators upon written request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An agency submitting applicants to the MICRB for certification as a State emergency services instructor, evaluator, or instructor trainer shall certify that the candidate has successfully completed each stage of the instructor-training approval process. The MICRB shall prepare and furnish standardized forms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The members, or alternates, in attendance at the MICRB meeting shall make certification decisions by a majority vote. The MICRB shall notify the applicant and sponsoring agency of the action within 30 calendar days following the meeting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An instructor candidate denied State certification or recertification by the MICRB may appeal the decision in writing. The candidate shall direct the appeal to the chairman of the MICRB within 30 calendar days from receipt of notification of action taken by the MICRB. If counsel represents the candidate, counsel shall advise the MICRB of the request for appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall hear the appeal at the next scheduled meeting, but not less than 30 calendar days, or more than 60 calendar days from the date of receipt of the appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall notify the instructor candidate of the date of the appeal hearing. The instructor candidate or counsel, or both, may attend the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall notify the instructor candidate within 30 calendar days following the hearing, stating the final decision of the MICRB.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall oversee the standards, ethics, and conduct of the State instructor certification process. The MICRB shall make recommendations to the MFRETC for modifications as needed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Higher Education Commission shall approve the proposed amendments to the process and these regulations.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board Revocation Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The MICRB shall only consider written requests for revocation. Requests for revocation shall be forwarded to the sponsoring agency for a response.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>MICRB may consider but not limit revocation for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Misconduct;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Insubordination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Incompetency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Misrepresentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Willful neglect of duty;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Conviction of a felony;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Conviction of a crime involving moral turpitude; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Failure to maintain required prerequisites for certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>MICRB shall make a preliminary decision to revoke certification by majority vote of the MICRB members present at the specific meeting at which charges are presented.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before revocation of certification, MICRB shall notify the State emergency services instructor or instructor trainer in writing by registered or certified mail sent to his or her address of record of the charges and of the preliminary revocation decision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice shall specify a date by which the State emergency services instructor or instructor trainer shall request, in writing, an appeal hearing. This due date may not be less than 30 calendar days from the date the MICRB mails the official notification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an appeal hearing is not requested within the time permitted, the revocation becomes effective on the due date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Appeal Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Written appeal shall be received by the chairman of the MICRB not later than the date the revocation is to become effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>MICRB may not schedule an appeal hearing less than 30 calendar days, or more than 60 calendar days, after the written appeal is received by the chairman.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The MICRB shall provide the appellant written notice of the hearing date not less than 15 calendar days in advance of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A quorum of the MICRB shall hear the individual, in person or by counsel. The individual may bring witnesses to the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A decision to revoke is by majority vote of the MICRB members present at the appeal hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The MICRB shall provide to the appellant in writing the decision of the appeal hearing within 30 calendar days of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The MICRB shall set the terms of revocation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The decision of the MICRB is final and shall be communicated to the individual and the sponsoring agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board Staffing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The University System of Maryland Central Administration shall provide staff support to the MICRB through the Maryland Fire and Rescue Institute, subject to the approved budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The MFRETC, the chief operating officers of the Maryland Fire and Rescue Institute and the Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems, the chairman of the Maryland Council of Fire and Rescue Academies, and the president of the Maryland State Firemen's Association may designate a representative as staff liaison to the MICRB in carrying out the MICRB's staff responsibilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The University System of Maryland shall reimburse members of the MICRB for expenses incurred in attending meetings. In its operating budget, the University System of Maryland shall provide for other necessary expenses incurred for the operations of the MICRB.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The agencies and organizations represented on the MICRB shall review these regulations and certification authority every 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>MICRB shall submit proposed changes to these regulations in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and through the Board of Regents of the University System of Maryland and the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|03|01|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Local Emergency Service Instructor Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="13B|03|01|.13|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the instructor candidate shall meet the requirements of NFPA 1041 Standard for Fire and Emergency Services Instructor Professional Qualifications, chapters 1—5.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The instructor candidate may meet the requirements of a recognized instructor training agency or educational institution if the requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cover all the elements specified in NFPA 1041 Standard for Fire and Emergency Services Instructor Professional Qualifications, chapters 1—5; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have been approved by MICRB.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The instructor candidate shall demonstrate knowledge and skills based on the general categories of NFPA 1041 Standard for Fire and Emergency Services Instructor Professional Qualifications, chapters 1—5, and the requisite knowledge and skills of each section.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">Education Article, §11-105 </cite>and Title 11, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-06-16">Effective date: June 16, 1980 (7:9 Md. R. 848)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|13.50.03">COMAR 13.50.03</cite> to 13B.03.01</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-02-20">Regulations <cite path="|13B|03|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13B|03|01|.04">.04</cite> repealed effective February 20, 1989 (16:3 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-02-20" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13B|03|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13B|03|01|.06">.06</cite> adopted effective February 20, 1989 (16:3 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-07-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13B|03|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13B|03|01|.06">.06</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13B|03|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13B|03|01|.14">.14</cite> adopted effective July 1, 1996 (23:13 Md. R. 946)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-05-19"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite> amended effective May 19, 1997 (24:10 Md. R. 711)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-05-19"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective May 19, 1997 (24:10 Md. R. 711)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1850)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-20"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective September 20, 2021 (48:19 Md. R. 803)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917); April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917); April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917); June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 706)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-20"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, E amended effective September 20, 2021 (48:19 Md. R. 803)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-20"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451); September 20, 2021 (48:19 Md. R. 803)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-22"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 706); April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 706)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917); June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 706)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-22"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite>, D amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-22"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.10|D.">Regulation .10D</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective September 20, 2021 (48:19 Md. R. 803); August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917); April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-22"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-20"><cite path="|13B|03|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> repealed effective September 20, 2021 (48:19 Md. R. 803)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
