<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Confidentiality of Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>With the exception of child protective services records, this chapter governs confidentiality of records and information of the Department of Human Services and local departments. <cite path="|07.02.07">COMAR 07.02.07</cite> governs the confidentiality of child protective services records.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If this chapter conflicts with any other applicable State or federal regulation or law, the provision which more strictly protects confidentiality of records applies.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Act" means the Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">State Government Article, §10-611 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means any of the following administrations within the Department of Human Services:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Social Services Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Family Investment Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Child Support Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Custodian" means an authorized employee of the Department, an administration, or a local department having actual control and custody of a record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Human Services, its administrations, and the local departments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Fugitive felon" means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is fleeing to avoid prosecution, or custody or confinement after conviction, for a crime or an attempt to commit a crime that, under the law of the place the individual is fleeing, is a felony; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is in violation of a condition of probation or parole.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Information" means any part of a record, in any form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>License.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"License" means formal written permission required by law to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Perform an act or provide a service; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Be obtained from the Department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"License" includes terms used for similar forms including "registration".</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Local department" means the local department of social services in a county or Baltimore City, and the Montgomery County Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Official custodian" means the executive head of the Department, administration, or local department in which a record is located.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Record" means the original or any copy of documentary material, in any form that, in the transaction of public business, is made by, received by, or received from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any county or city of the State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any subdivision or agency of the State, or a county or city.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Requestor" means a person requesting disclosure of or access to a record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"State" means the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Right to Information.</heading>
    <text>Except as prohibited by federal or State law, including this chapter, a custodian shall grant the proper request of a person for access to any record of the Department if provisions are made for the protection of the identity of:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The reporter of child abuse or neglect, or of abuse, neglect, self-neglect, or exploitation of a vulnerable adult; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any other individual whose life or safety may be endangered by disclosing the information.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|01|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Program Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as permitted by other law or regulation, a custodian shall deny a request for disclosure of any information or record concerning an applicant for service or customer under the following programs:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Social Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Family Investment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Purchase of Child Care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Community Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Child Support Enforcement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Medical Assistance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disclosure of Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Information described in <cite path="07|01|07|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may be disclosed as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Under a court order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To a State, local government, or federal official or employee, for a purpose directly connected with the administration of the programs specified in <cite path="07|01|07|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> including, but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Verification of eligibility, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Audits or criminal investigation of these programs;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To a volunteer or contractor of a State or federal agency for a purpose directly connected with the administration of a program listed in <cite path="07|01|07|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> if the volunteer or contractor has been informed of, and has executed a written agreement to abide by, State and federal confidentiality laws and regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Medical Assistance records and information may be disclosed only for a purpose directly connected with the administration of the program including assisting the Child Support Administration in locating absent parents.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The custodian shall disclose the current address of a customer to a federal, State, or local law enforcement officer who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Can be properly identified as a law enforcement officer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shows the custodian a signed warrant for the arrest of the customer which establishes that the customer is a fugitive felon; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provides the name and Social Security number of the customer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>With regard to a fugitive felon in a food stamp case, the custodian shall disclose the current address, the Social Security number, and, if available, a photograph of a food stamp household member to a federal, State, or local law enforcement officer who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Can be properly identified as a law enforcement officer engaged in official duties which include locating or arresting the food stamp household member;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Demonstrates that the food stamp household member either:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is a fugitive felon, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Has information concerning a fugitive felon; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provides the name of the food stamp household member.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice of Record Disclosure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When <cite path="07|01|07|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> does not apply, and disclosure is permitted under State law or regulation, the Department shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify an applicant or customer described in <cite path="07|01|07|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, when possible, of the request for a record concerning the applicant or customer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtain the applicant's or customer's consent to disclose the record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May require the requestor to obtain the applicant or customer's consent pursuant to <cite path="|07|01|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not provide a requestor with any information regarding whether:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Records exist for an individual, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An individual is an applicant or customer; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In an emergency, may disclose information without prior consent if the Department notifies the applicant or customer of the disclosure:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Orally or in writing, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Within 2 working days of the disclosure.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Food Stamps.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a written request from a responsible member of a household receiving food stamp assistance, the Department shall allow the individual to review the food stamp records for the household.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Before review by the household member, the Department shall remove from the record:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Names and identifying information of individuals who have disclosed information to the Department without the household's knowledge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Information about any criminal prosecutions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Research. The Department may disclose:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identifying information to an individual engaged in a research project only if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant or a customer who is the subject of a record to be disclosed has signed a written consent form for the disclosure, in accordance with <cite path="|07|01|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The official custodian has given prior written permission for the research project; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nonidentifying information for research purposes without the consent of the applicant or customer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Disclosure by Consent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant or customer may consent to disclosure of specific information to a third party, if the requirements of this regulation are met.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant or customer identified in the record shall sign a written consent form, which includes the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Specific information to be disclosed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Person or agency requesting the information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Person or agency to receive the information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Purpose for the disclosure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Date of the request;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Signature of the applicant or customer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Date signed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The applicant or customer shall verify the applicant's or customer's identity to the custodian, either in person or by affidavit or notarized consent form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant or customer who is 16 years old or older may sign the applicant's or customer's own consent form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an applicant or customer is a child younger than 16 years old, the child's parent, guardian, or attorney may consent under this regulation to release of information from the child's records, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The consenting individual is not alleged to have abused or neglected the child or any of the child's siblings; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disclosure is in the child's best interest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|01|07|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Mandatory Denial of a Request for Disclosure of Other Records—General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A custodian of a record shall deny a request for disclosure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the disclosure requested is contrary to any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State or federal statute or regulation,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland Rule of Procedure, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Court order;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Of a personnel record including, but not limited to an employee's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Letters of reference, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Home address or telephone number;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Of information concerning the security of an information system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Of a trade secret or confidential commercial information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Subject to <cite path="07|01|07|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, of information about the licensing of an individual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensing Records. Only the following information may be disclosed from a licensing record:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Business address, or, if the business address is not available, the home address,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Business telephone number,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Educational and occupational background,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Professional qualifications;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Findings and orders that result from formal disciplinary actions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Evidence that has been provided to the custodian to meet the requirements of a statute regarding financial responsibility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other licensing information which the official custodian determines should be disclosed to fulfill a compelling public purpose; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except for the identity of a reporter of any allegation of child abuse or neglect, or of abuse, neglect, self-neglect, exploitation of a vulnerable adult, information requested by a licensee who is the subject of the requested record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Discretionary Denial of Request for Disclosure of Records.</heading>
    <text>An official custodian may deny disclosure or personal review of a record otherwise required to be disclosed if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The official custodian believes that disclosure is contrary to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The public interest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In a child abuse or neglect case, the best interest of a child who was allegedly subject to abuse or neglect, of the child's siblings, or of other children in the household, family, or care of the alleged abuser or neglector; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In an adult protective service case, the best interest of a vulnerable adult who was allegedly subject to abuse, neglect, self-neglect, or exploitation; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>One of the following circumstances exists:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A State or federal statute or regulation, a Maryland Rule of Procedure, or a court order gives the custodian discretion to deny disclosure,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The official custodian determines, after consulting with counsel, that the record is subject to an attorney-client, attorney work-product, executive, or other privilege,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The information requested consists of specific details of a research project conducted by a State agency, except that the name, title, expenditures, and availability date of the final project summary shall be disclosed upon request, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The record concerns a law enforcement investigation, or is an investigatory file compiled for a law enforcement, judicial, or prosecution purpose, to the extent permitted by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-618">State Government Article, §10-618, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Reporting Crimes, Child Abuse, and Neglect.</heading>
    <text>The following prevail over the confidentiality provisions of this chapter:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Suspected child abuse or neglect, or abuse, neglect, self-neglect, or exploitation of a vulnerable adult, shall be reported in accordance with the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl">Family Law Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Suspected fraud in the administration of a Department program shall be reported as required by the regulations for that program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any ongoing or imminent criminal conduct of an applicant or customer may be reported to appropriate law enforcement personnel.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Continuing Requirements of Confidentiality.</heading>
    <text>When the custodian of the record discloses confidential information to an individual other than an employee of the Department or a law enforcement agency in accordance with this chapter and <cite path="|07.01.02">COMAR 07.01.02</cite>, the custodian shall inform the individual to whom the disclosure is made of the obligation to keep the information confidential, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="88A|6">Article 88A, §6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Criminal Penalty.</heading>
    <text>A court may find a disclosure of confidential information in violation of this chapter to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be a criminal offense punishable by a fine of not more than $500, or by 90 days imprisonment, or both; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Result in civil liability for damages.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Limitations on Information Sent to Customers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Materials sent or distributed to an applicant for service or customer, or to vendors of medical services provided to customers of public assistance, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be directly connected to the administration of the respective program and have no political implications; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the names only of individuals directly connected with the administration of the program, identified only in their official capacity with the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not prohibit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The distribution of information as part of the administration of a program, including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice of the availability of free medical examinations,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notice of the availability of surplus food, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consumer protection information; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Having on display, or otherwise making available in agency offices, materials containing public interest information, including voting materials.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Protection of Customer Case Files and Other Public Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A local department shall have written policies establishing procedures for the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintenance of customer case files; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Removal and return of materials to customer case files.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall safeguard information obtained from any State agency, or other state or federal agencies in accordance with the procedures, if any, established by that state or agency.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Article 88A, §§5 and 6; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">State Government Article, §10-611 </cite>et seq.; Article 41, Title 6; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-03-11">Effective date: March 11, 1985 (12:5 Md. R. 481)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-10-28">Regulations <cite path="|07|01|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|01|07|.12">.12</cite>, Access to Public Records, repealed effective October 28, 1991 (18:21 Md. R. 2306)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-10-28" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|07|01|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|01|07|.12">.12</cite>, Confidentiality of Records, adopted effective October 28, 1991 (18:21 Md. R. 2306)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-24"><cite path="|07|01|07|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite>, F amended effective May 24, 1993 (20:10 Md. R. 849)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-24"><cite path="|07|01|07|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective May 24, 1993 (20:10 Md. R. 849)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-06-28" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective June 28, 1999 (26:13 Md. R. 1018)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08"><cite path="|07|01|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
