<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Correction or Amendment of Personal Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes procedures for a person in interest to request the correction or amendment of personal records in the Department of Human Services or the local department under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-625">State Government Article, §10-625, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means any of the following administrations within the Department of Human Services:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Social Services Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Family Investment Administration; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Child Support Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Custodian" means an authorized employee of the Department, an administration, or a local department having actual control and custody of a record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Human Services, its administrations, and the local departments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Local department" means the local department of social services in a county or Baltimore City, and the Montgomery County Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Official custodian" means the executive head of the Department, administration, or local department in which a record is located.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Person in interest" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person, governmental unit, or entity that is the subject of a public record; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The legal guardian of the person who is the subject of a public record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Personal record" means a public record that identifies an individual by name, address, description, finger or voice print, picture, or other identifying factors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Who May Request.</heading>
    <text>A person in interest may request the Department or a local department to correct or amend a personal record pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-625">State Government Article, §10-625, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Requesting Correction or Amendment of Personal Records.</heading>
    <text>The request shall be in writing and state the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Name, address, and telephone number of the requestor;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Identity of the record the requestor is seeking to correct or amend;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Precise correction or amendment requested; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Justification for the correction or amendment.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Filing the Request.</heading>
    <text>A request to correct or amend a personal record of the Department or a local department shall be addressed to the custodian of the record.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Responding to a Request for Correction or Amendment of Personal Records.</heading>
    <text>Within 30 days after receipt of a request for correction or amendment of personal records that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complies with Regulations .04 and .05 of this chapter, the custodian shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make the requested correction or amendment and notify the requestor in writing; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inform the requestor in writing that the record may not be amended or corrected as requested because:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The requestor is not a person in interest,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The record to be corrected or amended is not a personal record,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The requestor is not entitled to inspect the records under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">State Government Article, §10-611 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other reasons mandated by law; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Does not comply with <cite path="|07|01|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, the custodian shall return the request to the requestor:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With an explanation for the return; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures for resubmitting the request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Notification to Third Party.</heading>
    <text>If the custodian previously disclosed information from a personal record to a third party and receives a request for correction or amendment to the personal record, the custodian:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Shall inform the third party in writing within 30 days of the correction or amendment to the personal record; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Does not need to notify the third party, if the custodian denies the request.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Statement of Disagreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Department or local department finally refuses a request to make a correction or amendment pursuant to Regulation .06, the person in interest may submit to the Department or local department a concise statement, not to exceed five 8-1/2 x 11 inch pages, of the reasons for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The requested correction or amendment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disagreement with the Department or local department's refusal to make the requested correction or amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department or local department which discloses to a third party information from a personal record about which a statement of disagreement has been filed, shall furnish a copy of the statement to the third party.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Administrative Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A requestor may seek an administrative review in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if the requestor has been denied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request to change a personal record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The right to file a statement of disagreement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The right to have a statement of disagreement forwarded to a third party.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual shall file a request for administrative review within 30 days of the date of the custodian's decision to deny a request to change a personal record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The administrative hearing shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conducted by the Office of Administrative Hearings; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Governed by the Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-625">State Government Article, §10-625, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09">Effective date: January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3127)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-06-28">Chapter revised effective June 28, 1999 (26:13 Md. R. 1018)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08"><cite path="|07|01|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
