<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Evaluation of the Local Directors of Social Services</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>These regulations establish the procedures for evaluating the local directors of social services, Department of Human Services.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Governing body" means the county executive, county commissioners, Mayor of Baltimore City, or the county council of Talbot County or Wicomico County.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Local board" means the local advisory board of the local departments of social services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Local department" means the local department of social services in each political subdivision of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Local director" means the director of the local department of social services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Process for Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary, the governing body of the jurisdiction, and the local board of social services shall annually evaluate, in writing, the local director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Secretary shall incorporate the evaluation of the governing body and the local board in the Secretary's evaluation of the local director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Secretary or the Secretary's designee, subject to the Secretary's approval, shall decide the applicable criteria to be used in the Secretary's evaluation of the local directors, and apprise the local directors in writing of the criteria.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Secretary shall request input from the Department to be used in evaluating a local director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Secretary, the governing body, and the local board or their designees shall jointly review their respective evaluations annually with the local director.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Article 88A, §13(b)(5) and (6)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-07-04">Effective date: July 4, 1994 (21:13 Md. R. 1154)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
