<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Appeal Hearings</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. "Good cause" means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A serious medical or health condition experienced by the property owner or the property owner's agent which prevents a scheduled departmental appeal hearing from being conducted; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any other extraordinary circumstance which prevents a scheduled departmental appeal hearing from being conducted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Postponements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon request of the property owner or the property owner's agent, a scheduled departmental appeal hearing will be postponed one time without cause.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any additional postponements will be granted only for good cause.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="18|01|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Proof of Representation for Real Property Assessment Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An appeal filed by a representative on behalf of a property owner or taxpayer shall include proper authorization from the property owner or taxpayer to pursue the appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The authorization required by <cite path="18|01|02|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be in writing and filed no later than:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>45 days from the date of the notice if the appeal is submitted pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|14-502">Tax-Property Article, §14-502(a)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>60 days after the date the property transfers if the appeal is submitted pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|14-502">Tax-Property Article, §14-502(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On or before the date of finality for the next taxable year if the appeal is submitted pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|14-503">Tax-Property Article, §14-503, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The failure to provide timely authorization as required by <cite path="18|01|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> will result in an appeal hearing being set up exclusively for the property owner or taxpayer and all future correspondence being directed to the property owner or taxpayer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If timely authorization is not provided as required by <cite path="18|01|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> and a property owner or taxpayer wants to be represented at a scheduled appeal hearing, proper authorization shall be received by the Department on or before the assigned hearing date.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Tax-Property Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|1-402">1-402</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|2-201">2-201</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|2-202">2-202</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-06">Effective date: October 6, 1997 (24:20 Md. R. 1405)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|18|01|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> adopted effective April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 368)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
