<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions; Rules of Construction</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this title, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Addictions counselor" means an employee whose primary duty is to provide substance abuse services in accordance with his or her level of education, training, and experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Appointing authority" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An appointing authority as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|1-101">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That appointing authority's designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Case manager" means an employee assigned to provide case-management services to youth under the Department's supervision, whether that supervision be informal, probation, detention, commitment, aftercare, or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Commit" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-8">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-8</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Commitment program" means any facility or program to which a committed youth is assigned by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Committed youth" means a youth who, on court disposition, is committed to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Community case manager" means an employee assigned to provide overall case-management to youth residing in the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Contraband" means any item, material, substance, or other thing that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prohibited for employee or youth possession by law, rule, or regulation, or by directive of the Secretary, a program manager, or an area director; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Brought into a facility or other program site in a manner or under circumstances that are prohibited by law, rule, or regulation, or by directive of the Secretary, a program manager, or an area director.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Juvenile Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Detained youth" means a youth who, pending court disposition, is assigned to the Department for detention.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Detention" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-8">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-8</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Detention program" means any facility or program to which a detained youth is assigned by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Direct care staff" means an employee whose primary duty is to provide direct supervision of youth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Employee" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any employee of the Department or of any facility or other program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any volunteer who provides direct or indirect services to any youth in a facility or other program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Facility case manager" means a case manager assigned to a residential facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Includes" or "including" means by way of illustration and not by way of limitation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Juvenile justice monitor" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|6-401">State Government Article, §6-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Person" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|1-101">Human Services Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Program" means any facility or program operated by, under contract with, licensed or certified by, or otherwise under the jurisdiction or supervision of the Department for the care or treatment of youth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Program manager" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual, regardless of title, who has on-site responsibility for and is in charge of all aspects of the management and operation of a facility or other program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That individual's designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Juvenile Services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary's designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Secure facility" means a residential facility characterized by physically restrictive construction or procedures that are intended to prevent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Detained or committed youth from departing at will; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unauthorized persons from having access to the facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Youth" means any detained youth, committed youth, or other individual referred to or under the jurisdiction of the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Rules of Construction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General. In interpreting and applying this title, the following rules of construction apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Gender. Words denoting one gender include and apply to the other genders as well.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Number. The singular includes the plural and vice versa.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Time Computations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Computation of Time After an Act, Event, or Default.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In computing any period of time prescribed by this title, the day of the act, event, or default after which the designated period of time begins to run is not included.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the period of time allowed is more than 7 days, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays are counted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the period of time allowed is 7 days or less, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays are not counted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The last day of the period so computed is included unless it is a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday, in which event the period runs until the end of the next day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Computation of Time Before a Day, Act, or Event.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In determining the latest day for performing an act that is required by this title to be performed a prescribed number of days before a certain day, act, or event, all days preceding that day, including intervening Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays, are counted in the number of days so prescribed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The latest day is included in the determination unless it is a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday, in which event the latest day is the first preceding day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|9-204">Human Services Article, §9-204, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-06-18">Effective date: June 18, 2007 (34:12 Md. R. 1067)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
