<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Administration</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|02|04|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Tax Returns and Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Alcoholic Beverage Tax Returns and Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Holders of a manufacturer's or a wholesaler's license authorized to sell beer, wine, or liquor, or Class E, F, or G license holders authorized to sell beer, wine, or liquor, or holders of a nonresident dealer permit authorized to sell beer shall file a tax return with the Revenue Administration Division on forms prescribed by the Comptroller for each month that their license or permit is active. A tax return is required for each period even if the licensee or permittee had no activity. Manufacturers and wholesalers shall file a beer, wine, or liquor tax return under a filing frequency provided in <cite path="03|02|04|.01|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>. Nonresident dealers shall file a beer tax return by the 15th of the month following the report month. Class E, F, and G licensees shall file the appropriate tax return by the 25th of the month following the report month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Holders of an import-export, nonresident storage, or a public storage permit shall file a report with the Revenue Administration Division on forms prescribed by the Comptroller for each month that their permit is active. A report is required for each month even if the permittee had no activity. Import-export, nonresident storage, and public storage reports are due by the 15th of the month following the report month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Family beer and wine facility permit holders shall file a report with the Revenue Administration Division on forms prescribed by the Comptroller for each year that the permit is active. A family beer and wine facility permit report is required for each report year beginning October 1 and ending September 30 of the following year. Reports are due by October 15 following the report year, and shall be filed even if the permittee had no activity for that year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Filing frequency for Manufacturers and Wholesalers of Beer, Wine or Liquor.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Comptroller shall notify manufacturers and wholesalers of their filing frequency under this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The required return shall be filed:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Monthly;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Quarterly; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Semiannually.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Monthly. The taxpayer is required to file and pay the tax monthly on or before the 20th day of the month following the report month.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Quarterly. The taxpayer is required to file and pay the tax quarterly on or before the 15th day of the month that follows a calendar quarter for that report. The reports will be due April, July, October, and January of the following year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Semiannually. The taxpayer is required to file the return and pay the tax semiannually on or before the 15th day of January and July.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A holder of a nonresident winery, distillery, and brewery permit authorized to sell wine, distilled spirits, or beer shall file a tax return with the Revenue Administration Division on forms prescribed by the Comptroller for each month that the holder's permit is active. A tax return is required for each month even if the permittee had no activity. A nonresident permit holder shall file a tax return by the 10th of the month following the report month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Tobacco Tax Returns.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A manufacturer of cigarettes shall file a tobacco tax return with the Revenue Administration Division on forms prescribed by the Comptroller, listing all sample cigarettes distributed within the State. A tobacco tax return is required for each month even if the manufacturer did not distribute sample cigarettes in this State. Sample cigarettes shipped into Maryland during the report month by a third party (advertising agency, etc.), on behalf of a manufacturer, shall be reported by the manufacturer. Sample cigarettes shipped to federal reservations in Maryland need not be reported. However, complete and accurate records of these shipments shall be maintained on the manufacturer's premises and shall be subject to audit verification. Manufacturers shall file returns by the 15th of the month following the report month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensed cigarette wholesalers shall file a tobacco tax return with the Revenue Administration Division on forms prescribed by the Comptroller for all months that their license is active. A tobacco tax return is required for each month even if the licensee did not take the first possession of any unstamped cigarettes in this State. Licensees shall file returns by the 21st of the month following the report month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Tax Return or Report Waiver. A license or permit holder described in §A or B of this regulation may file a written request for a waiver from filing a nonactivity return or report, and shall provide adequate reasons for the waiver. The Comptroller shall make a determination based on the reasons presented in the request and notify the license or permit holder in writing of the decision.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Reports of Boards of License Commissioners and County Dispensaries.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Report of Retail License Activity.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each retail alcoholic beverage license-issuing authority shall file on a monthly basis a report with the Comptroller, on forms provided or approved by the Comptroller, listing all retail alcoholic beverage license activity, including issuances, cancellations, transfers, revocations, etc., for the report month. Each issuing authority shall file the monthly report with the Comptroller by the 15th of the month following the report month. Reports are due even if there is no activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each alcoholic beverage license-issuing authority shall file annually a complete report of all retail alcoholic beverage licenses renewed for the year on forms provided or approved by the Comptroller. This annual report shall be filed by the 15th of the month following the month the licenses are renewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reports filed by the alcoholic beverage license-issuing authority shall include the names of licensees, entity name and trade name, address, and any other information the Comptroller may require. The Comptroller may adopt a Statewide control number to be used by the alcoholic beverage license-issuing authority when filing reports.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each alcoholic beverage license-issuing authority shall file annually a complete report of all revenue derived for the year preceding from retail alcoholic beverage licenses, on forms provided or approved by the Comptroller. This annual report shall be filed by August 15 annually.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Report of Dispensary Activities. Each county dispensary shall file annually a complete report summarizing all dispensary activities for the year on forms provided or approved by the Comptroller. This report shall be filed by August 15 annually and shall include gross profits, expenses, net profits of the dispensary, and any other information relating to the sale of alcoholic beverages that the Comptroller may require.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Alcohol Beverages Article, §1-302; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|2-103">Tax-General Article, §2-103</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-04-03">Effective date: April 3, 1989 (16:6 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|03|02|04|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1854); February 12, 1996 (23:3 Md. R. 166); September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1339); October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|03|02|04|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2006 (33:15 Md. R. 1271); amended permanently effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|03|02|04|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1823); July 18, 2016 (43:14 Md. R. 779); November 15, 2021 (48:23 Md. R. 979); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-11-15"><cite path="|03|02|04|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1854); November 15, 2021 (48:23 Md. R. 979)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-01"><cite path="|03|02|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective June 1, 1996 (23:10 Md. R. 730)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|03|02|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
