<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Enforcement</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes a framework within which the Commission may take enforcement action against a licensee that results in a reprimand, fine, or condition placed on a licensee, or a suspension or revocation of a license.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the terms defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which have the same meanings in this chapter, in this chapter the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Penalty” means a per day fine, not exceeding $5,000 for each separate violation, that the Commission may impose on a licensee under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-25(b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Sanction” means non-monetary enforcement action that the Commission may take against a licensee for a violation specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-25(a), Annotated Code of Maryland, and includes suspension or revocation of a license, reprimand, or imposition of a condition on a licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Violations.</heading>
    <text>A licensee may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Violate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A provision of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A regulation adopted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A directive of the Commission or the Director;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Take, or attempt to take, any action that is intended to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Change or influence the outcome of a video lottery terminal or table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Influence any person or unit of government that is involved in implementing or enforcing <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Interfere with the regular operation of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The central monitor and control system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A video lottery terminal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Associated equipment or software; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A table game; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fail to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conform to the information contained in a license application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet a licensing requirement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Promptly submit to the Commission a change to the information contained in a license application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Adequately remedy a deficiency of which the licensee has received notice under <cite path="|36|03|04|.04|E.">Regulation .04E of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintain a video lottery employee license in good standing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Notice of Violation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After receiving a report of a licensee’s alleged violation of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, the agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the licensee of the alleged violation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Investigate the report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may designate staff to serve on a review board that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reviews the investigation of an alleged violation conducted under <cite path="36|03|04|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Makes a recommendation to the Director for addressing the alleged violation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The review board’s recommendation to the Director may include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Requiring the licensee to implement a corrective action plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Issuing the licensee a warning letter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Entering into a settlement agreement with the licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recommending that the Director initiate Commission proceedings to impose a penalty or sanction on the licensee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other appropriate action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After reviewing the board’s recommendation, the Director may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initiate Commission proceedings to impose a penalty or sanction on the licensee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Direct staff to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Implement the board’s recommendation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Take other appropriate action.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall be provided a notice of the violation that describes the statute, regulation, or directive allegedly violated, along with the Director’s recommendation for addressing the alleged violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to require that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee receive an opportunity to meet with staff to discuss an informal settlement of a violation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The agency undertake a corrective action plan or attempt to reach a settlement with the licensee before the Director initiates Commission proceedings for imposition of a penalty or sanction against a licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|04|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Corrective Action Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Director directs staff to implement a corrective action plan with a licensee, agency staff shall give written notice to a licensee that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A description of the alleged violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the possible sanctions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The requirement for the licensee to submit a corrective action plan to the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Corrective Action Plan.  A corrective action plan shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Periodic monitoring or progress reports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Timelines for completing corrective action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Implementation of measures to guard against recurrence of the alleged violation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other measures necessary to resolve the alleged violation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Time for Implementing a Corrective Action Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days of receipt of a notice under <cite path="36|03|04|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the licensee shall submit a corrective action plan to the Director, or the Director’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director, or the Director’s designee, shall review the corrective action plan and inform the licensee whether the corrective action plan is acceptable.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the corrective action plan is acceptable, the licensee shall execute it immediately.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the corrective action plan is not acceptable, the licensee shall submit a revised plan immediately.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the licensee fails to submit an acceptable corrective action plan within the time described under <cite path="36|03|04|.05|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Director may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide the licensee with additional time within which to submit a revised corrective action plan; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Initiate proceedings before the Commission for imposition of a penalty or sanction on the licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Director, or the Director’s designee, provided a licensee with a notice under <cite path="36|03|04|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> and did not receive a timely written response, the Commission may adopt a recommendation by the Director for imposition of a penalty or sanction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Corrective Action Plan Outcome.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After a licensee has completed, to the satisfaction of the Director or the Director’s designee, a corrective action plan, the alleged violation is resolved, except that the alleged violation may be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The basis of a subsequent corrective action plan, settlement, penalty, or sanction if a similar violation occurs; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Raised during a Commission hearing as part of the agency’s enforcement record for the licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If at any time during the corrective action period the Director, or the Director’s designee, determines that the licensee has made insufficient progress toward fulfilling a requirement of the corrective action plan, the Director may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For good cause, extend the time for completion of a corrective action plan; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Initiate proceedings before the Commission for imposition of a penalty or sanction on the licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If at the end of the corrective action period the licensee has failed to satisfactorily complete the corrective action plan, the Director may initiate proceedings before the Commission for imposition of a penalty or sanction on the licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Settlement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may provide a licensee with the opportunity to discuss with staff a means of entering into a settlement agreement between the licensee and the Commission by which the violation is settled without a penalty or sanction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A settlement agreement:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be signed by an authorized representative of the licensee and the Director or the Director’s designee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be considered final and binding until approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a licensee violates a term of a settlement agreement, nothing in this regulation shall be construed to prevent the Commission from imposing a penalty or sanction against the licensee for that, or the underlying, violation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Commission Action.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. The Director may initiate Commission proceedings for imposition of a penalty or sanction against a licensee if a licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Violates a provision of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fails to timely or satisfactorily complete a corrective action plan required by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Violates a term of a settlement agreement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Engages in any conduct that exposes the State’s gaming program to a serious and imminent risk of harm to its integrity, security, or profitability.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Initiation of Commission Proceedings. The Director shall initiate Commission proceedings for the imposition of a penalty or sanction on a licensee by scheduling a Commission hearing in accordance with <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite> on the alleged violation and providing the licensee with written notice of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommendation for imposition of the penalty or sanction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basis for the recommendation for imposition of the penalty or sanction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Consequences of a decision by the Commission to impose a penalty or sanction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Date, time and location of the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Applicable hearing rights.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Emergency Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director may emergently suspend a license if the Director determines that suspension is necessary in order to protect the State’s gaming program against a serious and imminent risk of harm to its integrity, security, or profitability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Emergency Suspension—Process.  If the Director emergently suspends a license, the Director shall promptly schedule a Commission hearing on the emergency suspension and provide the licensee with the written notice required under <cite path="|36|03|04|.07|B.">Regulation .07B of this chapter</cite>, along with notice directing the licensee that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee shall immediately cease performing under the license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with the Director’s directive to cease performing under the license constitutes a separate violation of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> for which an additional penalty or sanction may be imposed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|04|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Imposition of Penalties and Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Consequences.  For a violation of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, the Commission may impose a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Penalty not exceeding $5,000 for each day and each violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sanction, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Revocation of a license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Suspension of a license for a period of time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reprimand; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Condition that must be met within a specified time as to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Training;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Staffing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supervision;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Compliance with internal controls;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Probationary periods; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Any other directive to address the violation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Penalty—Required Considerations.  To determine the amount of a penalty to impose on a licensee, the Commission shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The seriousness of the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The harm caused by the violation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the person who committed the violation acted in good faith.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sanction—Considerations.  To determine the appropriate sanction to impose on a licensee, the Commission may consider the factors in <cite path="36|03|04|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether a violation was willful;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the licensee had, or should have had, control of the situation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the violation may have occurred in connection with unclear or insufficient:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Communication; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Requirements;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any extraordinary circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prior disciplinary history with the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Profit that resulted, or may have resulted, from the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Harm that resulted, or may have resulted, from the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>How the violation was detected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Tailoring the discipline to address the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Action taken by the licensee to prevent recurrence of the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Action taken by the Commission to address similar violations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Any other information that the Commission finds relevant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Ignorance No Defense.  Because a licensee is presumed to be familiar with applicable statutes and regulations governing the State’s video lottery terminal program, a claim of ignorance of the law may not be used as a defense to a finding of a violation or to the imposition of a penalty or sanction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Imposition of penalty and sanction.  A penalty and a sanction may be imposed for each violation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Commission Action.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Commission action against a licensee for a violation of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> shall be conducted as specified in <cite path="36.01.02.06">COMAR 36.01.02.06</cite>, and the Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make a finding whether the licensee violated a provision of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the licensee violated a provision of <cite path="|36|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, decide whether, and to what extent, to impose a penalty or sanction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee may seek judicial review of the Commission’s decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensee against whom the Commission ordered the imposition of suspension or revocation of a license shall immediately comply with the Commission’s order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensee against whom the Commission imposed a penalty shall remit to the Commission payment in full of the penalty within 30 calendar days.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|24">24</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-25, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-20">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|04|.07">.07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 470); emergency action expired effective July 20, 2013</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-08-05" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|04|.10">.10</cite> adopted effective August 5, 2013 (40:15 Md. R. 1233)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-10-19"><cite path="|36|03|04|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective October 19, 2020 (47:21 Md. R. 905)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|03|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
