<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Mandatory Exclusion</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes a mechanism by which the Commission:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maintains a list of individuals who are to be mandatorily excluded or ejected from a video lottery facility; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establishes standards that require a video lottery operation licensee to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exclude or eject an individual from the premises of a video lottery facility; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that intoxicated individuals and individuals under the age of 21 are not allowed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To play video lottery terminals or table games; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In areas of the video lottery facility where video lottery terminals or table games are located.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Excluded individual” means an individual whose name and identifying information have been placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Mandatory exclusion list” means a list that is maintained by the Commission and identifies those individuals whom the Commission has directed be mandatorily excluded or ejected by a video lottery operation licensee from any video lottery operation licensed in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Unredeemed Item.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Unredeemed item” means a token, voucher, check, ticket, chip, coupon, or similar item that has monetary value, and that a player has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Won by playing a video lottery terminal or table game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Inserted into a video lottery terminal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Played at a table game; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Received by converting cash, check, or wire transfer at a video lottery facility.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Unredeemed item” does not include cash.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|07|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Mandatory Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall establish a mandatory exclusion list.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may place on the mandatory exclusion list an individual who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a career offender;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has been convicted of a criminal offense under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States that is a criminal offense involving moral turpitude or a gambling offense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Would adversely affect the interests of the State, the licensee, or the individual if the individual were to be present at a video lottery facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is the subject of any administrative or judicial order directing the individual to stay away from a video lottery or other gaming facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Presents a threat to the safety of any individual on the premises of a video lottery facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Engages in, or has a documented history of engaging in, disruption of video lottery or table game play;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Director or a facility operator has a reasonable belief has cheated, or attempted to cheat, at a facility by engaging in conduct including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Altering or misrepresenting the outcome of a game or event on which bets have been placed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Placing, cancelling, increasing, or decreasing a bet based on knowledge that is not available to other players;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Claiming or collecting a prize from a video lottery facility that the individual did not win or earn or that the individual was not otherwise authorized to claim or collect;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manipulating a video lottery terminal, a table game, a central monitor and control system, or associated equipment or software to affect the outcome of a game or bet; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Altering the elements of chance or methods of selection or criteria that determine the outcome of a game or bet; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Engages in any conduct that may adversely affect public confidence in, or perception of, video lottery or table game operations in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In evaluating whether to place an individual on the mandatory exclusion list, the Director may specify monetary amounts and circumstances, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The nature of the incident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual was a video lottery employee licensee at the time of the incident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the individual was a licensee, whether the individual was working at a video lottery facility while the individual engaged in conduct described in <cite path="36|03|07|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the incident directly impacts:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A video lottery facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A player; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A licensee;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The amount or type of loss to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A video lottery facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A player; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A licensee;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual made restitution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual was involved in a prior incident that meets the criteria of <cite path="36|03|07|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Whether a video lottery facility has other information the Director finds relevant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other information the Director finds relevant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The entry of an individual on the mandatory exclusion list shall include sufficient information to identify the excluded individual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The information used to identify an excluded individual may include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The individual’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and any nickname or alias;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Residential address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Telephone numbers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Gender;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Physical description, including any birthmarks, scars, or tattoos;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Race or ethnic origin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>For non-United States citizens, country of origin; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Photograph;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of placement on the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Brief statement of the basis for placing the individual on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other information the Commission requires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The mandatory exclusion list and related records are public records under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Inclusion on Mandatory Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of information that reasonably indicates an individual meets any criteria under <cite path="|36|03|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>, and after making any considerations described in <cite path="|36|03|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, the Director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evaluate the information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the information required under <cite path="|36|03|07|.03|E.">Regulation .03E of this chapter</cite> sufficiently identifies the individual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Decide whether to place the individual on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prior to placing an individual on the mandatory exclusion list, the Director or the Director’s designee may provide a video lottery facility with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Information used to identify an individual who may be excluded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The factual basis for placing an individual on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An opportunity to provide the Director with information identified in <cite path="|36|03|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Director decides to place an individual on the mandatory exclusion list, staff shall deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a written notice explaining:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The factual basis for placing the individual on the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The availability of a reconsideration meeting with the Director or the Director’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The requirements for submitting a request for a reconsideration meeting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a timely request for a reconsideration meeting is not submitted, the individual’s name shall be placed on a mandatory exclusion list and the name will be distributed to all facility operators in the State and be publicly available; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>That the excluded individual shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prohibited from entering any video lottery facility, and from playing any video lottery terminal or table game, in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Subject to criminal charges for trespassing or any other appropriate criminal charge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Required to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Redeem or liquidate an unredeemed item with monetary value that the individual has received since being placed on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Surrender to the Problem Gambling Fund established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland, any unredeemed items and prizes in the possession of the individual or received by the individual at a video lottery facility after placement on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reconsideration Meeting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may submit to the Director a written request for a reconsideration meeting within 15 days of the date of the individual’s receipt of the notice described in <cite path="36|03|07|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an individual fails to timely submit a request under <cite path="36|03|07|.04|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A reconsideration meeting may be held by the Director or the Director’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>During a reconsideration meeting, an individual may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be represented by counsel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Present evidence as to why the individual does not meet the criteria under <cite path="|36|03|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Director or the Director’s designee shall deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a written notice of the decision following the reconsideration meeting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual dissatisfied with the result of a reconsideration meeting may submit a written request to the Commission for an appeal hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The request for an appeal hearing shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted within 15 days of the date of the individual’s receipt of the written notice of the decision following the reconsideration meeting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describe the individual’s legal and factual bases for disagreeing with placement on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If an individual fails to timely submit a written request for an appeal hearing under <cite path="36|03|07|.04|D.|(7)">§D(7) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a timely written request for an appeal hearing, the Director or the Director’s designee shall provide the individual with a notice for the appeal hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Appeal Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If after an appeal hearing the Commission decides that the excluded individual does not meet any criteria under <cite path="|36|03|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>, the individual’s name may not be placed on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If after an appeal hearing the Commission decides that the excluded individual meets any criteria under <cite path="|36|03|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual’s name shall remain on the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commission shall notify all facility operators in the State of the individual’s addition to the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The individual may seek judicial review of the Commission’s decision; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The individual may request to be removed from the mandatory exclusion list only as provided in <cite path="|36|03|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|07|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Removal from Mandatory Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After an excluded individual has been on the mandatory exclusion list for at least 5 years, the individual may request removal from the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An excluded individual’s request under <cite path="36|03|07|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be submitted to the Director in writing and shall include a detailed statement about why there is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Good cause for removal of the individual from the list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A material change in the individual’s circumstances since the individual’s name was placed on the list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Director or the Director’s designee shall investigate the request and make a recommendation to the Commission whether to grant or deny the request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Director or the Director’s designee recommends removing the individual from the list, the Commission may approve the recommendation without a hearing, and Agency staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Remove the individual from the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a notice of removal from the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notify the State’s facility operators of the individual’s removal from the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the Director or the Director’s designee recommends continued inclusion on the mandatory exclusion list, the excluded individual may submit a written request for an appeal hearing to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Appeal Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The request for an appeal hearing shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted within 15 days of the date of the individual’s receipt of the written notice of the recommendation of the Director or the Director’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describe the individual’s legal and factual bases for disagreeing with the recommendation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an individual fails to timely submit a written request for an appeal hearing under <cite path="36|03|07|.05|F.|(1)|(a)">§F(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall remain on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a timely written request for an appeal hearing, the Director shall provide the individual with a hearing notice for a hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If after a hearing the Commission denies the individual’s request for removal, it shall deliver to the individual by U.S. mail a notice that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request was denied; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individual shall remain on the mandatory exclusion list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Separate from the individual’s ability to request removal under <cite path="36|03|07|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Director shall periodically review the mandatory exclusion list and may consider the following in order to determine if an individual should be removed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the individual is living;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether there are changed circumstances; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other relevant information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Judicial Review.</heading>
    <text>The Commission’s decision under Regulations .04E(2) and .05G of this chapter may be subject to judicial review.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <text>A facility operator may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Knowingly fail to exclude or eject from the facility premises an excluded individual;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fail to notify the Commission if an excluded individual is excluded or ejected from the facility;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Permit an intoxicated individual or individual under the age of 21 to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Play a video lottery terminal or table game; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be in areas of the video lottery facility where video lottery terminals or table games are located;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Knowingly allow the following individuals to collect a jackpot:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An excluded individual; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual under the age of 21; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Fail to obtain any unredeemed items and prizes in the possession of an excluded individual and transfer them to the Problem Gambling Fund established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|07|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Facility Exclusion Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall establish a plan for identifying and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excluding or ejecting from a facility:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Excluded individuals; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individuals who may be eligible for placement on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensuring that intoxicated individuals and individuals under the age of 21 are not allowed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To play video lottery terminals; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In areas of the video lottery facility where video lottery terminals or table games are located.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The plan required under <cite path="36|03|07|.08|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include at least the following elements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures and deadlines for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identification of facility personnel responsible for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities of facility personnel identified as responsible for implementation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Training for facility personnel on the requirements of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Regular monitoring of the mandatory exclusion list;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Prompt reports to the Commission about the presence on facility premises of an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is included on the mandatory exclusion list; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is required to be prevented from playing video lottery terminals or table games;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Prompt reports to the Commission about an individual who is permanently excluded from the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The facility’s response to the discovery of an individual who is on the mandatory exclusion list on facility property, which may include pursuing criminal charges against the individual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Any other element required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for its approval:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The exclusion plan required under <cite path="36|03|07|.08|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> at least 60 days before video lottery terminal operations are to commence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any amendments to a facility’s exclusion plan prior to implementation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An annual report describing the operation of the facility’s exclusion plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-24(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-20">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|07|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 470); emergency action expired effective July 20, 2013</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-08-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|07|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective adopted effective August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1347)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|36|03|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 208)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|03|07|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-06-23"><cite path="|36|03|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, C amended effective June 23, 2014 (41:12 Md. R. 670)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|36|03|07|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite>—E amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 208)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|03|07|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 208); October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-06-23"><cite path="|36|03|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, C amended effective June 23, 2014 (41:12 Md. R. 670)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|03|07|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 208); October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|03|07|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective June 23, 2014 (41:12 Md. R. 670); February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 208); October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|03|07|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-06-23"><cite path="|36|03|07|.07|D.">Regulation .07D</cite> amended effective June 23, 2014 (41:12 Md. R. 670)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|36|03|07|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective June 23, 2014 (41:12 Md. R. 670); February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 208)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
