<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Junkets</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Junket Agreements and Final Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall ensure that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A junket agreement between a facility operator and a junket enterprise, or junket representative, is in writing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An executed copy of the junket agreement is submitted to the Commission before a junket arrives at the video lottery facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A junket agreement shall include at least the following provisions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Commission disapproves a term of the junket agreement, or determines that a junket enterprise or junket representative has engaged in an activity prohibited under <cite path="|36|03|09|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Commission shall notify the facility operator that is a party to the junket agreement of the disapproval or determination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The operations under the agreement shall be suspended as of the date of the Commission’s disapproval until it is amended by the parties to the satisfaction of the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The junket enterprise or junket representative shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintain good standing with the Maryland Department of Assessment and Taxation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtain and maintain all required business licenses and permits;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The services of the junket enterprise and junket representative will comply with all applicable laws.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Junket final reports shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be prepared by a facility operator for a junket engaged in or on its property, and shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The origin of a junket and its date and time of arrival and departure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The name of all junket enterprises and junket representatives involved in the junket;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A junket manifest that lists the names and addresses of the junket participants;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The nature, amount, and value of complimentary services, accommodations, and other items provided by the facility to a junket participant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The total amount of services or other items of value provided to or for the benefit of a patron participating in a junket that was paid for by the junket enterprise, a junket representative, or an agent or employee of a junket enterprise or junket representative;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be prepared and signed by an employee of the facility operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be prepared within 7 days of completion of the junket; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon request of the Commission, be submitted to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Activities.</heading>
    <text>A facility operator shall ensure that a junket enterprise or a junket representative, or an agent or employee of a junket enterprise or a junket representative, does not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless approved in writing by the Commission, accept compensation on any basis other than theoretical win;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Engage in collection efforts;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Solicit, receive, or accept any fee or gratuity from a patron for the privilege of participating in a junket or for performance of any function for which the junket enterprise or junket representative is licensed;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless disclosed in writing to the facility operator for which the junket was arranged, pay for transportation or any other service or item of value that is provided to or for the benefit of a patron participating in a junket;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Extend credit to, or grant credit on behalf of a facility operator to, a patron participating in a junket;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Accept an advance of money or a loan from a patron participating in a junket;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Engage in conduct that would bring the State into disrepute;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Pursue economic gain in an occupational manner or context that is in violation of the laws of the State, if the pursuit creates a reasonable belief that participation of the junket enterprise or junket representative would be inimical to the policies of State law or the State’s video lottery terminal operations;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Engage in activities that create a reasonable belief that the junket enterprise or junket representative is, or is an associate of, a career offender or a member of a career offender cartel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Engage in a predatory marketing practice prohibited under <cite path="36.03.03.08">COMAR 36.03.03.08</cite>; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Perform junket services under an agreement that has not been reduced to writing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-12, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-20">Regulations .01 and .02 adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 470); emergency action expired effective July 20, 2013</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-08-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|09|.02">.02</cite> adopted effective adopted effective August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1347)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
