<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Facility Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>The terms defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland, have the same meanings in this chapter.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|11|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Hours of Operation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not offer fewer hours of operation than provided for in State law without the prior written approval of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator that has received Commission approval to offer fewer hours of operation under <cite path="36|03|11|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may, upon written notice to the Commission, extend its hours of operation up to and including those allowable under State law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Facility Design Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall, at its own expense, construct its facility in accordance with specifications established by the Commission, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Computer space for the central monitor and control system contractor that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Equipped with heating, ventilation, and air conditioning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supplied with power including an uninterruptible backup power supply;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Secured with a key or alternative locking mechanism maintained and controlled by representatives of the Commission and central monitor and control system operator in accordance with this subtitle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Equipped with a door that, when opened, audibly signals the facility operator’s surveillance monitoring room; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Covered by a surveillance system enabled to record all entry and exit to the computer space and activity in the area;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Equipment storage space for the central monitor and control system contractor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Equipment storage and repair space for video lottery terminal contractors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Cable infrastructure access to the gaming floor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All necessary wiring for the gaming floor, except that wiring which the Commission requires to be installed by a Commission contractor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A base and high backed seat for each video lottery terminal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>At least 400 square feet of office space for use by Commission staff that is located immediately adjacent to the gaming floor and is equipped with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Partitioned work space, computers, telephones, copy capability, and supplies sufficient to meet the Commission’s data processing and related needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Computer terminals permitting read only access by authorized Commission staff to any computerized slot monitoring system, casino management system, or player tracking system used by the facility operator; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Keys or alternative locking mechanisms which are under the exclusive control of the Commission;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A surveillance system approved in writing by the Commission that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Configured to provide surveillance of all video lottery terminal and table game related activities within the facility in accordance with standards established by the Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Enabled with a digital video recording format in accordance with standards established by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Equipped with a monitoring station for the exclusive use of the Commission which is configured with full camera control capability over the surveillance system and is capable of overriding the camera control capability of the facility operator;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>An alarm system connected to all emergency exits from the gaming floor which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Produces a distinguishable warning sound that is discernible in the vicinity of an exit when the emergency door is opened; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requires deactivation and reset by means of a key or alternative locking mechanism maintained and controlled by the security department;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>An area for the detention of individuals taken into custody by any law enforcement agency that has jurisdiction over the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Adequate space for use by the Commission in connection with conducting background investigations of applicants or licensees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Any signage required by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Communication systems capable of effecting timely communication between the facility and the Commission, law enforcement exercising proper jurisdiction over the facility, and emergency first responders; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Any other equipment or design feature required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State Lottery Games.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall provide at least two locations at the facility for the sale of State Lottery games that are offered by or through the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State Lottery game sales locations shall be situated as near as practicable to a cashiers’ cage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|11|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Table Games Surveillance Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Surveillance System. In addition to the surveillance system requirements in <cite path="|36|03|11|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> and <cite path="|36.03.10">COMAR 36.03.10</cite>, a facility operator that offers table games shall have a surveillance system that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Light sensitive cameras with lenses of sufficient magnification to allow the certificate holder to clandestinely monitor in detail:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The gaming conducted at each gaming table in the licensed facility with sufficient clarity and coverage to simultaneously:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identify patrons and dealers; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>View the table and determine the configuration of wagers, card, dice and tile values and game outcomes;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The movement of cash, gaming chips, and plaques, tip boxes, and drop boxes within the facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other activity or areas designated by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Stationary cameras dedicated to table games, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except for Craps, Baccarat, Roulette and Big Six Wheel, at least one stationary camera for each table game offered by the facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least two stationary cameras for each Craps table, with one camera covering each end of the table;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>At least two stationary cameras for each Baccarat table, with one camera covering each end of the table;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At least two stationary cameras for each Roulette table, with one camera covering the Roulette wheel and one camera covering the Roulette table layout;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>At least two stationary cameras for each Big Six Wheel, with one camera covering the Big Six Wheel and one camera covering the Big Six Wheel table layout;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Additional cameras as required by the Commission, which may include cameras with 360-degree pan, tilt, and zoom capabilities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Single stationary cameras that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Are capable of clearly identifying the entire table layout, conduct, and outcome of the game; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>May be used by a facility operator in lieu of cameras identified in §A(2)(b)—(e) of this regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Recordings. A facility’s surveillance system must continuously record transmissions from cameras used to observe the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gaming conducted at table games;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Collection of drop boxes and tip boxes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Distribution of cards, dice, and tiles to gaming pits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Inspection of cards, dice, and tiles in the gaming pits and at the gaming tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Retrieval of cards, dice, and tiles from the gaming pits at the end of the gaming day; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Delivery of cards, dice, and tiles to the location designated and approved by the Commission for inspection, cancellation, destruction, or, if applicable, packaging for reuse.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Retention.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The surveillance recordings required under <cite path="36|03|11|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be retained for a minimum of 14 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A surveillance recording of suspicious activity, suspected or alleged regulatory violations, or suspected or alleged criminal activity shall be retained for a minimum of 30 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A surveillance recording shall be made available for review upon request by law enforcement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Commission approval of monitoring rooms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prior to the commencement of table game operations, a facility shall submit to the Commission a revised minimum staffing submission for the facility operator’s surveillance monitor rooms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The minimum staffing submission must consider the size and layout of the licensed facility as well as the number of table games and must at all times provide for surveillance of activities inside and outside the licensed facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may not implement a surveillance plan, or an amendment to a surveillance plan or minimum staffing submission, without prior Commission approval.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|11|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Gaming Floor Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At least 60 days before video lottery terminal or table game operations are to commence, a facility operator shall submit a floor plan depicting its gaming floor and all restricted areas to the Commission for review and written approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not commence operations until its gaming floor plan is approved in writing by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A gaming floor plan that a facility operator submits to the Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be drawn to 1/8 inch scale, unless another scale is approved by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be certified by an architect licensed to practice in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Depict the gaming floor with a notation as to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Total square feet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Total square feet utilized for the placement of video lottery terminals and table games;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Total square feet reserved for future placement of video lottery terminals and table games;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each video lottery terminal or table game location, identified by number and notation as to whether it is proposed for present use or reserved for future use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Number of video lottery terminal and table game locations proposed for use on the gaming floor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Number of video lottery terminal and table game locations reserved for future use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Each seat on the gaming floor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Perimeter of the gaming floor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A clearly delineated route for an individual who is not allowed to play video lottery terminals or table games to bypass the gaming floor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Each automated bill breaker, gaming ticket redemption, coupon redemption, and jackpot payout machine; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Each security department zone, including a notation as to whether it is a fixed or roving post;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Depict all restricted areas within the facility with a notation as to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cashiers' cage, any satellite cashiers' cage, and ancillary offices, inclusive of each cashiers' cage window location and location number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Computer space allocated to the central monitor and control system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Count rooms and any trolley storage areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An area designated for the storage or repair of equipment or video lottery terminals or table game equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Information technology department operations centers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Progressive controller locations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Surveillance monitoring room;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Vault and armored car bay locations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Any area designated as restricted by the facility operator in its Commission-approved internal controls;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Depict each surveillance camera with a notation as to camera type and location number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Depict each automated teller machine installed in accordance with <cite path="36.03.03.07">COMAR 36.03.03.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a gaming floor includes an outdoor area, in addition to the requirements of <cite path="36|03|11|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> an operator shall submit to the Commission a gaming floor plan that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amenities that the operator intends to offer in the outdoor area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An affidavit from the chief executive officer attesting that the outdoor area and its intended use meet all applicable local and State requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A plan for player and equipment safety during inclement weather.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not implement any change to its approved gaming floor plan without the prior written approval of Agency staff.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Issuance of an Operation License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not commence video lottery operations until the Commission has issued an operation license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The operation license issued by the Commission shall specify:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date and time at which operations may commence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maximum square footage of gaming floor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maximum number of video lottery terminals which may be operated by the facility operator under the operation license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The initial 15-year term of an operation license shall commence with the date the Commission issues an operation license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may issue an operation license subject to conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission may issue an operation license after determining that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The facility operator’s proposed hours of operation comply with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-23, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|36|03|11|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facility complies with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|36|03|11|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All video lottery terminals and associated equipment have been tested and comply with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and any standards established by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The gaming floor plan complies with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|36|03|11|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The facility operator’s internal controls comply with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|36.03.10">COMAR 36.03.10</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The facility operator is prepared to implement the internal controls, surveillance, and security procedures that are necessary to ensure that the operation of the video lottery terminals and video lottery facility is conducted safely and legally;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The facility operator’s employees are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed and registered with the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Trained in the performance of their responsibilities;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The facility is prepared in all respects to receive the public;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The facility operator has complied with any additional pre-opening conditions imposed by the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The facility operator has successfully completed a test period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|11|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Permanent Facility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall commence operation of video lottery terminals in a permanent facility within 18 months after the date the Commission issues an operation license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The permanent facility must be located at the location for which the Video Lottery Facility Location Commission awarded a video lottery operation license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission may approve an extension of time for the commencement of operations if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator submits a written request for an extension; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission determines that extenuating circumstances exist that are beyond the control of the facility operator which have prevented the facility operator from complying with <cite path="36|03|11|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approve an extension of 6 months to comply with <cite path="36|03|11|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not grant more than two extensions to a facility operator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator fails to comply with the requirements of this regulation, its operation license shall be revoked and shall automatically revert to the State.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Temporary Facility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may issue an operation license for a temporary facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A temporary facility must comply with the requirements this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon the written submission of a facility operator, the Commission may authorize a deviation from the requirements of <cite path="|36|03|11|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> when it issues an operation license for a temporary facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility shall be operational in a permanent facility no later than 30 months after the Commission issues an operation license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the Commission issues an operation license for a temporary facility, the facility operator shall be responsible for all costs associated with the transition from a temporary facility to a permanent facility, including the cost of relocating the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Central control monitor and control computer system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Video lottery terminals; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Associated equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">§§9-1A-02, 9-1A-04, 9-1A-11, and 9-1A-23, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-20">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|11|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|11|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 470); emergency action expired effective July 20, 2013</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-08-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|11|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|11|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective adopted effective August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1347)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|03|11|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|03|11|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-08-17"><cite path="|36|03|11|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective August 17, 2015 (42:16 Md. R. 1056)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|03|11|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite>, E amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
