<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Transportation and Testing of Video Lottery Terminals and Table Game Equipment</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transport; Transportation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Transport" or "transportation" means any shipping, transfer, delivery, or other movement of a video lottery terminal or table game equipment into or out of the State, or between facilities within the State.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Transport" or "transportation" does not include the movement of a video lottery facility or table game equipment within a facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Written notice" means information provided to the Commission in an electronic or written form or format designated by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Compliance with Federal Law.</heading>
    <text>A person who transports a video lottery terminal or table game equipment shall comply with applicable provisions of 15 U.S.C. §§1171—1178, commonly known as the Johnson Act.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|12|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Transportation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise directed by the Commission, a person shall submit a written notice to the Commission prior to transporting a video lottery terminal or table game equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person proposing to transport a video lottery terminal or table game equipment shall submit to the Commission a written notice containing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name and address of person initiating transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reason for transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Method of transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Name of and address of carrier;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Anticipated beginning and end dates of transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Name and address of destination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Name and address of manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Manufacturer's serial number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Model number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Description; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The person proposing to transport or transporting a video lottery terminal or table game equipment shall promptly provide the Commission with written notice of any changes to the information already submitted as required under <cite path="36|03|12|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person transporting a video lottery terminal or table game equipment shall plainly and clearly label the package so that the name and address of the shipper and recipient, and the contents of the package, may be readily ascertained during an inspection of the outside of the package.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After delivery of a video lottery terminal or table game equipment, the facility to which the terminal is delivered shall promptly provide the Commission with written notice that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date video lottery terminal or table game equipment was received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date video lottery terminal or table game equipment will be placed into operation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Storage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a video lottery terminal or table game equipment will not be placed into operation upon delivery to a facility, the facility shall provide the Commission with written notice that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Identification of the video lottery terminal or table game equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reason for storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Storage facility location; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility shall store a video lottery terminal or table game equipment only in a manner that the Commission has approved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|12|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall maintain a register of each video lottery terminal and specified table game equipment placed in operation in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The table game equipment for which the Commission shall maintain a register under <cite path="36|03|12|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Table games that contain an approved table layout;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Automated table game shuffling devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Table game progressive controllers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other table game equipment specified by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For each video lottery terminal placed into operation, the Commission shall incorporate the video lottery terminal into the Commission's central monitoring system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For each piece of video lottery and table gaming equipment specified in <cite path="36|03|12|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> that is placed into operation, the Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assign a registration control number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Affix a Commission registration tag.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A video lottery terminal or gaming table may not be transported out of the State unless the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approves the action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the video lottery terminal is being permanently removed from the State, removes the registration tag.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Testing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may test video lottery terminals and associated equipment for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Accuracy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Compatibility with the central monitor and control system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other function that the Commission determines may be necessary to validate the proper functionality and performance of the terminals and equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may test table game rules and table game equipment for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Accuracy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any other function the Commission determines is necessary to validate the proper functionality and performance of table game equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|03|12|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Request for Authorization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility shall obtain prior written Commission authorization before taking any of the following actions with respect to a video lottery terminal or table game equipment in its facility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Placing a video lottery terminal or table game into operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Relocating a video lottery terminal or table game within the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Converting a game theme or table layout;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Converting a play denomination on a video lottery terminal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Changing percentage payout;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Changing an erasable programmable read only memory chip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Changing a jackpot lockup amount;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Changing a configuration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Performing a substantial replacement of parts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Implementing any variation, composite, or new feature of a table game; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Performing any other action that materially alters or interrupts the operation of a video lottery terminal or table game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before the Commission may authorize an action described in <cite path="36|03|12|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, a facility shall submit to the Commission written notice of the request that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Description of proposed action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location of action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Start and end dates and times;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Estimated "go live" date for the video lottery terminal or table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Approval of the manufacturer of the affected video lottery terminal or table game equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Approval of the operator of the central monitor and control system for video lottery terminals; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any other information requested by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice of Changes. A facility shall promptly provide the Commission with written notice of any changes to the information already submitted under §A or B of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Commission Response to Request for Authorization.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may impose additional requirements on the facility or the manufacturer before authorizing the action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may deny approval of the action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A facility shall notify the Commission if the action is not completed as approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|15">15</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-21, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-20">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|12|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|12|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 470); emergency action expired effective July 20, 2013</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-08-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|36|03|12|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|03|12|.06">.06</cite> adopted effective adopted effective August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1347)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
