<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Veterans Claims Service</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to assist veterans and their dependents who are or may be entitled to aid from the United States government, pursuant to federal law for the benefit of veterans and their dependents, in preparing and presenting their claims to the proper federal authorities and agencies, and in securing and expediting action on those claims.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Veterans Claim Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A veteran residing within the State, or a veteran's dependent, who is or may be entitled to aid from the United States government pursuant to federal law for the benefit of veterans and their dependents, may file with a service officer at the principal office of the service program, or at any of the State service centers, a request for assistance in the preparation, presentation, and prosecution of claims to the proper federal authorities and agencies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a request, the service officer shall prepare the claim in proper manner, and the service officer shall present to the proper federal authority or agency, and shall secure and expedite action on it and prosecute it through to conclusion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The service officer shall make all reasonable efforts to relieve and prevent congestion of these claims, and provide, as far as possible, for every veteran and dependent of any veteran making these claims to receive promptly and regularly the maximum relief and benefit to which they are, or may become, entitled to under federal law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-901">9-901</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-902">9-902</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-904">9-904</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-905">9-905</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-07-23">Effective date: July 23, 1975 (2:16 Md. R. 1138)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-08-11" discontinuity="true">Chapter <cite path="|14.05.01">14.05.01</cite> repealed effective August 11, 2008 (35:16 Md. R. 1392)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-08-11" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|35|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|35|02|01|.02">.02</cite> adopted effective August 11, 2008 (35:16 Md. R. 1392)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
