<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Disclosure Statements for Sale of Halal Food</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this chapter is to provide disclosure statements for persons who represent to the public that food that is sold or served is halal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter sets forth the disclosures that shall be made to a consumer regarding the source of food and the preparation, handling, and sale of the food. The disclosures allow a consumer to make an informed choice as to whether the source of the food and manner of food preparation and handling conform to the consumer's standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not make a determination as to whether a food is halal.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Consumer Protection of the Office of the Attorney General.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Packaged Food.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Packaged food" means food packaged in advance of sale by a producer or packer of the product in units suitable for retail sale.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Packaged food" does not include food intended for consumption at its point of manufacture.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Person" includes an individual, corporation, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, association, two or more persons having a joint or common interest, or any other legal or commercial entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|01|10|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Disclosure Statements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to packaged food.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person who represents to the public that unpackaged food sold or served is halal shall complete a disclosure statement described in <cite path="02|01|10|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Disclosure Statement for Persons Who Represent That They Sell or Serve Unpackaged Halal Food.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall state the name of the person selling or serving halal food and the date of the disclosure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall state in the affirmative or negative whether the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sells or serves only halal foods; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sells or serves both halal and non-halal foods.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall state in the affirmative or negative whether the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sells or serves products that are certified by a halal certifying entity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sells or serves products that are purchased from vendors who represent that their products are halal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Keeps halal and non-halal foods separate during preparation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Prepares foods in accordance with Islamic religious requirements.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The names of vendors from whom the person purchased unpackaged halal food products; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the address and phone number of the named vendors will be furnished on request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall, if applicable, state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name of the person certifying the food as halal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the address and phone number of the named certifying persons will be furnished on request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall describe the halal food preparation and handling process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall be amended as necessary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Disclosure Statement for Persons Who Represent That They Sell or Serve Both Halal and Non-Halal Foods.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall include the requirements under <cite path="02|01|10|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The disclosure statement shall state in the affirmative or negative whether the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Uses separate ovens, sinks, and preparation areas for halal and non-halal foods;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Uses separate utensils and equipment for halal and non-halal foods;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Uses separate refrigerators, freezers, and storage areas for halal and non-halal foods; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Mixes non-halal and halal foods.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The completed disclosure statement shall be posted in the manner set forth in <cite path="|02|01|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Division shall develop a form for the disclosure statement described in §§C and D of this regulation, and shall make forms available upon request.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Method of Posting.</heading>
    <text>The disclosure statement described in <cite path="|02|01|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> shall be posted in a clear and conspicuous manner, so that the consumer can easily see it before the consumer buys or consumes the foods about which the disclosures are made.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Commercial Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|13-205">13-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|14-3602">14-3602</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|14-3604">14-3604</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23">Effective date: March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
