<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>General Information</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the services that are available through the support enforcement agency and the manner of service delivery.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Child Support Enforcement Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Available Services. An individual eligible for support enforcement services may receive the following services as appropriate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Location of a parent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establishment of paternity and a support obligation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review and modification of a support obligation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Enforcement of a support obligation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Collection and disbursement of support payments.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility and Application Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual receiving TCA or Medical Assistance is eligible for child support enforcement services without filing an application or payment of an application fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual who is no longer eligible for TCA or Medical Assistance may continue to receive child support enforcement services without filing an application or paying an application fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A child who receives foster care by a local department is eligible for child support enforcement services upon referral by the local department director or the director's designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §B(1)—(3) of this regulation, an individual who requests child support enforcement services is eligible for the services upon:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Filing an application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paying a $15 application fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="07|07|02|.02|B.|(6)">§B(6) of this regulation</cite>, the support enforcement agency shall assess the $15 application fee only once to an individual regardless of the number of child support cases for which the individual makes application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If an individual requests termination of child support services for all of the individual’s child support cases and subsequently reapplies for services, the individual shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a written application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the $15 application fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>When an individual requests child support services, the support enforcement agency shall provide to the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application form:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On the day of the request, if the request is made in person, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Within 5 working days, if the request is made by telephone or by mail; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pamphlets which provide information about the program including available services, rights, and responsibilities, and the distribution of child support collections.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>When an individual applies for TCA, foster care, or Medical Assistance, the local department shall provide the applicant with information about the child support enforcement program including available services, rights and responsibilities, and distribution of child support collections:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At the time of application; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within 5 working days of referral to the support enforcement agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Other Fees. An annual collection fee of $15 shall be deducted from child support payments in a case in which a family:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Never received TCA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has received at least $3,500 in child support payments during the federal fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Failure to Cooperate.</heading>
    <text>The support enforcement agency shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notify the FIA when a custodial parent applying for or receiving TCA, Medical Assistance, or Purchase of Child Care fails to cooperate with the support enforcement agency to establish or enforce a support obligation; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Suspend all child support activities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If FIA notifies the support enforcement agency that a claim of good cause for refusal to cooperate has been made, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Until FIA determines that good cause no longer exists.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Intergovernmental Support Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall cooperate with support enforcement agencies of other states to provide child support services when the parties reside in different states.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall maintain a Maryland Central Registry to coordinate intergovernmental case activities.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Case Closure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency may close a case which meets one or more of the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is no longer a current support order and arrearages are under $500 or unenforceable under State law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent or putative father is deceased and further action, including a levy against the estate, may not be taken;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Paternity cannot be established because:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The child is 18 years old or older and action to establish paternity has not commenced;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A genetic test or a court or administrative process has excluded the putative father and no other putative father can be identified;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The agency has determined that it would not be in the best interests of the child to establish paternity in a case involving:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Incest;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Forcible rape; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Pending legal proceedings for adoption; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The identity of the biological father is unknown and cannot be identified after diligent efforts, including at least one interview by the child support enforcement caseworker with the recipient of services;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent's location is unknown and diligent efforts have been made using multiple sources, which have been unsuccessful to locate the noncustodial parent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Over a 1-year period when there is insufficient information to initiate  an automated locate effort; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Over a 3-year period, when there is sufficient information to initiate an automated locate effort;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent cannot pay support for the duration of the child's minority because the noncustodial parent has no income or assets which can be attached for support and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is institutionalized in a psychiatric facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is incarcerated; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has a medically verified total and permanent disability with no evidence of support potential;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent resides abroad and one of the following applies:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>No court order for support exists and Maryland has no reciprocal child support agreement with the country in which the noncustodial parent resides; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A court order for support exists and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The noncustodial parent does not work for the U.S. government;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The noncustodial parent does not work for a company with offices in the United States;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The country does not accept a support petition from Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The noncustodial parent has no domestic income or assets that can be garnished, levied, or attached;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In a TCA, Purchase of Child Care, or Medical Assistance case, FIA has determined that the custodial parent has good cause for refusing to cooperate and the support enforcement agency may not proceed without risk of harm to the child or caretaker;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>In a non-TCA case:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The support enforcement agency is unable to contact the custodial parent within a 60-day period after unsuccessful attempts by telephone and first-class mail;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The custodial parent refuses to take the necessary action for the provision of support enforcement services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The custodial parent requests closure and there is no assignment to the State of accrued arrears under the support order; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The support enforcement agency has provided federal parent location service only; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>In an intergovernmental case, the support enforcement agency documents failure by the initiating state to take an action which is essential for the next step in providing services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency shall notify the custodial parent, in writing, 60 days before closing a case of its intent to close the case, except if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency has provided federal parent location services only;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The non-TCA custodial parent requests closure and there is no assignment to the State of arrears accrued under the support order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In a TCA or Medical Assistance case, there has been a finding of good cause; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The case is an intergovernmental case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In an intergovernmental case, the support enforcement agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the initiating state of its intent to close a case 60 days prior to case closure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Stop income withholding notice within 10 working days of receipt of instructions for case closure from an initiating state pursuant to 45 CFR §303.11(c)(12).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Record Maintenance.</heading>
    <text>The support enforcement agency shall maintain records of all cases including payment records, court actions, and correspondence.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reporting.</heading>
    <text>Support enforcement agencies shall compile statistical and fiscal reports as required by the Administration.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-106">10-106</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-116">10-116</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-118">10-118</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-119">10-119</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-119">10-119</cite>.3—10-144, and 10-303—10-359, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference—45 CFR §§302, 303.2—303.15, 303.30, 303.31, and 303.71—303.106; 42 U.S.C. §654(6)(B)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22">Effective date: March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|07|07|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1619); August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 952)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-09"><cite path="|07|07|02|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective December 6, 2007 (34:24 Md. R. 2157); March 9, 2009 (36:5 Md. R. 421)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-17"><cite path="|07|07|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1619)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-11-14"><cite path="|07|07|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective November 14, 2011 (38:23 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-11-14"><cite path="|07|07|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1995); November 14, 2011 (38:23 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-30"><cite path="|07|07|02|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1619); July 16, 2009 (36:14 Md. R. 984); April 30, 2012 (39:8 Md. R. 533)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
