<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Establishment of Paternity</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the procedures of the support enforcement agency to establish paternity for a child eligible for support enforcement services.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Legal Action.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency shall initiate legal action to establish paternity when paternity is at issue as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-1006">Family Law Article, §5-1006, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 90 days of locating the alleged father, the support enforcement agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Legally establish paternity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exclude the alleged father as the biological father; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete service of process, if necessary, to commence proceedings to establish paternity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an alleged father is excluded, but another alleged father has been identified, the support enforcement agency shall initiate paternity action against the newly identified alleged father.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In a TCA case in which the custodial parent fails to cooperate without good cause, the prosecutor may file the petition with the State named as the plaintiff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If attempts at service of process are unsuccessful, the support enforcement agency shall document the unsuccessful attempts.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Intergovernmental Establishment of Paternity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maryland as the Initiating State.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency shall attempt to establish paternity using Maryland's long-arm statutes, if appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If use of Maryland's long-arm statutes is inappropriate or unsuccessful, the support enforcement agency shall refer the case to the responding state's intergovernmental central registry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When referring a case to another state for establishment of paternity, the support enforcement agency shall include all documentation required by UIFSA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maryland as the Responding State. Upon receipt of a request from another state for establishment of paternity, the Maryland Central Registry shall forward the request to the appropriate Maryland support enforcement agency which shall take action to establish paternity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Maryland's Uniform Interstate Family Support Act (UIFSA). When providing services to establish paternity in an intergovernmental case, the Maryland support enforcement agency shall comply with the provisions of UIFSA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Paternity Testing Laboratories.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall maintain a list of laboratories which perform paternity testing to identify or exclude an alleged father from paternity for use by the circuit courts of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A laboratory located in Maryland or out-of-State may apply to the Administration to be on the list of paternity testing laboratories.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A laboratory's application shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The names and qualifications of the laboratory's directors and officers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation that the laboratory is qualified to perform DNA analysis; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation establishing that the laboratory is accredited as described in <cite path="07|07|04|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A laboratory included on the list shall be accredited by the American Association of Blood Banks' Parentage Testing Committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Administration's list of laboratories shall be qualified to perform DNA analysis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall delete a laboratory from the list if it ceases to meet the criteria in <cite path="07|07|04|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Laboratories denied listing or removed from the list may appeal in writing to the Executive Director of the Administration within 30 days of the notice of the denial or removal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the laboratory list in the Child Support Enforcement Program Policy Manual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide a copy of the list to each circuit court in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-1005">5-1005</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-1048">5-1048</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-301">10-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-359">10-359</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>(Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference — 45 CFR §§302.31, 303.5, and 305.24)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22">Effective date: March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20"><cite path="|07|07|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1824)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-31"><cite path="|07|07|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-28"><cite path="|07|07|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective February 4, 2013 (40:2 Md. R. 72); April 28, 2014 (41:8 Md. R. 469)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
