<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Establishment of Support Obligation</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the actions to be taken by the support enforcement agency to establish court-ordered support obligations.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Legal Action to Establish a Support Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency shall initiate legal action to establish a court-ordered support obligation for a child:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Eligible for support enforcement services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Who has not had a support obligation established.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the parent of a child is a minor, the support enforcement agency may attempt to establish a court-ordered support obligation for the child against the parents of the minor parent if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Child for whom support is sought receives TCA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Minor parent has insufficient financial resources to support the child.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency is not required to establish a court order for support when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cannot be located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Receives benefits from a means tested public assistance program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is confined to a hospital or other care institution for the chronically, mentally, or physically ill and has no income or assets; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is imprisoned without earnings or assets, and is not:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Participating in an institutional work release program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Eligible for release before the child reaches the age of majority;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The custodial parent who receives TCA or Medical Assistance fails to cooperate with good cause;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The child is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Married or has been married;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>18 years old and is not enrolled in secondary school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>19 years old or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Otherwise emancipated; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Deceased; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Paternity cannot be established.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For any other situation not listed in <cite path="07|07|05|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the support enforcement agency, within 90 days of locating an absent parent, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish an order for support, including a provision:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For health insurance for a child that is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Reasonable in cost; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Accessible for the child; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For cash medical support that is reasonable in cost, until health insurance is available;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete service of process, if necessary, to commence proceedings to establish an order for support; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Document unsuccessful attempts to serve process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>To establish a child support order, the support enforcement agency shall petition the court to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide for an earnings withholding and health insurance enrollment order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Authorize the immediate service of the earnings withholding and health insurance enrollment order on the obligor's employer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>When taking legal action in a TCA case in which the custodial parent does not cooperate and does not have good cause, the prosecutor may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name the State as the plaintiff; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File the petition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency may not attempt to establish a spousal support order.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Review and Modification of Child Support Orders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Every 3 years, the Administration shall notify each parent subject to a child support order of the right to request that the Administration review the order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of the method for obtaining the Administration's review of an order; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The information that each parent must provide to the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Cases Eligible for Review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon request of either parent subject to a child support order, the support enforcement agency shall conduct a review of the order for possible modification at 36-month intervals from the date the order was established, modified, or last reviewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In cases with an assignment of support, the support enforcement agency may conduct a review of the order for possible modification at 36-month intervals from the date the order was established, modified, or last reviewed without the request of either party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In intergovernmental cases, the support enforcement agency shall conduct a review of the order at the request of another state if the request for a review is appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In cases that have a material change of circumstances that may result in a change of the child support order, a review may be conducted in less than the 36-month interval.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Conduct of Review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before conducting a review, the support enforcement agency shall gather information required for application of the Maryland child support guidelines from any of the following sources:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Federal and State automated databases to which the agencies have access;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The parties in the case;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other sources as determined appropriate by the support enforcement agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In cases when a review is conducted, the support enforcement agency shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Evaluate information required for application of Maryland's child support guidelines as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl">Family Law Article, Title 12, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to determine the appropriate support obligated amount; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine if the order provides for a provision for health insurance or cash medical support, until health insurance is available for the child.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency shall notify both parents subject to the order of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Outcome of the review; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Support enforcement agency's intent regarding further action on the case.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency shall initiate action to modify the support order if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Material change in circumstance has occurred;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Modification is needed to provide for a provision for health insurance or cash medical support, until health insurance is available for the child; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Modification is needed to extend the duration of the order to provide for support of a child who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is 18 years old;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is enrolled in secondary school; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Has not attained 19 years old.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>When modifying a child support order in which the obligor is not subject to earnings withholding, the support enforcement agency shall petition the court to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide for an earnings withholding;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide for a health insurance enrollment order, if appropriate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Authorize the immediate service of the earnings withholding and health insurance enrollment order on the obligor's employer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>For cases that qualify for a review, within 180 calendar days of receiving a request for a review or locating the nonrequesting parent, whichever occurs later, the support enforcement agency shall conduct a review of the order, and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Take appropriate steps to adjust the order; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine that the order should not be adjusted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Intergovernmental Establishment and Modification of Support Order.</heading>
    <text>When providing services in an intergovernmental case to establish or modify an order for support, the support enforcement agency shall comply with the provisions of UIFSA.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">10-114</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-204">10-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-301">10-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-359">10-359</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-101">12-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-204">12-204</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference — 45 CFR §§302.56, 303.4—303.5, 303.8, and 303.31; 42 U.S.C. §652(f)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22">Effective date: March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-17"><cite path="|07|07|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1620)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-16"><cite path="|07|07|05|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective August 16, 2004 (31:16 Md. R. 1253)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17"><cite path="|07|07|05|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective September 8, 2008 (35:18 Md. R. 1600); May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 721)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-17"><cite path="|07|07|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1620)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-08"><cite path="|07|07|05|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, C amended effective September 8, 2008 (35:18 Md. R. 1600)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-31"><cite path="|07|07|05|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-17"><cite path="|07|07|05|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective August 16, 2004 (31:16 Md. R. 1253); May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 721); March 17, 2014 (41:5 Md. R. 341)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-31"><cite path="|07|07|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
