<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Enforcement of Support Obligation</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the procedures of the support enforcement agency to enforce compliance with the terms of child support orders under its supervision.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Earnings withholding notice" means a notice in a format prescribed by federal law issued by the administration to an employer requiring the employer to deduct support payments from the earnings of an obligor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Earnings withholding order" means an order in a format prescribed by federal law issued by a tribunal to an employer requiring the employer to deduct support payments from the earnings of an obligor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Garnishment" means a legal proceeding by which a noncustodial parent's property, money, or money owed the noncustodial parent is withheld from the noncustodial parent or a third party and applied to the payment of the noncustodial parent's child support obligation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"IRS full collection service" means a program in which the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) collects arrears on child support obligations for the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Monitoring.</heading>
    <text>The support enforcement agency shall review, at least once a month, the payment status of each case for which it is responsible.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Enforcement of the Child Support Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enforce each obligation for which payment is delinquent in an amount equal to the support payment for 1 month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take appropriate enforcement action within 30 days of identifying a delinquency or the location of the noncustodial parent, whichever occurs later; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Take appropriate action to enforce a health insurance enrollment order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If service of process is necessary before enforcement action, the support enforcement agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete service and take enforcement action within 60 days of identifying the delinquency or locating the noncustodial parent, whichever occurs later; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In cases where service of process is not completed, document unsuccessful attempts to serve the noncustodial parent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To enable the support enforcement agency to properly enforce the order, the custodial parent shall notify the support enforcement agency when the child:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Marries;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Becomes 18 years old and is enrolled in secondary school;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Otherwise emancipates; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Dies.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Methods of Child Support Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Earnings Withholding. The support enforcement agency shall issue an earnings withholding notice in accordance with <cite path="|07.07.19">COMAR 07.07.19</cite> for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Civil child support orders; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Criminal nonsupport orders.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Noncustodial Parent Contact. The support enforcement agency may contact the noncustodial parent, by telephone or mail, to negotiate a lump sum payment or a payment plan to pay the arrears.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Court Action.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency may initiate contempt proceedings against the noncustodial parent when the noncustodial parent accumulates more than 30 days arrears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When an arrearage exists under a child support order issued in a criminal nonsupport proceeding, the support enforcement agency shall notify the attorney for the support enforcement agency of the arrearage not later than 60 days before the expiration of the order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency may request that the attorney for the support enforcement agency provide all necessary legal services for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Garnishing financial accounts and attaching assets of the noncustodial parent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Securing a performance bond; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Using any other form of legal process considered appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>IRS Full Collection Service. The support enforcement agency may apply for collection by the IRS, when the support enforcement agency documents that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There are arrears equal to or exceeding $750;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Local, State, and intergovernmental enforcement efforts have failed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent has known assets.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Lien Against Real Property. The support enforcement agency may file a notice of a child support lien with the clerk of a circuit court under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-141">Family Law Article, §10-141, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent is in arrears for a child support obligation in an amount exceeding $500;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The unpaid child support constitutes a lien under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-140">Family Law Article, §10-140, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Real property deeded to the noncustodial parent has been identified and the noncustodial parent's ownership interest in the property has been verified.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Garnishment of Financial Accounts. The support enforcement agency may initiate action to garnish the financial account of a noncustodial parent under Maryland Rule 2-645, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent owes at least $500 arrears; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The support enforcement agency has verified that the noncustodial parent has ownership interest in the account.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Performance Bond. The support enforcement agency may request that a court order a noncustodial parent to post a bond to ensure consistent payment of a child support obligation if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent owes at least $500 arrears;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Financial accounts of the noncustodial parent cannot be garnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Financial accounts of the noncustodial parent have sufficient value to satisfy:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All arrears owed; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A portion of the arrears equal to 6 months of the support ordered amount;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Self-employed; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Earnings withholding has not been effective;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent's payment history has been poor as evidenced by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Irregular payments; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payments less than the support ordered amount; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The noncustodial parent is out of compliance with the most recent support order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>National Medical Support Notice (NMSN). The support enforcement agency shall issue a NMSN in accordance with <cite path="|07.07.20">COMAR 07.07.20</cite> to enforce the medical support provisions of a child support order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Other Remedies. The support enforcement agency shall initiate other enforcement remedies as provided for in this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Intergovernmental Enforcement.</heading>
    <text>The support enforcement agency shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Cooperate with child support enforcement agencies of other states to secure compliance with court orders for child support;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Use all appropriate enforcement methods in intergovernmental cases that the support enforcement agency uses in intrastate cases;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Initiate intergovernmental earnings withholding procedures when an obligor is liable for earnings withholding and the obligor's employer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is located outside the State, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has no agent in the State; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Comply with the provisions of UIFSA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-108">10-108</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-108">10-108</cite>.2, 10-113—10-116, 10-119, 10-119.3—10-359, and 12-102; Article 1, §24; Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference — 45 CFR §§302.60—302.65, 302.80, 303.6, 303.31, 303.71—303.100, 303.102, and 303.104</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22">Effective date: March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|06|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|06|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|06|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|07|07|06|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> adopted effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1184)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|06|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-01-19"><cite path="|07|07|06|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, H amended effective January 19, 2004 (31:1 Md. R. 30)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-31"><cite path="|07|07|06|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1345)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-31"><cite path="|07|07|06|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1345)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
