<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>State Comptroller Intercept Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes the procedures of the Child Support Administration for identifying and reporting certain delinquent child support obligors to the Comptroller for interception of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State tax refunds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Abandoned property; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any payment due to the obligor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The interception by the Comptroller of these payments is to satisfy child support arrears.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Abandoned property” means any personal property delivered to the Comptroller as abandoned by any person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Comptroller” means the Comptroller of the Treasury.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Duties of the Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall annually certify to the Comptroller child support obligations which are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>More than $150 in arrears; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Owed on cases in which the obligee is receiving services under Title IV-D of the Social Security Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The certification shall include, if known, the name of the obligor, Social Security number (when known), the total amount of accumulated arrears, the address, case number, and any known alias of the person certified, and the name of the obligee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Written Notice of Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall send a written notice of the certification to the last known address of the obligor at least 30 days before certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice shall advise the obligor of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Right to request an investigation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Method of doing so.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The certification does not affect the authority of the Administration otherwise to enforce payment of support obligations under other provisions of this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall instruct the Comptroller to delete a certified obligation or to reduce a certified arrearage upon the Administration's conclusion that a person has been wrongly certified, or has since paid all or a significant portion of the support obligation arrearage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In a case certified for non-TCA arrears only, the Administration shall remit the intercepted amount to the obligee within 30 days after its receipt from the Comptroller, if no appeal of intercept is made.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Duties of the Comptroller of the Treasury.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller may not question the certifications of the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall compare the names certified by the Administration with persons who file tax returns and are entitled to a tax refund, not less often than weekly.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall delete certified names or change amounts when instructed by the Administration. If, because an intercept has been made the Comptroller is unable to do so, the Comptroller shall inform the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a match is made between a taxpayer eligible for a tax refund and a certified obligor, the Comptroller shall determine whether the refund or the arrears due the obligee or the Administration are greater. If the refund is equal to or less than the arrears due, the Comptroller shall pay the full refund to the Administration. If the refund is greater than the arrears, the Comptroller shall pay only that portion of the refund to the Administration which is equal to the arrears. The Comptroller shall pay the remainder of the refund to the obligor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall send written notification of the intercept to the obligor within 15 days of the intercept. The notification shall inform the obligor of the right to appeal and of the method of doing so.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a match occurs with one of the parties to a joint tax return, the entire refund is subject to intercept. If a match occurs with a party to a combined separate return, the refund due the obligor only is subject to intercept.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall remit payments from tax returns of obligors to the Administration not less often than weekly. The Comptroller shall submit to the Administration a list identifying the obligors for whom remittance is made. The list shall include the taxpayer's name, Social Security number, Administration case number, the taxpayer's home address, and any other information from his files the Comptroller finds appropriate to substantiate the matching of names.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If the Comptroller receives a request to intercept a tax refund for another obligation, other than a tax obligation to the State or any of its subdivisions, the Comptroller shall remit the refund, up to the amount of arrearages certified, to the Administration before honoring the other request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Withhold the amount of the arrears from abandoned property or any payment due to the obligor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Remit the amount withheld to the Administration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notify the obligor of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The amount paid to the Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The right to appeal the intercept:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>To the Office of Administrative Hearings; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Pursuant to <cite path="|07|07|08|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon notice of certification, the obligor has a right to request an investigation by the Administration if the obligor disputes the existence or amount of the arrears.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may decline to investigate a complaint under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The complaint concerns an issue other than the existence or the amount of the arrears;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The complaint requesting an investigation was received more than 15 days from the date the notification of certification was sent to the obligor for a tax refund; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The complaint requesting an investigation was received more than 30 days from the date the notification of certification was sent to the obligor for abandoned property or any payment due to the obligor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall submit to the complainant and, in an NAFDC case, to the obligee, a report of its findings within 30 days from the date that the complaint was received.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the investigation concludes that the obligation should not have been certified under these regulations, the Administration shall instruct the Comptroller to delete the obligation from the certified list. If the conclusion is that the amount certified was incorrectly high, the Administration shall instruct the Comptroller to reduce the amount.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Appeal Rights and Restrictions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certified obligor has the right to appeal the intercept of all or part of the obligor’s tax refund, abandoned property, or any payment due to the obligor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An appeal shall be conducted according to <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An obligor may not appeal except on the claim that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The arrearage certified does not exist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The arrearage does exist but in a lesser amount than that certified by the Administration, or intercepted by the Comptroller.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The obligor may not raise on appeal any issue regarding the amount of tax refund otherwise due the taxpayer. This restriction does not prejudice any rights available under the tax laws.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Remedies.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If, in the case of an appeal of intercept, the administrative law judge decides that no arrearage exists, the Administration shall pay the full amount to the obligor within 30 days of the date of that determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If, in an NAFDC case, the administrative law judge decides that the intercept, or part of the intercept, is due the obligee, the Administration shall remit the correct amount to the obligee within 15 days after expiration of the period of appeal to the circuit court. If the case is appealed to the circuit court, the Administration shall distribute the intercepted amount as ordered by the court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the administrative law judge determines that the tax refund, abandoned property, or any payment due to the obligor remitted to the Administration is in excess of the arrears as of the date of the review or hearing, the Administration shall remit the excess to the obligor within 30 days of the date of the decision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-113">10-113</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-113">10-113</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-03-13">Regulations <cite path="|07|07|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|07|08|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective November 3, 1980 (7:23 Md. R. 2159); adopted permanently effective March 13, 1981 (8:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-09-26">Regulations .01, .02B—I, .04C, and .05A—D amended effective September 26, 1983 (10:19 Md. R. 1689)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-02">Regulations .01, .02B—I, .03A—E, G, .04A—D, and .05A—C amended, and .03H adopted effective January 2, 1984 (10:26 Md. R. 2339)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-06-19"><cite path="|07|07|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 19, 1995 (22:12 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-07"><cite path="|07|07|08|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 7, 1985 (12:20 Md. R. 1923)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-03-06"><cite path="|07|07|08|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective March 6, 1989 (16:4 Md. R. 494)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-03-06"><cite path="|07|07|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1964); March 6, 1989 (16:4 Md. R. 494)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-09-28"><cite path="|07|07|08|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1703)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-06-19"><cite path="|07|07|08|.02|K.">Regulation .02K</cite> repealed effective June 19, 1995 (22:12 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-06-19"><cite path="|07|07|08|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1703); June 19, 1995 (22:12 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-06-19"><cite path="|07|07|08|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective March 6, 1989 (16:4 Md. R. 494); September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1703); June 19, 1995 (22:12 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-06-19"><cite path="|07|07|08|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1703); June 19, 1995 (22:12 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Annotation: This chapter was adopted in conjunction with the Comptroller of the Treasury.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|07.07.02">COMAR 07.07.02</cite> to <cite path="|07.07.08">COMAR 07.07.08</cite> effective March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-11-12"><cite path="|07|07|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540); November 12, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1935)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-11-12"><cite path="|07|07|08|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective November 12, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1935)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05"><cite path="|07|07|08|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-05-16" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 16, 2011 (38:10 Md. R. 614)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-25"><cite path="|07|07|08|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite> repealed effective April 25, 2016 (43:8 Md. R. 497)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
