<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Federal Income Tax Refund Offset Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"IRS" means the Internal Revenue Service of the U.S. Department of the Treasury, which, under federal law, offsets income tax refunds against certain support obligation arrearages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Offset" means withholding by the IRS of all or part of a federal income tax refund due a taxpayer, and remitting it to OCSE for transmittal to the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall certify to OCSE a noncustodial parent whose support obligation assigned to the State is in arrears $150 or more.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall certify to OCSE any non-TCA child support arrears which are not assigned to the State if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amount of arrears equals or exceeds $500; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obligation is payable to the Administration or other public child support collection agency, and the arrears certified are on record in that agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall notify the noncustodial parent of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pending certification of arrears to OCSE; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Right to request an investigation and manner to do so.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The certification shall provide the noncustodial parent's name, Social Security number, case number, and the total amount of accumulated arrearages as of the date of the certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Without further notice to the obligor, the Administration shall provide OCSE with updates at least monthly to adjust the amount of arrears to reflect any payments or additional arrears that accrue after the date of certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall instruct OCSE to remove a noncustodial parent's name from certification upon the Administration's conclusion that the noncustodial parent has been wrongly certified, or no longer meets the criteria for certification.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The noncustodial parent has a right to request an investigation by the Administration if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Noncustodial parent disputes the existence or amount of the arrears; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Request is received by the Administration not later than 15 days after the date on the notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may decline to conduct an investigation under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The request concerns an issue other than the existence or the amount of the arrears; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The request was received more than 15 days from the date the notification of certification was sent to the noncustodial parent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall submit to the noncustodial parent a written report of its findings within 30 days from the date that the request for investigation was received.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If, as a result of the investigation, the Administration finds that the obligation should not be certified under this chapter, the Administration may not proceed with the certification.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person who has been notified by IRS that all or part of the federal income tax refund has been offset for a support obligation arrearage certified by the Administration is entitled to an appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The appeal shall be conducted according to <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The date for calculation of the amount of any arrearage used in the decision is the date of the review or hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the decision on the appeal is that no arrearage exists, or that the amount of the income tax refund exceeds the arrearage, the Administration shall reimburse the appellant the appropriate amount within 60 days of the date of the decision, or within 60 days of the date the money is received from the U.S. Treasury, whichever is later.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In the case of a consolidated appeal concerning a federal income tax offset and an intercept of a State income tax refund, reimbursement to the appellant, if any, is due 60 days from the date of the decision or 60 days from the date the money from the federal income tax refund is received from the U.S. Treasury, whichever is later.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Distribution.</heading>
    <text>If an amount is offset from a noncustodial parent owing certified non-TCA and TCA arrears, the intercepted amount shall be applied first to the TCA obligation, and if there is any amount remaining, to the non-TCA obligation.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-110">10-110</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-113">10-113</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">10-114</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference — 45 CFR §303.72; 42 U.S.C. §664</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-10-10">Effective date: October 10,1983 (10.20 Md. R. 1785)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-07">Regulations .01 and .02 amended effective October 7, 1985 (12:20 Md. R. 1924)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-03-06"><cite path="|07|07|09|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective March 6, 1989 (16:4 Md. R. 495)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|07|07|09|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1964)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-09-28"><cite path="|07|07|09|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, E amended effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1704)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-06-19"><cite path="|07|07|09|.03">Regulation .03</cite> A, C, E, G amended effective June 19, 1995 (22:12 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-07"><cite path="|07|07|09|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective October 7, 1985 (12:20 Md. R. 1924)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|07.07.03">COMAR 07.07.03</cite> to <cite path="|07.07.09">COMAR 07.07.09</cite> effective March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05"><cite path="|07|07|09|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-11-12" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective November 12, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1935)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-11-24"><cite path="|07|07|09|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective November 24, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1825)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-25"><cite path="|07|07|09|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> repealed effective April 25, 2016 (43:8 Md. R. 497)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
