<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Child Support Enforcement Incentives</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Under federal law, the Office of Child Support Enforcement (OCSE) computes and pays the State an incentive payment based on the efficiency and effectiveness of the State's child support enforcement program as measured by prescribed performance standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Federal and State laws provide that incentives paid to the State shall be divided between the State and its political subdivisions based on a formula devised by the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes a formula to determine the amount of the incentive to be paid to a political subdivision.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collections.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Collections" means child support payments received and disbursed for cases within a subdivision's child support caseload.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Collections" includes payments received from other states as well as payments forwarded to other states.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Privatized" means operated by a private company as provided in <cite path="|07.07.14">COMAR 07.07.14</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Subdivision" means Baltimore City or a Maryland county.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Support enforcement agency" means a State or local government unit in a subdivision that administers one or more functions of the child support enforcement program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|11|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Distribution of Incentives.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The total amount of federal incentives earned by the State shall be allocated between the State and its local subdivisions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall determine annually what portion of the total federal incentives shall be made available for distribution to subdivisions Statewide.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall pay incentives to an individual subdivision based on a measurement of performance for that subdivision:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Paternity establishment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Support order establishment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Current support collections;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Cases with collections on arrears; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Cost-effectiveness; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using the methodology used by OCSE to measure the performance of states as provided in 42 U.S.C. §658a(b)(6).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The incentive amount paid to a subdivision shall be allocated among the support enforcement agencies within that subdivision. The total incentive amount paid to an individual support enforcement agency shall be based on the number of full-time staff employed by that agency relative to the number of full-time staff employed by the subdivision's support enforcement agencies collectively.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite path="07|07|11|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the incentive amount that would be paid to a privatized support enforcement agency in a subdivision shall be retained by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall make quarterly incentive payments to support enforcement agencies.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Local Subdivision Participation in the Development of the Distribution Methodology.</heading>
    <text>Before adoption of any change in the distribution methodology, the Administration shall submit a draft of the proposed methodology, including the projected fiscal impact of the change on individual support enforcement agencies, to the administrators of support enforcement agencies for review and comment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Use of Incentives.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A support enforcement agency shall expend incentives only for activities that contribute to the efficiency and effectiveness of the Statewide child support enforcement program, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Privatizing and outsourcing of child support enforcement services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Improving automation capabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Creating public awareness projects;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Developing programs and special projects;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Assisting in staff development and training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Establishing community outreach programs and activities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Other activities approved by the Secretary of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A support enforcement agency's request for approval of expending incentives on beneficial activities not currently eligible for funding under the federal child support enforcement program shall be submitted to the Administration in accordance with instructions issued by OCSE.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A support enforcement agency may not use incentives to supplant its budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall require support enforcement agencies to periodically report or provide other documentation regarding the activities for which incentive funds were expended.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-106">10-106</cite>.1 and 10-114, Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference — 45 CFR §§302.55, 303.52, and 304; 42 U.S.C. §§658 and 658a</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-25">Effective date: December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2709)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-06-20"><cite path="|07|07|11|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 20, 1994 (21:12 Md. R. 1060)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|07.07.05">COMAR 07.07.05</cite> to <cite path="|07.07.11">COMAR 07.07.11</cite> effective March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-06-11" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective June 11, 2001 (28:11 Md. R. 1053)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15"><cite path="|07|07|11|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective  April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15"><cite path="|07|07|11|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective  April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
