<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Reporting to Consumer Reporting Agencies</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. "Consumer reporting agency" means any person or entity that, for monetary fees or dues, or on a cooperative nonprofit basis, regularly engages in whole or in part in the practice of assembling or evaluating consumer credit information or other information on consumers for the purpose of furnishing consumer credit reports to third parties.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Disclosure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall disclose to any consumer reporting agency information regarding an administrative or court-ordered support obligation owed by the noncustodial parent that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is payable to a support enforcement agency; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has arrears equal to or greater than payments required in a 60-day period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before disclosing any information to a consumer reporting agency concerning arrears, the Administration shall send written notice to the last known address of the noncustodial parent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The notice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State that the Administration periodically intends to disclose information regarding the noncustodial parent's support obligation to consumer reporting agencies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the amount of the current obligation shown on the support enforcement agency's records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State the amount of arrears shown on the support enforcement agency's records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advise the noncustodial parent of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Right to request a review by the Administration if the noncustodial parent disputes the existence or the amount of the support obligation or of the arrears, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Procedures to request a review.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When a proper request for a review is received, the Administration may not disclose information to a consumer reporting agency until the noncustodial parent's claim is investigated and a decision is rendered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If no request for review is received within 15 days of the date of the notice, the Administration may disclose to a consumer reporting agency information regarding a support obligation that is 60 days or more in arrears.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Request for a Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent has a right to request that the Administration review the accuracy of the information that it intends to disclose to a consumer reporting agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for a review is effective only if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed by the noncustodial parent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Administration at the address indicated in the notice within 15 days of the date on the notice of the Administration's intent to disclose information to a consumer reporting agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An noncustodial parent may request a review only on a claim that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support obligation does not exist; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amounts specified in the notice are incorrect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A request for a review may be withdrawn by the noncustodial parent at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon request for review, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use the date of the review as the date of determination of the support obligation amount and the calculation of the amount of any arrears due;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written summary of the conclusions of its review;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Forward its review summary to the noncustodial parent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advise the noncustodial parent of the right to appeal the decision of the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration's notice of the right to appeal shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The result of the Administration's review;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The procedures for requesting a hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Filing fee information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>When the Administration has notified the noncustodial parent of the decision, the Administration, if appropriate, may disclose information to consumer reporting agencies about the support obligation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Receive and process requests from a consumer reporting agency regarding the reverification of information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Respond to requests made by a consumer reporting agency in a timely manner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Correction of Information.</heading>
    <text>If the Administration finds that it has supplied erroneous information to a consumer reporting agency concerning arrears owed by a noncustodial parent, the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administration shall notify the consumer reporting agency; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Consumer reporting agency shall remove any information concerning the erroneous arrears from the noncustodial parent's credit file.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Appeal Rights and Restrictions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A noncustodial parent has the right to appeal the decision made by the Administration to disclose to consumer reporting agencies information regarding an administrative or court-ordered support obligation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An appeal shall be conducted according to <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A noncustodial parent may not appeal except on the claim that the arrearage:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As determined by the Administration does not exist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is a lesser amount than determined by the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Remedies. The date of the review or hearing is the date for calculating the amount of any arrearage used in the decision.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-108">Family Law Article, §10-108</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference—42 U.S.C. §666(a)(7)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07">Effective date: November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1874)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-02">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|07.07.06">COMAR 07.07.06</cite> to <cite path="|07.07.12">COMAR 07.07.12</cite> effective March 2, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|12|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05"><cite path="|07|07|12|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|12|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|12|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-26"><cite path="|07|07|12|.03|H.">Regulation .03H</cite> amended effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 399)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|12|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15"><cite path="|07|07|12|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540); October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1781)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
