<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>Driver's License Suspension Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter sets out the procedures of the Child Support Administration for reporting to the Motor Vehicle Administration (MVA) non-custodial parents who owe child support arrears. The purpose of reporting the delinquent non-custodial parents to the MVA is to have the non-custodial parent's license or privilege to drive suspended.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"License" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-128">Transportation Article, §11-128, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Motor Vehicle Administration (MVA)" means the Motor Vehicle Administration of the Department of Transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Potential employment" means a bona fide offer of employment or enrollment in job-related training which may lead to a bona fide offer of employment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Administration Referral to the MVA.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may send to the MVA information regarding child support cases in which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration is providing services under Title IV-D of the Social Security Act, 42 USC §651 et seq.; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The obligor is 60 days or more out of compliance with the most recent court or administrative order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before reporting information to the MVA, the Administration shall send written notice of the proposed action to the last known address of the noncustodial parent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The written notice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the support enforcement agency's address and telephone number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the following noncustodial parent identification information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full name,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Last known address,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Social Security number,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Child support case number, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Arrearage amount as of the date of the written notice;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advise the noncustodial parent of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Opportunity and procedures for entering into an arrearage payment schedule agreement as described in <cite path="|07|07|15|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Right to a reasonable opportunity to contest the Administration's proposed action by requesting an investigation by the Administration as described in <cite path="|07|07|15|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Procedures to request an investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration may not send information to the MVA if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An arrearage payment schedule agreement has been negotiated under <cite path="|07|07|15|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, and the noncustodial parent is in compliance with that agreement and with any court order embodying the terms of that agreement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration has received a proper and timely request for an investigation from the noncustodial parent, as specified in <cite path="|07|07|15|.05|B.">Regulation .05B of this chapter</cite>, and, after completion of the investigation, or completion of any subsequent appeal to OAH, the Administration has determined that a claim specified in <cite path="|07|07|15|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite> is valid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an arrearage payment schedule agreement is not reached or the noncustodial parent's request for an investigation is not postmarked within 30 days of this notice, the Administration may report the noncustodial parent's information to the MVA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Arrearage Payment Schedule Agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An noncustodial parent may contact the support enforcement agency to arrange a written arrearage payment schedule agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency and the noncustodial parent shall attempt to negotiate a mutually acceptable agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The arrearage payment schedule agreement shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide for the payment of the full amount of arrearage at the time of the agreement or the reduction of the total arrearage to less than the payments required in a 60-day period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establish a time limit for the payment of the full amount of the arrearage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide for payment of the total amount of arrearage owed based on the noncustodial parent's ability to pay; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Include the date and signature of the noncustodial parent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The agreement shall state that to be in compliance, the noncustodial parent shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pay the current support amount;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comply with the arrearage payment schedule agreement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make all payments on or by the date each payment is due.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency may petition the court to enter a court order that includes the terms of the agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency shall monitor the noncustodial parent's compliance with the agreement. If the noncustodial parent fails to comply with the agreement, the Administration shall send the noncustodial parent's information to the MVA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|15|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Noncustodial Parent's Request for an Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent may contest the Administration's proposed action by requesting an investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for an investigation shall be effective only if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed by the noncustodial parent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Administration postmarked within 30 days of the date on the notice of the Administration's intent to report information to the MVA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent may request an investigation only on a claim that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The support obligation does not exist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amounts specified in the notice are incorrect and the noncustodial parent is less than 60 days out of compliance with the most recent support order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Suspension of the noncustodial parent's license or privilege to drive would be an impediment to the obligor's current or potential employment because a driver's license is required by the employer to perform the duties of the job;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Suspension of the noncustodial parent's license or privilege to drive would place an undue hardship on the obligor because of the noncustodial parent's documented disability resulting in a verified inability to work; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Suspension of the noncustodial parent's license or privilege to drive would place an undue hardship on the noncustodial parent because of the noncustodial parent's subsequent inability to comply with the court order due to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unemployment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Insufficient income to meet the child support obligation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Incarceration, not on work release and no other resources to meet the child support obligation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent may submit any documents relevant to the noncustodial parent's claim.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A request for an investigation may be withdrawn by the noncustodial parent at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Within 5 days of receiving a request for an investigation, the Administration shall send a letter to the custodial parent advising that parent of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administration's proposed action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Noncustodial parent's request for an investigation, including the grounds specified; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Right to submit information relevant to the investigation to the Administration within 15 days of the date of the letter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a request for an investigation, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use the date of the written notice as the date of determination of the support obligation amount and the calculation of the amount of any arrearage due;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conduct an investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review any documents submitted by the noncustodial parent under <cite path="07|07|15|.05|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Review any documents submitted by the custodial parent under <cite path="07|07|15|.05|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written summary of the conclusions of its investigation and issue a decision concerning the amount of the arrearage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Forward its investigation summary to the noncustodial parent and to the custodial parent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Advise the noncustodial parent of the right to appeal the decision of the Administration to OAH.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall advise the noncustodial parent of the right to appeal and the procedures for filing an appeal with OAH.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If the request for an appeal hearing is not received within 20 days of the date of the results of the investigation, the Administration may report the information to the MVA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent has the right to appeal to OAH the Administration's proposed action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An appeal shall be conducted according to <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent may not appeal except on a claim specified in <cite path="|07|07|15|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Remedies. The administrative law judge shall use the date of the review or hearing as the date for calculating the amount of any arrearage used in the decision.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement of Noncustodial Parent's Driver's License.</heading>
    <text>The noncustodial parent is eligible for driver's license reinstatement when the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Noncustodial parent has paid the arrearage in full;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Noncustodial parent has paid the administrative or court-ordered amount of support for 6 consecutive months;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Administration finds that the noncustodial parent's claim under <cite path="|07|07|15|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite> is valid; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The MVA receives an administrative or court order which orders the MVA to reinstate the noncustodial parent's license.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Notification to the MVA.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall notify the MVA when the noncustodial parent satisfies the reinstatement criteria cited in <cite path="|07|07|15|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">10-114</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-119">10-119</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-203">Transportation Article, §16-203</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference—42 U.S.C. §666(a)(16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-02-24">Regulations <cite path="|07|07|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|07|15|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective November 1, 1996 (23:24 Md. R. 1673); adopted permanently effective February 24, 1997 (24:4 Md. R. 290)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|07.07.09">COMAR 07.07.09</cite> to <cite path="|07.07.15">COMAR 07.07.15</cite> effective March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 482)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05"><cite path="|07|07|15|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05"><cite path="|07|07|15|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1782)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-25"><cite path="|07|07|15|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 25, 2004 (31:21 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-25"><cite path="|07|07|15|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective June 7, 2004 (31:11 Md. R. 856); October 25, 2004 (31:21 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-25"><cite path="|07|07|15|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite>, D, E amended effective October 25, 2004 (31:21 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|07|07|15|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-25"><cite path="|07|07|15|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 25, 2004 (31:21 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|07|07|15|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite>, C amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-25"><cite path="|07|07|15|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, C amended effective October 25, 2004 (31:21 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-25"><cite path="|07|07|15|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 25, 2004 (31:21 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
