<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Business, Occupational, and Professional License Suspension Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the procedures for identifying and reporting certain delinquent obligors of child support to a licensing authority for the purpose of suspension or denial of the obligor's license necessary to practice or engage in a business, occupation, or profession.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Arrearage" means unpaid and past due child support payments owed under a court order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Days" means calendar days except when business days are specified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"License" means a license, certificate, registration, permit, or other authorization that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issued by a licensing authority;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Subject to suspension, revocation, forfeiture, or termination by a licensing authority; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Necessary for an individual to practice or engage in a particular business, occupation, or profession.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Licensing Authority.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Licensing authority" means a State agency, unit of an agency, a commission, board, office, or Court of the State that issues licenses.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Licensing authority" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Clerks of the court;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Comptroller of the Treasury;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Department of Agriculture;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Department of Health;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Department of Human Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Department of Natural Resources;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Department of the Environment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Department of Transportation</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Maryland Insurance Administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Maryland Department of Labor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Office of the Attorney General;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Public Service Commission;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Secretary of State;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>State Department of Education; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Court of Appeals.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Administration's Request for License Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may request information under this chapter from a licensing authority concerning an obligor who is in arrears amounting to more than 120 days under the most recent court order that is payable through a support enforcement agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The request for information shall contain the obligor's:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Full name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Social Security number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Most recent address, if known.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Licensing Authority's Responsibility for Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon request from the Administration, a licensing authority shall submit to the Administration information regarding an obligor who is licensed by or has applied for a license from the licensing authority. The licensing authority shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The obligor's full name, including aliases, if known;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The obligor's most recent home and business addresses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The obligor's Social Security number, if known;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A description of the license applied for or held by the obligor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The date the license was issued, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The licensing authority shall make available any record compiled under this regulation only to an individual in an official capacity who has a right to the record, except as otherwise provided by law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Administration's Request to Suspend or Deny License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in Regulations .06 and .08 of this chapter, the Administration may request a licensing authority to suspend or deny an obligor's license if the obligor is in arrears amounting to more than 120 days under the most recent court order, and the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administration has accepted an assignment of support under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="88A|50">Article 88A, §50(b)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recipient of support payments has filed an application for support enforcement services with the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send the obligor written notice of the intended action as provided in <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>When Licensing Authority is the Court of Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an individual meets the criteria specified in <cite path="|07|07|16|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> and holds a license issued by the Court of Appeals, the Administration may make a referral to the Attorney Grievance Commission of Maryland for proceedings in accordance with the Maryland Rules governing attorney discipline.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At the recommendation of the Attorney Grievance Commission of Maryland, the Court of Appeals may suspend an individual's license or take other action against the individual as authorized by the Maryland Rules governing attorney discipline.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Administration's Notice to Obligor of Request to Suspend or Deny License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send written notice of the proposed action to the obligor at the obligor's last known address at least 30 days before:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Requesting a licensing authority to suspend or deny a license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Making a referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The written notice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the support enforcement agency's address and telephone number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the following identification information on the obligor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Last known address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Social Security number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Child support case number; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Arrearage amount as of the date of the written notice; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advise the obligor of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Opportunity and procedure for entering into an arrearage payment schedule agreement as provided in <cite path="|07|07|16|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Right to contest, within 15 days of the date of the notice, the accuracy of the information by requesting an investigation by the Administration as provided in <cite path="|07|07|16|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Procedures to request an investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Prohibition of Administration's Request to Suspend or Deny a License.</heading>
    <text>The Administration may not request a licensing authority to suspend or deny a license or make a referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration has entered into an arrearage payment schedule agreement with the obligor, as provided in <cite path="|07|07|16|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>, and the obligor is complying with the agreement;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration has received an investigation request from the obligor, as provided in <cite path="|07|07|16|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>, and the Administration has determined that it is inappropriate to suspend or deny the license;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The obligor has appealed the decision of the Administration to the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) and a decision:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has not yet been reached; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In favor of the obligor was reached; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A court has issued an order:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For the obligor's scheduled payment of arrearage to which the obligor is complying;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Which prohibited the Administration from requesting the licensing authority to suspend or deny the obligor's license or make a referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Which otherwise would be violated by, or in conflict with, a request for license suspension or referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Arrearage Payment Schedule Agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An obligor may contact the support enforcement agency to arrange a written arrearage payment schedule agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency shall attempt to negotiate with the obligor to reach a mutually acceptable agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The arrearage payment schedule agreement shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Payment of the full amount of arrearage at the time of the agreement, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reduction of the total arrearage to less than the payments required in a 120-day period;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establish a time limit for the payment of the full amount of the arrearage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide for payment of the total amount of arrearage owed based on the obligor's ability to pay; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be signed by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obligor, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Representative of the local support enforcement agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The agreement shall state that to be in compliance, the obligor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pay the current support amount;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comply with the arrearage payment schedule agreement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make all payments on or by the due date of each payment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Comply with all other court orders and support payment agreements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The support enforcement agency may petition the court to enter a court order that includes the terms of the agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration may forward to the licensing authority a request for suspension or denial of the obligor's license or make a referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An arrearage payment schedule agreement is not reached; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The obligor fails to comply with an agreement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|16|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Obligor's Request for an Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An obligor may request that the Administration investigate the accuracy of the Administration's records regarding the support obligation and the arrears.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for an investigation is effective only if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed by the obligor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Administration in an envelope postmarked within 15 days of the date of the Administration's notice issued under <cite path="|07|07|16|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An obligor may request an investigation on a claim that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support obligation does not exist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obligor is not the individual who owes support under the court order; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Amounts specified in the notice are incorrect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An obligor may submit to the Administration any documents relevant to the accuracy of the claim.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An obligor may withdraw a request for an investigation at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the Administration does not receive an investigation request as specified in <cite path="07|07|16|.10|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Administration may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Forward to the licensing authority a request for suspension or denial of the obligor's license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make a referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Administration's Responsibility for Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a written request for an investigation, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct an investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use the date of receipt of the request as the date of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determination of the support obligation amount, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Calculation of the amount of any arrearage due;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review any documents submitted by the obligor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written summary of the conclusions of its investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Issue a decision concerning the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amount of the arrearage, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Intent to proceed with the request for license suspension; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Forward to the obligor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Administration's investigation summary, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Information of the obligor's right to appeal the Administration's decision to OAH.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration's notice of the obligor's right to appeal the Administration's decision shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The result of the Administration's investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The procedures for requesting a record review or an appeal hearing if the results are adverse to the obligor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Filing fee information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If, after the investigation, the Administration finds its records are incorrect, the Administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall correct its records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not send a notification about an individual to a licensing authority or make a referral under <cite path="|07|07|16|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Obligor's Appeal of Administration's Decision to OAH.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An obligor may appeal to OAH the Administration's decision to request a licensing authority to suspend or deny the obligor's license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The obligor may appeal the decision only on a claim that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support order does not exist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obligor is not the individual who owes support under the order; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Amount of arrearage owed is incorrect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The obligor shall file a signed written appeal with OAH, which shall be received by OAH within 30 days of the Administration's decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The appeal request shall be for a hearing or record review and be accompanied by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the investigation summary and a notice of the right to appeal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment of any fee required by OAH.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The appeal to OAH shall be conducted as provided in <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Licensing Authority's Responsibility for Suspension or Denial of License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon request from the Administration, the licensing authority shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Suspend the obligor's license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deny the license of the obligor who is an applicant for a license from the licensing authority.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least 30 days before the licensing authority suspends or denies a license, the licensing authority shall provide written notice to the obligor of the proposed license suspension or denial at the obligor's last known address.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The written notice shall advise the obligor of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Effective date of the proposed suspension or denial;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Opportunity to prevent the suspension or denial by contacting the child support enforcement agency within 15 days of the date of the notice to arrange to pay the arrears in full;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Right to appeal the proposed license suspension within 30 days of the date of the notice; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures for filing the appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The licensing authority shall suspend or deny the obligor's license not later than 45 days from the date of the notice unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration notifies the licensing authority that the obligor has paid the arrears in full; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The obligor appeals the proposed suspension or denial within 30 days of the date of the notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The licensing authority shall notify the Administration of the effective date of the suspension of an obligor's license.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Obligor's Appeal of License Suspension or Denial.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An obligor may appeal the licensing authority's decision to suspend or deny the obligor's license by filing a signed written appeal, within 30 days of the date of the licensing authority's notice of suspension, with the licensing authority or OAH.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The obligor may appeal the decision only on a claim of mistaken identity and has the burden of proof to prove that the obligor is not the individual in question.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The appeal to OAH shall be conducted as provided in <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The licensing authority may require that a representative from the Administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide testimony or evidence; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit documents for a hearing or record review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Administration's Request to Reinstate Obligor's License.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall notify the licensing authority to reinstate any license suspended or denied within 10 days after the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administration receives a court order to reinstate the suspended license;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Obligor pays the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support arrearage in full; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ordered amount of support for 4 consecutive months after the effective date of the license suspension; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Administration discovers it has erred in its decision to request suspension.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Licensing Authority's Reinstatement of Obligor's License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The licensing authority shall reinstate the license of an obligor within 1 business day upon receipt of a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice from the Administration requesting reinstatement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Court order:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directing the licensing authority to reinstate the license, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Which otherwise would be violated or in conflict with the license suspension.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The obligor shall pay the licensing authority any fees associated with reinstatement of the license.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-119">Family Law Article, §10-119</cite>.3, Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>(Agency Note: Federal Statutory Reference—42 U.S.C. §666(a)(16))</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-06-28">Effective date: June 28, 1999 (26:13 Md. R. 1019)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-03-24" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective March 24, 2008 (35:6 Md. R. 696)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
