<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>17</num>
  <heading>Passport Denial and Revocation Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes the procedures of the Child Support Administration for identifying and reporting certain delinquent obligors of child support to the federal Office of Child Support Enforcement (OCSE) for the denial, revocation, or limitation of the obligor's passport.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An obligor with support obligations over $2,500 is subject to denial, revocation, or limitation of the obligor's passport.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Notice of Certification for Passport Denial or Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall certify to OCSE an obligor whose support obligation arrearage exceeds $2,500.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send written notice of the certification to the obligor at the obligor's last known address at least <br/>30 days before certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The notice shall advise the obligor of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amount of the arrears as of the date of the notice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possibility that the obligor's passport will be denied, revoked, or restricted by the State Department of the United States;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Opportunity to contest the accuracy of the arrears by requesting an investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures for requesting an investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Right to appeal the denial, revocation, or limitation of the obligor's passport.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The mailing of the notice of certification to the obligor at the last address known to the Administration is considered proper and sufficient notice.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Obligor's Request for Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon notice of certification, an obligor may request that the Administration investigate the accuracy of the records regarding the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support obligation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Arrears.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for an investigation is effective if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed by the obligor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Administration postmarked within 15 days of the date of the Administration's notice of certification for passport denial or limitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An obligor may request an investigation on a claim that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support obligation does not exist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amounts specified in the notice are incorrect and the arrearage does not exceed $2,500; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Passport is required for employment purposes and neither the obligor nor the obligor’s employer is able to pay the arrears in full.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An obligor may submit to the Administration any documents relevant to the accuracy of the information.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An obligor may withdraw a request for an investigation at any time.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Administration's Response to Investigation Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a timely request for an investigation, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use the date of receipt of the written request for an investigation as the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date of determination of the support obligation amount, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Calculation of the amount of any arrearage due;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conduct an investigation by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determining the date of the notice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determining the support obligation amount; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Calculating the amount of any arrearage due;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review any documents submitted by the obligor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written summary of the conclusions of the investigation which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A decision concerning the amount of the arrearages; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The intent of the agency; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Forward the investigation summary to the obligor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Administration determines that the child support arrears were in excess of $2,500 as of the date of the notice, the Administration shall notify the obligor that to prevent passport denial or revocation, the obligor shall pay the arrears in full.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Administration determines that a support obligation does not exist or the obligor owed arrears in an amount of $2,500 or less as of the date of the notice, the Administration shall update the records to reflect the results of the investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Administration determines that a passport is needed for employment purposes, and that neither the obligor nor the obligor’s employer is able to pay the arrears in full, the Administration may request that the Office of Child Support Enforcement withdraw the passport denial or revocation upon a payment that is less than the full amount of arrears.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Obligor's Appeal of Passport Denial or Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State Department of the United States will notify an obligor when the obligor's passport has been denied, revoked, or limited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of receipt of the State Department's notice, the obligor may appeal the Administration's certification of arrears to the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The obligor may appeal only on the claim that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An arrearage does not exist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An arrearage does exist but never exceeded the $2,500 threshold; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A passport is required for employment purposes and neither the obligor nor the obligor’s employer is able to pay the arrears in full.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The appeal shall be conducted in accordance with <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Administration's Request to Withdraw Passport Denial.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall request that the Office of Child Support Enforcement withdraw the passport denial if the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administration has received a court order to withdraw the passport denial;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Obligor has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Paid the support arrearage in full; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provided documentation from the employer that a passport is required for employment purposes and that the Administration has been paid an agreed upon amount that is less than the full amount of arrears;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Obligor has appealed the passport denial to OAH and OAH has ruled in favor of the obligor; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Secretary of the Department or a designee of the Secretary determines that the passport denial or revocation would result in undue hardship.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">Family Law Article, §10-114, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>42 U.S.C. §654(31)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-05-17">Effective date: May 17, 1999 (26:10 Md. R. 797)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|07|07|17|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|07|07|17|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|07|07|17|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2002-11-25"><cite path="|07|07|17|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective November 25, 2002 (29:23 Md. R. 1810)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|07|07|17|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, C amended effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2002-11-25"><cite path="|07|07|17|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, C amended effective November 25, 2002 (29:23 Md. R. 1810)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|07|07|17|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective November 25, 2002 (29:23 Md. R. 1810); October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2002-11-25"><cite path="|07|07|17|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective November 25, 2002 (29:23 Md. R. 1810)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
