<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Administrative Offset Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the procedures of the Child Support Administration for identifying and reporting certain delinquent obligors of child support to the federal Office of Child Support Enforcement (OCSE) for the offset of certain federal payments.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Financial Management Services (FMS)" means the unit of the U.S. Department of the Treasury, which, under federal law, offsets certain federal payments to satisfy support obligation arrears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Offset" means withholding by the FMS of all or part of certain federal payments due an individual, and remitting payments to OCSE for transmittal to the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall certify to OCSE support arrears which are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assigned to the State if the arrears are $150 or more; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not assigned to the State if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amount of arrears equals or exceeds $500;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obligation is payable to a support enforcement agency, and the certified arrears are on record in that agency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Obligee is receiving services under the Social Security Act, Title IV, Part D.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least 30 days before certification, the Administration shall send written notice of the certification to the obligor, at the obligor's last known address, which shall advise the obligor of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amount of the arrears as of the date of the notice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possibility that the individual may have certain federal payments offset by FMS;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Opportunity to contest the accuracy of the arrears by requesting an investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures for requesting an investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Right to appeal the offset.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The certification shall provide the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obligor's name, Social Security number, and case number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Total amount of accumulated arrears.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Without further notice to the obligor, the Administration shall provide OCSE with updates at least monthly to adjust the certified arrears to reflect any payments or additional arrears that accrue.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The certification does not affect the Administration's authority to enforce payment of support obligations under other provisions of this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Request for Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon notice of certification, an obligor may request that the Administration investigate the accuracy of the Administration's records regarding the support obligation and arrears.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for an investigation is effective if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed by the obligor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Administration postmarked within 15 days of the date of the certification notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An obligor may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request an investigation only on a claim that the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Support obligation does not exist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Arrears are inaccurate; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Certification was based on a mistaken identity;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit to the Administration any documents relevant to the accuracy of the information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Withdraw a request for an investigation at any time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Administration's Response to Investigation Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a timely request for an investigation, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct an investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Review any documents submitted by the obligor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Calculate the arrears owed as of the date of the investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Update the case records to reflect new or additional information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written summary of the investigation conclusions including a decision concerning the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amount of the arrears; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administration's pending actions, if any; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Forward the investigation summary to the obligor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Administration determines that the obligor owes child support arrears pursuant to <cite path="|07|07|18|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, the Administration shall transmit the certification to OCSE.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>FMS notifies an obligor in writing when all or part of the obligor's federal payment has been offset.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of receipt of the notice from FMS, the obligor may appeal the offset of the federal payment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The appeal may be based only on a claim:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the arrearage:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Does not exist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does exist, but is less than the amount offset; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Of mistaken identity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The appeal shall be conducted in accordance with <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">Family Law Article, §10-114, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland; 31 U.S.C. §3716, Debt Collection Improvement Act, Public Law 104-134</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-09-20">Effective date: September 20, 1999 (26:19 Md. R. 1447)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-26"><cite path="|07|07|18|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 399)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
