<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>20</num>
  <heading>Administrative Enforcement of Medical Support</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establish the procedures of the Child Support Administration for issuing a national medical support notice (NMSN) to an employer of a parent who is obligated under a child support order to provide medical support for the child;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establish specific responsibilities, procedures, and time frames for employers, insurers, and health insurance plan administrators with respect to enrolling children in health insurance plans; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Create an administrative appeal process for the parent to contest the enforcement of the NMSN.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Child support order" means an order issued by a tribunal establishing a parent's obligation to pay child support or provide medical support for a child.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Health insurance coverage" means any type of health care coverage under which medical care services can be provided to the child through an insurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Insurer" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An insurer, a nonprofit health service organization, or a health maintenance organization operating in the State under a certificate of authority issued by the Maryland Insurance Commissioner;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An entity that provides a group health plan, as defined in §607(1) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (ERISA); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An entity offering a service benefit plan as defined by federal law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"National medical support notice (NMSN)" means a notice in a format prescribed by federal law and issued by a tribunal for the purpose of enforcing the medical support provisions in a child support order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Plan administrator" means the person responsible for administering the group health plan or other employer's insurance plan in which an obligated parent is enrolled or eligible for enrollment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Qualified medical child support order" means a medical child support order issued under State law that complies with §609(A) of ERISA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Tribunal" means a court, administrative agency, or quasi-judicial entity authorized to establish, enforce, or modify a child support order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|20|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Issuance of an NMSN by the Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall issue an NMSN for any child support case in which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual is receiving services under Title IV-D of the Social Security Act;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A tribunal has ordered the obligated parent to include the child in the parent's health insurance coverage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Health insurance coverage is available through the obligated parent's employer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The child does not have health insurance coverage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When the Administration issues an NMSN pursuant to <cite path="07|07|20|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Administration shall issue the NMSN within 2 business days of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Receipt of employment information from the State directory of new hires indicating that the employer offers health insurance coverage; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verification of employment information from sources other than the State directory of new hires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A properly completed NMSN has the same force and effect as a qualified medical child support order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Subject to federal law, an NMSN has priority over any other lien or legal process, except for the current support and support arrears withheld under an earnings withholding order or notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An NMSN issued by a tribunal in any other state or territory has the same force and effect as an NMSN issued in this State.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|20|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Service of NMSN on an Employer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall serve an employer with an NMSN by first class mail.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may issue an NMSN separate from or in conjunction with an earnings withholding order or an earnings withholding notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When the Administration serves an NMSN on the employer of an obligated parent under order to provide medical support, the Administration shall forward to the obligated parent:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notification that the NMSN was sent to the employer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A form that the obligated parent completes to request an investigation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send the information as provided for in <cite path="07|07|20|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> by first class mail to the obligated parent at the parent's:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Home address last reported to the court; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Place of employment, if the Administration has reason to believe that the home address is incorrect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Processing the NMSN.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 20 business days of receipt of the NMSN, the employer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete and forward Part A of the NMSN to the Administration if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The employer does not maintain or contribute to plans providing dependent or family health care coverage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The employee is not eligible for family health coverage; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Health care coverage is not available because the employee is no longer working for the employer; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Forward Part B of the NMSN to the employer's insurer, as required by the NMSN.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 20 business days of receipt of an NMSN from an employer, an insurer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine if the NMSN contains the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employee's name and mailing address; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Child's name and mailing address or the address of the Administration;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the NMSN does not contain the required information, complete Part B of the NMSN and forward it to the Administration and the employer indicating that the NMSN is incomplete and therefore does not constitute a qualified medical child support order; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the NMSN contains the required information, enroll the child in a health care plan and send written notification of eligibility for enrollment and information about the insurance plan as specified in the NMSN to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other parent; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If requested, the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon receiving notice from the insurer of the eligibility of an employee's child for enrollment, the employer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Withhold from the employee's next pay and each pay thereafter the amount of the employee contribution required to enroll the child, and notify the employee of the deduction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the employee's child is ineligible for health insurance coverage but will become eligible, withhold from the employee's earnings, at the earliest time the employee's child becomes eligible, the contribution required to enroll the child, and notify the employee of the deduction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the employer determines that the employee's child is not eligible for health insurance coverage, complete and forward Part A of the NMSN to the Administration indicating the reason the child is ineligible; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Federal Consumer Credit Protection Act withholding limitations or prioritization as specified in <cite path="|07|07|20|.06|B.">Regulation .06B of this chapter</cite> prevents withholding from the employee's earnings the amounts required for enrollment, complete and forward Part A of the NMSN to the Administration indicating the employee's income is insufficient for enrollment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the employer withholds a contribution under §D(1) or (2) of this regulation, the employer shall send to the insurer the amount deducted from the employee's earnings each pay period within 10 business days after the day on which the earnings are paid to the employee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Within 15 days of the first deduction from the employee's pay, the employer shall provide to both parents and to the Administration the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The employee's Social Security number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of the insurer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The policy number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The group number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The effective date of coverage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any schedule of benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Limitation on Earnings to be Withheld.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The amount of an employee's contribution for health insurance coverage to be withheld by an employer may not exceed the lesser of the amount:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Specified in the underlying child support order; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Allowed by the limits of the Federal Consumer Credit Protection Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an employee's wages are insufficient for full withholding of all court-ordered obligations and the full cost of health insurance, the employer shall withhold in accordance with the following priority:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Current child support;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Child support arrears;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Health insurance coverage premiums;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other medical support costs pursuant to the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-101">Family Law Article, §12-101(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other costs owed to the Administration as allowed by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the amount available for withholding is insufficient to pay amounts owed for court ordered support and the full cost of health insurance premiums, the employer shall complete and forward Part A of the NMSN to the Administration.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|20|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Administration's Selection of a Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the insurer sends written notice to the Administration that the obligated parent is eligible for more than one health insurance plan, and the parent is not enrolled in any plan that provides dependent coverage, the Administration shall select a plan in consultation with the custodial parent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Administration attempts to consult with the custodial parent as provided for in <cite path="07|07|20|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, and the custodial parent fails to participate in the selection of a plan, the Administration shall select a plan:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That provides comprehensive coverage, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hospital services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Medical services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Prescriptions;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That provides services that are accessible to the child; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whose cost, in combination with the amount withheld for cash support, does not exceed the applicable withholding limits set by the Federal Consumer Credit Protection Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If more than one plan meets the criteria set forth in <cite path="07|07|20|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Administration shall select the least costly plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If no plan meets all of the criteria set forth in <cite path="07|07|20|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not select a plan; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall allow the insurer to select a default plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Penalties for Employer and Insurer.</heading>
    <text>A parent or the Administration may take civil action against an employer or insurer who fails to comply with the provisions of the NMSN without good cause.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|20|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An obligated parent shall have one opportunity to contest the withholding of earnings for the cost of health care coverage for a child enrolled in the plan pursuant to an NMSN, based on a mistake of fact, by requesting an investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for an investigation pursuant to <cite path="07|07|20|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing on a form provided by the Administration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Administration not later than 15 days after:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Receiving the notification as specified in <cite path="|07|07|20|.04|C.">Regulation .04C of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The first deduction for the health insurance premium is made from the employee's earnings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The only issues that may be contested are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The identity of the obligated parent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That there is no underlying child support order requiring the parent to provide medical support for the child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the amount of the withholding exceeds the limits of the Federal Consumer Credit Protection Act; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That the child for whom health insurance coverage is sought is emancipated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Within 15 days of receiving a timely request for an investigation, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct an investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify the obligated parent in writing of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Results of the investigation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Right to appeal the Administration's decision to the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) as provided in <cite path="|07|07|20|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Enrollment of an employee's child may not be stayed or terminated until the employer receives written notice from the Administration that the contest is resolved in the employee's favor.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Appeal to the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The obligated parent may appeal to the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) the results of the Administration's investigation based on a mistake of fact.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The only issues that may be appealed to OAH are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The identity of the obligated parent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That there is no underlying court order requiring the employee to provide medical support for the child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the amount of the withholding exceeds the limits of the Federal Consumer Credit Protection Act; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That the child for whom health insurance coverage is sought is emancipated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The appeal to OAH is effective only if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submitted in writing on a form provided by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed by the obligated parent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Received by OAH within 15 days after receiving the written results of the investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Accompanied by a copy of the results of the Administration's investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Accompanied by payment of any fee required by OAH.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>OAH shall conduct the hearing and inform the obligated parent and the Administration of the hearing results in accordance with <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Enrollment of an employee's child may not be stayed or terminated until the employer receives written notice from the Administration that the appeal has been resolved in the employee's favor.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Terminating an NMSN.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall send a notice to the employer to terminate the NMSN within 15 days of obtaining documentation that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The court order requiring medical support was terminated by the court;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The order for medical support is no longer in effect;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The child has died or reached the age of emancipation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The results of an investigation conducted pursuant to <cite path="|07|07|20|.09">regulation .09 of this chapter</cite> warrant termination of the NMSN; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A decision from the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) in an appeal filed by the parent was resolved in favor of the parent.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">10-114</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-102">12-102</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-102">12-102</cite>.3; Health-General Article, §19-706; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-405">Insurance Article, §15-405</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>(Agency Note: Federal Regulatory References: 29 CFR Part 2590 and 45 CFR §303.32); 42 U.S.C. §652(f)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2003-08-04">Effective date: August 4, 2003 (30:15 Md. R. 991)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|07|07|20|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, C amended effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|07|07|20|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|07|07|20|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite>, B amended effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-09"><cite path="|07|07|20|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective August 9, 2010 (37:16 Md. R. 1060)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|07|07|20|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
