<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>22</num>
  <heading>Affidavit of Support</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the procedures of the Administration to establish a child support obligation by means of an affidavit of support. The chapter also describes the process for rescinding an executed affidavit of support.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Child support order" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-1">Family Law Article, §10-1</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Date of execution" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date that all parties and the Administration have signed the affidavit of support form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a party or the Administration signs the affidavit of support on a date that is different from the date the other party or the Administration has signed, then the latest of the dates.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Executed affidavit of support" means an affidavit of support form that all parties and the Administration have signed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"On the record" means a document attached to the affidavit of support which delineates the reasons for deviating from child support guidelines pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl">Family Law Article, Title 12, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Party" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-1">Family Law Article, §10-1</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Support conference" means a conference conducted by the Administration to provide an opportunity to the parties to voluntarily agree to the provisions of a support obligation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|22|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Affidavit of Support to Establish a Support Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may initiate action to establish a child support obligation pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl">Family Law Article, Title 10, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A party is receiving child support services under Title IV, Part D, of the Social Security Act;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Paternity of the child has been established;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A support conference, as specified in <cite path="07|07|22|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, has been conducted; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The support conference resulted in an agreement by the parties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Support Conference. Before the execution of an affidavit of support, the Administration shall provide notice to the parties to attend the support conference. The notice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Specify the date, time, and location of the support conference;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advise the parties of the purpose of the support conference;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Specify the documentation the parties are required to provide; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be provided to the parties at least 30 days before the date on which the support conference will be held.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Support Obligation Amount.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall compute the child support obligation pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl">Family Law Article, Title 12, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration may consider the factors stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-202">Family Law Article, §12-202, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to determine if application of the guidelines would be unjust or inappropriate in a particular case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon determining that application of the guidelines is unjust or inappropriate in a particular case, the Administration shall make a written finding on the record. The Administration's finding shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The amount of child support that would have been required under the guidelines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>How the affidavit of support varies from the guidelines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>How the finding serves the best interest of the child; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In cases in which items of value are conveyed instead of a portion of the support presumed under the guidelines, the estimated value of the items conveyed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Executing an Affidavit of Support.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An affidavit of support shall be on a standardized form developed by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The completed affidavit of support form shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Those statements provided for in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-1">Family Law Article, §10-1</cite>A-02(c), Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any other information considered appropriate by the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Before completing an affidavit of support form, the Administration shall inform the parties, orally and in writing, of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The legal consequences of executing the affidavit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The right to seek legal counsel.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall provide each party with a copy of the executed affidavit of support.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Following the 60-day rescission period specified in <cite path="|07|07|22|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>, the Administration shall file the affidavit of support with the clerk of a circuit court within 30 days following the recission period for the court's approval.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Rescinding an Affidavit of Support.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A party may rescind the affidavit of support within 60 days after execution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To be effective, the request for rescission shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing, on a standardized form developed by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signed and dated before a notary public; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Received by the Administration within 60 days from the date of execution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When an affidavit of support is properly rescinded:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The obligation for ongoing support terminates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any arrears accrued after the affidavit of support was executed remain owed to the obligee until paid; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any support amount paid and disbursed to the custodial parent after the affidavit of support was executed, is owed to the custodial parent and is not subject to a refund to the noncustodial parent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Enforcement of an Affidavit of Support.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall enforce the provisions of the affidavit of support and collect the support obligation, including arrearages, from the date of execution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The affidavit of support shall be regarded in the same manner as a child support order issued by a court, with all the same enforcement remedies, including contempt of court, that are available to a support order issued by a tribunal.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Modification of Support Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-1">Family Law Article, §10-1</cite>A-03, Annotated Code of Maryland, if any party to the affidavit of support presents evidence to the Administration of a material change in circumstances since entry of the last child support order, the parties may execute a subsequent affidavit of support.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If there is a preexisting child support order, the subsequently executed affidavit of support supersedes the order until overruled by a tribunal.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, Title 10, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-11-03">Effective date: November 3, 2008 (35:22 Md. R. 1956)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
