<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>23</num>
  <heading>Child Support Payment Incentive Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish the procedures for administering the Child Support Payment Incentive Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this Program is to encourage low income noncustodial parents to make consistent payments of child support in exchange for a reduction of permanently assigned State owed arrears.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Noncustodial parent's household" means the noncustodial parent, the children living in the noncustodial parent's current household, and the children for whom the noncustodial parent is required to pay child support under a support order that is the subject of the application to the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the Child Support Payment Incentive Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be considered for participation in the Program, the noncustodial parent shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit to the Administration a completed application on a form provided by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide all information specified in the application form; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include documentation as required by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall provide a written decision to the noncustodial parent not later than 60 days after the receipt of the application.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Eligibility Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall be the noncustodial parent associated with a Maryland court order, for which there has been an assignment of support rights pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|5-312">Human Services Article, §5-312(b)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The noncustodial parent's gross income shall be less than 225 percent of the federal poverty level, as defined by the United States Department of Health and Human Services, for the noncustodial parent's household size as defined in <cite path="|07|07|23|.02|B.|(1)">Regulation .02B(1) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|07|23|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of the Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 60 days of receiving a complete application, the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Take into consideration:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The noncustodial parent's current ability to pay;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether the reduction of arrearages will encourage the noncustodial parent's economic stability; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whether the agreement serves the best interests of a child for whom the noncustodial parent is required to support;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make a determination to accept or deny the application for participation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide written notice to the noncustodial parent regarding the Administration's decision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If participation in the Program is denied, provide information regarding:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The noncustodial parent's right to appeal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The manner in which the appeal may be made pursuant to <cite path="|07|07|23|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Administration determines that the noncustodial parent's situation meets any one of the criteria described in <cite path="07|07|23|.05|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Administration may presume that it is in the best interest of the State to authorize a noncustodial parent to participate in the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an unemployed noncustodial parent applies to participate in the Program, the Administration shall give the noncustodial parent a list of referrals to programs that prepare individuals for entry into the workforce.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Appeal Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If participation to the Program is denied, the Administration shall provide information to the noncustodial parent regarding a right to appeal the decision to the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall provide an appeal form along with the notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A noncustodial parent who is appealing the Administration's decision shall file the appeal with OAH not later than 30 days from the date of the Administration's decision notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>OAH shall conduct an appeal in accordance with <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Program Agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the noncustodial parent is authorized to participate in the Program, the Administration shall enter into an agreement with the participating noncustodial parent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The agreement shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An arrearage reduction schedule as described in <cite path="|07|07|23|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement that all enforcement actions shall be suspended, unless the suspension would be in conflict with federal law, such as Passport Denial and federal tax intercept; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The requirement that any earnings withholding in place shall continue in an amount consistent with the agreement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Arrearage Reduction Schedule.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the noncustodial parent makes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>12 months of consecutive court ordered payments, the arrearages shall be reduced by 50 percent of the amount of arrearages owed at the time of the agreement or the balance due at the end of the 12-month period, whichever is less; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>24 months of consecutive court ordered payments, the remaining arrearages from the original agreement shall be reduced to zero.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall distribute any child support arrearages received under this regulation in accordance with federal law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Termination from the Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the noncustodial parent fails to make two consecutive monthly support obligation payments, the noncustodial parent shall be terminated from the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the noncustodial parent is terminated from the Program more than two times, the noncustodial parent is ineligible for future participation in the Program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Reapplication into the Program.</heading>
    <text>If the noncustodial parent is terminated from the Program, as described in <cite path="|07|07|23|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>, and requests reapplication into the Program, the noncustodial parent may reapply and enter into a new agreement with the understanding that the time period starts from the time the noncustodial parent enters into the new agreement.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-112">10-112</cite>.1 and 10-114, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-09">Effective date: March 9, 2009 (36:5 Md. R. 421)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
