<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>24</num>
  <heading>Incarcerated Obligor</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall establish a procedure by which an obligee may challenge the Administration’s intent to adjust the payment record of an obligor who has been sentenced to a period of incarceration of 18 months or more. The dministration may only make such an adjustment under this regulation with respect to a support order issued or modified after October 1, 2012.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Applicability Criteria for Payment Record Adjustment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the time of sentencing is expected to be imprisoned for 18 consecutive months or more:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Including time served; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Excluding any portion of the sentence that is suspended;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Has no resources from which to pay support;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Is not on work release; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Did not commit the crime with the intent of being incarcerated or otherwise becoming impoverished.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of the Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration is providing services under Title IV-D of the Social Security Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may adjust an eligible obligor’s payment account after an obligor is sentenced to at least 18 consecutive months, without filing a motion with the court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send written notice of the proposed action to the obligee, prior to adjusting the obligor’s payment account, that indicates that the obligee may object to the proposed action.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Request for Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 20 days of the date of the notice, an obligee may object to the proposed action by requesting that the Administration conduct an investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An obligee may request an investigation only on a claim that the obligor:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Was sentenced prior to October 1, 2012;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Was sentenced to less than 18 consecutive months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Had resources from which to pay support;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Was on work release; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Committed the crime with the intent of becoming incarcerated or otherwise impoverished.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An obligee shall submit to the Administration any documents relevant to the claim.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Administration’s Response to Investigation Request.</heading>
    <text>Upon receipt of a timely request for an investigation, the Administration shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Conduct an investigation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Review any documents submitted by the obligee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prepare a written summary of the investigation, including any pending action; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Forward the investigation summary to the obligee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Request for Appeal.</heading>
    <text>In the event the obligee disagrees with the action of the Administration, the obligee may file their objection with the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-114">10-114</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|12-104">12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15">Effective date: April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
