<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>General Approval of State and Local Agency Programs Which Result in Development of Local Significance on Private Lands or Lands Owned by Local Jurisdictions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definition.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, “minor development” has the meaning stated in <cite path="27.02.01.01">COMAR 27.02.01.01</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Rather than obtaining certification for an individual project or action, as provided in <cite path="|27.02.02">COMAR 27.02.02</cite>, a State or local agency may seek a general approval from the Commission for a program or class of activities that will result in development of local significance in the Critical Area, such as forest management plans and soil conservation and water quality plans.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Agencies wishing to apply for general approval shall submit the following information to the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A description of the program or class of activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An assessment of the extent to which development resulting from the program or class of activities will be consistent with the criteria described in <cite path="|27.01">COMAR 27.01</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A proposed process by which the program or class of activities could be so conducted as to conform with the requirements of <cite path="|27.01">COMAR 27.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall seek comments from affected local jurisdictions in the Critical Area on any proposed general approval for State or local agency programs or activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may approve requests for general approval upon considering the comments of the affected local jurisdictions and after finding that the programs or activities conform with the requirements of <cite path="|27.01">COMAR 27.01</cite> and will not cause any significant adverse effects on the growth allocation of a local jurisdiction as described in <cite path="27.01.02.06">COMAR 27.01.02.06</cite>. In approving these requests, the Commission may condition, or request modifications to, the program or class of activities. The Commission may also establish a termination date for any general approval and specify the conditions by which an agency shall be required to seek renewal of a general approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission may revoke a general approval with 90 days notice to the affected State or local agency, if the Commission finds that the agency has failed to follow the process described in §B(3), above.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Appeal of the Commission's decision may be made in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="|27.02.08">COMAR 27.02.08</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-1814">Natural Resources Article, §8-1814, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-06-11">Effective date: June 11, 1988 (15:7 Md. R. 852)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container"><cite path="|14.19.03">COMAR 14.19.03</cite> recodified to <cite path="|27.02.03">COMAR 27.02.03</cite> in August, 1992</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|14.19.03">COMAR 14.19.03</cite> recodified to <cite path="|27.02.03">COMAR 27.02.03</cite> in August, 1992</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-06" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|27|02|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective September 6, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 694)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-20"><cite path="|27|02|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> recodified to be Regulation .02 effective January 20, 2025 (52:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-20"><cite path="|27|02|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted effective January 20, 2025 (52:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
