<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Motor Fuel License and Tax</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applications for licenses shall be on forms provided by the Comptroller and shall indicate the type and class of license sought, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dealer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Class "A",</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Class "B",</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Class "C",</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Class "D",</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Class "G-Temporary";</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Special Fuel Seller;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Special Fuel User;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Distributor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Turbine Fuel Seller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the licensee discontinues business, the license shall be returned to the Comptroller for cancellation. Unless a bond rider has been accepted by the Comptroller, licensees shall apply for a new license and furnish a new bond under the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When there has been a change in the name of the company even though the ownership remains the same;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the business of an individual or a partnership is taken over and continued by a corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the licensee is a corporation and surrenders its charter and the business is continued by an individual, a partnership, or any other legal entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When an individual is licensed as a dealer, user, or seller, dies, and the business is continued by another person or entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>When an individually owned business is taken over and continued by a partnership;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>When a business owned by a partnership is taken over and continued by an individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>When a business which is owned by a partnership is taken over and continued by an individual, another partnership, or corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>When any other situation arises in which a business that is owned by one type of legal entity is taken over and continued by a different legal entity; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>When there is a change in the Federal Identification Number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensed special fuel users making a sale of special fuel that is exempt from the motor fuel tax shall be reclassified and licensed as a special fuel seller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Change of Class of Dealer License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a licensed dealer fails to meet the qualifications required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-319">Tax-General Article, §9-319, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for the specific class of license held, the dealer shall immediately notify the Comptroller.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dealer shall provide the Comptroller any additional information requested by the Comptroller.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Comptroller may then issue to the dealer any alternative license to which the dealer may be entitled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Sales to Unlicensed Seller or User.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Sales of motor fuel shall be made with the motor fuel tax, as applicable, included.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Special fuel:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When sold and delivered into a storage tank permanently and solely connected to a heating plant, commercial stationary apparatus, stationary vapor burning apparatus (including propane tanks not connected to the vehicle propulsion system on recreational type vehicles), or watercraft,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When sold to the holder of a valid exemption certificate, provided the certificate exempts that particular type of special fuel; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When sold to agencies and instrumentalities of the United States Government;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Aviation turbine fuel when sold to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Carriers and operators as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-303">Tax-General Article, §9-303(c)(1) </cite>and (2), Annotated Code of Maryland,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The State of Maryland,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Local governments of this State,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Agencies and instrumentalities of the United States Government, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Foreign governments.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Motor Fuel Tax Report.</heading>
    <text>All dealers, special fuel users, special fuel sellers, and turbine fuel sellers shall provide the name and address of the person or persons responsible for preparing the applicable tax report. This person shall provide all information requested in the following areas:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Stock reports;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>EDP systems;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Marketing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Security;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Internal audit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Motor fuel taxes; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Aviation fuel taxes.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Security Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All securities shall be in an amount of an even $1,000.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Cash offered as security shall be converted by the offeror into a banking instrument as specified by and in the manner determined by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Dealers that are licensed special fuel sellers, special fuel users, or turbine fuel sellers are required to post only one security, the amount of which will be determined by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller may increase the amount of the security requirement on 30 days' notice.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Filing—Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="03|03|01|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, fuel tax returns shall be filed monthly with appropriate remittance on forms prescribed by the Comptroller. If no sales or operations were conducted in any particular reporting period, required returns shall be filed, stating this fact.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Annual Filing Option.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A special fuel user engaged in the business of agriculture may request approval to file an annual fuel tax return.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To qualify for the annual filing option, a special fuel user shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be engaged in the business of agriculture;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have an average taxable use of 2,000 gallons or less; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submit a written request and receive written approval from the Comptroller, before filing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special Fuel Sellers and Turbine Fuel Sellers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Special fuel sellers and turbine fuel sellers shall maintain records of all special fuels acquired, sold, or used, both taxable and nontaxable. Records shall include the total miles the seller's own vehicles were operated and all records shall be available at the time of the audit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All sales or use of special fuels made from retail type dispensers at retail service stations shall be made with tax included (kerosene may be excluded provided the seller is the holder of a valid Exemption Certificate).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Special fuel users shall maintain records of all special fuels acquired and used, both taxable and nontaxable, and records of the miles traveled by each special fuel powered vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The inability of the Motor Fuel Tax Bureau to trace motor fuel from seller to purchaser as a result of inadequate reporting or record keeping may result in the assessment of tax and interest against either the supplier or the purchaser.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Exemption certificate holders shall file annually on forms prescribed by the Comptroller, at renewal time, all purchases of special fuel by type of product as well as each supplier thereof. (Licensed dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers are excluded.)</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Licensed distributors shall report receipts, sales, and use of all motor fuels on forms provided by the Comptroller as prescribed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Sales—Exchanges—Transfers—Exports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Arrangements for the transfer of ownership of motor fuel by dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, turbine fuel sellers, and distributors, for future delivery, whether called sales, loans, exchanges, or otherwise, shall be recognized only when such arrangements are reflected in sales agreements or contracts. They shall be reported as "sales" only when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The "fuels" sold move physically from the possession of the vendor to that of the vendee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The "fuels" sold remain in the storage of the vendor, the full quantity being immediately available to the vendee for disposition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When a sales agreement or contract is made on temperature corrected gallons, the invoices or delivery ticket required for audit purposes shall show the volumetric gallonage and the temperature adjusted gallonage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sales of motor fuel for exportation, under such circumstances that title passes to the purchaser in Maryland, may be sold tax exempt for immediate exportation under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To purchasers of gasoline possessing a valid Class A or D license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To purchasers of gasoline possessing a valid Class C license and a letter of special permission issued by the Motor Fuel Tax Bureau for the product to be acquired and exported;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To purchasers of special fuels possessing a currently valid exemption certificate for type of special fuel being acquired;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The transportation of motor fuel shall be accomplished by vehicles owned and operated by a petroleum transporter registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 10, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Documentation (a bill of lading, meter ticket, or loading ticket) shall accompany each vehicle transporting motor fuel and shall conform to <cite path="03.03.03.05">COMAR 03.03.03.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Whenever diesel fuel is modified or created by blending kerosene and fuel oil, metered loading tickets shall be attached to sales invoices, bills of lading, or delivery tickets showing the quantity of each product blended. These documents shall be available at the time of the audit or inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers importing motor fuel into the State shall maintain on file a shipping and receiving document indicating specifications of the product received.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Records, receiving documents, delivery tickets, sales invoices, and bills of lading shall be maintained for audit purposes by all dealers that blend casinghead or natural gasoline, benzene, naphtha, gas, oil, kerosene, heating oil, butane, alcohol, or any combination of these or other items into a motor fuel within the State, or create motor fuel within the State. These records shall indicate the name and address of each customer to whom sales have been made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>All vehicles used to make metered sales of motor fuel shall utilize a meter calibrated to meet the accuracy requirements set forth in the current edition of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Handbook 44, as specified by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|11-203">Agriculture Article, §11-203(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Invoices Used as Proof of Payment of the Tax.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except for retail service station invoices, motor fuel invoices shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contain the amount of Maryland motor fuel tax charged; or if the tax is not charged, the statement "Maryland motor fuel tax is not included";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the date of delivery;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contain the name and address of purchaser;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Contain the name and address of seller pre-printed on the invoice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Contain the number of gallons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be serially or sequentially numbered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Contain the trade name and type of fuel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Retail service station invoices shall include the statement "The seller certifies that the motor fuel tax will be paid as required by law."</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Gains—Losses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Stock gains and losses shall be reported on forms and in accordance with instructions provided by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Losses or gains shall be established upon products metered or physically inventoried as received in the State. Losses which occur in inventory after the receipt shall be supported by gauger's reports or other acceptable documentation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Transportation gains or losses incurred enroute for delivery into the State shall be recorded for audit purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Losses of motor fuel resulting from theft, faulty equipment, or any other cause except temperature correction shall be reported to the Comptroller upon discovery or by the first business day thereafter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Allowable losses incurred in the storage of motor fuel shall be prorated on the percentage of tax exempt sales to total sales. Direct shipments from supplier to customer are not allowed in the proration calculation. Direct shipments shall be deducted from total sales and from either taxable or nontaxable sales, as applicable.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Volumetric and Temperature Adjusted Gallons.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licensees Reporting on a Temperature Adjusted Basis.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inventory. If inventory is reported on a temperature adjusted basis ("net"), all receipts shall be reported on that basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sales. If inventories and receipts are reported on a "net" basis (temperature adjusted), and any sales are made on a "gross" (not temperature adjusted) basis, the sales shall be documented and the adjustments resulting therefrom reported on the appropriate form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensees Reporting on a Gross (Not Temperature Adjusted) Basis.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inventory. If inventory is reported on a "gross" (not temperature adjusted) basis, all receipts shall be reported on that basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sales. If inventories and receipts are reported on a "gross" (not temperature adjusted) basis, and any sales are made on a "net" (temperature adjusted) basis, the sales shall be documented and the adjustments reported on the appropriate form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Volumetric gallon of motor fuel" means the United States gallon of 231 cubic inches as measured by volume.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>"Temperature corrected gallon of motor fuel" means a volumetric gallon of 231 cubic inches adjusted to the measurement of a gallon at 60?F as determined by API/ASTM-IP Petroleum Measurement Table, "Table 6B".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Natural Gas. In order to determine the quantity of liquid or compressed natural gas consumed, the following formulas will be used:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Liquefied natural gas: 100 cubic feet at <cite path="|14.73">14.73</cite> psi and 60?F shall be considered as 1 gallon of liquid motor fuel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Compressed natural gas: 1 cubic foot multiplied by .00831 shall be considered as 1 gallon of liquid motor fuel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Liquid Propane Gas. To determine the quantity of liquid propane gas consumed, the following formula will be used:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If product is gauged in decitherms, divide by 9.1 to convert to gallons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If product is gauged in pounds, divide by 4.24 to convert to gallons (To convert decitherms to pounds, multiply by .465).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Special Fuel Dispensers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Retail type special fuel dispensers (pumps) may have a security seal affixed by a State motor fuel agent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Whenever a retail type dispenser is used to dispense special fuel and the computer metering device of the dispenser is removed, replaced, or repaired, the meter readings and serial numbers of both the retail dispenser and metering device shall be reported to the Comptroller within 30 days, and a copy of the service or repair order shall be maintained on the premises and shall indicate date of service, location, type of service performed, serial number, and meter readings of both the defective device and the replacement device, if a replacement is made.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Contaminated Product.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Contaminated products (interface, interface mix, transmix, and products failing to meet State specifications) may not be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Imported, exported, or moved within the State without the written approval of the Comptroller;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Commingled and inventoried in any gasoline or special fuel storage within the State without written approval of the Comptroller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A statement signed by the appropriate official confirming proper disposal of product shall be filed with supporting records before credit for contaminated product can be considered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensees may not receive credit for sludge removed from storage tanks until proof has been established by a representative of the Comptroller that contaminated products were actually inventoried.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Motor Fuel Consumed by Licensed Dealers.</heading>
    <text>Licensed dealers under normal report procedures may take credit for motor fuel taxes on gallonage for which a refund would be allowed under these regulations, provided that adequate records are available at the time of the audit to support the refund credits.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Inventory.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers shall have at their bulk plants, marine terminals, and tank farms, calibration charts for each tank containing motor fuel. These charts shall show the tank number, capacity, dimensions, and gallons corresponding to measurements in feet, inches, and fractions that indicate the amount of fuel in the tank or tanks.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers shall have gauge sticks, tapes, or electronic measurement devices. The devices shall correspond to the calibration charts for each tank and shall be capable of determining the gallonage contained in each tank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Inventory Records.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers shall keep a monthly physical inventory record which shall show the quantity of each product on hand at the close of each month's business which shall be the result of actual measurements taken physically on that date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At locations where multiple ownership of inventories are maintained, segregated or commingled, whether called throughput, terminal, or other identification, a reconciliation of ownership of each product shall be presented to each owner by the entity having control of the inventory. The physical inventory reconciliation schedule shall be reflective of the same date and time for all parties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Tax liability accrues on special fuel upon delivery to a retail service station unless that retail service station recipient is the holder of a valid exemption certificate for that specific type of fuel. Inventories of motor fuel that are the property of the supplier, but in the care of a service station dealer, are taxable upon delivery as are deliveries to supplier operated retail service stations. Kerosene, dyed fuel, and propane at supplier operated service stations are excluded, provided they are not sold for taxable use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers having inventories in their custody for another party, shall report all receipts and disbursements from that inventory as sales to and receipts from participants maintaining multiple ownership of the commingled inventory. The custodian shall report, as his inventory, all products in his care and control.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers, who are participants in commingled inventories, shall obtain authorization from the Comptroller before beginning this activity. The request for permission shall be in writing, indicate the names and addresses of all participants involved, and the terms and duration of the arrangements. Authorization is not required when the commingled inventory results from a sale to a purchaser, the terms of which include the total withdrawal from sellers inventory within 60 days of the date of sale. All other requirements of this chapter are applicable to fuels involved in this type of transaction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Inventories stored at locations operated by persons other than a licensed dealer, special fuel seller, special fuel user, or turbine fuel seller shall be reported by each individual licensee that owns the fuel.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Security of Motor Fuels.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Dealers, special fuel sellers, special fuel users, and turbine fuel sellers shall maintain adequate security programs at all storage locations maintained in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All bulk plants, terminals, and tank farms maintaining storage of motor fuels shall have approved seals on all meters indicating compliance with the requirements of the most current edition of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Handbook 44, as specified by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|11-203">Agriculture Article, §11-203(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Blending and Injection—Reporting.</heading>
    <text>All authorized dealers, special fuel sellers, and turbine fuel sellers are required to report separately, on appropriate schedules, commingled, casinghead or natural gasoline, benzene, naphtha, heating oil, alcohol, additives, or any other component, or any combination of them, that is blended into a refined motor fuel after the fuel has been received in this State. The schedule shall indicate the percentages and gallonages of the various materials blended.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Exemption Certificates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exemption certificates are issued to identify purchasers authorized to acquire tax exempt special fuel from a licensed special fuel seller, or turbine fuel seller. They are issued and applicable only for specific types of fuel and valid only for the period indicated on the certificate. Suppliers are responsible for the tax on all sales made to holders of expired or otherwise invalid exemption certificates and for the tax on all sales to purchasers not in possession of a valid exemption certificate, except as provided for in <cite path="|03|03|01|.02|B.|(1)">Regulation .02B(1) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The type of special fuel to be exempt from the tax will be determined by the certificate number as designated on schedules published by the Comptroller and available to licensed suppliers upon request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the exemption certificate holder discontinues business, the exemption certificate shall be returned to the Comptroller for cancellation. Exemption certificates are non-transferable and holders are expected to apply for and secure a new certificate under the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When there has been a change in the name of the company or entity even though the ownership remains the same;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the business of an individual or a partnership is taken over and continued by a corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the licensee is a corporation and surrenders its charter and the business is continued by an individual, a partnership, or any other legal person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When an individual licensed as a dealer, user, or seller, dies, and the business is continued by another person or entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>When an individually owned business is taken over and continued by a partnership;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>When a business owned by a partnership is taken over and continued by an individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>When a business which is owned by an individual, partnership, or corporation is taken over and continued by a different individual, partnership, or corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>When any other situation arises in which a business that is owned by one type of legal entity is taken over and continued by a different legal entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>When there is a change in the Federal Identification Number; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>When the use of a previously exempted product for which the exemption was granted is changed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An application for an exemption certificate shall be on forms provided by the Comptroller and shall indicate the type of special fuel for which an exemption is sought.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An exemption certificate for kerosene may be issued to sellers of kerosene at retail if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Kerosene is the only special fuel (other than propane) offered for sale and never sold for taxable use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All other taxable special fuels (other than propane) offered for sale are purchased tax paid from the supplier; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The seller is a licensed special fuel seller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An exemption certificate for propane may be issued to sellers of propane at retail if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Propane is the only special fuel (other than kerosene) offered for sale and never sold for taxable use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All other taxable special fuels (other than kerosene) offered for sale are purchased tax paid from the supplier; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The seller is a licensed special fuel seller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Racing Fuel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Gasoline having an anti-knock index (R + M)/2 of greater than 98 may be considered racing fuel if the manufacturer's specifications have been filed with and approved annually by the Field Enforcement Bureau.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Racing fuel may not be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Considered a motor fuel as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-101">Tax-General Article, §9-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Blended with any other gasoline and offered for sale; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Used as a fuel, either straight or blended, in a motor vehicle operated on a highway.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purpose of the administration of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-319">Tax-General Article, §9-319, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to storage capacity requirements:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Control" means having absolute authority and responsibility for all fuels placed into and removed from a given tank or tanks. If "control" is claimed by a person leasing or renting a tank or tanks owned by another person, the lease or rental arrangement shall be for a period of at least 3 years beyond the date of the filing of the application for a dealer's license by the person claiming "control".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Maintaining" means same as "control".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Storage capacity" for a Class A licensee means a minimum of 1,000,000 gallons of gasoline and 1,000,000 gallons of special fuel.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Warehousing—Terminalling—Storing for Others.</heading>
    <text>Unlicensed entities that provide motor fuel storage facilities or related services, or both, shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Obtain written permission from the Comptroller before storing motor fuel or providing related services;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Report monthly on forms provided by the Comptroller; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provide a reconciliation of ownership of each product, monthly, to each owner maintaining an inventory at that facility.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Penalties and Interest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a person fails to pay a tax when due, the Comptroller may assess a penalty in an amount not to exceed 10 percent of the tax.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a person fails to file a return when due, the Comptroller may assess a penalty in an amount not to exceed $25.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Interest.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a person fails to file a return when due, interest shall be assessed as prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg">Tax-General Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. Interest will not be assessed, however, unless the computed interest for a return exceeds $2.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interest on unpaid tax assessments shall be assessed as prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg">Tax-General Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, but the $2 minimum does not apply.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Appeals—Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall schedule a hearing before denial of an application for a motor fuel tax license or an exemption certificate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may appeal the Comptroller's decision canceling a motor fuel tax license or an exemption certificate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The hearing process is governed by <cite path="03.01.01.05">COMAR 03.01.01.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|2-103">Tax-General Article, §2-103, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1973-04-01">Effective date: April 1, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Regulations <cite path="|03|03|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|03|03|01|.04">.04</cite>; .07C, E, F; .08C, D; .09A, D, F; .12A, C; .13C;</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22">.14C; .15A; .17 amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2255)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Regulations .02, .07F, and .13C amended, and .03G adopted</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-10-08">effective October 8, 1984 (11:20 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.07|F.">Regulation .07F</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|01|.18">Regulation .18</cite> adopted effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-10-08">2255); repealed effective October 8, 1984 (11:20 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26">Chapter repealed effective August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1698)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|03|03|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|03|03|01|.20">.20</cite> adopted effective August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1698)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container"><cite path="|03|03|01|.21">Regulation .21</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective May 21,</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">1987 (14:12 Md. R. 1348); emergency status expired August 30, 1987</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">(Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-23" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 23, 1989 (16:1 Md. R. 66)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|03|03|01|.20">Regulation .20</cite> repealed effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1987)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Regulations .01, .02, .04—.06, and .17 amended, and new Regulation .21</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-09-28">adopted effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1703)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.11|B.">Regulation .11B</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .13C amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .16E, F amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16"><cite path="|03|03|01|.17|A.">Regulation .17A</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19); May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.18|C.">Regulation .18C</cite> adopted effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.20|A.">Regulation .20A</cite> amended effective May 8, 1995 (22:9 Md. R. 644); January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R.19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|03|03|01|.21">Regulation .21</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
