<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Petroleum Transporters</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Loading Tickets and Manifests.</heading>
    <text>Vehicles and vessels transporting petroleum products shall carry a loading ticket or manifest containing the following information:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Name of petroleum transporter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Date and time loaded;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Volumetric gallons of each grade of product loaded;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Name of company operating facility where loaded;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Name of shipper (title holder of product after loading);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Name and address of ultimate consignee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Any deviation from original manifest or loading ticket shall be indicated thereon or by an additional ticket, all of which must show the names and addresses of all parties involved in the transaction;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A serial numbering sequence; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The certified octane rating as determined under the Federal Petroleum Marketing Practices Act for each grade of gasoline.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Marking of Compartments.</heading>
    <text>Each pot or compartment of each vehicle shall be labeled to indicate the certified gallonage capacity, based on a volumetric gallon equaling 231 cubic inches of liquid, on each side of the pot or compartment in a place and manner that shall be readily discernible at a distance of 50 feet when the vehicle is not in motion. The gallonage capacity of each pot or compartment need not be labeled if the vehicle bears an identification plate affixed by the manufacturer indicating the certified gallonage capacity by pot or compartment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Loading Tickets or Manifests Required for Commingled Products.</heading>
    <text>A loading ticket or manifest as described in <cite path="|03|03|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> is required to transport commingled products as defined in <cite path="03.03.05.15">COMAR 03.03.05.15</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Loading Tickets or Manifests for Home Heating Oil and Certain Other Deliveries.</heading>
    <text>Petroleum transporters making deliveries of fuel oil or kerosene for use as a heating fuel only by the purchasers, and when the gallons to be delivered are unknown until the actual delivery, shall have in their possession:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A loading ticket, manifest, or other documentation containing all information required by Regulation .05A—E of this chapter; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Delivery tickets for each drop made indicating date, product, volume, name, and address for each individual delivery point.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Transporters of Waste Oil.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Transporters of motor fuel from tank cleaning or spill clean-up operations shall be considered petroleum transporters regardless of whether the products are contaminated, commingled, or clean.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Transporters of used crankcase motor oils and solvents may not be considered petroleum transporters provided that no other motor fuel is being simultaneously transported.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Inspection of Petroleum Transporters.</heading>
    <text>Any designated agent of the Field Enforcement Bureau of the Comptroller of the Treasury, or any police officer as defined in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-147">Transportation Article, §11-147, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may examine and inspect a vehicle, its manifest, its carried product, and other information in order to determine compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 10, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and related regulations.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Reporting Fuel Movements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A registered petroleum transporter who is also a common or contract carrier shall report all intrastate and interstate movements of motor fuel monthly in a format prescribed by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registered petroleum transporter who is not a common or contract carrier shall report movements of motor fuel upon the request of and on forms provided by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Display of Owner's Name.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The name required for display on the conveyance shall be the name of the petroleum transporter as registered under the federal employers' identification number.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The name may be an individual's name when it is a sole proprietorship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A trade name, division name, or logo may be displayed in addition to, but not instead of, the registered petroleum transporter's name.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Hazardous Material Placarding or Labeling.</heading>
    <text>Vehicles transporting motor vehicle fuel or aviation fuel in one or more cargo tanks having a combined capacity exceeding 1,000 pounds (approximately 140 U.S. gallons), shall display on all 4 sides of the vehicle, hazardous materials placards as prescribed by the United States Department of Transportation.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Color and Symbol Coding of Vehicle Discharge Valves.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To facilitate the clean transfer of motor fuel from a distribution point to a purchaser, discharge valves of vehicles used in transporting motor fuel shall be color coded. Color coding shall conform to the American Petroleum Institute (API) recommended system which is found at <cite path="03.03.05.14">COMAR 03.03.05.14</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Whenever a petroleum transport vehicle loads product at a bulk plant, terminal, or distribution point, the operator of the vehicle shall display a tag, an identification card, or other acceptable product identification marker on each discharge valve or connection on the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The tag, identification card, or acceptable product identification marker shall be of the proper color code, indicating what product is in the line after loading the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The color of the tag, identification card, or acceptable product identification marker shall match the color coding of equipment at the loading facility for each grade of motor fuel loaded.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Care should be exercised at out-of-State loading facilities as their color coding systems may differ from Maryland's.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The petroleum transporter should ensure that each vehicle is furnished with sufficient tags, identification cards, or acceptable product identification markers to be in compliance with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Color coded tags, identification cards, or acceptable product identification markers may not be removed from a discharge valve or connection until a different product is loaded and after thorough draining or when replacement is necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Deliveries of motor fuel may not be made to any facility not in compliance with the color coding requirements of <cite path="03.03.05.14">COMAR 03.03.05.14</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The requirements of this regulation are not applicable to the storage or transportation of liquefied petroleum gas (LPG) or liquefied natural gas (LNG).</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Loading of Conveyances.</heading>
    <text>Whenever the operator of a petroleum transporter conveyance is intending to load a different grade or type of motor fuel than was previously contained in a pot, compartment, or hold, the operator shall first ensure complete drainage before loading.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-202">Business Regulation Article, §10-202 </cite>and Title 10, Subtitle 4; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|2-103">Tax-General Article, §2-103</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-30">Effective date: June 30, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1010)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-16">Chapter revised effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2022)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulation .01 adopted effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed and new Regulation .02 adopted effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22">Regulations .05J, K and .11 adopted effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2256)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.05|K.">Regulation .05K</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20">Regulations .05, .07, and .08 amended effective August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1987)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963);</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20">August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1987)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|03|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed and new Regulation .11 adopted effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07">Regulations <cite path="|03|03|03|.12">.12</cite>—<cite path="|03|03|03|.14">.14</cite> adopted effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20"><cite path="|03|03|03|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1987)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20"><cite path="|03|03|03|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1987)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .10 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .15 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
