<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Motor Carrier Tax</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, unless otherwise specified, "IFTA" means the International Fuel Tax Agreement.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>International Fuel Tax Agreement.</heading>
    <text>The provisions and requirements of the International Fuel Tax Agreement (IFTA) Articles of Agreement, Procedures Manual, and Audit Manual apply to the fuel use, taxation, registration, and reporting requirements of motor carriers licensed under IFTA by Maryland, without reference to any other Maryland statute or regulation under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-205">Tax-General Article, §9-205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|04|.01-2">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-2</num>
    <heading>Registration — Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Motor carriers shall file an IFTA report and fuel use tax schedule of their operations in all IFTA jurisdictions and pay all taxes due all IFTA jurisdictions for each filing period. The report, schedule, and any taxes due shall be postmarked or received by the Comptroller not later than the last day of the next month following the close of the filing period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Filing of Quarterly IFTA Reports and Schedules.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Motor carriers shall file on a quarterly basis for quarters ending the last day of March, June, September, and December.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annual Filing of Quarterly IFTA Reports and Schedules. Motor carriers that operate less than 5,000 miles annually in all IFTA jurisdictions except Maryland may submit a written request to the Comptroller to file the four quarterly reports and schedules once annually by January 31 for the prior year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The motor carrier shall have written permission from the Comptroller to file on the annual basis described in <cite path="03|03|04|.01-2|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, after the Comptroller receives approval from all other affected IFTA jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Reports shall be signed by an officer or authorized representative of the motor carrier, certifying that the IFTA reports and schedules are true and correct.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to file IFTA reports and schedules on time, or to pay taxes when due, may result in the denial of additional identification markers for the current year and the denial of an annual renewal application. The registration and IFTA license of any motor carrier currently delinquent for one or more tax filing periods will be considered revoked, and the Maryland State Police or the Field Enforcement Bureau is authorized to remove all identification markers and copies or originals of IFTA licenses from the vehicles of a motor carrier operating on State highways.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Every motor carrier shall notify this office within 30 days concerning any change of name, address, federal identifying number, or Social Security number.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>When more than one operating division operates vehicles over State highways, a single IFTA report and schedules shall be filed by the parent company covering all operations under one IFTA license.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Credits and Refunds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any credits accrued and applied for fuel purchased in any IFTA jurisdiction shall be supported by invoices as defined in <cite path="03|03|04|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a motor carrier elects to file for refund of the excess credit, the motor carrier may do so under the provisions of §§C and D of this regulation by entering the appropriate refund amount requested on the IFTA report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A motor carrier requesting refund under the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-214">Tax-General Article, §9-214, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall have filed quarterly IFTA tax reports and schedules.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Every motor carrier shall be prepared to present evidence to substantiate a claim for refund of the excess purchases of fuel on which any IFTA jurisdiction motor fuel tax has been paid. Those motor carriers who maintain bulk storage shall have records substantiating inventories and gallons metered for each unit. The evidence shall consist of invoices of the vendor which comply with the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-310">Tax-General Article, §9-310, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and shall show:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For invoices where fuel is delivered into bulk storage of the motor carrier:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Actual date of delivery,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name and address of purchaser,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Preprinted name and address of seller on the invoice,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The amount of motor fuel tax charged,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If tax is not charged, the statement "Maryland (or appropriate other IFTA jurisdiction) Motor Fuel Tax is not included",</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Number of metered gallons purchased, type of fuel, and total cost of fuel, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Serialized invoice number;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For retail service station invoices:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date of purchase,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Seller's name and address/location,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Purchaser's name (in the case of a lessee/lessor agreement, invoices shall be accepted in either name, providing a legal connection can be made to the reporting party),</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Number of gallons and total cost of fuel,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Fuel type, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Company unit number or vehicle license plate number and state.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Credit card invoices containing the purchaser's account number without the purchaser's name shall be accepted, if supporting documentation is provided that confirms the account number of the refund claimant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Fuel credit card invoices, bank credit card invoices, or other purchase receipts will not be acceptable for refund purposes unless they meet all the requirements of §§D(2) and E of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Account receivable invoices and monthly statements will not be acceptable for refund purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Claims accompanied by invoices on which there is evidence of alteration will be investigated. If the investigation proves an invoice has been altered in any respect, the altered invoice will not be honored.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="03.03.02.03">COMAR 03.03.02.03</cite>, carbon copies of invoices may not be accepted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Refund claimants shall maintain an accurate record of gallonage used for highway and non-highway purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>All refund claims submitted shall be prepared on forms supplied by the Comptroller. Supporting schedules shall be complete and all trip records and fuel invoices shall be maintained for audit. Microfilm records of these documents, instead of the original, may be accepted if prior approval is obtained from the Comptroller and retrieval of those microfilm records is available at time of audit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>The refund may not be payable unless tax paid on the number of gallons of motor fuel purchased in all IFTA jurisdictions exceeds tax due on the number of gallons of motor fuel used in all IFTA jurisdictions during the period covered by the refund claim.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Retail Electronic Invoicing System. Electronically generated documents may be considered original invoices if they:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet all the requirements of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have been approved for use by the Comptroller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Surety Bond.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller may require an applicant for an IFTA license to post a surety bond if an examination of the applicant's prior filing history indicates:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant has failed to file a quarterly return;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant has failed to pay required tax; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A financial guarantee is necessary to protect the interest of the State or other IFTA jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall post a bond in an amount equal to the estimated average annual net tax due to IFTA member jurisdictions rounded to the next even $1,000.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Bond amounts may be adjusted at the discretion of the Comptroller to insure compliance with the IFTA requirements.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Every motor carrier required to register and report to the Comptroller shall keep satisfactory records of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The miles traveled in all operations within:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each other jurisdiction; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The fuel purchased within:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each other jurisdiction where the fuel is used in qualified motor vehicles.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Miles traveled, fuel purchased, and fuel use records shall distinguish the operation of vehicles not subject to the IFTA from those vehicles subject to the IFTA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Records maintained on fuel purchases and use shall be identified as to type of fuel used.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Trip Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A motor carrier may obtain a trip permit for an unregistered commercial motor vehicle from either the Field Enforcement Bureau or one of its duly authorized trip permit agents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Registered and unregistered motor carriers may obtain a trip permit for an unregistered commercial motor vehicle, provided that the request for the trip permit includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name, address, federal identification number or Social Security number of the motor carrier; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make, serial number, and state in which the vehicle is licensed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Trip permits are valid for 15 consecutive days beginning and ending on the dates specified on the face of the trip permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Trip permits shall be carried in the cab of the vehicle whenever the vehicle is in the State, and they are not transferable between motor carriers or between vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A trip permit may not be issued to any licensee who is currently suspended or revoked in any IFTA jurisdiction.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|04|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Lease Agreements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A lessor, lessee, independent contractor, or household goods agent shall be licensed, liable for reporting, and liable for payment of fuel use taxes as required by the International Fuel Tax Agreement (IFTA).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A lessor regularly engaged in the business of leasing or renting motor vehicles without drivers, for compensation to licensees or to other lessees, may be deemed to be the licensee. The lessor may be issued a license if an application has been properly filed and approved by the base jurisdiction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the case of a carrier using independent contractors under long-term leases (30 days or more), the lessor and lessee are given the option of designating which party will report and pay fuel use tax. In the absence of a written agreement or contract, or if the document is silent regarding responsibility for reporting and paying fuel use tax, the lessee is responsible for reporting and paying fuel use tax. If the lessee (carrier) through a written agreement or contract assumes responsibility for reporting and paying fuel use taxes, the base jurisdiction for purposes of IFTA is the base jurisdiction of the lessee, regardless of the jurisdiction in which the qualified motor vehicle is registered for vehicle registration purposes by the lessor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In the case of a short-term motor vehicle rental by a lessor regularly engaged in the business of leasing or renting motor vehicles without drivers for compensation to licensees or other lessees of 29 days or less, the lessor shall report and pay the fuel use tax unless the following two conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The lessor has a written rental contract which designates the lessee as the party responsible for reporting and paying the fuel use tax; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lessor has a copy of the lessee's IFTA fuel tax license which is valid for the term of the rental.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In the case of a carrier using independent contractors under short-term/trip leases of 29 days or less, the trip lessor shall report and pay all fuel taxes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Household Goods Carrier.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of a household goods carrier using independent contractors, agents, or service representatives, under intermittent leases, the party liable for motor fuel tax is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The lessee (carrier) when the qualified motor vehicle is being operated under the lessee's jurisdictional operating authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The lessor (independent contractor, agent, or service representative) when the qualified motor vehicle is being operated under the lessor's jurisdictional operating authority.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="03|03|04|.06|F.|(1)|(a)">§F(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the base jurisdiction for purposes of IFTA is the base jurisdiction of the lessee (carrier), regardless of the jurisdiction in which the qualified motor vehicle is registered for vehicle registration purposes by the lessor or lessee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="03|03|04|.06|F.|(1)|(b)">§F(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>, the base jurisdiction for purposes of IFTA is the base jurisdiction of the lessor, regardless of the jurisdiction in which the qualified motor vehicle is registered for vehicle registration purposes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Filing of leases is not required as a condition of licensing, but leases shall be made available upon request of an IFTA jurisdiction.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Registration of Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>IFTA Licenses and Identification Markers (Decals). IFTA licenses and decals shall be valid upon issuance and shall expire on December 31 of the year indicated on the license. A carrier is allowed a 2-month grace period during January and February to display the new year IFTA license and decals, if the carrier displays the immediate prior year IFTA license and decals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Display of IFTA Decals. A motor carrier shall display an IFTA decal on the exterior portion of both sides of the cab, permanently affixed in a conspicuous place, and shall follow the directions for applying the decals to the vehicle as indicated on the reverse side of the decal. In the case of transporters, manufacturers, dealers, or driveway operations, the decals need not be permanently affixed, but may be temporarily displayed in a visible manner on both sides of the cab.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an IFTA decal which has been issued by the Field Enforcement Bureau becomes illegible, the motor carrier may apply to the Field Enforcement Bureau for issuance of a duplicate decal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A motor carrier shall be issued an IFTA license and a 2-decal set for each vehicle and the original license or copy shall be carried in the vehicle at all times. Once IFTA decals are affixed to a specific vehicle, they are not transferable to any other vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>When a vehicle to which IFTA decals have been affixed is sold, traded, or otherwise disposed of by the operator, or passes from the control of the operator through lease or otherwise, the Field Enforcement Bureau shall be notified within 30 days of the cancellation. If the motor carrier neglects or fails to notify the Field Enforcement Bureau, the motor carrier is responsible for reporting the miles traveled by the vehicle and paying the tax due.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A motor carrier shall return unused IFTA decals to the Field Enforcement Bureau.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A Maryland domiciled carrier that is required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-219">Tax-General Article, §9-219, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to display IFTA decals on each commercial motor vehicle, and that purchases a commercial motor vehicle for titling in Maryland, has 30 days from the date of purchase to obtain an IFTA license and affix IFTA decals to the vehicle. The bill of sale or temporary registration identification documents issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-402">Transportation Article, §13-402 </cite>or 13-405, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall be carried in the cab of the vehicle during this 30-day period. The motor carrier may not operate the vehicle outside Maryland until IFTA decals are displayed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Revocation.</heading>
    <text>The Comptroller is empowered to suspend or revoke the IFTA license and decals of any motor carrier, upon a finding by the Comptroller that the registrant has failed to comply with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg">Tax-General Article, Title 9, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any regulation promulgated by the Comptroller under that statute. The revocation shall be made only after 30 days notice to the registrant to comply with all sections of the law and regulations. Reapplication for registration will not be granted until a motor carrier has complied with all sections of the law and regulations.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Improper Use of Licenses and Decals.</heading>
    <text>The Maryland State Police shall remove and return to the Field Enforcement Bureau all IFTA licenses and decals that are being used in any improper manner.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Penalty for False Statements.</heading>
    <text>Any person who willfully and knowingly makes a false statement, orally or in writing, in the form of a receipt for the sale of motor fuel for the purposes of obtaining or attempting to obtain or to assist any other person, partnership, or corporation to obtain or attempt to obtain a credit or refund or reduction of liability for taxes under this subtitle will be notified to the effect that all permits and registrations have been revoked.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Licensing of Trip Permit Vendors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Qualifications. In order to ensure a sufficient number and availability of locations where a motor carrier may purchase a trip permit required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-219">Tax-General Article, §9-219, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, before entering this State, the Field Enforcement Bureau, in its discretion, may license applicants to issue trip permits if they meet the following qualifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall have 3 years experience in the issuance of trip permits or other similar experiences;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall possess a business rating, reputation, and capability satisfactory to the Field Enforcement Bureau;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall be capable of providing the service at all times specified by the Field Enforcement Bureau;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall be capable of delivering copies of all issued trip permits to the offices of the Field Enforcement Bureau by the next working day; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall possess the financial capability to purchase trip permits from the Field Enforcement Bureau in advance of sale in quantities of not less than 200.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Issuance of Trip Permits by Licensees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensees shall sell trip permits in the manner prescribed by the Field Enforcement Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The licensee may charge the purchaser of a trip permit a fee for its service not to exceed the rate established by the Field Enforcement Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Licensees may only sell permits to a motor carrier for a specific commercial motor vehicle. Permits may not be sold for resale.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Liability. The Field Enforcement Bureau is not liable for the illegal or improper acts of its licensees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Inspection of Records. The applicant agrees to the availability and inspection of all its records by the Field Enforcement Bureau, during normal business hours, for the determination of compliance with the Field Enforcement Bureau requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Transferability and Revocation of License. The license to sell trip permits is nontransferable and revocable for cause or for no cause upon 10 days written notice from the Field Enforcement Bureau to the licensee that the license is revoked. Licensees may terminate the license by giving 30 days written notice to the Field Enforcement Bureau. If the license arrangement is cancelled by either party, the licensee shall promptly turn in to the offices of the Field Enforcement Bureau all unissued trip permits, and the Field Enforcement Bureau shall refund their cost.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Penalties and Interest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a person fails to file an IFTA report and schedules when due, a penalty shall be assessed in the amount of 10 percent of the tax due, with a minimum assessment of $50.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A penalty of $50 shall be assessed when an IFTA report and schedules are not filed when due, even if taxes are not due.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a person files an IFTA report and schedules timely but, for whatever reason, underpays the proper tax due an IFTA jurisdiction, a penalty shall be assessed in the amount of 10 percent of the additional tax due, with a minimum assessment of $50.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Interest.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a person fails to file a return when due, interest shall be assessed as prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg">Tax-General Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interest on unpaid tax assessments shall be assessed as prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg">Tax-General Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Appeal—Informal Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person desiring to appeal an assessment or denial of a refund may apply for an informal hearing which shall be held in accordance with procedures set forth in <cite path="03.01.01.04">COMAR 03.01.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Informal hearings shall be held at a location determined by the Comptroller, and the location shall be set in the notice issued by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Tax-General Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|2-103">2-103</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-205">9-205</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1974-06-01">Effective date: June 1, 1974</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257); September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|04|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|04|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective June 2, 1978 (5:11 Md. R. 881); September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|04|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.02|F.">Regulation .02F</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.02|H.">Regulation .02H</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1986-10-20"><cite path="|03|03|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 20, 1986 (13:21 Md. R. 2319)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-06-02"><cite path="|03|03|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective June 2, 1978 (5:11 Md. R. 881)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26"><cite path="|03|03|04|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476); November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257); August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1699)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|04|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite> amended effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 509); September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> repealed and new Regulation .05 adopted effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective June 2, 1978 (5:11 Md. R. 881); September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476); November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257); September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476); November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257); September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1476); November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257); September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-06-02"><cite path="|03|03|04|.12|F.">Regulation .12F</cite> amended effective June 2, 1978 (5:11 Md. R. 881)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-06-02"><cite path="|03|03|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective June 2, 1978 (5:11 Md. R. 881)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-07"><cite path="|03|03|04|.13|E.">Regulation .13E</cite> amended effective September 7, 1987 (14:18 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26"><cite path="|03|03|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2257); repealed effective August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1699)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-23" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 23, 1989 (16:1 Md. R. 66)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|03|03|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> repealed effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised and recodified from <cite path="|03.03.06">COMAR 03.03.06</cite> to <cite path="|03.03.04">COMAR 03.03.04</cite> effective August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1987)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1890)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-09-28">Regulations .02, .05, .07, .10, and .12 amended, and Regulation .14 adopted effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1703)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-05-08"><cite path="|03|03|04|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective May 8, 1995 (22:9 Md. R. 644)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .01-2C amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2004-06-21"><cite path="|03|03|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 21, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 911)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .05A amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .07 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-06-19"><cite path="|03|03|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective June 19, 2006 (33:12 Md. R. 996)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .10 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .12 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
