<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Motor Fuel Inspection</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated, unless otherwise specified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"ASTM" means the American Society for Testing and Materials.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Bureau" means the Field Enforcement Bureau of the Comptroller of the Treasury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Conventional gasoline" means any gasoline meeting the minimum specifications established by ASTM, but not meeting the standards for reformulated gasoline established by the United States Environmental Protection Agency (US EPA).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Dispenser" means a device from which motor fuel is transferred from storage at a retail outlet or wholesale purchaser-consumer facility to an ultimate consumer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Ethanol blend" means gasoline which contains at least 9 percent by volume ethanol, excluding denaturants, as determined in accordance with one of the test methodologies specified in <cite path="03.03.06.03|B.">COMAR 03.03.06.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Ethanol-enhanced oxygenated gasoline" means gasoline containing less than 9 percent by volume ethanol, excluding denaturants, as determined in accordance with one of the test methods specified in <cite path="03.03.06.03|B.">COMAR 03.03.06.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Ethanol flex fuel" means automotive fuel blend of gasoline and 51 to 83 percent volume ethanol, commercially known as "E85", for use in ground vehicles equipped with flexible-fuel spark ignition engines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Gasoline" means any fuel sold for use in internal combustion spark-ignited engines and which is commonly or commercially known or sold as gasoline, including oxygenated gasoline.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Motor fuel" means gasoline or special fuel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle fuel" means motor fuel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Nonoxygenated gasoline" means gasoline which contains no oxygenates or oxygenates in quantities less than or equal to 0.4 percent oxygen by weight.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Oxygenate" means any oxygen-containing compound approved for use in gasoline under the US EPA's substantially similar definition or under a bona fide US EPA oxygenate waiver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Oxygenated gasoline" means gasoline which contains one or more oxygenates in quantities exceeding 0.4 percent oxygen by weight.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Oxygenated gasoline control area" means a geographic area in which all gasoline sold or dispensed during an oxygenated gasoline control period is subject to the minimum oxygen content requirements of Regulation .01-1N of this chapter. There are three oxygenated gasoline control areas as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Northeast Oxygenated Gasoline Control Area is comprised of Cecil County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Baltimore Oxygenated Gasoline Control Area is comprised of Baltimore City and Anne Arundel, Baltimore, Carroll, Harford, Howard, and Queen Anne's counties; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Washington Oxygenated Gasoline Control Area is comprised of Calvert, Charles, Frederick, Montgomery, and Prince George's counties.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Oxygenated gasoline control period" means the 4-month period which begins each November 1 and runs without interruption through the following February 28 or, in leap years, the following February 29.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Oxygenate waiver" means an authorization granted by the Administrator of the US EPA under §211(f)(4) of the federal Clean Air Act which permits the addition of specified oxygenates in specified volumes to unleaded nonoxygenated gasoline.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Ozone attainment areas" means the geographic areas of the State which are not ozone nonattainment areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Ozone nonattainment area" means the geographic areas of the State comprised of Baltimore City and Anne Arundel, Baltimore, Calvert, Carroll, Cecil, Charles, Frederick, Harford, Howard, Kent, Montgomery, Prince George's, and Queen Anne's counties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Reformulated gasoline (RFG)" means gasoline meeting the requirements of the US EPA definition established under §211(k) of the federal Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. §7545).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Reformulated gasoline control area" means ozone nonattainment areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Retail outlet" means an establishment at which motor fuel is sold or offered for sale to an ultimate consumer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Special fuel" means any fuel other than gasoline which is sold for use in motor vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Substantially similar definition" means an interpretive rule issued by the Administrator of the US EPA under §211(f)(1) of the federal Clean Air Act which permits the addition of specified oxygenates in specified volumes to unleaded nonoxygenated gasoline. The most recent definition appeared in the February 11, 1991, Federal Register (56 FR 5352).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Transfer" means the physical transfer of custody or the transfer of title of motor fuel from one person to another, excluding the sale or dispensing of motor fuel at a retail outlet or wholesale purchaser-consumer facility for direct consumption in a motor vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Ultimate consumer" means a person who purchases or obtains motor fuel for direct consumption in an automotive engine and who does not transfer or offer to transfer the motor fuel to any other person following purchase or receipt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Unleaded gasoline" means gasoline which is produced without the use of any lead additive and which contains not more than 0.013 gram of lead per liter (0.05 gram of lead per gallon) and not more than 0.0013 gram of phosphorus per liter (0.005 gram of phosphorus per gallon).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"VOC control region 1" means all of the Maryland reformulated gasoline control area except for Cecil County.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"VOC control region 2" means that portion of the Maryland reformulated gasoline control area consisting of Cecil County.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Wholesale purchaser-consumer" means an ultimate consumer who receives delivery of motor fuel solely intended for ultimate consumption into a storage tank with a capacity of at least 550 gallons which is substantially under the control of the ultimate consumer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Wholesale purchaser-consumer facility" means an establishment at which a wholesale purchaser-consumer stores and dispenses motor fuel for direct consumption in a motor vehicle or an internal combustion engine.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|05|.01-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Standard Specifications for Gasoline.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exemptions. Gasoline not sold or dispensed to an ultimate consumer may be exempted from the requirements of this regulation upon written approval of the Bureau and the Department. Exemption from vapor pressure requirements shall only be granted in instances where the applicant complies with the requirements of proposed 40 CFR §80.27(e), which is incorporated by reference as published in the October 18, 1991, Federal Register (56 FR 52321). Requests for exemption from oxygen content requirements shall comply with the requirements of 40 CFR §80.27(e), except that all data shall be applicable to oxygen content rather than vapor pressure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless the gasoline is segregated and clearly documented as noncomplying and not for sale or supply to an ultimate consumer in an applicable control area, a person may not produce, store, transport, supply, offer to supply, transfer or otherwise handle, sell, offer for sale, or dispense gasoline that does not meet the limits specified in §§C—N of this regulation when tested in accordance with the latest version of the specified test methods.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Distillation. Except as provided in <cite path="03|03|05|.01-1|C.|(5)">§C(5) of this regulation</cite>, the rates of evaporation under the ASTM D-86 standards for the stated months of the year are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evaporation — during the months of, January, February, March, and December</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>10 percent — 50°C (122°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaporation — during the months of, January, February, March, and December</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 110°C (230°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>90 percent — 185°C (365°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>End Point — 225°C (437°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Residue — 2 percent maximum</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evaporation — during the months of April, October, and November</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>10 percent — 55°C (131°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 62.8°C (145°F) minimum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 113°C (235°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>90 percent — 185°C (365°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>End Point — 225°C (437°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Residue — 2 percent maximum</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Evaporation — May through September 15</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>10 percent — 70°C (158°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 77°C (170°F) minimum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 121°C (250°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>90 percent — 190°C (374°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>End Point — 225°C (437°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Residue — 2 percent maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An ethanol blend and an ethanol-enhanced oxygenated gasoline are subject to the following limit: 50 percent — 66°C (150°F) minimum</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Evaporation — September 16 through September 30</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>10 percent — 60°C (140°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 66°C (150°F) minimum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>50 percent — 116°C (240°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>90 percent — 185°C (365°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>End point — 225°C (437°F) maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Residue — 2 percent maximum</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An ethanol blend and an ethanol-enhanced oxygenated gasoline are subject to the following limit: 50 percent — 66°C (150°F) minimum</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To accommodate for the receipt of new product and disbursement of old stock, the following allowances are made from the fixed change-over date:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Product complying with the specifications for the volatility period beginning May 1 is acceptable up to 45 days before May 1;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Product complying with the specifications for the volatility period beginning September 16 is acceptable only on or after September 16; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Product complying with the specifications for any other volatility period is acceptable 15 days before or after the fixed change-over date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Vapor Pressure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The vapor pressure of gasoline may not exceed the following limits when tested in accordance with ASTM Test Method D-5191 or as otherwise required under <cite path="|03.03.06">COMAR 03.03.06</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>103 kPa (15.0 psi) during the months of January, February, and December;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>93 kPa (13.5 psi) during the months of March, April, October, and November;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>62 kPa (9.0 psi) during the month of May;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>During the months of June, July, and August and from September 1 through September 15:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>51 kPa (7.4 psi) for all gasoline sold, intended for sale, or supplied to an ultimate consumer in RFG VOC control region 1,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>57.2 kPa (8.3 psi) for all gasoline sold, intended for sale, or supplied to an ultimate consumer in RFG VOC control region 2, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>62 kPa (9.0 psi) for all gasoline sold, intended for sale, or supplied to an ultimate consumer in ozone attainment areas; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>79 kPa (11.5 psi) September 16 through September 30, inclusive.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ethanol blend and ethanol-enhanced oxygenated gasoline are subject to the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An ethanol blend is considered to be in compliance with §D(1)(a), (b), (c), (d), and (e) of this regulation if its measured vapor pressure does not exceed the limit specified by more than 1.0 psi, the gasoline portion of the product was not produced and identified as VOC gasoline by the refiner, and the product is sold only for use or distribution outside a VOC control region;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An ethanol-enhanced oxygenated gasoline is considered to be in compliance with §D(1)(a), (b), and (e) of this regulation if its measured vapor pressure does not exceed the limit specified by more than 1.0 psi from September 16—May 31, the gasoline portion of the product was not produced and identified as VOC gasoline by the refiner, and the product is sold only for use or distribution outside a VOC control region;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A 15-day transition period is allowed before and following each change in vapor pressure limits as specified in <cite path="03|03|05|.01-1|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite>, except as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Gasoline complying with the April vapor pressure limit is allowed throughout May at retail outlets and wholesale purchaser-consumer facilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Gasoline complying with the April vapor pressure limit is not allowed after April 30 at any location other than retail outlets or wholesale purchaser-consumer facilities, unless the gasoline also complies with the May vapor pressure limit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Gasoline complying with the May vapor pressure limit is not allowed after May 31, unless the gasoline also complies with the June vapor pressure limit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Gasoline complying with the September 16 through September 30 vapor pressure limit is not allowed before September 16, unless the gasoline also complies with the September 1 through September 15 vapor pressure limit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>V/L Ratio. Except as provided in <cite path="03|03|05|.01-1|E.|(4)">§E(4) of this regulation</cite>, the V/L Ratio Temperature in °C (°F) for a Vapor-Liquid Ratio of 20 Minimum under ASTM-D5188 standards is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>39°C (102°F) during the months of January, February, and December.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>42°C (107°F) during the months of March, April, October, and November.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>47°C (116°F) during the months of May, June, July, August, and September.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To accommodate for the receipt of new product and disbursement of old stock, the following allowances are made from the fixed change-over date:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Product complying with the specifications for the volatility period beginning May 1 is acceptable on or after March 16;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Product complying with the specifications for the volatility period beginning September 16 is acceptable only on or after September 16; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Product complying with the specifications for any other volatility period is acceptable 15 days before or after the fixed change-over date for that volatility period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Corrosion (ASTM D-130). Copper Strip Scale, No. 1, maximum at 50°C (122°F).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Sulfur (ASTM D-2622-21  or ASTM D-7039).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conventional gasoline — 0.0095 percent by mass, maximum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reformulated gasoline — 0.0095 percent by mass, maximum.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Existent Gum Content (ASTM D-381). 5 milligrams per 100 milliliters, maximum (after heptane wash).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Visible Water and Sediment. Shall be visually free of undissolved water, sediment, and suspended matter and shall be clear and bright at the ambient temperature or 21°C (70°F), whichever is higher.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Lead (ASTM D-3237).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unleaded — 0.013 gram per liter maximum (0.05 gram per U.S. gallon maximum).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Leaded — Greater than 0.013 gram per liter (0.05 gram per U.S. gallon), except that after December 31, 1995, leaded gasoline may not be sold for or used as fuel in a highway motor vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Octane Test. The octane rating shall be determined in accordance with Title II of the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act and regulations adopted under that title. In addition, gasoline with an anti-knock index of 87 shall have a motor octane number not less than 82.0.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Phosphorus (ASTM D-3231). Unleaded — 0.0013 gram per liter maximum (0.005 gram per U.S. gallon maximum).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Gasoline with a lead content of 0.013 gram per liter (0.05 gram per U.S. gallon) or less shall only be sold as unleaded.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Oxygen Content.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gasoline shall meet the oxygen content requirements specified in §N(2)—(4) of this regulation when tested in accordance with ASTM Test Method D-4815-22 or as otherwise required under <cite path="|03.03.06">COMAR 03.03.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Oxygenates used in gasoline shall be of a type and quality allowed under either the US EPA's substantially similar definition or under a bona fide US EPA oxygenate waiver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable oxygen content of gasoline shall be limited to that established under either the US EPA's substantially similar definition or that established under a bona fide US EPA oxygenate waiver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Phase Separation. Oxygenated gasoline shall consist of a single homogenous mixture, presenting no indication of phase separation when tested at the following temperatures in accordance with the test methods described in X8 of ASTM Specification D-4814-24a, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>-9°C (16°F) during the month of January;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>-8°C (17°F) during the month of February;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>-3°C (27°F) during the month of March;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>3°C (37°F) during the month of April;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>9°C (48°F) during the month of May;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>10°C (50°F) during the months of June, July, August, and September;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>4°C (39°F) during the month of October;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>-2°C (28°F) during the month of November; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>-8°C (17°F) during the month of December.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Specifications for No. 1-D and No. 2-D Diesel Fuel (ASTM D-975).</heading>
    <text>All No.1-D diesel fuel and No. 2-D diesel fuel shall meet the requirements of the following specifications, when tested in accordance with the latest version of the American Society for Testing and Materials Methods of Tests:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Cloud Point (ASTM D-2500) — -7°C (20°F) maximum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Flash Point (ASTM D-93).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No. 1-D Diesel — 38°C (100°F) minimum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No. 2-D Diesel.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>52°C (125°F) minimum (May, June, July, August, September, October).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>43°C (110°F) minimum (November, December, January, February, March, April).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Viscosity (ASTM D-445).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No. 1-D Diesel.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Kinematic at 40°C, 1.3 centistokes minimum, 2.4 centistokes maximum.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Kinematic at 100°F, 1.4 centistokes minimum, 2.5 centistokes maximum.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No. 2-D Diesel.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Kinematic at 40°C, 1.9 centistokes minimum, 4.1 centistokes maximum.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Kinematic at 100°F, 2.0 centistokes minimum, 4.3 centistokes maximum.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Visible water and sediment (ASTM D-1796) — 0.05 percent maximum by volume.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Carbon Residue on 10 percent Residuum (ASTM D-524).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No. 1-D Diesel, 0.15 percent, maximum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No. 2-D Diesel, 0.35 percent, maximum.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Ash (ASTM D-482) — 0.01 percent, maximum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Cetane.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Number method (ASTM D-613) 40, minimum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Index method (ASTM D-976) 40, minimum.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Distillation (ASTM D-86).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No. 1-D Diesel — 90 percent point, 288°C (550°F) maximum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No. 2-D Diesel — 90 percent point:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>282°C (540°F) minimum*;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>338°C (640°F) maximum.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <aftertext>* When cloud point less than -12°C (10°F) is specified, the minimum viscosity shall be 1.7 cSt (or mm2/s) and the 90 percent point shall be waived.</aftertext>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Corrosion (ASTM D-130). Copper Strip, 3 hours at 50°C (122°F), No. 3 maximum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Sulfur (ASTM D-2622 or ASTM D-7039) 0.0015 percent by mass, maximum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Color.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On-highway diesel fuel may not contain any dyes or coloring agents.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Non-highway diesel fuel shall be dyed with Solvent Red 164 at the concentration spectrally equivalent to at least 3.9 pounds of the solid dye Standard Red 26 per 1,000 barrels in accordance with the mandate of the US EPA and Internal Revenue Service (IRS). It may not be used in any vehicle designed for on-highway use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02-1</num>
    <heading>Other Motor Fuels.</heading>
    <text>A fuel other than those meeting the specifications detailed in Regulation .01-1 or .02 of this chapter may not be sold, offered for sale, or dispensed for use in motor vehicles unless approval for the sale or dispensation has been obtained in advance from the Bureau and the Department.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Specifications for Kerosene (ASTM D-3699).</heading>
    <text>Kerosene shall be a refined petroleum distillate consisting of a homogenous mixture of hydrocarbons essentially free from water, inorganic, acidic, or basic compounds, and excessive amounts of particulate contaminants. It shall meet the requirements of the following specifications when tested in accordance with the latest version of the American Society for Testing and Materials Methods of Tests:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>No. 1-K Kerosene.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Color (ASTM D-156).</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The color may not be darker than +16 Saybolt Scale.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dyeing agents may not be used to change the naturally refined color except when required by the US EPA or IRS.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When dyeing of 1-K kerosene is required, it shall be dyed with Solvent Red 164 at the concentration spectrally equivalent to at least 3.9 pounds of the solid dye Standard Red 26 per 1,000 barrels in accordance with federal mandates.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Flash Point (ASTM D-56)—38°C (100°F) minimum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Distillation (ASTM D-86)—End point 300°C (572°F) maximum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sulfur (ASTM D-4045)—0.04 percent by mass, maximum.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>No. 2-K Kerosene.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Color (ASTM D-156). The color, before dyeing, may not be darker than +16 Saybolt Scale. Additionally, 2-K kerosene shall be dyed with Solvent Red 164 at the concentration spectrally equivalent to at least 3.9 pounds of the solid dye Standard Red 26 per 1,000 barrels in accordance with federal mandate to indicate that it is illegal for use as a propelling fuel in a vehicle designed for on-highway use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Flash Point (ASTM D-56)—38°C (100°F) minimum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Distillation (ASTM D-86)—End point 300°C (572°F) maximum.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sulfur (ASTM D-4045)—0.30 percent by mass, maximum.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person acquiring kerosene for resale or redistribution as 1-K kerosene shall only acquire the product from a supplier who certifies to the purchaser that it is, in fact, 1-K kerosene.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|05|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Specifications for No. 1 and No. 2 Fuel Oil (ASTM D-396).</heading>
    <text>No. 1 fuel oil is a distillate oil intended for vaporizing pot-type and similar burners. No. 2 fuel oil is a distillate oil for general purpose domestic heating use in burners not requiring No. 1 fuel oil. Both shall meet the requirements of the following specifications, when tested in accordance with the latest version of the American Society for Testing and Materials Methods of Tests:</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">No. 1 Fuel Oil</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">No. 2 Fuel Oil</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Flash Point (ASTM D-93).</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">38°C <br/>(100°F) <br/>minimum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">38°C <br/>(100°F) <br/>minimum</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>B. Pour Point (ASTM D-97).</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-18°C <br/>(0°F) <br/>maximum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-7°C<br/>(20°F) <br/>maximum</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-vertical-align="middle">C. Visible Water and Sediment (ASTM D-1796) <br/>     percent by volume maximum.</td>
            <td data-text-align="center">0.05</td>
            <td data-text-align="center">0.05</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-vertical-align="middle">D. Viscosity (ASTM D-445).</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Kinematic at 40°C, centistokes.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-2" data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Minimum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.3</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.9*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-2" data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Maximum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2.1</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.4</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Kinematic at 100°F, centistokes.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-2" data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Minimum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.4</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2.0*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-2" data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Maximum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2.2</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.6</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-vertical-align="middle">E. Gravity (ASTM D-287). API minimum.</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">35°</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">30°</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-vertical-align="middle">F. Distillation (ASTM D-86).</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(1) 10 percent point maximum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">216°C (420°F)</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(2) 90 percent point maximum</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">288°C (550°F)</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">338°C (640°F)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-vertical-align="middle">G. Sulfur (ASTM D-1552) percent by mass shall not exceed the following maximums:</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(1) On and after July 1, 2016</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.05</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.05</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(2) On and after July 1, 2019</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.0015</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.0015</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1" data-vertical-align="middle">(3) No. 1 and No. 2 Fuel Oil that was stored in this State by the ultimate final consumer prior to July 1, 2019, which met the applicable maximum allowable sulfur content for fuel oil before July 1, 2019, set forth in <cite path="03|03|05|.04|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite> at the time it was stored, may be used by the ultimate consumer in the State on and after July 1, 2019, until the supply is depleted.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Color. No. 1 and No. 2 fuel oil, containing greater than 0.0015 percent by mass sulfur, shall be dyed with Solvent Red 164 at the concentration spectrally equivalent to at least 3.9 pounds of the solid dye Standard Red 26 per 1,000 barrels in accordance with the mandates of the US EPA and IRS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Cetane. Unless sold specifically and documented on all transfer documents as a burner fuel only, off-highway No. 2 fuel oil shall meet the same cetane requirements as stated in <cite path="|03|03|05|.02|G.">Regulation .02G of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <text>* Lower or higher pour points may be specified whenever required by conditions of storage or use. When pour point less than -18°C (0°F) is specified, the minimum viscosity shall be 1.7 centistokes.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Labeling of Pumps.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Bureau shall label all retail dispensing pumps.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The label in <cite path="03|03|05|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> at the discretion of the Bureau, shall be placed as close as practical to the product dispensing nozzle or the money value display indicator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The retailer shall further identify and label all retail dispensing pumps with the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The brand name and trade name of the product being sold except a trade name may not be used if it conflicts with one of the required grade names shown in <cite path="03|03|05|.05|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For gasoline, the octane rating in accordance with 15 U.S.C. §§2821—2824, Title II of the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act and regulations under the Act, 16 CFR §§306.0—306.11 for each grade dispensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For gasoline, the grade name in accordance with one of the following for each grade dispensed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Regular" if the certified octane is 87 or 88;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Mid-grade" or "Plus" if the certified octane is 89 or 90; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Premium" if the certified octane is 91 and above, but less than 98;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For special fuel, the type of fuel which shall be either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1-K Kerosene;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>2-K kerosene;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>1-D diesel (if purchased or sold as same); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Diesel, as applicable; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Identification as required under §C(3) and (4) of this regulation, which shall be in letters and numerals of uniform size, a minimum 2 inches high with a minimum 1/4 inch stroke.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Retention of Documents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A location registered under the Motor Fuel and Lubricants Law shall retain on the premises to which motor fuel has been delivered a loading ticket, a delivery ticket, or any other combination of documents that provides the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date, terminal name, city of origin, shipper, consignee name, volume of each grade, and type of motor fuel loaded and delivered including the product cost and freight charges per gallon;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For gasoline, including oxygenated fuels, the certified minimum octane rating;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For oxygenated and reformulated gasolines, the maximum concentration of individual oxygenates; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Name of the petroleum transporter making the delivery.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Retention of documentation required by this regulation shall be limited to the four most recent deliveries of each grade of the product; however, all parties should be aware that federal retention requirements are for 5 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All documents shall be readily available for inspection at the delivery site during normal business hours.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06-1</num>
    <heading>Below Cost Compliance Verification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To determine compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-304">Business Regulation Article, §10-304</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Comptroller shall inspect the documents specified in <cite path="|03|03|05|.06|A.|(1)">Regulation .06A(1) of this chapter</cite> at the site of the registered location about which the complaint was made. If the information required in <cite path="|03|03|05|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> is not immediately available upon request, the Comptroller shall promptly determine the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Product cost by type of motor fuel as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-301">Business Regulation Article, §10-301(d)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Freight charges referenced in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-301">Business Regulation Article, §10-301(d)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, at the rate of 3 cents per gallon.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If product cost and freight charges are determined in accordance with §A(1) and (2) of this regulation, and the price computed is not lower than the selling price, the retailer shall immediately adjust the current retail price of motor fuel so that it is not below the cost computed under §A(1) and (2) of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If required documents become available to review at the site during the inspection or are provided to the Comptroller within 3 business days from the date of inspection, and if the documents are determined by the Comptroller to be acceptable and show that the price computed is lower than or equal to the selling price, a violation may not be determined to have occurred and the Comptroller shall authorize appropriate price adjustments.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|05|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this regulation and for the purposes of the administration of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-303">Business Regulation Article, §10-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Company" means a sole proprietorship, partnership, corporation, or other business entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Enclosed work areas" means a service bay;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Jobber" means a company other than a wholesaler, that acquires possession of motor fuel for bulk resale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Manufacturer" means producer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle fuel" or "motor fuel" means gasoline, special fuels, or both;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Producer" means a company which engages (or which has an agent, a parent company, a subsidiary, or a joint venturer which engages) in extracting crude oil from the earth;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Refiner" means a company which engages (or which has an agent, a parent company, a subsidiary, or a joint venturer which engages) in refining crude oil into motor fuel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Retail outlet" means the real property and its improvements from which motor fuel is sold at retail and delivered into the tanks of motor vehicles or vessels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Retail service station dealer" means a company offering motor fuel for sale at retail;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Service of motor vehicles" means at least lubrication, oil change, tire repair, battery charge, and replacement of fan belts, radiator hoses, and wiper blades;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Subsidiary" means a company which has more than 50 percent of its assets, capital stock, or voting securities held directly or through attribution by another company or which as a practical matter is controlled by another company. Practical control shall be presumed to exist if 15 percent or more of the assets, capital stock, or voting securities of a company are held directly or through attribution by another company;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Wholesaler" means a "dealer" or "distributor" as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-301">Tax-General Article, §9-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Registration. Each company proposing to sell motor fuel in Maryland as a wholesaler, diesel fuel seller, heating oil distributor, manufacturer, refiner, jobber, or retail service station dealer, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain a Certificate of Registration from the Bureau before initially selling or exposing or offering for sale any motor fuel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain a renewal Certificate of Registration from the Bureau before June 1 before selling or exposing or offering for sale motor fuel during each State fiscal year after initial registration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Display prominently a current Certificate of Registration at the location from which the motor fuel is sold.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Form of Application. Applications for Certificates of Registration for each class of motor fuel seller shall be in such form and require such information that is not inconsistent with these regulations and the Motor Fuel and Lubricants Law, as required by the Comptroller for enforcement of these regulations and that law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Restriction on Issuance of Certificates of Registration to the Retail Service Station Dealer Class.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Certificate of Registration may not be issued to a company whose retail outlet has been physically changed in any manner, excepting normal maintenance, after July 1, 1977, and before October 1, 2000, unless the retail outlet contains enclosed work areas from which the applicant offers or will offer the service of motor vehicles, irrespective of whether motor vehicle fuel is purchased.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exceptions. This restriction does not apply to the following applications:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant whose retail outlet did not have enclosed work areas immediately before being physically changed in any manner, excepting normal maintenance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant at whose retail outlet motor fuel was not previously sold or exposed or offered for sale.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Issuance of Temporary Retail Service Station Dealer Certificates of Registration to Producers or Refiners.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to <cite path="03|03|05|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a producer or refiner which satisfies the criteria specified in Regulation .25A will be issued upon application a 90-day retail service station dealer Certificate of Registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to <cite path="03|03|05|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a producer or refiner entitled, under <cite path="|03|03|05|.25|E.">Regulation .25E of this chapter</cite>, temporarily to operate a retail service station will be issued upon application a temporary retail service station dealer Certificate of Registration, the term of which will be coextensive with the period of entitlement. For the purposes of this subsection an authorization which expires due to the grant of an extension under <cite path="|03|03|05|.25">Regulation .25 of this chapter</cite> will constitute an enlargement of the original period of entitlement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Certificate of Registration issued under these regulations does not authorize the operation of a retail service station in violation of the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 10, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Samples and Test Tolerances.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sample taken to determine compliance with the provisions of this chapter and <cite path="|03.03.06">COMAR 03.03.06</cite> may not exceed 4 liters.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise indicated, all samples necessary to determine compliance with this chapter and <cite path="|03.03.06">COMAR 03.03.06</cite> shall be taken in accordance with the methodologies detailed in 40 CFR Part 80, Appendix D, which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Tolerances.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A producer of motor fuels shall formulate, blend, and store fuels in such a manner that consideration is given for testing tolerances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Gasoline samples obtained for analysis shall meet:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vapor pressure specifications within a tolerance limit equal to +0.3 psi; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Oxygen content specifications within a tolerance limit equal to +/-0.30 percent oxygen by weight.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Excluding gasoline vapor pressure and oxygen content analyses, the tolerance limits for motor fuel analyses shall be as determined by the Bureau.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>"Stop Sale" at Retail Service Stations.</heading>
    <text>A "Stop Sale" notice will be issued to retail service station dealers for gasoline and special fuels failing to meet established specifications. The supplier shall be notified accordingly by the retail service station dealer, and a release will be awarded only after final disposition has been agreed upon by the Bureau. Confirmation of disposition shall be submitted in writing and contain an explanation for its failure to meet specification. The "Stop Sale" applies only to the location where sample analysis indicates specification violation. Upon discovery of fuels failing to meet established specifications, physical inventory shall be taken and reported in the confirmation of disposition.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>"Stop Sale" at Bulk Storage Plants.</heading>
    <text>A "Stop Sale" notice will be issued when petroleum products maintained in bulk plant facilities fail to meet specifications. Confirmation of disposition of "Stop Sale" product in the bulk plant and all such products returned to that bulk plant shall be submitted in writing and contain an explanation for its failure to meet specification. The registrant shall immediately notify all customers that have received inferior product of the Bureau's findings and make any arrangements necessary to replace or adjust to specifications all products failing the specification. All records showing the delivery, notification, return, replacement, or adjustment of product shall be made available to the motor fuel agents upon request.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Warning for Water.</heading>
    <text>A warning shall be issued to the retail service station dealer whenever an underground storage tank is found to contain 2 inches or more of water as determined by the use of water-finding paste on a gauge stick. A "Stop Sale" order will be issued if the water is not removed within the time period prescribed by the Bureau.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Meter Requirements.</heading>
    <text>All tank trucks, tank trailers, and tank semitrailers making metered sales or deliveries of gasoline or special fuels shall maintain a meter calibrated for that specific fuel being dispensed. Whenever a vehicle is utilized to deliver both gasoline and special fuels, separate meters shall be maintained and calibrated for gasoline and special fuels respectively, unless a National Type Evaluation Program (NTEP) approved multi-product metering system is utilized.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Color Coding for Bulk Storage Facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility in this State required to register under the Motor Fuel and Lubricants law and used to store motor fuel in fixed bulk storage tanks shall implement the American Petroleum Institute (API) recommended system of color coding equipment which is set out as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gasoline — unleaded:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>E10 Regular — white;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>E10 Midgrade — blue;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>E10 Premium — red;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>E0 Regular — white with black "0";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>E0 Midgrade — blue with white "0";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>E0 Premium — red with white "0";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Isobutanol blend — blue with yellow "IB";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>E15 — copper with black "E15";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>E85 — copper with black "E85";</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Diesel:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On-Road (USLD) — yellow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On-Road (USLD) &gt;5 percent biodiesel — yellow with black "BXX" (where "XX" is the biodiesel percentage);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Off-Road (Dyed Red) — yellow with red "OFF";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Off-Road (Dyed Red) &gt;5 percent biodiesel — yellow with red "OFF" and black "BXX" (where "XX" is the biodiesel percentage);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Biodiesel — light blue;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Fuel Oil:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>No. 1 — dark green with black "1";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No. 2 — dark green with black "2";</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Kerosene — brown;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Vapor recovery — orange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Observation or Monitoring Wells — white with black triangle in the center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Methods of Coloring.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Facilities Except Bulk Plants, Terminals, and Distribution Points.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The required color scheme shall be applied to all fillbox (manhole) covers and shall extend at least 3 inches beyond the fillbox cover to prevent mismatching of fillboxes with the appropriate cover.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the bulk storage tank is an above-ground tank, the required color coding shall be affixed to the tank close to the fill and to the draw-off point and be at least 8 inches in overall diameter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other methods of identification such as tagging fillbox adapters, rims, or the use of plastic inserts inside the fillbox rim may be used in addition to the required coloring, but not as a substitute, for underground storage tanks.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bulk Plants, Terminals, and Distribution Points.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The required color scheme shall be prominently placed on all rack-loading and vapor recovery equipment, as close as possible to the point of product or vapor transfer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Storage tanks may be labeled using the appropriate color scheme when operating conditions permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Required color coding shall be maintained clean and clearly legible at all times.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility required to use the color coding system in this regulation shall post a sign or signs in a prominent location on the premises indicating the color scheme.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Product Transfer — Prohibition. Motor fuel may not be transferred from a shipping facility or delivered to a receiving facility in this State unless the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shipping and receiving facilities are in compliance with this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Petroleum transporter is in compliance with <cite path="03.03.03.15">COMAR 03.03.03.15</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Commingled Products.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For the specific purpose of this regulation, "commingled products" means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pipeline interface or transmix; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A mixture of gasoline and light distillates.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Commingled products may be blended into gasoline for redistribution, provided the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Person blending is a common carrier pipeline or holds a valid Class A dealer license issued by this State, and has obtained written approval from this State to blend; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Resultant product, after blending, at the time of the first sale or delivery, meets the specifications for the particular grade as prescribed by Regulation 01-1 of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Addition of Commingled Products.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A common carrier pipeline may add commingled products only once to a particular batch of product between the point of origin and the final receiving terminal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a commingled product is added to a batch, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Quantity of the commingled product may not exceed 0.25 percent by volume of the batch movement and shall be dispersed throughout the batch; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Common carrier pipeline shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Notify the receiving terminal, in advance of receipt, of the quantity added, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Indicate the volume of the commingled product added on the delivery ticket.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A receiving or shipping terminal may "line blend" its own commingled product into a receipt or shipment, provided the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Finished blend meets all applicable specifications of Regulation .01-1 of this chapter and the specifications for the product as registered with this State by the Class A dealer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Volume of the commingled product does not exceed 0.25 percent of the product being shipped or received, and is dispersed throughout the batch.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A Class A dealer may "tank blend" commingled products with gasoline, provided the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class A dealer can demonstrate the blending does not result in stratification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Volume of the commingled product does not exceed 0.25 percent of the tank volume at any time; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Finished blend meets all applicable Maryland specifications and the minimum specifications for the product as registered by the Class A dealer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A Class A dealer shall routinely accept, when possible, drainages of small quantities of commingled products from tank vehicles. Quantities over 5 gallons may be accepted at the discretion of the terminal.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Annual Terminal Agreements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before a terminal owner/operator stores product for another product owner, a terminal agreement shall be filed with the Bureau.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Forms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Terminal agreements shall be filed annually during the month of December for the anticipated succeeding calendar year's activity, on forms provided by the Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A separate form shall be completed for each terminal location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A form required by this section shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Address only the specific type and grade of product being stored for the product owner; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contain original signatures of persons authorized to represent the terminal owner/operator and the product owner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Additional terminal agreements which may be entered into during the calendar year shall be filed with the Bureau before the start of new activity.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Annual Exchange Agreements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person receiving for distribution within the State a product containing a unique, advertised additive shall file an exchange agreement with the Bureau.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Forms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exchange agreements shall be filed annually during the month of December for the succeeding calendar year's activity, on forms provided by the Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A form required by this section shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Address only the specific product to be acquired at each point of acquisition; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contain original signatures of persons authorized to represent the receiver and the supplier.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Additional exchange agreements which may be entered into during the calendar year shall be filed with the Bureau within 10 days of initial product receipt.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Refinery Specifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Refinery specifications mean typical specifications and the designation of any unique additives placed into any grade of product marketed within the State. For proper identification, the refinery specification shall include the trade name and, for gasoline, the certified octane number determined in accordance with 15 U.S.C. §§2821—2824, Title II of the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act and regulations under the Act, 16 CFR §306.0—306.11. Refinery specifications shall be filed annually in December for the succeeding calendar year and at least 10 days before any change occurs after the annual filing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pipeline specifications instead of typical refinery specifications will be accepted only if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pipeline company makes direct terminal deliveries in Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Importer of the product is not a refiner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Additive Specifications.</heading>
    <text>Additive specifications may be filed in detail or by means of an acceptable analytical method to be used to determine the presence or absence of any unique additive.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Trade Secrets.</heading>
    <text>Refinery or additive specifications considered to be a trade secret should be so indicated and shall meet with the concurrence of the Comptroller.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Inventory of Refined Products.</heading>
    <text>Under normal operating procedures, all petroleum products refined and imported into Maryland shall be inventoried by the refined product identification used on the shipping or delivery manifest.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Violations for Which a Warning Will Be Issued.</heading>
    <text>Warnings will be issued at the discretion of the motor fuel agent for violations such as, but not limited to, price sign violations, failure to register, and unposted certificate of registration. If, after the time prescribed by the agent, the violation still exists, a "Stop Sale" notice will be issued.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Foreign Imports and Waterborne Transfers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Motor fuel, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-101">Tax-General Article, §9-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, imported into the State or transported within the State via a vessel, shall be considered to be under a "Stop Sale" order until after it has been inspected, sampled, analyzed, and approved for sale or use by the Bureau.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions. Section A of this regulation does not apply under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Motor fuel imported from sources outside the State (foreign or domestic) may be placed directly into working tanks for immediate sale and distribution, providing the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cargo manifest and specifications are available at time of inspection and those specifications meet or exceed State minimum requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bureau is notified by the receiving terminal operator at least 24 hours before the vessel's arrival.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Motor fuel transported intrastate may be placed directly into working tanks for immediate sale, use, and distribution providing the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shipper holds a valid dealer, special fuel seller, or special fuel user license issued pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-318">Tax-General Article, §9-318, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shipper of product for resale or distribution has on file with the Bureau specifications for that grade of motor fuel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Bureau is notified by the receiving terminal operator at least 24 hours before the vessel's arrival.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Terminal operators shipping motor fuel for export to another state shall notify the Bureau at least 24 hours before the vessel's scheduled departure.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Ban Against Operation of Service Stations by Producers or Refiners.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation and <cite path="|03|03|05|.25">Regulation .25 of this chapter</cite>, and for the purposes of the administration of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-311">Business Regulation Article, §10-311, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commissioned agent" means a company (or any of its officers, directors, agents, or employees) which directly or indirectly receives, from a producer or refiner and for participation in the operation of a station, compensation determined by reference to the profits earned or revenues generated at a station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Company" means a sole proprietorship, partnership, corporation, or other business entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Company personnel" means one or more employees, servants, or agents of a producer, a refiner, or a subsidiary of a producer or refiner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Fee arrangement" means any agreement whereby a company (or any of its officers, directors, agents, or employees) directly or indirectly receives, from a producer or refiner and for participation in the operation of a station, compensation determined other than by reference to the profits earned or revenues generated at a station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle fuel" or "motor fuel" means gasoline, special fuels, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Producer" means a company which engages (or which has an agent, a parent company, a subsidiary, or a joint venturer which engages) in extracting crude oil from the earth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Refiner" means a company which engages (or which has an agent, a parent company, a subsidiary, or a joint venturer which engages) in refining crude oil into motor fuel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Retail service station" or "station" means the real property and its improvements from which motor fuel is sold at retail and delivered into the tanks of motor vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Retail service station dealer" or "dealer" means a company engaged in the operation of a station, which company (and its officers, directors, agents, and employees) is neither a producer, refiner, commission agent, party to a fee arrangement, subsidiary of a producer or refiner, nor operated by company personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Subsidiary" means a company which has more than 50 percent of its assets, capital stock, or voting securities held directly or through attribution by another company or which as a practical matter is controlled by another company. Practical control shall be presumed to exist if 15 percent or more of the assets, capital stock, or voting securities of a company are held directly or through attribution by another company.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|05|.25">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Temporary Operation of Station by Producer or Refiner.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After July 13, 1979, a producer or refiner may operate a retail service station previously dealer-operated for a period not to exceed 90 days and pursuant to a Certificate of Registration issued under <cite path="|03|03|05|.07|E.|(1)">Regulation .07E(1) of this chapter</cite> if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dealer has died (if a sole proprietor);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dealer has vacated the station in breach of the lease;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Dealer has been evicted by the producer or refiner for cause;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Producer or refiner has notified all of its dealers in the State of its intent to withdraw from the Maryland market in compliance with Title 1 of the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act (15 U.S.C. §2801 et seq.) and the dealer has agreed to vacate the station before the announced market withdrawal date; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Producer or refiner has acquired the retail service station from the dealer as a result of a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Purchase of the retail service station property from the dealer, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Merger or acquisition of stock in the dealer or its parent corporation by a producer or refiner.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to this section, the producer or refiner may immediately commence operation of the retail service station and operate it for 5 business days under the Certificate of Registration issued to the prior dealer if, during that period, the producer or refiner notifies the Bureau in writing of its commencement. The notification shall set forth the date operation by the producer or refiner commenced, the address of the retail service station, and a statement of the reason for the operation by the producer or refiner. The date of commencement shall constitute the initial day of the 90-day temporary operation period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications for Extensions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applications to the Comptroller for an extension of the time period specified in <cite path="03|03|05|.25|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> will be considered only if they are submitted in writing and, with regard to each station specified therein, contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The station address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The basis for the applicability of <cite path="03|03|05|.25|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the previous dealer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The reason why the extension is sought;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The duration of the extension sought; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A complete description of the actions being taken to locate a new dealer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applicants shall promptly provide additional information when requested by the Comptroller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Action by Comptroller on Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Decisions by the Comptroller on applications made pursuant to <cite path="03|03|05|.25|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> will be written and sent by certified mail to the applicant at the return address appearing on the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Comptroller may grant or deny the extension sought or may grant an extension for a period of time less than that sought in the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Operation Pending Action by Comptroller. Operation of a previously dealer-operated station by a producer or refiner in excess of the time period specified in <cite path="03|03|05|.25|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> and during the pendency of an application made pursuant to <cite path="03|03|05|.25|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> will not be allowed unless the contrary has been authorized in writing by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Entitlement to Temporary Certificate of Registration. A decision granting an extension to the time period specified in <cite path="03|03|05|.25|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> or an authorization issued under <cite path="03|03|05|.25|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> entitles the recipient to a temporary retail service station dealer Certificate of Registration pursuant to <cite path="|03|03|05|.07|E.|(2)">Regulation .07E(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Seasonal Retail Product Changes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The storage and sale of diesel fuel and kerosene at retail may be alternated seasonally from the same storage or dispensing system, under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The retailer or the supplier notifies the Bureau at least 10 days before the change;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notification includes the registered name and specific locations of the facility along with the product change date; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dispensing equipment is properly identified as required under <cite path="|03|03|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> to reflect the new type of fuel actually being dispensed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A motor fuel agent shall visit the specific location before the newly alternated fuel is sold to verify that, when changing from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Diesel fuel to kerosene, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Storage tanks are reasonably dry before the receipt of kerosene into storage,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Delivery of kerosene and adequate purging of affected lines and dispensing equipment have taken place, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proper identification of dispensers as to the type and grade of fuel has been made;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A kerosene to diesel fuel:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Current sales records, meter readings, and inventory are reconciled to the last day of kerosene sales,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Maryland motor fuel tax on any remaining inventory of kerosene is promptly paid, when applicable, as required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|9-314">Tax-General Article, §9-314, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any bulk transfer to another location of unsold kerosene is properly documented, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The proper identification of dispensers as to the type and grade of fuel has been made.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Under no circumstances will a seasonal switch between gasoline and any other type of motor fuel be permitted.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="03|03|05|.27">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Brand Integrity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Brand integrity" means that the purchaser of a major brand product does not mix or commingle that product with any other major brand, secondary brand, or unbranded products for resale or distribution as the major brand.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When Applicable.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Brand integrity is applicable whenever a refiner files refinery specifications and trade name for a product to be marketed in this State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The branded product in <cite path="03|03|05|.27|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> may only be acquired from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Terminal source points designated by the refiner; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Distributors, as authorized by the refiner, who make:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Direct deliveries of the product from the refiner's designated terminal to the distributor's customers, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Deliveries of the product from the distributor's segregated storage to the customer's storage tanks.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>Blending.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For the purpose of this regulation, "blending" means to combine for resale or distribution two grades of motor fuel, previously registered with the Comptroller, to create another grade. Blending does not include the addition of any additive.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Blending at retail service stations shall be allowed only when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Brand integrity, when applicable, is maintained;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A fixed blender or variable-blending retail dispensing device, meeting all requirements of the most current edition of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Handbook 44, as specified by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|11-203">Agriculture Article, §11-203(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is used;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The dispensing device is manufactured by a nationally recognized manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The dispensing device contains adequate security devices to prevent the change of any blend ratio except by personnel authorized by the dispenser manufacturer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The blended product is registered with the Comptroller and, in the case of a major brand, does not conflict with the annual registration of the brand owner and is done with the written concurrence of the brand owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Blending at bulk storage/terminal facilities shall be allowed only when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of gasoline, the blending is done by the holder of a valid Class A dealer license who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except in the case of ethanol flex fuel, uses an "inline blending" system between the bulk storage tanks and loading rack or under short-term emergency conditions and with the prior approval of the Comptroller, directly supervises the loading of blended product;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Registers the resultant blend with the Comptroller before making a sale and on an annual basis after that; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Furnishes the petroleum transporter, at the time of loading, with sufficient documentation for compliance with <cite path="03.03.03.05">COMAR 03.03.03.05</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the case of special fuel, the blending is done by the holder of a valid Class S special fuel seller license who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Blends previously registered special fuel products with the resulting blend conforming to specifications contained in Regulations .02 and .04 of this chapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Furnishes the petroleum transporter, at the time of loading, with sufficient documentation for compliance with <cite path="03.03.03.05">COMAR 03.03.03.05</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.29</num>
    <heading>Additives — Special Fuel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Under certain approved conditions by the Comptroller, additives may be added to special fuel, if they do not contain any dyes or coloring agents when used in on-highway diesel fuel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Additives that have been properly registered with and approved by the Comptroller may be added to special fuel by a bulk supplier licensed as a special fuel seller, provided the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Introduction of any additive to branded special fuel products is done with the prior written concurrence of the brand owner on an annual basis, with a copy of the concurrence forwarded to the Comptroller;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Additive manufacturer has no restrictions on the use of the additive in any type of special fuel application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Additive is introduced by an automatic metering pump or injection system at the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Time of product receipt, into a bulk storage tank of the special fuel seller;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Loading rack of the special fuel seller at the time of filling a delivery truck; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Retail service station or fueling site in a manner approved by the Comptroller.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.30</num>
    <heading>Reporting of End-of-Month Inventories.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Who Shall Report. Each person maintaining fixed bulk storage in Maryland for resale or redistribution (retail service stations are exempt), shall file an inventory report when required by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>What to Report. The report shall state the exact location and the amount in gallons of the month-end inventory of gasoline, kerosene, No. 1-D diesel fuel, No. 2-D diesel fuel, No. 1 fuel oil, No. 2 fuel oil, and propane (LPG). Inventories not physically located in Maryland may not be reported.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>How to Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each person required to file an inventory report shall file the report on forms provided by the Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All inventories shall be reported in actual physical gallons. Book inventories are not acceptable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A report shall be filed regardless of whether there is end-of-month inventory. If there is no end-of-month inventory, the report shall so state.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When and Where to File a Report. An inventory report shall be received by the Comptroller within 5 working days following the end of the month for which inventory is being reported. If the report is mailed, it shall be postmarked within 3 days following the end of the month. This report is in addition to any other report required by the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.31</num>
    <heading>Report—Tax-Free Sales to End Users.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A motor fuel seller registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall report the volume of sales for each type of motor fuel sold to end users in the State exclusive of the motor fuel tax. Tax-free sales to a reseller are not to be included in this report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A report shall be filed for each fiscal year ending June 30. A completed annual report shall be forwarded to and received by the Comptroller by July 15.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall furnish the report form.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.32</num>
    <heading>Additives for Gasoline.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Additives may be injected by a licensed dealer, other than a Class A dealer, with an “in-line blending” process or an equivalent or superior to in-line blending system to ensure proper additization of gasoline and only with prior approval from the Comptroller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Applications.  Applications shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A description of the system used to inject the additive into fuel, including a detailed summary of the additive injection and delivery process, verifiable identification that the process is “in-line blending” or equivalent to or superior to in-line blending, and any security systems to ensure proper additization of gasoline;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Detailed system schematics and manufacturer information describing the equipment used in the system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The EPA registration for the additive which shall be approved by the Comptroller.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller reserves the right to rescind any prior approval of additive introduction into gasoline by a dealer other than a licensed Class A dealer, or issue a stop sale to said dealer, for failure to comply with any statute, regulation or licensing requirements, or for product failure after the Comptroller’s laboratory analysis.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Business Regulation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-202">10-202</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-308">10-308</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-309">10-309</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|10-323">10-323</cite>.1; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|2-103">Tax-General Article, §2-103</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-30">Effective date: June 30, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1010)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148); November 24, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1706); October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1876)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> amended effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2022); August 10, 1979 (6:16 Md. R. 1329); October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1876)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-11-24"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148); November 24, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1706)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148); November 24, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1706); October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1876)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02|F.">Regulation .02F</cite> amended effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02|H.">Regulation .02H</cite> amended effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2022); August 10, 1979 (6:16 Md. R. 1329); September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1477)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>—C amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.03|H.">Regulation .03H</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.03|I.">Regulation .03I</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>—C amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.04|H.">Regulation .04H</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.04|I.">Regulation .04I</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148); March 15, 1982 (9:5 Md. R. 525); November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2258); February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|05|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148); September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1477)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.07|D.">Regulation .07D</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.07|F.">Regulation .07F</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-08-10"><cite path="|03|03|05|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective August 10, 1979 (6:16 Md. R. 1329)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.08|D.">Regulation .08D</cite> adopted effective November 22, 1982 (9:23 Md. R. 2258)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.08|D.">Regulation .08D</cite> amended effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.09">Regulation .09</cite> repealed and new Regulation .09 adopted effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-04-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective April 7, 1978 (5:7 Md. R. 520); April 20, 1979 (6:8 Md. R. 650)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-12-12"><cite path="|03|03|05|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective December 12, 1980 (7:25 Md. R. 2332)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.10|D.">Regulation .10D</cite> amended effective October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1876); September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1477); February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.12">Regulation .12</cite> repealed effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-08-10"><cite path="|03|03|05|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective August 10, 1979 (6:16 Md. R. 1329)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03"><cite path="|03|03|05|.12|F.">Regulation .12F</cite>—J adopted effective October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1876)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.12">Regulation .12</cite> repealed and new Regulation .12 adopted effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-12-30"><cite path="|03|03|05|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective December 30, 1985 (12:26 Md. R. 2542)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1986-02-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.12|G.">Regulation .12G</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 21, 1986 (13:6 Md. R. 667) (Emergency provisions are temporary and are not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.18">Regulation .18</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03"><cite path="|03|03|05|.24">Regulation .24</cite> amended effective October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1876)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-09-14"><cite path="|03|03|05|.28">Regulation .28</cite> amended effective September 14, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1477)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.28">Regulation .28</cite> repealed effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.30">Regulation .30</cite> amended effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-09"><cite path="|03|03|05|.31">Regulation .31</cite> repealed effective February 9, 1979 (6:3 Md. R. 148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|03|03|05|.31">Regulation .31</cite> adopted effective May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 862)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.31">Regulation .31</cite> repealed and new Regulation .31 adopted effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Regulations <cite path="|03|03|05|.32">.32</cite>—<cite path="|03|03|05|.34">.34</cite> originally adopted as Regulations <cite path="|03|03|05|.34">.34</cite>—<cite path="|03|03|05|.36">.36</cite>, respectively</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-07-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.32">Regulation .32</cite> adopted effective July 20, 1977 (4:15 Md. R. 1145)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-04-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.32">Regulation .32</cite> amended effective April 20, 1979 (6:8 Md. R. 650)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-12-12"><cite path="|03|03|05|.32|A.">Regulation .32A</cite> amended effective December 12, 1980 (7:25 Md. R. 2332)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-03-14"><cite path="|03|03|05|.32|B.">Regulation .32B</cite> amended effective December 12, 1980 (7:25 Md. R. 2332); March 14, 1983 (10:5 Md. R. 463)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-02-10"><cite path="|03|03|05|.32|D.">Regulation .32D</cite> amended effective February 10, 1978 (5:3 Md. R. 135)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-07-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.33">Regulation .33</cite> adopted effective July 20, 1977 (4:15 Md. R. 1145)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-04-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.33">Regulation .33</cite> amended effective April 20, 1979 (6:8 Md. R. 650)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-04"><cite path="|03|03|05|.33|A.">Regulation .33A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 24, 1985 (12:14 Md. R. 1428); adopted permanently effective November 4, 1985 (12:22 Md. R. 2103)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-07-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.34">Regulation .34</cite> adopted effective July 20, 1977 (4:15 Md. R. 1145)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-04-20"><cite path="|03|03|05|.34">Regulation .34</cite> amended effective April 20, 1979 (6:8 Md. R. 650)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|03|03|05|.34">Regulation .34</cite> repealed effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-22">Regulations .35 and .36 adopted as an emergency provision effective July 10, 1979 (6:15 Md. R. 1268); adopted permanently effective November 24, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1706); repealed effective February 22, 1988 (15:4 Md. R. 470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Annotation: <cite path="03.03.07.32">COMAR 03.03.07.32</cite> discussed in Comptroller of the Treasury v. Crown Central Petroleum Corporation, 52 Md. App. 581 (1982)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-20" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised and recodified from <cite path="|03.03.07">COMAR 03.03.07</cite> to <cite path="|03.03.05">COMAR 03.03.05</cite> effective August 20, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1988)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> recodified to Regulation .01-1 and amended effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1894) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1894) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-01-31"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 31, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 400); emergency status expired March 1, 1994</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-07-05"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 5, 1994 (21:13 Md. R. 1154)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-18"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 13, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1536); amended permanently effective December 18, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1960)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-01-31"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite>-1C, D amended as an emergency provision effective January 31, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 400); emergency status expired March 1, 1994</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-07-05"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite>-1C, D amended effective July 5, 1994 (21:13 Md. R. 1154)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-18"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite>-1N amended as an emergency provision effective September 13, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1536); amended permanently effective December 18, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1960)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite>-1 adopted effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1894) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1894) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-18"><cite path="|03|03|05|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 13, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1536); amended permanently effective December 18, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1960) Regulation .06A amended as an emergency provision effective January 31, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 400); emergency status expired March 1, 1994</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-07-05"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective July 5, 1994 (21:13 Md. R. 1154)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26">Regulations .08 and .09 repealed effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1984) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1894) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective October 26, 1992 (19:21 Md. R. 1894) (19:22 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-28"><cite path="|03|03|05|.30">Regulation .30</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 28, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2318) (Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-12-10"><cite path="|03|03|05|.30">Regulation .30</cite> adopted effective December 10, 1990 (17:24 Md. R. 2836)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1993-04-26"><cite path="|03|03|05|.31">Regulation .31</cite> adopted effective April 26, 1993 (20:8 Md. R. 722)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 3, 2014 (41:4 Md. R. 299); May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|03|03|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite>-1 amended effective April 20, 2009 (36:8 Md. R. 594); May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562); March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 218)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .02J amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-06"><cite path="|03|03|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective December 6, 2018 (45:24 Md. R. 1162)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-13"><cite path="|03|03|05|.04|G.">Regulation .04G</cite> amended effective October 13, 2014 (41:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .04H amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .05C amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1844)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06">Regulation .06</cite>-1 adopted effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1844)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-06-16"><cite path="|03|03|05|.06">Regulation .06</cite>-1B, C amended effective June 16, 2008 (35:12 Md. R. 1120)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .10 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16"><cite path="|03|03|05|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective June 19, 2006 (33:12 Md. R. 996); May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .13 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .14 amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-11-27"><cite path="|03|03|05|.25|A.">Regulation .25A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 15, 2000 (27:12 Md. R. 1136); emergency status expired November 10, 2000; adopted permanently effective November 27, 2000 (27:23 Md. R. 2146)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|03|03|05|.28|C.">Regulation .28C</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 519)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-12-02"><cite path="|03|03|05|.29">Regulation .29</cite> amended effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .30D amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-16">Regulations .31B amended effective May 16, 2022 (49:10 Md. R. 562)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|03|03|05|.32">Regulation .32</cite> adopted effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 519)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
