<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Table Game Equipment</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Chip runner” means an employee of a facility operator whose job duties include transporting cash to the poker room cage or the poker cashier window at the main cage for dealers or players of the poker room to be exchanged for value chips.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Edge” means the surface of a gaming chip across which its thickness can be measured in a perpendicular line from one face to the other.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Edge spot” means an identifying characteristic used on the edge of each value chip issued by a facility operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Face” means each of the two surfaces of a gaming chip across which the diameter of the gaming chip can be measured.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Game account” means the funds that are available to a player for use at a dealer controlled electronic table game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Impress” means the roulette chips, which are used for gaming, that remain at each roulette table.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Impressment” means an inventory conducted on each impress.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Primary color” means the predominant color used on a gaming chip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“RFID card” means a card which contains a radio-frequency identification tag which can be used to determine the value on the face of the card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“RFID chip” means a value or roulette chip which contains a radio-frequency identification tag which can be used to determine the authenticity of the chip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Secondary color” means any color on the face or edge of the gaming chip that is used as a contrast to the gaming chip’s primary color.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Gaming Chips and Promotional Chips.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A gaming chip issued by a facility operator shall be in the form of a disk.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A gaming chip may not be issued by a facility operator or utilized in a facility until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The facility operator submits to the Commission for approval the design specifications of the proposed gaming chip, including a detailed schematic depicting the actual size and location of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each face, including any indentations or impressions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The edge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any colors, words, designs, graphics, or security measures contained on the gaming chip;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facility operator submits to the Commission, a sample of each gaming chip, manufactured in accordance with its approved design specifications; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission approves the gaming chip design under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To prevent the counterfeiting of the gaming chip, a gaming chip issued by a facility operator shall be designed and manufactured with graphics and security measures required to appear on the face or edge of a value chip under this regulation and Regulation.03 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prohibitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may not issue, use or allow a player to use in its facility, a gaming chip that it knows, or reasonably should know, is materially different from the sample of a gaming chip approved in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility operator or other person licensed by the Commission may not manufacture, sell or distribute to, or use in, a licensed facility outside of Maryland a gaming chip that has the same edge spot or design specifications as a chip approved for use in a facility in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Promotional Nongaming Chips.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may issue a promotional nongaming chip that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is unique from an approved gaming chip and promotional chip in size or color;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has no edge designs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On both faces, bears:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of the facility issuing the promotional nongaming chip; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Language that the promotional nongaming chip has no redeemable value.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A promotional nongaming chip may not be used for table game play in a facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To prevent confusion with approved gaming chips in use in Maryland facilities, the physical characteristics of promotional nongaming chips must be sufficiently distinguishable from approved gaming chips.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for approval a detailed schematic depicting the actual size, face, and any colors, words, designs, or graphics on the promotional nongaming chip under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may issue a promotional chip with value that is permitted to be used for gaming purposes in a licensed facility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The physical characteristics of promotional chips with value must be sufficiently distinguishable from approved gaming chips issued by any facility operator in Maryland so as to reasonably ensure that the promotional chips with value will not to be confused with approved gaming chips and promotional nongaming chips.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for approval, under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>, a detailed schematic depicting the actual size, face and any colors, words, designs or graphics on the promotional gaming chip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At a minimum, a promotional gaming chip shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be unique in terms of size or color;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have no edge designs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Bear the name of the facility operator issuing the promotional gaming chip; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Contain language on both faces stating value of the promotional chip.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A promotional chip with value may be redeemed only at a gaming table in which a player wagers against the house.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The dealer shall deposit the promotional chip with value into the drop box attached to the gaming table at the time the winning wager is paid or the losing wager is collected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the wager wins, it shall be paid in accordance with the terms and conditions of the promotional chip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Value Chips.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may issue and use value chips in denominations of $1, $2, $2.50, $5, $20, $25, $100, $500, $1,000, $5,000, $10,000, $25,000, and other denominations approved in advance by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A primary color may not be used as a secondary color on a value chip of another denomination if its use on the edge is reasonably likely to cause confusion as to the chip’s denomination when the edge alone is visible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A manufacturer shall submit sample color disks to the Commission that identify all primary and secondary colors to be used for the manufacture of value chips for facility operators in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may not approve a primary color for use in a value chip unless it visually appears, when viewed in daylight or incandescent light, as the following colors for these denominations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>$1, white;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>$2, blue;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>$2.50, pink;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>$5, red;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>$20, yellow;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>$25, green;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>$100, black;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>$500, purple;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>$1,000, fire orange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>$5,000, brown;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>$10,000, silver; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>$25,000, gold.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After the Commission has approved a manufacturer’s primary or secondary color for a gaming chip, the color shall be consistently manufactured in accordance with the approved sample color disk.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>At least once on any location of each face of a value chip, a value chip issued by a facility operator must contain identifying characteristics that are applied in a manner ensuring that each identifying characteristic is clearly visible and remains a permanent part of the value chip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The identifying characteristics required under <cite path="36|05|02|.03|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> shall be visible to surveillance employees using the licensed facility’s surveillance system, and include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The denomination of the value chip, expressed in numbers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, logo or other Commission-approved identification of the facility operator issuing the value chip; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The letters “MD” and the name of the city or county in which the licensed facility is located.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>In addition to the characteristics specified in <cite path="36|05|02|.03|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, a value chip in a denomination of $100 or more must contain a design or other identifying characteristic that is unique to the gaming chip manufacturer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>After the Commission approves a manufacturer’s value chip design or characteristic under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The manufacturer has the exclusive right to use that design or characteristic on any denomination of value chip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The approved unique design or characteristic:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May be used on all value chips manufactured for use in Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be changed only after receiving the Commission’s written approval of a new unique design or other identifying characteristic under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Each value chip issued by a facility operator must contain an edge spot that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is applied in a manner that ensures the edge spot:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is clearly visible on the edge and on each face of the value chip; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Remains a permanent part of the value chip; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is created using both:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The primary color of the chip; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One or more secondary colors; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Includes a design, pattern, or other feature that an individual may use to identify, through the facility’s surveillance system, the denomination of a particular value chip that is in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A stack of gaming chips;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The table inventory; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other location when only the edge of the value chip is visible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall use as a secondary color to make an edge spot on a particular denomination of value chip only a secondary color that is reasonably likely to differentiate the facility operator’s value chip from the same denomination of value chip issued by any other facility operator in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>If an approved value chip uses a single secondary color, no other facility operator may use a similar secondary color as the sole secondary color on the same denomination of value chip unless it is used in a different pattern or design approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not use the identical combination of secondary colors on the same denomination of value chip unless it is used in a different pattern or design approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>A value chip issued by a facility operator is limited to a specific size for each denomination:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Less than $500 must have a uniform diameter of 1-9/16 inch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>$500 and $1,000 must have a uniform diameter of 1-9/16 inch or 1-11/16 inch; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>$5,000 or more must have a uniform diameter of 1-11/16 inch.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>In addition to the features that are required under this regulation to appear on the face and edge of a value chip:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each value chip with a denomination below $100 must contain at least one anti-counterfeiting measure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each value chip with a denomination of $100 or more must contain at least two anti-counterfeiting measures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Roulette Chips.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall issue a roulette chip solely for the purpose of gaming at roulette.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least once on any location of each face of a roulette chip, a roulette chip issued by a facility operator must contain identifying characteristics that are applied in a manner ensuring that each identify characteristic is clearly visible and remains a permanent part of the roulette chip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The identifying characteristics required under <cite path="36|05|02|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be visible to surveillance employees using the facility’s surveillance system, and include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, logo or other Commission-approved identification of the facility operator issuing the roulette chip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A unique design, insert or symbol that will permit a set of roulette chips being used at a particular roulette table to be distinguished from the roulette chips being used at another roulette table in the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The word “Roulette”;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Color and design combinations distinguish the roulette chips of a player at a particular roulette table from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The roulette chips of another player at the same roulette table; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The value chips issued by a facility operator; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An edge spot that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is applied in a manner which ensures that the edge spot;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is clearly visible on the edge and on each face of the roulette chip; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Remains a permanent part of the roulette chip; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is created by using the colors approved for the face of the particular roulette chip in combination with one or more other colors that provides a contrast with the color on the face of the roulette chip and that enables the roulette chip to be distinguished from the roulette chips issued by any other facility operator; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Includes a design, pattern or other feature that an individual may use to identify, through the facility’s surveillance system, the player to whom the roulette chip has been assigned when the roulette chip is placed in a stack of gaming chips or in any other location where only the edge of the roulette chip is visible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Roulette Chips—Permitted Uses, Inventory, and Impressment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A roulette chip shall be issued to a particular roulette table and be used for gaming at that table only, and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A roulette chip used at a particular roulette table must have the same design, insert or symbol as required under <cite path="|36|05|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility operator or an employee may not knowingly allow a player to remove a roulette chip from the roulette table to which it was issued.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A player at a roulette table may not purchase or be permitted to game with roulette chips that are identical in color and design to any roulette chip purchased by another player at the same table. When a player purchases a roulette chip, the dealer shall place a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Roulette chip of the same color and design in a slot or receptacle attached to the outer rim of the roulette wheel, or in another device or location approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Marker button denoting the value of a stack of 20 roulette chips of the same color and design in the slot, receptacle or other device.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At least once every 3 months, a floorperson, or higher-ranking individual specified in the facility operator’s internal controls, shall complete an impressment of the Roulette chips assigned to a roulette table; and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall record the results of the impressment in the chip inventory ledger required under <cite path="|36|05|02|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If additional roulette chips are required to restore the impress, the floorperson, or higher-ranking individual specified in the facility operator’s internal controls, shall complete a Roulette Chip Impressment Form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The completed Roulette Chip Impressment Form required under <cite path="36|05|02|.05|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be maintained by the accounting department and contain at least the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date and time of preparation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The design schematic of the chip, including its primary color and the applicable table number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The number of roulette chips needed to restore the impress;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The signature of the individual who completes the Roulette Chip Impressment Form and the impressment for the table; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The signature of the main bank cashier or chip bank cashier who issued the roulette chips to restore the impress.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The accounting department shall immediately report a discrepancy in the impressment to a Commission compliance representative on a written report that includes at least the following for each roulette chip color and design:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The balance on hand at the beginning of the 3-month period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of roulette chips distributed to the roulette table during the 3-month period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The number of roulette chips returned to inventory during the 3-month period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The balance on hand at the end of the 3-month period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Tournament Chips.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator conducts a table game tournament, the tournament shall be conducted using tournament chips.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The identifying characteristics of a tournament chip must include at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, logo, or other approved identification of the facility operator issuing the tournament chip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The word “Tournament”;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The denomination of the chip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The phrase “No Cash Value”;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Color or design combinations that distinguish the tournament chips from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Roulette chips used for the play of roulette at the facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Value chips issued by a facility operator in the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Poker rake chips.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall store tournament chips in a secure area approved in advance by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall conduct an inventory of all tournament chips prior to the start and after the completion of each tournament.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall send a weekly report to Commission compliance representatives of a discrepancy in the inventory on a report that shall include the balance for each denomination of tournament chip on hand at the beginning of the tournament and the balance on hand at the end of each tournament.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Poker Rake Chips.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To facilitate the collection of the rake, a facility operator may use poker rake chips in the poker room.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Poker rake chips:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall only be used by dealers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May only be substituted for value chips that have been collected as part of the rake prior to the rake being placed in a drop box.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A dealer shall keep unused poker rake chips in the table inventory container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The denominations that may be used for poker rake chips are $2, $3, or $4.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The identifying characteristics of a poker rake chip must include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, logo or other approved identification of the facility operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The words “Poker Rake Chip”;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One of the following denominations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“$2”;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“$3”;or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“$4”; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Color or design combinations to distinguish the poker rake chips from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Roulette chips used for the play of roulette at the facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Tournament chips used for tournament play at the facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Value chips issued by any facility operator in the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Additional Gaming Chips; Removing Chips from Use.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Value Chips.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 120 days of the commencement of table games at a facility, the facility operator shall have at least one Commission-approved set of value chips that may be used as a back-up for $100 and $500 value chips in active use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A back-up set of value chips maintained for use by a facility operator shall have secondary colors that are different from the secondary colors of the value chips in active use and may use a different shade of the primary color.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A back-up set of value chips shall conform to the color and design requirements in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Roulette Chips.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall have at least one reserve set of roulette chips for each color roulette chip used in the facility with a design insert or symbol different from the roulette chips comprising the primary sets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A back-up set of roulette chips must conform to the color and design requirements in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>RFID chips. If a facility operator uses RFID chips for its value or roulette chips, the facility operator may submit a request to the Commission for waiver of the requirements in §A or B of this regulation B that shall include at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A detailed description of the RFID technology and devices that will be used at the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A detailed description of how the RFID chips and related equipment will be used in the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A detailed explanation of how the use of the RFID chips and related equipment will reduce or eliminate the potential use of counterfeit value or roulette chips; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The approximate length of time it will take the facility operator to install the necessary devices and related equipment for the RFID technology to be operational in the facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The facility operator shall remove a set of gaming chips in use from active play when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator reasonably believes that the facility is taking on multiple counterfeit chips valued at $100 or more so as to call into question the security and integrity of the gaming chip set;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility operator determines there is an impropriety or defect in the use of a set of chips makes removal of the chips in active use necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission directs a facility operator to remove a set of chips from active use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall place into active play a Commission- approved back-up set of value chips or a reserve set of roulette chips required under §§A and B of this regulation when an active set is removed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Before a set of chips in active use is removed from play, the facility operator shall notify the Commission compliance representatives of the impending removal and the reasons for the removal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall immediately notify a Commission compliance representative of the discovery of counterfeit value chips.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Plaques.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A plaque issued by a facility operator shall be a solid, one-piece object constructed entirely of plastic or other substance, and a plaque shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be square, rectangular, or elliptical in shape;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have at least two, but not more than six, smooth, plane surfaces;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have at least two faces opposite and parallel to each other and identical in shape;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall not issue a plaque or allow its use in a facility unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The facility operator submitted design specifications of the proposed plaque to the Commission that included a detailed schematic depicting the actual size and location of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each face;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The edge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any colors, words, designs, graphics, or security measures on the plaque including the minimum identifying characteristics listed in <cite path="36|05|02|.09|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>, the facility operator made available for the Commission’s inspection a sample plaque of each denomination to be manufactured and used in accordance with its approved design specifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission approved the facility operator’s submissions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The facility operator submitted to the Commission a system of internal procedures and administrative and accounting controls governing the distribution, redemption, receipt and inventory of plaques, by serial number that the Commission approved as part of the facility operator’s internal controls.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Dimensions of a Plaque.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The face of a square plaque shall have a surface area of not less than 9 square inches.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The face of a rectangular or elliptical plaque may not be less than 3 inches in length by 2 inches in width.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The length and width of an elliptical plaque shall be measured by its axes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A plaque issued by a facility operator shall be designed and manufactured with sufficient graphics or other security measures to prevent, to the extent possible, the counterfeiting of the plaque.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Denominations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may issue and use plaques in denominations of $5,000 or $10,000, and in other denominations approved by the Commission in advance under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A plaque of a specific denomination used by a facility operator shall be in a shape and of a size that is identical to the shape and size of all other plaques of that denomination issued by the facility operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The size and shape of each denomination of plaque issued by a facility operator must be readily distinguishable from the size and shape of every other denomination of plaque issued by the facility operator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A plaque issued by a facility operator must contain identifying characteristics that appear at least once on each face of the plaque and are applied in a manner that ensures each identifying characteristic is clearly visible and remains a permanent part of the plaque.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The characteristics required under <cite path="36|05|02|.09|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> must be visible to surveillance employees using the licensed facility’s surveillance system, and shall include at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The denomination of the plaque, expressed in numbers of at least 3/8 inch in height;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, logo, or other approved identification of the facility operator issuing the plaque; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A unique serial number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not issue, use, or allow a player to use in its facility, any plaque that it knows, or reasonably should know, is materially different from the sample of that plaque approved in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Permissible Wagers; Exchange and Redemption of Chips and Plaques.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Wagering at table games in a facility shall be conducted with gaming chips, plaques, electronic wagering credits, and other wagering instruments approved in advance by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A value chip previously issued by a facility operator that is not in active use by that facility operator may not be used for any gaming purpose in a facility, and may be redeemed only at the cage as provided in <cite path="36|05|02|.10|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall issue a gaming chip or plaque to a player only at the request of the player, and may not be given as change in any transaction other than a gaming transaction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A gaming chip or plaque shall be issued to player by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A dealer at a banking or nonbanking table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The poker room cage, poker room impressed bank or the poker window cashier at the main cage; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A chip runner to a player seated at a poker table at which a game is in progress.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A player may redeem a plaque or value chip only at the cage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §§L and M of this regulation, or as otherwise approved in advance by the Commission, a facility operator shall redeem a gaming chip or plaque that it issued only from players.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Roulette Chips.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A player may present a roulette chip for redemption only at the roulette table from which it was issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a player presents a roulette chip for redemption, a dealer shall accept it in exchange for an equivalent amount of value chips.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Value Chips at Roulette.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may permit, limit or prohibit the use of a value chip in gaming at roulette in accordance with its rules submission submitted under <cite path="36.05.03.19">COMAR 36.05.03.19</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a value chip is use at roulette, the facility operator and its employees shall keep accurate account of the wagers being made with value chips so that wager made by one player are not confused with the wagers made by another player at the table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A gaming chip or plaque is solely evidence of a debt that the issuing facility operator owes to an individual legally in possession of the gaming chip or plaque, and it remains the property of the issuing facility operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Redemption at the Facility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall have the right at any time to demand that an individual possessing a gaming chip or plaque surrender the gaming chip or plaque for redemption in accordance with this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless a gaming chip or plaque was obtained or is being used unlawfully, a facility operator shall promptly redeem its gaming chip or plaque presented by a player.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall redeem its value chip or plaque by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Exchanging the value chip or plaque for an equivalent amount of cash; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exchanging the value chip or plaque for a check issued by the facility operator in the amount of the value chip or plaque surrendered and dated the day of the redemption.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Redemption by Mail.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the requirements of <cite path="36|05|02|.10|J.">§J of this regulation</cite>, if a player requests by mail to redeem value chips, in any amount, by mail, a facility operator may effectuate the redemption in accordance with its approved internal controls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility operator’s internal controls for redemption of a value chip by mail shall, at a minimum, include procedures for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facility operator’s issuance of a check to the player; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Transfer of a surrendered value chip to the chip bank in a documented transaction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall accept, exchange, use or redeem only a gaming chip or plaque that the facility operator has issued and may not knowingly accept, exchange, use or redeem a gaming chip or plaque, or an object that appears to be a gaming chip or plaque, that has been issued by any other facility operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="36|05|02|.10|L.">§L of this regulation</cite>, a facility operator may accept and redeem a value chip issued by another facility operator in the State from a player.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Employee Receiving a Value Chip as Gratuity.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A video lottery employee of a facility operator may receive a value chip as a gratuity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A video lottery employee may receive a value chip in exchange for food or beverage that a player purchases from the video lottery employee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A video lottery employee of a facility operator who receives a value chip as a gratuity, or in exchange for food or beverage, shall redeem the value chip prior to leaving the facility at the end of the work shift during which the employee received the value chip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A value chip received by a video lottery employee shall be redeemed at the cage or at another secure location approved in advance by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A value chip received by a video lottery employee that is redeemed at a noncage employee redemption site shall be exchanged on a daily basis with the cage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall include in its internal controls a means of ensuring the proper exchange and accounting of a value chip received as a gratuity or for the purchase of food and beverage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Redemption of Facility Chips From Another Operator.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall promptly redeem its own value chip that is presented to it by another facility operator in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall include in its internal controls a system for the exchange, with other legally operated facility operators, of a value chip that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is in the facility operator’s possession that has been issued by another facility operator in the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The facility operator has issued that is presented to it for redemption by another facility operator in the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall post, in a prominent place on the front of the main cage, any satellite cage and the poker room cage, a sign that reads as follows: "Gaming chips or plaques issued by another facility may not be used, exchanged or redeemed in this facility."</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Chips and Plaques—Receipt, Inventory, Security, Storage, and Destruction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Receipt.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A shipment of gaming chips or plaques that is received from a manufacturer or supplier shall be unloaded and transported to a secure area, which is covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system, by at least two employees of the facility operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The chips or plaques shall then be opened and checked by at least two employees, who shall promptly report to a Commission compliance representative any deviation between the invoice accompanying the shipment of gaming chips or plaques and the actual chips or plaques received, or any defects found in the chips or plaques.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The functions required under §A(1) and (2) of this regulation shall be performed by at least the following employees of the facility operator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A supervisor from the accounting department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An employee from the security department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inventory.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After a shipment of gaming chips or plaques is checked as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the employees identified in <cite path="36|05|02|.11|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite> shall record, in a chip inventory ledger, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Denomination of the value chips and plaques received;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Number of each denomination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Serial numbers of the value chips and plaques received;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For any roulette chips received, the number and description of the roulette chips received;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Date of the receipt;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Signatures and license numbers of the employees who checked the chips and plaques.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the value chips or roulette chips are not to be immediately put into active use, the chip inventory ledger must also identify the storage location of the chips.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Storage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A gaming chip or plaque not in active use shall be stored in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A vault located in the main bank;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Locked cabinets in the main cage; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Another restricted storage area approved in advance by the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A gaming chip or plaque may not be stored in the same storage area as dice, cards, pai gow tiles or any other table game equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When a gaming chip or plaque is removed from or returned to an approved storage area, at least the two employees identified in <cite path="36|05|02|.11|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite> shall be present and ensure that the chip inventory ledger contains the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Signatures and license numbers of the employees supervising the transaction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Quantity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If applicable, the serial numbers and dollar amounts for each denomination of value chip or plaque;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Number and description of the roulette chip;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Specific storage area being entered; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Reason for the entry into the storage area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>At the end of each gaming day, a facility operator shall compute and record the unredeemed liability for each denomination of value chip and plaque according to procedures specified in the facility operator’s internal controls.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Inventory.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall inventory all sets of value chips, roulette chips and plaques in its possession and record the result of the inventory in the chip inventory ledger.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inventory required under <cite path="36|05|02|.11|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be conducted at least once every month for value chips and plaques and at least once every 3 months for roulette chips.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a facility operator’s inventory procedures incorporate the sealing of the locked compartment containing the facility’s value chips, roulette chips, and plaques not in active use, a physical inventory of value chips, roulette chips, and plaques not in active use is required to be conducted annually.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall include in its internal controls the procedures to be utilized to inventory value chips, roulette chips, and plaques.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Destruction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 5 days prior to the destruction of a gaming chip or plaque, a facility operator shall notify a Commission compliance representative of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date and the location at which the destruction will be performed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Denomination, number, and when applicable, the serial number and amount of value chips or plaques to be destroyed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Description and number of roulette chips to be destroyed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Detailed explanation of the method of destruction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The destruction of a gaming chip or plaque shall be carried out in the presence of at least the two employees identified in <cite path="36|05|02|.11|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall record in the chip inventory ledger the names and license numbers of all employees and nonemployees involved in each destruction, and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The denomination, quantity, total value, and serial number, if applicable, of all value chips or plaques destroyed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The description and number of roulette chips destroyed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The signatures and license numbers of the individuals who carried out the destruction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The date and location where the destruction took place.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall ensure that at all times there is adequate security for all gaming chips and plaques in the facility operator’s possession.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Dice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in §§B and C of this regulation, each die used in the play of table games shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be formed in the shape of a perfect cube and of a size not smaller than 0.750 inch on each side nor any larger than 0.775 inch on each side, with a tolerance of +/- 0.005;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be transparent and made exclusively of cellulose except for the spots, name or logo of the facility operator, and serial number or letters on the die;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be perfectly flat on the surface of each of its sides, with the spots contained in each side flush with the area surrounding them;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have all edges and corners perfectly square and forming 90 degree angles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Have the texture and finish of each side identical to the texture and finish of all other sides;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Have its weight equally distributed throughout the cube with no side of the cube heavier or lighter than any other side of the cube;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Have the six sides bearing white circular spots from one to six respectively with the diameter of each spot equal to the diameter of every other spot on the die;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Have spots arranged so that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The side containing one spot is directly opposite the side containing six spots;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The side containing two spots is directly opposite the side containing five spots; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The side containing three spots is directly opposite the side containing four spots;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Have each spot shall be placed on the die by drilling into the surface of the cube and filling the drilled out portion with a compound which is equal in weight to the weight of the cellulose drilled out and which forms a permanent bond with the cellulose cube and extends into the cube exactly the same distance as every other spot extends into the cube to an accuracy tolerance of 0.0004 inch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Have imprinted or impressed on the die a serial number or letters and the name or logo of the facility operator using the die.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pai Gow and Pai Gow Poker. Dice used in the table games of pai gow and pai gow poker must comply with the requirements of <cite path="36|05|02|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, except as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each die must be formed in the shape of a perfect cube and of a size not smaller than 0.637 inch on each side nor any larger than 0.643 inch on each side;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>With the Commission’s approval, a facility operator may have an identifying mark imprinted or impressed on each die instead of the name or logo of the facility operator; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The spots on each die do not have to be equal in diameter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sic Bo. Dice used in the table game of sic bo must comply with <cite path="36|05|02|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, except each die may be formed in the shape of a cube 0.625 inch on each side with ball edge corners.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Dice may not be used in a facility unless a detailed schematic depicting the actual size and color of the dice, and the location of serial numbers, letters or logos on the dice, has been submitted to, and approved by, the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Dice — Receipt, Storage, Inspection, and Removal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Receipt.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A shipment of dice that is received from a manufacturer or supplier shall be immediately unloaded and transported to a secure area which is covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system under the supervision of at least two employees of the facility operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The boxes of dice shall then be inspected by at least two employees of the facility operator to ensure that the seals on each box are intact, unbroken and free from tampering.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Boxes that do not appear to be intact, unbroken and free from tampering shall be immediately inspected to ensure that the dice in those boxes conform to the requirements of this chapter and there is no evidence of tampering with them.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If dice inspected as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.13|A.|(2)|(a)">§A(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> show no evidence of tampering, they shall be placed, along with boxes of dice that are intact, unbroken and free from tampering, for storage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dice shall be stored in a storage area that the Commission has approved in advance under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The functions required under §A(1), (2), and (3) of this regulation shall be performed by at least the following employees of the facility operator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A floor supervisor or above; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An employee from the security department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Storage. The Commission-approved storage area must have two separate locks, to which access shall be controlled as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The security department shall maintain one key and the gaming operations department shall maintain the other key; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An employee of the gaming operations department, below a floorperson in the organizational hierarchy, may not have access to the gaming operations department key.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Dice which are to be distributed to gaming pits or tables for use in gaming shall be distributed from the approved storage area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Once each gaming day and at other times as may be necessary, a floorperson or above, in the presence of a security department employee, shall remove the appropriate number of dice for that gaming day from the approved storage area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Envelopes and containers used to hold or transport dice must be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transparent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designed or constructed with seals so that any tampering is evident; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Commission and approved under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Inspection and Distribution. Dice shall be inspected and distributed to the gaming tables in accordance with one of the following alternatives:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Alternative No. 1.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The floorperson or above, and the security department employee who removed the dice from the approved storage area, shall distribute sufficient dice directly to the pit manager or above in each pit, or place them in a locked compartment in the pit stand, the keys to which shall be in the possession of the pit manager or above.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Immediately upon opening a table for gaming, the floorperson or above shall distribute a set of dice to the table.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>To ensure that the dice are in a condition to ensure fair play and otherwise conform to the requirements of this chapter, at the time of receipt of a set of dice, a floorperson at each craps, pai gow, pai gow poker, sic bo or mini-craps table, shall, in the presence of the dealer, inspect the dice with a micrometer or any other instrument approved by the Commission to perform the function of a micrometer, a balancing caliper, a steel set square and a magnet.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The instruments described in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(1)|(b)|(i)">§F(1)(b)(i) of this regulation</cite> shall be kept in a compartment at each craps table or pit stand and shall be at all times readily available for use by the Commission compliance representatives or other Commission employees.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The inspection required under <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(1)|(b)|(i)">§F(1)(b)(i) of this regulation</cite> shall be performed on a flat surface which allows the dice inspection to be observed through the facility operator’s surveillance system and by any persons in the immediate vicinity of the table.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Following the inspection required under <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(1)|(b)|(i)">§F(1)(b)(i) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For craps, the floorperson shall, in the presence of a dealer, place the dice in a cup on the table for use in gaming;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For mini-craps, the floorperson shall, in the presence of a dealer, place the dice in a cup on the table for use in gaming;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>For sic bo, the floorperson shall, in the presence of the dealer, place the required number of dice into the shaker and seal or lock the shaker, and the floorperson shall secure the sic bo shaker to the table in the presence of the dealer who observed the inspection; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>For pai gow and pai gow poker, the floorperson shall, in the presence of the dealer, place the dice in the pai gow shaker.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The floorperson or above shall place extra dice for the dice reserve in the pit stand.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Dice in the pit stand shall be placed in a locked compartment, the keys to which shall be in the possession of the floorperson or above.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>No dice taken from the pit stand reserve may be used for actual gaming until the dice have been inspected in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(1)|(b)|(i)">§F(1)(b)(i) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Alternative No. 2.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The pit manager or above and the security department employee who removed the dice from the approved storage area shall distribute the dice directly to the following facility operator’s employees who shall perform an inspection in each pit:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For craps and mini-craps, a floorperson in the presence of another floorperson, both of whom are assigned the responsibility of supervising the operation and conduct of a craps or mini-craps game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For sic bo, pai gow and pai gow poker, a floorperson, in the presence of another floorperson, both of whom are assigned the responsibility of supervising the operation and conduct of sic bo, pai gow or pai gow poker games;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>For storage of the dice for the dice reserve in the pit stand, to the pit manager or above.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To ensure that the dice are in a condition to ensure fair play and otherwise conform to the requirements of this chapter, at the time of receipt of a set of dice, the dice shall be inspected by one of the individuals listed in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(2)|(a)">§F(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> with a micrometer or other instrument approved by the Commission which performs the same function as a micrometer, a balancing caliper, a steel set square, and a magnet.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The instruments described in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(2)|(b)">§F(2)(b) of this regulation</cite> shall be kept at the pit stand and shall be at all times readily available for use by the Commission compliance representatives or other Commission employees.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The inspection required under <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(2)|(a)">§F(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall be performed on a flat surface which allows the dice inspection to be observed through the facility operator’s surveillance system and by any persons in the immediate vicinity of the pit stand.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>After completion of the inspection, the dice shall be distributed as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For craps and mini-craps, the floorperson who inspected the dice shall, in the presence of the other floorperson who observed the inspection, distribute the dice to the floorperson assigned at each craps table or to the floorperson assigned at each mini-craps table, and the craps floorperson or the mini-craps floorperson shall, in the presence of the dealer, place the dice in a cup on the table for use in gaming.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For sic bo, the floorperson who inspected the dice shall, in the presence of the other floorperson who observed the inspection, place the required number of dice into the shaker and seal or lock the shaker, and the floorperson shall then secure the sic bo shaker to the table in the presence of the other floorperson who observed the inspection.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>For pai gow and pai gow poker, the floorperson who inspected the dice shall, in the presence of the other floorperson who observed the inspection, distribute the dice directly to the dealer at each pai gow table, and the dealer shall immediately place the dice in the pai gow shaker.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The pit manager or above shall place extra sets of dice for the dice reserve in the pit stand, as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Dice in the pit stand shall be placed in a locked compartment, the keys to which shall be in the possession of the pit manager or above.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Except as otherwise provided in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(2)|(e)">§F(2)(e) of this regulation</cite>, dice taken from the reserve in the pit stand shall be reinspected by a floorperson or above in the presence of another floorperson or above in accordance with the inspection procedures set forth in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(2)|(b)">§F(2)(b) of this regulation</cite> prior to their use for actual gaming.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Previously inspected reserve dice may be used for gaming without being reinspected if the dice are maintained in a locked compartment in the pit stand in accordance with the following procedures:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For craps and mini-craps, a set of five dice, after being inspected, shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container, to which shall be attached a label that identifies the date of inspection and contains the signatures of those responsible for the inspection shall be attached to the envelope or container.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For sic bo, three dice, after being inspected, shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container or sealed or locked in a sic bo shaker, to which shall be attached a label or seal that identifies the date of inspection and contains the signatures of those responsible for the inspection shall, respectively, be attached to each envelope or container or placed over the area that allows access to open the sic bo shaker.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>For pai gow and pai gow poker, a set of three dice, after being inspected, shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container, to which shall be attached a label that identifies the date of inspection and contains the signatures of those responsible for the inspection shall be attached to each envelope or container.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Removal. A facility operator shall remove dice at any time of the gaming day and submit a Dice Discrepancy Report as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.13|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If there is any indication of tampering, flaws or other defects that might affect the integrity or fairness of the game; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the request of a Commission compliance representative or other Commission employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the end of each gaming day or at other times as may be necessary, a floorperson or above, other than the individual who originally inspected the dice, shall visually inspect each die that was used for play for evidence of tampering. Evidence of tampering shall be immediately reported to a Commission compliance representative by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completing a two-part Dice Discrepancy Report; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submitting the completed Dice Discrepancy Report and the dice to a Commission compliance representative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dice showing evidence of tampering shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A label shall be attached to each envelope or container that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identifies the table number, date, and time the dice were removed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Contains the signatures of the person assigned to directly operate and conduct the game at that table and the floorperson assigned the responsibility for supervising the operation and conduct of the game.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A floorperson or above, or a security department employee responsible for delivering the dice to the casino compliance representatives, shall also sign the label.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Commission compliance representative receiving the dice shall sign the original and duplicate copy of the Dice Discrepancy Report and retain the original copy.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Commission compliance representative shall return the duplicate copy to the pit and maintain it in a secure place within the pit until it is collected by a security department employee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other dice that were used for play shall be put into envelopes or containers when removed from active use at the table.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A label shall be attached to each envelope or container which:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identifies the table number, date and time the dice were removed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Contains the signatures of the person assigned to directly operate and conduct the game at that table and the floorperson assigned the responsibility for supervising the operation and conduct of the game.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The envelope or container shall be sealed and maintained within the pit until it is collected by a security department employee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Reserve dice in the locked compartment in a pit stand at the end of the gaming day may be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collected and transported to the security department for cancellation or destruction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Returned to the approved storage area; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Retained in the locked compartment in the pit stand for future use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Reserve dice in the locked compartment in a pit stand at the end of the gaming day that are to be destroyed or cancelled shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container, with a label attached to each envelope or container which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identifies the pit stand where the reserve dice were being stored;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identifies the date and time the dice where placed in the envelope or container; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contains the signature of the pit manager or above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>At the end of each gaming day or at least once each gaming day, as designated by the facility operator and approved in advance by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>, and at other times as may be necessary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|K.|(2)">§K(2) of this regulation</cite>, a security department employee shall collect and sign all envelopes or containers of used dice and reserve dice that are to be destroyed or cancelled and transport the dice to the security department for cancellation or destruction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an alternative procedure for collecting, destroying or cancelling dice described in §(K)(1) of this regulation has been submitted to, and approved by, the Commission, a security department employee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall collect all envelopes or containers and return them to the security department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May sign the envelopes or containers; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The security department employee shall also collect any duplicate copies of Dice Discrepancy Reports.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>An assistant table games shift manager or above may collect all reserve dice in a locked compartment in a pit stand.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If collected:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reserve dice shall be returned to the approved storage area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reserve dice shall be collected at the end of each gaming day or at least once each gaming day, as designated by the facility operator and approved in advance by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for dice maintained in a locked compartment in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>, if the reserve dice are not collected, all dice in the dice reserve shall be reinspected in accordance with one of the alternatives listed in <cite path="36|05|02|.13|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> prior to their use for gaming.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Facility operators shall submit to the Commission for approval internal control procedures for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A dice inventory system which includes, at a minimum, records of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Number of three and five dice sticks, and the corresponding number of single die, received from a manufacturer or supplier;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Balance of three and five dice sticks, and the corresponding number of single die, on hand;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Number of three and five dice sticks removed from storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Number of three and five dice sticks returned to storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Number of single die destroyed or canceled;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Date of each transaction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Signatures of the individuals involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A daily reconciliation of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Number of three or five dice sticks distributed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Number of single die destroyed or cancelled;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Number of three or five dice sticks returned to the approved storage area; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Reserve three or five dice sticks in a locked compartment in a pit stand, if any; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A physical inventory of all dice at least once every 3 months:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That shall be performed by an individual with no incompatible functions and shall be verified to the balance of dice on hand required under <cite path="36|05|02|.13|M.|(1)|(a)">§M(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For which discrepancies shall immediately be reported to a Commission compliance representative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Destruction or Cancellation of Dice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Other than those retained for Commission or facility operator inspection, destruction or cancellation of dice shall be completed within 7 days of collection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cancellation shall be accomplished by drilling a circular hole of at least 1/4 inch in diameter through the center of the die.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Destruction shall be accomplished by shredding or crushing the die.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The destruction or cancellation of dice must take place in a secure location in the facility that is covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Rotation and Replacement of Dice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A set of five dice used at a craps or mini-craps table shall be changed at least once every 24 hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A new set of dice shall be used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When a craps or mini-craps table is reopened for gaming;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a die goes off the table during play and is lost;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If a die show signs of tampering or alteration; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A die is otherwise marked, chipped, scratched, or no longer suitable for play.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dice that have been placed in a shaker for use in gaming may not remain on a table for more than 24 hours in the games of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pai Gow Tiles; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pai Gow Poker.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Sic Bo Shaker Security Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Storage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Manual and automated sic bo shakers that have not been filled with dice may be stored in a locked compartment in a pit stand.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An automated sic bo dice shaker which has been filled with dice shall be secured to the sic bo table at all times.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the end of each gaming day, a pit manager or above shall inspect all sic bo shakers that have been placed in use for gaming for evidence of tampering.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evidence of tampering shall be immediately reported to a Commission compliance representative on a written report that includes at least:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date and time when the tampering was discovered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The name and signature of the individual discovering the tampering;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The table number where the sic bo shaker was used; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The name and signature of the employee who is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Assigned to directly operate and conduct the game at the sic bo table; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The supervisor assigned the responsibility for supervising the operation and conduct of the game at the sic bo table.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise approved by the Commission, cards used to play table games shall be in decks of 52 cards with each card identical in size and shape to every other card in the deck.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Nothing in this regulation shall be construed to prohibit a manufacturer from manufacturing decks of cards with one or more jokers in each deck.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Jokers may not be used by the facility operator in the play of any game unless authorized by the rules of the game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise approved by the Commission, each deck shall be composed of cards in four suits: diamonds, spades, clubs and hearts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each suit shall be composed of 13 cards:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ace;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>King;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Queen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Jack;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>10;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>9;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>8;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>7;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>5;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>4;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>3; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>2.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If approved in advance by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">36.05.03.16</cite>, the face of the ace, king, queen, jack and 10 may contain an additional marking that will permit a dealer, prior to exposing the dealer’s hole card at the game of blackjack, to determine if the value of the hole card gives the dealer a blackjack.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The backs of each card in a deck shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be identical and may not contain any marking, symbol or design that may enable an individual to know the identity of any element printed on the face of the card or that will in any way differentiate the back of the card from any other card in the deck;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be designed to diminish the ability of any individual to place concealed markings thereon; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contain the name or logo of the facility operator using the cards, unless otherwise approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each deck of cards shall be packaged separately or in a batch containing the number of decks selected by a facility operator for use in a particular table game.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each package of cards shall be sealed in a manner approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite> to reveal evidence of any tampering with the package.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If multiple decks of cards are packaged and sealed in a batch, the package must have a label that indicates or contain a window that reveals an adequate description of the contents of the package, including the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of the facility operator for which the cards were manufactured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Colors of the backs of the cards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Date that the cards were manufactured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Total number of cards in the batch; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Total number of decks in the batch.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Individual decks of cards that are packaged and sealed in a multideck batch may not be separated from the batch for independent use at a table game.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The cards used by a facility operator for poker shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Visually distinguishable from the cards used by that facility operator for other banked table game play; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Made of plastic.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Each facility operator that offers the game of poker shall have and use on a daily basis at least four decks of cards with visually distinguishable card backings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Card backings may be distinguished by different logos, different colors or different design patterns.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall submit, as part of its internal controls, the procedure for distributing and rotating the four visually distinguishable decks of cards required for use in the game of poker.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>At a minimum, all poker cards that have been in play at least 4 months shall be replaced.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Cards may not be utilized in a facility unless a schematic depicting the face and backs of the cards, the colors, words, designs and graphics has been submitted to, and approved by, the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>RFID Cards. A facility operator may use RFID cards in table games if the Commission has reviewed and approved the facility operator’s plan for use of RFID cards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A facility operator’s request for Commission approval of the use of RFID cards shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A detailed description of the RFID technology and devices that will be used at the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A detailed description of the RFID technology security features that will ensure the integrity of the table games where RFID cards are in use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A detailed description of how the RFID cards and related equipment will be used in the facility; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other information required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Cards — Receipt, Storage, Inspection, and Removal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Receipt.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A shipment of decks of cards that is received from a manufacturer or supplier shall be unloaded immediately and transported to a secure area which is covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system under the supervision of at least two employees of the facility operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The boxes of decks of cards shall be opened and inspected to ensure that the seals on each box are intact, unbroken, and free from tampering.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Boxes that do not appear to be intact, unbroken, and free from tampering shall be immediately inspected to ensure that the decks of cards in those boxes conform to the requirements of this chapter and there is no evidence of tampering with them.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the decks of cards inspected as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|A.|(2)|(a)">§A(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> show no evidence of tampering, they shall be placed, along with boxes of cards that are intact, unbroken and free from tampering, for storage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Decks of cards shall be stored in a storage area that the Commission has approved in advance under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The functions required under §A(1) and (2) of this regulation shall be performed by the employees identified in <cite path="|36|05|02|.13|A.|(4)">Regulation .13A(4) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Storage. The Commission-approved storage area shall have two separate locks, to which access shall be controlled as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The security department shall maintain one key and the gaming operations department shall maintain the other key.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An employee of the gaming operations department, below a floorperson in the organizational hierarchy, may not have access to the gaming operations department key.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the facility operator has a separate poker storage area, an employee below a poker supervisor in the organizational hierarchy may not have access to the gaming operations department key to the poker storage area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Distribution.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, as may be necessary, a floorperson or above, in the presence of a security department employee, shall remove the appropriate number of decks of cards from the approved storage area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The floorperson or above and the security department employee who removed the decks shall distribute sufficient decks to the pit managers or above and, if applicable, to the poker supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The number of decks distributed shall include extra decks that shall be placed in the pit stand for the card reserve.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Decks of cards in the pit stand shall be placed in a locked compartment, the keys to which shall be in the possession of the pit managers or above or the poker supervisor or above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the decks are to be inspected at open gaming tables under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the pit manager or above shall distribute the decks to the dealer at each table or the poker supervisor shall transport the decks to the poker pit stand for subsequent distribution to the dealer at each poker table either directly by the poker supervisor or through the floorperson assigned to supervise the dealer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the decks are to be preinspected and preshuffled at a closed gaming table as permitted under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|R.">§R of this regulation</cite>, the pit manager or above or poker supervisor shall deliver the decks to the dealer and the floorperson or above at the closed gaming table where the preinspection and preshuffling shall be performed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the decks have already been preinspected, preshuffled, sealed in containers and placed in the card storage area as permitted under §R(8)(b) or (e) of this regulation, the pit manager or above and a security department employee shall transport the number of sealed containers of cards needed for that gaming day to the gaming pits where the cards will be utilized and shall ensure that the containers are locked in the pit stand.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Consistent with the facility operator’s internal controls, the security department shall maintain a record of the removal of the sealed containers of cards from the approved storage area and the distribution of sealed containers to the gaming pits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Removal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the decks of cards to be used for poker are removed from the poker storage area, the poker supervisor or above and a security department employee shall, at times as may be necessary, remove the appropriate number of decks from the poker storage area and distribute the decks under §D(1), (2) or (3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of decks distributed shall include extra decks that shall be placed in the pit stand for the card reserve.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Decks of cards in the pit stand shall be placed in a locked compartment, the keys to which shall be in the possession of the poker supervisor or above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Verification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for decks of cards that are preinspected and preshuffled under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|R.">§R of this regulation</cite>, the dealer shall sort the cards in each deck according to suit and in sequence to verify that all cards are present and visually inspect the backs of the cards for any defects that might compromise the integrity or fairness of the game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The floorperson or above shall verify the inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unsuitable or Missing Card. If, while inspecting the cards in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the dealer finds that a card is unsuitable for use, a card is missing from the deck or an extra card is found, the following procedures shall be observed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A supervisor or above or a poker supervisor shall bring a replacement deck of cards or card from the card reserve in the pit stand.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The unsuitable deck or card shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container, identified by table number, date and time and signed by the dealer and floorperson assigned to that table or above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above or a poker supervisor shall maintain the envelope or container in a secure place within the pit until collection by a security department employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Envelopes and containers used to hold or transport cards shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transparent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designed or constructed with seals so that any tampering is evident; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Commission and approved under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Damaged Cards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If any card in a deck appear to be damaged during the course of play, the dealer shall immediately notify a floorperson or above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If after inspection, the floorperson or above determines that the card is damaged and needs to be replaced, the floorperson shall notify the pit manager or above or the poker supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above or the poker supervisor shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify surveillance of a card change;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bring a replacement deck of cards or card from the pit stand to replace the damaged card or cards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Place the damaged card face up on the table and remove the matching card from the replacement deck and place it face up on the table;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Turn over both the damaged card and the replacement card to verify that the backs of the cards match;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Place the replacement card in the discard rack;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Tear the damaged card down the center, or cancel the card, and place it face up in the replacement deck; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Return the replacement deck to the pit stand.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At least once each gaming day, the personnel operating table games shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collect the replacement cards and place the replacement cards in an envelope or container;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Seal the envelope or container;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attach a label to each envelope or container that identifies the deck as a replacement deck; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Obtain the signature of the pit manager or above on the label.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>On an as-needed basis, the personnel operating poker table games shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collect the replacement decks of poker cards and place the replacement poker cards in an envelope or container;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Seal the envelope or container;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attach a label to each envelope or container that identifies the deck as a replacement deck; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Obtain the signature of the poker manager or above, or the poker supervisor, on the label.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above or the poker supervisor shall maintain the sealed envelopes or containers in a secure place within the pit until collection by a security department employee in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|M.">§M of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>This subsection does not apply to cards showing indications of tampering, flaws or other defects that might affect the integrity or fairness of the game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Removing Cards from Active Use.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personnel operating table games shall put decks of cards that were used for play into envelopes or containers when the decks of cards are removed from active use at the table.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personnel operating table games shall attach a label to each envelope or container which identifies the table number, date and time the decks of cards where collected and shall be signed by the dealer and floorperson assigned to the table.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The poker supervisor or pit manager or above shall maintain the sealed envelopes or containers in a secure place within the pit until collection by a security department employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall remove a deck of cards at any time if there is an indication of tampering, flaws or other defects that might affect the integrity or fairness of the game, or at the request of a Commission compliance representative or other Commission employee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Personnel operating table games shall place extra decks or packaged sets of multiple decks in the card reserve with broken seals in a sealed envelope or container, with a label attached to each envelope or container that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contains the number of decks or packaged sets of multiple decks that are included;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date and time the decks were placed in the envelope or container; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The signature of the floorperson or above for decks used for poker and the pit manager or above for decks used for all other games.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>At the end of each gaming day or at least once each gaming day, as designated by the facility operator and approved in advance by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>, and at other times as may be necessary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|05|02|.16|M.|(2)">§M(2) of this regulation</cite>, a security department employee shall collect and sign all envelopes or containers with damaged decks of cards, decks of cards required to be removed that gaming day, and all extra decks in the card reserve with broken seals and return the envelopes or containers to the security department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an alternative procedure for collecting, destroying or cancelling a deck of cards described in <cite path="36|05|02|.16|M.|(1)">§M(1) of this regulation</cite> has been submitted to, and approved by, the Commission, a security department employee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall collect all envelopes or containers and return them to the security department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May sign the envelopes or containers; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A table game department supervisor or above may collect all extra decks with intact seals in the card reserve.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Inspection of Cards. When the envelopes or containers of used cards and reserve cards with broken seals are returned to the security department, the cards shall be inspected for tampering, marks, alterations, missing or additional cards, or anything that might indicate unfair play:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For cards used in blackjack, Spanish 21, baccarat, midibaccarat or minibaccarat, the facility operator shall inspect:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All decks used during the day; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If Commission has approved, as part of the facility’s internal controls, the procedures for selecting the sample size and for ensuring a proper selection of the sample, a sample of decks selected at random or in accordance with an approved stratification plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall also inspect:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A deck of cards that the Commission requested the facility operator to remove for the purpose of inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A deck of cards the facility operator removed for indication of tampering;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All cards used for all banked table games other than the games listed in <cite path="36|05|02|.16|N.|(1)">§N(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All cards used for poker.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The procedures for inspecting all decks required to be inspected under this subsection shall include the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sorting of cards sequentially by suit or utilizing a machine approved by the Commission capable of reading the cards to determine whether any deck contains missing or additional cards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Inspection of the backs with an ultraviolet light;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Inspection of the sides of the cards for crimps, bends, cuts or shaving; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Inspection of the front and back of all plastic cards for consistent shading and coloring.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If during the inspection procedures required for cards used in poker, one or more of the cards in a deck are determined to be unsuitable for continued use, those cards shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container and a two-part Card Discrepancy Report shall be completed in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|N.|(8)">§N(8) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Upon completion of the inspection procedures required under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|N.|(2)">§N(2) of this regulation</cite>, each deck of cards used in poker that is determined suitable for continued use shall be placed in sequential order, repackaged and returned to the approved or poker storage area for subsequent use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall develop internal control procedures for returning the repackaged cards to the poker card inventory in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|R.">§R of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An individual performing an inspection shall complete a work order form which details the procedures performed and lists the tables from which the cards were removed and the results of the inspection, and shall sign the form upon completion of the inspection procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall submit to the Commission the training procedures for the employees performing the inspections required under this subsection in its internal controls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Evidence of tampering, marks, alterations, missing, or additional cards or anything that might indicate unfair play discovered during an inspection, or at any other time, shall be immediately reported to a Commission compliance representative by the completion and delivery of a two-part Card Discrepancy Report.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The two-part report shall include the cards or decks of cards which are the subject of the report.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The cards or decks of cards shall be retained by a Commission compliance representative for further inspection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for approval internal control procedures for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A card inventory system, which includes, at a minimum, records of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Balance of decks of cards on hand;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Decks of cards removed from storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Decks of cards returned to storage or received from a manufacturer or supplier;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Date of each transaction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Signatures of the employees involved;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A daily reconciliation of the decks of cards distributed, destroyed or cancelled, returned to the storage area and any the decks of cards in the card reserve; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A physical inventory of all decks of cards at least once every 3 months;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A physical inventory shall be performed by an individual with no incompatible functions and shall be verified to the balance of decks of cards on hand required in <cite path="36|05|02|.16|O.|(1)|(a)">§O(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Discrepancies shall immediately be reported to a Commission compliance representative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Destruction or Cancellation. Except for plastic cards used at poker which are of sufficient quality for reuse, decks of cards in an envelope or container that are inspected as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|N.">§N of this regulation</cite> and found to be without any indication of tampering, marks, alterations, missing or additional cards or any indication of unfair play shall be destroyed or cancelled within 7 days of collection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cards submitted to the Commission shall be destroyed or cancelled within 5 days of release from the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Destruction of cards must be by shredding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cancellation of cards must be by drilling a circular hole of at least 1/4 inch in diameter through the center of each card in the deck.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The destruction or cancellation of cards shall take place:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>[in] In a secure location in the licensed facility covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system, the physical characteristics of which shall be approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If conducted by a vendor that is registered or certified under <cite path="36.03.02.17">COMAR 36.03.02.17</cite> and done in accordance with an internal control of the licensed facility that has been approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.03.10.05">COMAR 36.03.10.05</cite>, at a location other than the facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Reused Deck.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a deck of plastic cards has been determined to not be suitable for reuse by the individual performing the inspection procedures required under subsection <cite path="36|05|02|.16|N.|(3)">§N(3) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The personnel operating table games shall place the deck in a sealed envelope or container with a label attached which identifies the date and time the deck was placed in the envelope or container; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The poker supervisor or floorperson shall sign the label.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the end of the gaming day or at other times as may be necessary, the envelope or container shall be collected by a security department employee and returned to the security department for destruction or cancellation in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|P.">§P of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Preinspection and Preshuffling. If a facility operator elects to preinspect and preshuffle cards at a closed gaming table prior to the delivery of the cards to an open gaming table, a dealer and supervised by a floorperson or above with no concurrent supervisory responsibility for open gaming tables shall perform the procedures required under this section.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall provide a Commission compliance representative with a schedule of the proposed time and location for the preinspection and preshuffling at least 24 hours prior to commencement of the process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The procedures required under §R(1)—(7) of this regulation shall be recorded by the surveillance department and the facility operator shall retain a recording for at least 7 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the decks of cards in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, the dealer shall perform the procedures in §R(2)—(7) of this regulation independently for each batch of cards that will be sealed in a container in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|R.|(7)">§R(7) of this regulation</cite> with the number of decks of cards in each batch being equal to the number of decks of cards required for the table game in which the decks are intended to be used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The dealer shall visually inspect the back of each card to assure that it is not flawed, scratched, or marked in a way that might compromise the integrity or fairness of the game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>By hand or by using a machine approved by the Commission, the dealer shall inspect the front of each card to ensure that all cards are present and that there are no extra cards in the deck.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If after inspection a card is determined to be unsuitable for use, or the deck is missing a card or an extra card is found, the following procedures shall occur:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The personnel operating table games shall place the deck containing the unsuitable, missing, or extra card in an envelope or container which shall be identified by table number, date, and time the deck of cards was placed in the envelope or container and signed by the dealer and floorperson or above performing the preinspection and preshuffle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The floorperson or above shall maintain the sealed envelope or container containing the deck containing the unsuitable, missing, or extra card until collection by a security department employee at the conclusion of the preinspection and preshuffling procedure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The dealer shall then shuffle the cards by hand or by using an automated card shuffling device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Upon completion of the preinspection and preshuffling process of the cards in the batch, the dealer and floorperson or above shall complete a two-part Preshuffled/Preinspected Form or other documentation that includes the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Time and date the Preshuffled/Preinspected Form was prepared;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Number of decks in the batch;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Table games at which the batch will be utilized if the batch contains more or less than 52 cards per deck;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Signature of the dealer who preinspected and preshuffled the cards, certifying that the cards were preinspected and preshuffled in accordance with this subsection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Signature of the floorperson or above who witnessed and verified the preinspection and preshuffling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Time, date and gaming table to which the sealed container of cards is subsequently delivered; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Signature of the floorperson or above who delivered the sealed container of cards to the gaming table in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.16|R.|(9)">§R(9) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The dealer shall place the preinspected and preshuffled batch of cards, together with the Preshuffled/Preinspected Form or other documentation, in a clear container that conforms to the requirements under <cite path="36|05|02|.16|H.">§H of this regulation</cite> and seal the container with a prenumbered label unique to the container.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall include in its internal controls procedures for the maintenance and security of unused seals, and the distribution, return and reconciliation of seals used on containers holding preinspected and preshuffled cards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The sealed containers of cards shall be transported by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A pit manager or above or poker supervisor to the gaming pit of the gaming tables where the cards will be utilized and locked in the pit stand; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An assistant table games shift manager or above and a security department employee to the approved storage area or poker storage area where the cards shall be placed back into the card inventory and segregated from cards that have not been preinspected and preshuffled.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>A record of the transport of the sealed containers of cards to the approved storage area shall be maintained by the security department in a manner consistent with the facility operator’s approved internal controls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>When the preinspected and preshuffled cards are needed for play, each container of cards shall be delivered by a floorperson or above to an open gaming table.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Upon delivery, the floorperson or above shall unseal the container, place the decks of cards on the gaming table in front of the dealer, complete and sign the Preshuffled/Preinspected Form, drop the original Preshuffled/Preinspected Form in a locked box in the gaming pit, and forward the copy of the Preshuffled/Preinspected Form to the security department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The dealer at the gaming table shall then cut the cards in the manner prescribed by the rules governing the particular table game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>If the Commission has approved a licensed manufacturer or contractor to provide preinspected and preshuffled decks or batches of decks, a facility operator may use preinspected and preshuffled decks or batches of decks obtained from that licensed manufacturer or contractor in the same manner as decks or batches of decks that are preinspected and preshuffled <cite path="36|05|02|.16|R.">§R of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Card Rotation. The facility operator shall change:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The decks of cards used for all banked table games except the games set forth in §T(2)—(5) of this regulation at least every:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>4 hours, if the cards are dealt by hand; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>8 hours, if the cards are dealt from a manual or automated dealing shoe;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The decks of cards used in blackjack at least every:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>4 hours, if the cards are dealt by hand; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>24 hours, if the cards are dealt from a manual or automated dealing shoe;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The decks of cards used in mini baccarat at least every 24 hours, if the cards are dealt from a manual or automated dealing shoe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The decks of cards used in midi baccarat after the play of each dealing shoe; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The two decks of cards used in poker at least every 24 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.17">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Dealing Shoes and Automated Card Shuffling Devices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Base plate” means an interior shelf of a dealing shoe on which a card rests.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Face plate” means the front wall of the dealing shoe against which the next card to be dealt rests and which typically contains a cutout.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A manual dealing shoe must be designed and constructed to maintain the integrity of the game at which the shoe is used, and shall include these features:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least the first 4 inches of the base plate shall be white;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The sides of the shoe below the base plate shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be transparent, have a transparent sealed cutout, or be otherwise constructed to prevent any object from being placed into or removed from the portion of the dealing shoe below the base plate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Permit the inspection of this portion of the shoe; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A stop underneath the top of the face plate that precludes the next card to be dealt from being moved upwards more than 1/8 inch.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="36|05|02|.17|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a manual dealing shoe used in minibaccarat, midibaccarat or baccarat must also meet these specifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a removable lid that is opaque from the point where it meets the face plate to a point at least 4 inches from the face plate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The sides and back above the base plate must be opaque; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have a device within the shoe which, when engaged, prevents the cards from moving backward in the shoe.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An automated card shuffling device that has been submitted, and approved by the Commission may be used in addition to a manual or automated dealing shoe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An automated shuffling device must meet a 95 percent confidence level using a standard chi-squared test for goodness of fit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An automated card shuffling device may not provide any information that can be used to aid a player in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Projecting the outcome of a game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Tracking the cards played and cards remaining to be played;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Analyzing the probability of the occurrence of an event relating to a game; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Analyzing the strategy for playing or betting to be used in a game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Tampering.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the beginning of each gaming day and before a card is placed in them, the floorperson assigned to the table shall inspect the dealing shoes and automated card shuffling devices to be used for gaming to ensure that they have not been tampered with.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evidence of tampering shall be immediately reported to a Commission compliance representative in a written report that shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date and time when the tampering was discovered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The name and signature of the individual who discovered the tampering;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A description of the evidence of tampering;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The table number where the dealing shoe or shuffler was used; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The name and signature of the person assigned to directly operate and conduct the game and the supervisor assigned the responsibility for supervising the operation and conduct of the game.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Pai Gow Tiles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pai gow shall be played with a set of 32 rectangular tiles</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each tile in a set must be identical in size and shading to every other tile in the set, and shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be made of a nontransparent black material, formed in the shape of a rectangle, and be not smaller than 2-1/2 inches in length, 1 inch in width and 3/8 inch in thickness;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the surface of each of its sides perfectly flat, except that the front side of each tile must contain spots which extend into the tile exactly the same distance as every other spot;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have on the back or front of each tile an identifying feature unique to each facility operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except for the front side containing spots, have an identical texture and finish on each side;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Have no tile within a set contain any markings, symbols or designs that would enable a player to know the identity of any element on the front side of the tile or that would distinguish any tile from any other tile within a set; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Have identifying spots on the front side of the tiles which are red, white or both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless a facility has submitted to the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite> a detailed schematic depicting the actual size and identifying features on pai gow tiles, and the Commission has approved the submission, pai gow tiles shall not be used in a facility</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each set of tiles shall be packaged separately and sealed under <cite path="36.05.03.19">COMAR 36.05.03.19</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.19">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Pai Gow Tiles — Receipt, Storage, Inspection, and Removal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Receipt.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A shipment of tiles that a facility operator receives from a manufacturer or contractor shall be unloaded immediately and transported to a secure area which is covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system under the supervision of at least two employees of the facility operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The boxes of tiles shall then be inspected by at least two employees of the facility operator to ensure that the seals on each box are intact, unbroken, and free from tampering.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Boxes that do not appear to be intact, unbroken and free from tampering shall be inspected immediately to ensure that the tiles in those boxes conform to the requirements of this chapter and there is no evidence of tampering with them.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If tiles inspected as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.19|A.|(2)|(a)">§A(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> show no evidence of tampering, they shall be placed, along with boxes of tiles that are intact, unbroken and free from tampering, for storage in a storage area, the location and physical characteristics of which shall be approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The functions required under §A(1) and (2) of this regulation shall be performed by at least the following employees of a facility operator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A floorperson or above; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An employee from the security department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sets of tiles which are to be distributed to gaming pits or tables for use in gaming shall be distributed from the approved storage area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approved Storage Area. The approved storage area shall have two separate locks, to which access shall be controlled as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The security department shall maintain one key and the gaming operations department shall maintain the other key; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An employee of the gaming operations department below a floorperson in the facility’s organizational hierarchy may not have access to the gaming operations department key.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Once each gaming day and at other times as may be necessary, a floorperson or above, in the presence of a security department employee, shall remove the appropriate number of sets of tiles from the approved storage area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Envelopes and containers used to hold or transport tiles shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transparent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designed or constructed with seals so that any tampering is evident; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submitted to, and approved by, the Commission in advance under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Distribution of Tiles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The floorperson or above shall distribute sufficient sets of tiles to the pit manager or above in each pai gow pit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above shall then distribute the sets of tiles to the dealer at each pai gow table and place extra sets of tiles in the reserve in the pit stand.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sets of tiles in the reserve shall be placed in a locked compartment in the pit stand, keys to which shall be in the possession of the pit manager or above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Damaged Tiles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If during the course of play a damaged tile is detected, the dealer or a floorperson shall immediately notify the pit manager or above, who shall bring a substitute set of tiles to the table from the reserve in the pit stand to replace the entire set of tiles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A set containing a damaged tile shall be placed in an envelope or container, identified by table number, date and time the tiles were placed in the envelope or container and sealed and signed by the dealer and the floorperson responsible for supervising the table or the pit manager or above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above shall maintain the sealed envelope or container in a secure place within the pit until collection by a security department employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Collection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The floorperson responsible for supervising the table or the pit manager or above shall collect used tiles which shall be placed in an envelope or container when removed from active use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A label shall be attached to each envelope or container which identifies the table number, date and time the tiles were placed in the envelope or container and sealed and signed by the dealer and the floorperson responsible for supervising the table or the pit manager or above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above shall maintain the sealed envelopes or containers in a secure place within the pit until collection by a security department employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Removal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator shall remove a tile from play if there is any indication of tampering, flaws, or other defects that might affect the integrity or fairness of the game, or at the request of a Commission compliance representative or other Commission employee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A label shall be attached to each envelope or container which identifies the table number, date, and time the tiles were placed in the envelope or container and sealed and signed by the dealer and the floorperson responsible for supervising the table or the pit manager or above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The pit manager or above shall maintain the sealed envelopes or containers in a secure place within the pit until collection by a security department employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Extra sets of tiles in the reserve which have been opened shall be placed in an envelope or container with a label attached to each envelope or container which identifies the date and time the tiles were placed in the envelope or container and sealed and is signed by the pit manager or above.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>At the end of each gaming day or in the alternative, at least once each gaming day, as designated by the facility operator and approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.05.03.16">COMAR 36.05.03.16</cite>, and at other times as may be necessary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A security department employee shall collect and sign all envelopes or containers with damaged tiles, tiles used during the gaming day, and all extra tiles in the reserve which have been opened, and return the envelopes or containers to the security department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A floorperson or above may collect all extra sets of tiles in the reserve which have not been opened, and, if collected, all unopened sets of tiles shall be cancelled, destroyed, or returned to the approved storage area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When envelopes or containers of used tiles and reserve sets of tiles which have been opened are returned to the security department, the security department shall inspect the tiles for tampering, marks, alterations, missing, or additional tiles or anything that might indicate unfair play.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The procedures for inspecting sets of tiles shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sorting of tiles by pairs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Visually inspecting the sides and back of each tile for tampering, markings, or alterations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Inspecting the sides and back of each tile with an ultraviolet light.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The individual performing the inspection shall complete a work order form which details the procedures performed, lists the tables from which the tiles were removed and the results of the inspection, and shall sign the form upon completion of the inspection procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall submit to the Commission the training procedures for the employees performing the inspections required under this subsection in its internal controls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Evidence of tampering, marks, alterations, missing, or additional tiles or anything that might indicate unfair play discovered during the inspection, or at any other time, shall be immediately reported to a Commission compliance representative by the completion and delivery of a two-part Tile Discrepancy Report.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The two-part report shall include the tiles which are the subject of the report.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A Commission compliance representative shall retain the tile for further inspection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Commission compliance representative receiving the tile shall sign the original and duplicate copy of the tile discrepancy report and retain the original.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The facility operator shall retain the duplicate copy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>If after completing the inspection procedures required under <cite path="36|05|02|.19|N.">§N of this regulation</cite>, it is determined that a complete set of 32 tiles removed from a gaming table is free from tampering, markings, or alterations, the set shall be packaged separately and sealed before being returned to the pai gow storage area for subsequent use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall develop internal control procedures for returning the repackaged tiles to the tile inventory in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.19|P.">§P of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Individual tiles from different sets may not be used to make a complete set for subsequent gaming.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may create replacement and reconstructed sets in accordance with the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If after completing the inspection procedures required under <cite path="36|05|02|.19|M.">§M of this regulation</cite>, it is determined that a tile has scratches or other markings on the back, sides or edges which make the tiles unsuitable for continued use, the tile shall be removed from the set and destroyed in accordance with <cite path="36|05|02|.19|R.">§R of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The remaining usable tiles from the set shall be designated as a replacement set.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The employee who removes the tiles from a set shall complete a two-part form that shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Include the date and time the tiles were removed from the set;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify the specific tile or tiles removed from the set and sent for destruction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contain the name and signature of the individuals involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The duplicate copy of the form shall be retained with the replacement set and the security department shall retain the original.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The assistant table games shift manager or above shall return the replacement set, accompanied by the duplicate copy of the form, to the tile inventory under <cite path="36|05|02|.19|P.">§P of this regulation</cite> where replacement sets shall be inventoried and stored separately from any stored and new, used or complete reconstructed sets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Tiles in one or more replacement sets may be used to create a complete reconstructed set of tiles in accordance with the following procedures:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The assistant table games shift manager or above shall conduct an inspection of each reconstructed set in the storage area, in the presence of a security department employee, and ensure that any replacement tile possesses the same color, texture, and finish as all other tiles in the reconstructed set.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The assistant table games shift manager or above shall sort the tiles by pairs and verify the needed replacement tile or tiles and visually inspect the sides, backs and edges of each tile in the reconstructed set for tampering, markings, and alterations and for comparison as to shading, texture and finish.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>After a complete set of tiles has been assembled from replacement sets, the assistant table games shift manager or above shall attach a label to the envelope or container for the reconstructed set, which shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Include the date and time of reconstruction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Contain the signature of the assistant table games shift manager or above and the security department employee who witnessed the inspection; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Identify the inspection steps that were followed to determine that the reconstructed set of tiles is suitable for use in gaming.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for approval internal control procedures for returning the reconstructed sets into inventory, identifying all reconstructed sets and maintaining an accurate inventory balance of remaining replacement sets.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit internal control procedures for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inventory system which includes records of at least the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The balance of sets of tiles on hand;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The sets of tiles removed from storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The sets of tiles returned to storage or received from a manufacturer or contractor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The date of each transaction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The signatures of the individuals involved;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A daily reconciliation of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sets of tiles distributed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sets of tiles destroyed or cancelled;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Sets of tiles returned to the approved storage area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sets of tiles in the tile reserve in a pit stand; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A physical inventory of the sets of tiles at least once every 3 months.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An inventory shall be performed by an individual with no incompatible functions and shall be verified to the balance of the sets of tiles on hand required in <cite path="36|05|02|.19|Q.|(1)|(a)">§Q(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Discrepancies shall immediately be reported to a Commission compliance representative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Destruction or Cancellation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Destruction or cancellation of tiles other than those retained for Commission inspection shall be completed within 7 days of collection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The method of destruction or cancellation shall be included in the facility operator’s internal controls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The destruction or cancellation of tiles shall take place in a secure location in the licensed facility covered by the facility operator’s surveillance system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Tile Rotation. A facility operator shall change the tiles at least every 12 hours.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Dealer Controlled Electronic Table Games — Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Wagering. A facility operator may conduct electronic wagering at a table game in accordance with this chapter.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Electronic wagering at a table game shall be conducted through the use of a dealer controlled electronic table game system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a dealer controlled electronic table game system is in use at a table game, a player may make only those wagers that are approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The computer controlling the dealer controlled electronic table game system shall be under dual key control, with one key controlled by the accounting department and the other key controlled by the table games department or the slot operations department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All aspects of a dealer controlled electronic table game system, including the computer and any related hardware, software or related devices, shall be tested by an independent certified testing laboratory and approved by the Commission prior to use by a facility operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements for table games under <cite path="|36.05">COMAR 36.05</cite>, a facility operator using a dealer controlled electronic table game system shall include in its internal controls, at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Procedures to ensure the physical security of the computer and related hardware, software and other devices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures to ensure the integrity and security of all sensitive data and software.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Procedures to ensure that access to sensitive data and software is limited to only appropriate personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures to ensure the logging of the events and the availability of records to enable an effective audit of the conduct of the system and the reporting of revenue.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A dealer controlled electronic table game shall have the ability to authenticate the transmission of data between the various components of the dealer controlled electronic table game system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A dealer controlled electronic table game system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Credit funds to the game account of a player when a player buys in to a game at a particular table game and debit any remaining funds from the game account when a player cashes out of the game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Permit a player to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Wager from a game account;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collect a losing wager from a game account; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pay a winning wager by crediting the amount of the winnings and corresponding wager to the game account;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In the game of Poker:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Debit a game account and increment pot for a wager;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Distribute a winning pot by crediting the game account of a winning player in the appropriate amounts;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Extract the rake from a player or pot according to the rake procedures established under the standard rules for Poker, and debit the game account of a player in the correct amounts; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Make a player’s balance or table stakes visible to all players in the game;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Depict the transactions described in §F(1), (2) and (3) of this regulation through one or more electronic fund displays that are visible to each player and to the dealer or boxperson;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Disclose to a player at all times the current balance in the player’s game account;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Accurately report and audit the table game’s win or loss, or Poker revenue, in accordance with the standard rules for Poker;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Be capable of generating reports setting forth, by gaming day, for each table game using the dealer controlled electronic table game system:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The total amount deposited into the game account of a player;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The total amount deposited into game accounts by all players;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The total amount credited to the game account of a player in payment of winnings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The total amount credited to the game accounts of all players in payment of winnings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The total amount collected from a player as losing wagers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The total amount collected from all players as losing wagers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The total amount withdrawn from game accounts by each player;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The total amount withdrawn from game accounts by all players; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The table game win or loss; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>If applicable, for Poker:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The total amount deducted from the game account of a player for collection of Poker rake time charges under the standard rules for Poker;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The total amount collected from the accounts of each player for collection of Poker rake time charges under the standard rules for Poker;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The total amount collected from Poker pots for collection of Poker rake under the standard rules for Poker; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The table game Poker revenue.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The display of a virtual chip on a dealer controlled electronic table game that depicts the transactions described in §F(1), (2) and (3) of this regulation is not required to meet the physical requirements for chips under <cite path="|36.05.02">COMAR 36.05.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A dealer controlled electronic table game system shall have no more than 14 table game positions in operation for every dealer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>After installation, Agency staff shall inspect a dealer controlled electronic table game system prior to use by a facility operator.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Dealer Controlled Electronic Table Game System — Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a table game using a dealer controlled electronic table game system is equipped with a bill validator, a player may participate in wagering at the table game by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inserting currency or a gaming voucher into the bill validator; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Presenting currency or value chips to the dealer or boxperson.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A dealer controlled electronic table game system that is equipped with a bill validator shall communicate with the Commission’s central monitor and control computer system to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transmit accounting and auditing information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Retrieve information in real time; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Activate or disable a dealer controlled electronic game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a table game using a dealer controlled electronic table game system is not equipped with a bill validator, a player shall participate in wagering by presenting currency or value chips to the dealer or boxperson.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When a player presents currency, a gaming voucher, or value chips as described in §A or C of this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The dealer controlled electronic table game system shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Credit to the player’s game account an amount of funds equivalent to the currency, gaming voucher or value chips presented by the player; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Display on the electronic fund display the amount of funds deposited into the player’s game account; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The player shall acknowledge the amount of funds deposited into the player’s game account.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A player shall cash out of a table game using a dealer controlled electronic table game system by receiving:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A gaming voucher equal in value to the balance in the player’s game account; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Value chips from the dealer or boxperson from the table inventory container that are equal in value to the balance in the player’s game account.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>After a player has cashed out of a table game using a dealer controlled electronic table game system, the dealer or boxperson shall zero out the electronic fund display of the player’s game account.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Tables.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for approval the layout for a table game that contains at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name or logo of the facility operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Betting areas designated for the placement of wagers authorized under the standard rules; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inscriptions that advise a player of the payout odds or amounts for all permissible wagers offered by the facility operator, except that if payout odds or amounts are not inscribed on the layout, a sign identifying the payout odds or amounts for all permissible wagers shall be posted at each table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator offers a Progressive Payout Wager, a table shall have a progressive table game system for the placement of Progressive Payout Wagers that includes a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wagering device at each betting position that acknowledges or accepts the placement of the Progressive Payout Wager; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Device that controls or monitors the placement of Progressive Payout Wagers at the gaming table and includes a lock-out button or other mechanism that prevents the recognition of any Progressive Payout Wager that a player attempts to place after the dealer has announced “no more bets”.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A table shall have a drop box and a tip box attached on the same side of the gaming table as, but on opposite sides of, the dealer, as approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may approve an alternative location for the tip box when a card shuffling device or other table game equipment prevents the placement of the drop box and tip box on the same side of the gaming table as, but on opposite sides of, the dealer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each table shall have a discard rack securely attached to the top of the dealer’s side of the table except for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Craps; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Roulette.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|02|.23">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Roulette — Ball, Table, and Wheel Inspection; Security Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A ball used in Roulette shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Made completely of a nonmetallic substance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not less than 12/16 inch nor more than 14/16 inch in diameter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Roulette shall be played on a table having a Roulette:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wheel of at least 30 inches in diameter at one end of the table; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Layout imprinted on the opposite end of the table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prior to opening a Roulette table for gaming activity, a floorperson or member of a facility operator’s security department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspect the Roulette ball by passing it over a magnet or compass to assure its nonmagnetic quality;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inspect the Roulette table and Roulette wheel for any magnet or contrivance that would affect the fair operation of the Roulette wheel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inspect the Roulette wheel to assure that the wheel is level and rotating freely and evenly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Inspect the Roulette wheel to assure that all parts are secure and free from movement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator uses a Roulette wheel that has external movable parts, any adjustments to the movable parts shall be made by a floorperson or a member of the facility operator’s gaming operations department in the presence of a security department member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All adjustments shall be completed prior to the required inspections under <cite path="36|05|02|.23|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may replace any of the movable parts at any time, except that an inspection as required under <cite path="36|05|02|.23|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall be completed prior to reopening the Roulette wheel and table for play.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall maintain an inspection log, which shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date and time of inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Roulette table number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether an adjustment or replacement was completed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A description of the adjustment or replacement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If required, a certification that an inspection was completed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The signature and license number of the individual making the adjustment or replacement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>When a Roulette table is not open for play, the Roulette wheel shall be secured by a cover that is placed over the entire wheel and securely locked.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-04, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-06-24">Regulations <cite path="|36|05|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|05|02|.19">.19</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 471); adopted permanently effective June 24, 2013 (40:12 Md. R. 1044)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-02"><cite path="|36|05|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 89); emergency status expired May 12, 2014</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|05|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective May 26, 2014 (41:10 Md. R. 566); January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|05|02|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite>, F amended effective September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|05|02|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-18"><cite path="|36|05|02|.13|K.">Regulation .13K</cite> amended effective August 18, 2014 (41:16 Md. R. 948)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|02|.13|O.">Regulation .13O</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|05|02|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|05|02|.15|A.">Regulation .15A</cite>, B amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-06"><cite path="|36|05|02|.15|H.">Regulation .15H</cite> amended effective September 6, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|02|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 319); January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597); October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-10-23"><cite path="|36|05|02|.16|B.">Regulation .16B</cite>, P amended effective October 23, 2017 (44:21 Md. R. 985)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|05|02|.16|D.">Regulation .16D</cite>, P amended effective October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-18"><cite path="|36|05|02|.16|M.">Regulation .16M</cite> amended effective August 18, 2014 (41:16 Md. R. 948)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-06"><cite path="|36|05|02|.16|N.">Regulation .16N</cite> amended effective September 6, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|05|02|.19">Regulation .19</cite> amended effective September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-02"><cite path="|36|05|02|.20">Regulation .20</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 89); emergency status expired May 12, 2014</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-26"><cite path="|36|05|02|.20">Regulation .20</cite> adopted effective May 26, 2014 (41:10 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|02|.20|A.">Regulation .20A</cite>, F amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-02"><cite path="|36|05|02|.21">Regulation .21</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 89); emergency status expired May 12, 2014</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-26"><cite path="|36|05|02|.21">Regulation .21</cite> adopted effective May 26, 2014 (41:10 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|02|.22">Regulation .22</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|02|.23">Regulation .23</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
