<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Table Games Procedures</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Personnel Operating and Conducting Table Games.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may use the following personnel to operate table games:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dealer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Stickperson;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Boxperson;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Floorperson;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pit manager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Poker manager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Assistant table games shift manager; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Table games shift manager.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall maintain the following minimum levels of staffing when table games are being operated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excluding craps or baccarat, one dealer for a table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two dealers for a big baccarat table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Two dealers for a craps table, one of whom shall act as the stickperson; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One boxperson or floorperson for a craps table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall provide a sufficient number of floorpersons to supervise the operation of table games in accordance with the standards in this chapter, so that a floorperson may not supervise more than the number of tables specified in one of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excluding baccarat, midibaccarat, craps, mini-craps, and pai gow, six tables comprised of a combination of banking table games;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One baccarat table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Three midibaccarat tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Excluding baccarat, caps and mini-craps, one midibaccarat table and one table of any other table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Three craps tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Excluding baccarat, midibaccarat, mini-craps and pai gow, two craps tables and two tables of a banking table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Excluding baccarat, midibaccarat, mini-craps and pai gow, one craps table and three tables of a banking table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If only one dealer is assigned to a table, two mini-craps table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>If the there is a dealer and a stickperson assigned to the tables, four mini-craps tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>If the tables are in a side-by-side configuration, two pai gow tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Excluding baccarat, craps and mini-craps, one pai gow table and one table of another banking table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Ten poker tables; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>If the floorperson assigned to poker does not have responsibilities for seating players, 12 poker tables.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the gaming tables being supervised by a floorperson are dealer controlled electronic table games, the maximum number of gaming tables that the floorperson may supervise may be increased by 100 percent of the limits provided in <cite path="36|05|03|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Subject to the limitation that a pit manager or assistant table games shift manager may not directly supervise more than 12 floorpersons, a facility operator shall provide a sufficient number of pit managers or assistant table games shift managers to supervise the operation of table games.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall provide a poker manager to supervise all open poker tables.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If no more than three poker tables are open, a poker manager is not required.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall provide a table games shift manager to supervise the operation of table games during every shift.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An assistant table games shift manager may be designated to act as the table games shift manager in the table games shift manager's absence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An assistant table games shift manager designated under <cite path="36|05|03|.01|H.|(1)">§H(1) of this regulation</cite> may not be counted toward the number of pit managers or assistant table games shift managers required under <cite path="36|05|03|.01|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may request the Commission to approve its use of a staffing plan that differs from the minimum standards in this section by submitting a written alternate minimum staffing plan which must include at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The pit number and configuration of any pit affected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The type, location and table number of any table affected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The standard staffing level required under this regulation for a gaming table and the proposed alternative staffing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The days, shifts or times during which the alternative staffing would be in effect; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A narrative explaining the rationale for the proposed alternative staffing and how the alternative staffing would protect the integrity of gaming at the affected gaming tables.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not implement an alternate minimum staffing plan unless the Commission has approved the plan in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall be construed to limit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator from using more personnel than required by this regulation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission’s discretion to direct a facility to use more personnel than required by this regulation in the operation of table games.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Table Inventory.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a table game is opened for gaming, table game operations shall commence with the table inventory.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may not cause or permit gaming chips, coins, or plaques to be added to, or removed from, a table inventory during the gaming day except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In exchange for cash;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In exchange for an issuance copy of a counter check presented by a player;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For the payment of winning wagers and collection of losing wagers made at the gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In exchange for a gaming chip or plaque received from a player having an equal aggregate face value;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In conformity with fill and credit procedures; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>For the collection of vigorish.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When a table game is not open for gaming activity, the table inventory and a Table Inventory Slip shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be stored in a locked container that is clearly marked on the outside with the game and the gaming table number to which it corresponds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the information on the Table Inventory Slip be visible from the outside of the container; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be stored either in the cage or secured to the gaming table, in a manner consistent with the facility’s approved internal controls.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the requirements in <cite path="36|05|03|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, for table games that are not open for gaming activity during the gaming day, a facility operator may use this alternative procedure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A floorperson or above shall complete a Closed Table form for every table that was not open for gaming during the gaming day;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The table inventory shall remain locked during completion of the Closed Table form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Closed Table form shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date and identification of the shift ended;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The game and table number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The date the table was last opened for gaming; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The signature and license number of the floorperson or above who completed the Closed Table form; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After completion of the procedure, the floorperson or above who completed the Closed Table form shall deposit the form into the drop box.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The keys to the locked containers containing the table inventories shall be maintained and controlled by the gaming operations department and may not be made accessible to cage personnel or to any employee responsible for transporting the table inventories to or from the gaming tables.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Table Inventory Slips shall be two-part forms upon which the following is recorded:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date and identification of the shift ended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The game and table number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total value of each denomination of value chips, coins and plaques remaining at the gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The total value of all denominations of value chips, coins and plaques remaining at the gaming table; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The signatures of the dealer, or boxperson and floorperson, assigned to the gaming table who conducted the count of the table inventory when the gaming table was closed and when the gaming table was opened.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Opening a Table Game.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a table game is to be opened for gaming activity, a security department employee shall transport directly from the cage to the gaming table the locked container with the table inventory and the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip if the Slip is not already attached to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Immediately prior to opening the table game for gaming, the floorperson assigned to the gaming table shall unlock the container with the table inventory after assuring that it is the proper container for that gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The dealer or boxperson assigned to the gaming table shall count the contents of the table inventory in the presence of the floorperson assigned to the gaming table and reconcile the count to the totals on the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip removed from the container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The dealer or boxperson assigned to the table, and the floorperson who observed the dealer or boxperson count the contents of the container, shall attest to the accuracy of the information recorded on the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip by signing the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip has been signed as required under <cite path="36|05|03|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the dealer, boxperson or floorperson shall immediately deposit the slip into the table game drop box attached to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If there is a discrepancy between the amount of gaming chips and plaques counted and the amount of the gaming chips and plaques recorded on the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The discrepancy shall be immediately verbally reported to the floorperson or above, the security department and a Commission compliance representative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the presence of the floorperson or above, the dealer or boxperson assigned to the table shall recount the table inventory and complete a new Table Inventory Slip reflecting the results of the dealer’s or boxperson’s recount of the table inventory;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The floorperson or above shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prepare an Error Notification Slip, which shall be a three-part form containing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The date and time;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The type of game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The table number and pit; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>An explanation of the discrepancy;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Write "Incorrect Copy" on the copy of the Table Inventory Slip that was in the table inventory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Sign the "Incorrect Copy"; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Write "Correct Copy" on both copies of the Table Inventory Slip required to be prepared by the dealer or boxperson under <cite path="36|05|03|.03|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The "Correct Copy" shall be signed by the dealer or boxperson who recounted the table inventory, and the floorperson or above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>After the signatures required under <cite path="36|05|03|.03|F.|(4)">§F(4) of this regulation</cite> have been obtained, the dealer or boxperson shall deposit in the drop box the "Incorrect Copy" Table Inventory Slip, both copies of the "Correct Copy" Table Inventory Slip and the first copy of the Error Notification Slip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A dealer or boxperson shall give the second copy of the Error Notification Slip to the pit clerk or floorperson or above, and shall deliver the third copy of the Error Notification Slip to a Commission compliance representative.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>For any unresolved discrepancy greater than $100, the security or surveillance department shall investigate the discrepancy and, within 24 hours, complete a written incident report and immediately forward a copy to a Commission compliance representative.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Distributing Chips, Coins, and Plaques to a Gaming Table.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pit clerk or floorperson or above shall prepare a request for a fill to add value chips, coins, and plaques to a table game using a Fill Request Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Access to the blank Fill Request Slips shall be restricted to pit clerks and floorpersons or above.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A Fill Request Slip shall be a two-part form on which the following information shall be recorded:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date, time and shift of preparation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The denomination of value chips, coins and plaques to be distributed to the gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total amount of each denomination of value chips, coins and plaques to be distributed to the gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The game and table number to which the value chips, coins and plaques are to be distributed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The signature of the floorperson or above requesting the fill.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After the Fill Request Slip has been prepared, the security department employee shall transport the chip bank copy of the Fill Request Slip directly to the chip bank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The dealer or boxperson shall place the drop box copy of the Fill Request Slip in view of the facility operator’s surveillance system on the gaming table to which the value chips, coins, and plaques are to be received.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the requirements of §§A—E of this regulation, a fill request may be prepared electronically if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The input data for preparation of the fill is entered by, and ability to input data is restricted to, the pit clerk or a floorperson or above; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Fill Slip is generated in the chip bank as a direct result of the input.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A Fill Slip shall be prepared by a chip bank cashier or, if the required information was inputted in conformity with <cite path="36|05|03|.04|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the Fill Slip may be electronically generated in the chip bank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A Fill Slip shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A serially prenumbered form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Used in sequential order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accounted for by employees with no incompatible functions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If applicable, marked "Void" and signed by the preparer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If a Fill Slip is manually prepared, the following procedures and requirements shall be observed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each series of Fill Slips shall be a four-part form and shall be inserted in a locked dispenser or bound in a Fill Slip form book that permits an individual Fill Slip in the series and its copies to be written upon while still locked in the dispenser or bound in the Fill Slip form book;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Fill Slip dispenser shall discharge the drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Fill Slip while the accounting copy remains in a continuous, unbroken form in the dispenser; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a Fill Slip form book is utilized, the accounting copy must remain in the bound Fill Slip form book until removed in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.04|I.|(4)">§I(4) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Access to copies of the Fill Slips shall be maintained and controlled by accounting department employees with no incompatible functions who are responsible for controlling and accounting for the unused supply of Fill Slips, placing Fill Slips in the dispensers and removing the accounting copies of the Fill Slips from the dispensers or Fill Slip form book each gaming day.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If a Fill Slip is electronically prepared, each series of Fill Slips must be a three-part form and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be inserted in a printer that will simultaneously print a drop box, acknowledgment and chip bank copy of the Fill Slip in the chip bank; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Store, in machine readable form, the information printed on the drop box, acknowledgement, and chip bank copies of the Fill Slips so that the stored data may not be susceptible to change or removal by any personnel involved in the preparation of a Fill Slip after the Fill Slip has been prepared.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A copy of a Fill Slip and, if applicable, the stored data, must contain at least the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Denominations of the value chips, coins, and plaques being distributed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Total amount of each denomination of value chips, coins, and plaques being distributed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Total amount of all denominations of value chips, coins, and plaques being distributed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Game and table number to which the value chips, coins, and plaques are being distributed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Date and shift during which the distribution of value chips, coins, and plaques occurs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Signature of the preparer or, if electronically prepared, the license number of the preparer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>The time of preparation of the Fill Slip shall be recorded on the drop box, acknowledgement, and chip bank copies of the Fill Slip upon preparation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>A security department employee shall directly transport a value chip, coin or plaque distributed to a gaming table from the chip bank to a gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a value chip, coin or plaque at a gaming table, the floorperson shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Compare the Fill Request Slip to the Fill Slip; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attest to the accuracy of the fill by signing the drop box copy and acknowledgement copy of the Fill Slip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>If a fill request is generated electronically in the chip bank in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.04|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the floorperson shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Compare the Fill Slip with the electronically generated fill request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attest to the accuracy of the fill by signing the drop box and acknowledgement copies of the Fill Slip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Signatures on the drop box and acknowledgement copies of the Fill Slip attesting to the accuracy of the information contained on a Fill Slip shall be required of the specified employees at the specified times:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The chip bank cashier, upon preparation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The security department employee transporting the value chips, coins and plaques to the gaming table, upon receipt from the cashier of the value chips, coins and plaques to be transported;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The dealer or boxperson assigned to the gaming table, upon receipt and verification of the amounts of the value chips, coins and plaques at the gaming table from the security department employee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The floorperson assigned to the gaming table, upon receipt and verification of the amounts of the value chips, coins and plaques at the gaming table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>After the signature requirements in <cite path="36|05|03|.04|P.">§P of this regulation</cite> have been satisfied, the security department employee who transported to a gaming table a value chip, coin or plaque, the drop box, and acknowledgement copies of the Fill Slip, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Observe the dealer’s or boxperson’s immediate placement of the drop box copy of the Fill Slip and the drop box copy of the Fill Request Slip, if applicable, in the drop box attached to the gaming table to which a value chip, coin, or plaque was transported; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Return the acknowledgement copy of the Fill Slip to the chip bank cashier.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>The chip bank cashier shall maintain together the chip bank copies of the Fill Request Slip, if applicable, and the chip bank and acknowledgement copies of the Fill Slip, until those items are forwarded to the accounting department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>All parts of voided Fill Slips, as well as the chip bank copies of Fill Request Slips, if applicable, and the acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Fill Slips that are maintained and controlled in conformity with <cite path="36|05|03|.04|Q.">§Q of this regulation</cite>, shall be forwarded to the accounting department for agreement, on a daily basis, with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The drop box copies of the Fill Request Slips, if applicable, and Fill Slips removed from the drop box on the gaming table; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If applicable, the electronically stored data and accounting copies of the Fill Slips.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Removing a Value Chip, Coin, or Plaque from a Gaming Table.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pit clerk or floorperson or above shall prepare a request for a credit to remove a value chip, coin or plaque from a table game by using a Credit Request Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Access to the blank Credit Request Slips shall be restricted to pit clerks and floorpersons or above.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A Credit Request Slip shall be a two-part form on which the following information shall be recorded:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date, time and shift of preparation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The denomination of chips, coins, and plaques to be removed from the gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total amount of each denomination of value chips, coins and plaques to be removed from the gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The game and table number from which the value chips, coins, and plaques are to be removed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The signature of the floorperson or above assigned to the gaming table from which the value chips, coins and plaques are to be removed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A security department employee shall transport the chip bank copy of a prepared Credit Request Slip directly to the chip bank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A dealer or boxperson shall place the drop box copy of the Credit Request Slip in view of the facility operator’s surveillance system on the gaming table from which the value chips, coins and plaques are to be removed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The drop box copy of the Credit Request Slip may not be removed until the drop box and acknowledgement copies of the Credit Slip are received from the chip bank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the requirements of §§A—F of this regulation, a request for a credit may be prepared electronically if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The input data for preparation of the credit is entered by, and ability to input data is restricted to, the pit clerk or a floorperson or above; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Credit Slip is generated in the chip bank as a direct result of the input.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A Credit Slip shall be prepared by a chip bank cashier or, if the required information was inputted in conformity with <cite path="36|05|03|.05|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, the Credit Slip may be electronically generated in the chip bank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Credit Slips shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Serially prenumbered forms;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Used in sequential order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accounted for by employees with no incompatible functions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If applicable, marked "Void" and signed by the preparer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>When Credit Slips are manually prepared, the following procedures and requirements shall be observed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each series of Credit Slips shall be a four-part form and shall be inserted in a locked dispenser or bound in a Credit Slip form book that permits an individual Credit Slip in the series and its copies to be written upon while still locked in the dispenser or bound in the Credit Slip form book;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Credit Slip dispenser must discharge the drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip while the accounting copy remains in a continuous, unbroken form in the dispenser; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a Credit Slip form book is utilized, the accounting copy must remain in the bound Credit Slip form book until removed in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.05|J.|(4)">§J(4) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Access to the copies of the Credit Slips shall be maintained and controlled by accounting department employees with no incompatible functions who shall be responsible for controlling and accounting for the unused supply of the Credit Slips, placing Credit Slips in the dispensers, and removing the accounting copies of the Credit Slips from the dispensers or Credit Slip form book each gaming day.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>When Credit Slips are electronically prepared, each series of Credit Slips must be a three-part form and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be inserted in a printer that simultaneously prints drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip in the chip bank;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Store, in machine-readable form, the information printed on the drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The stored data may not be susceptible to change or removal by any personnel after the preparation of a Credit Slip after the Credit Slip has been prepared.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Copies of the Credit Slip, and when applicable, the stored data, must contain at least the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The denominations of the value chips, coins, and plaques being returned to the chip bank;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The total amount of each denomination of value chips, coins and plaques being returned;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total amount of all denominations of value chips, coins, and plaques being returned;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The game and table number from which the value chips, coins, and plaques are being returned;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The date and shift during which the removal of value chips, coins, and plaques occurs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The signature of the preparer or, if electronically prepared, the identification code of the preparer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>When the Credit Slip is prepare, the time of its preparation shall be recorded on the drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>After the Credit Slip has been prepared by the chip bank cashier or has been printed in the chip bank as a result of the information being inputted electronically by a pit clerk or floorperson or above, the security department employee shall transport the drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip directly to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>The dealer or boxperson shall compare the value chips, coins and plaques to be removed from the table inventory container with the drop box copy of the Credit Slip and the Credit Request Slip, if applicable, and shall sign the Credit Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Signatures on the drop box, acknowledgement and chip bank copies of a Credit Slip attesting to the accuracy of the information contained on the Credit Slip shall be required of the specified employees at the specified times:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The chip bank cashier, upon receipt of the value chips from the table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dealer or boxperson assigned to the gaming table, upon removal of the value chips, coins and plaques from the table inventory container and verification of the Credit Slip and Credit Request Slip, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The floorperson assigned to the gaming table, upon observing the removal of the value chips, coins and plaques from the table inventory container and the verification of the Credit Slip and Credit Request Slip, if applicable; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The security department employee, upon receipt of the value chips, coins and plaques from the gaming table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>After meeting the signature requirements required under <cite path="36|05|03|.05|P.">§P of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The security department employee shall transport the value chips, coins and plaques directly to the chip bank along with the acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dealer or boxperson shall place the drop box copy of the Credit Slip on the gaming table in view of the facility’s surveillance system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the value chips, coins and plaques from the security department employee, the chip bank cashier shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Compare the chip bank copy of the Credit Request Slip with the Credit Slip; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the credit request is electronically generated in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.05|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, the chip bank cashier shall compare the Credit Slip with the electronically generated credit request; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The chip bank cashier shall attest to the accuracy of the credit by signing the acknowledgement and chip bank copies of the Credit Slip.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After transporting the acknowledgement copy of the Credit Slip back to the gaming table from which the value chips, coins and plaques were removed, the security department employee shall observe the immediate placement by the dealer or boxperson of the drop box copy of the Credit Request Slip, if applicable, and the drop box and acknowledgement copies of the Credit Slip into the drop box.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The chip bank copies of the Credit Request Slip, if applicable, and Credit Slip shall be maintained together by the chip bank cashier until forwarded to the accounting department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>All parts of voided Credit Slips, chip bank copies of Credit Request Slips, if applicable, and the chip bank copies of the Credit Slips that are maintained and controlled in conformity with <cite path="36|05|03|.05|Q.">§Q of this regulation</cite>, shall be forwarded by a chip bank cashier to the accounting department for agreement, on a daily basis, with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The drop box copies of the Credit Request Slips, if applicable, and the drop box and acknowledgement copies of the Credit Slips removed from the drop box on the gaming table; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The electronically stored data and accounting copies of Credit Slips, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Accepting Cash for Gaming Chips, Plaques, or Electronic Wagering Credits.</heading>
    <text>When a player presents cash at a table game for exchange for gaming chips, plaques or electronic wagering credits:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The dealer or boxperson shall spread the cash on the top of the gaming table in full view of the player who presented it, the floorperson assigned to the gaming table and the facility operator's surveillance system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The amount of cash shall be verbalized by the dealer or boxperson accepting it in a tone of voice to be heard by the player who presented it and the floorperson assigned to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Immediately after an equivalent amount of gaming chips, plaques or electronic wagering credits has been given to the player by the dealer or boxperson, the dealer or boxperson shall take the cash from the top of the gaming table and place it into the drop box attached to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Drop at an Open Table Game.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a table game being dropped is to remain open for gaming activity, the dealer or boxperson assigned to the gaming table shall count the value chips, coins, and plaques remaining in the table inventory at the time of the drop and record the amount on a Table Inventory Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The floorperson who is responsible for supervising the table game at the time of the drop shall observe the count required under <cite path="36|05|03|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The dealer or boxperson assigned to the table, and the floorperson who observed the dealer or boxperson count the contents of the table inventory, shall attest to the accuracy of the information recorded on the Table Inventory Slip by signing the Table Inventory Slip.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After the Table Inventory Slip is signed as required under <cite path="36|05|03|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The dealer or boxperson shall deposit the original copy of the Table Inventory Slip in the drop box that is attached to the gaming table immediately before the drop box is removed from the gaming table as part of the drop; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dealer or boxperson shall deposit the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip in the drop box that is attached to the gaming table immediately after the removal of the drop box that is removed from the gaming table as part of the drop.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Closing a Table Game.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When gaming activity at a table game is concluded, the dealer or boxperson assigned to the gaming table, in the presence of the floorperson assigned to the gaming table, shall count the value chips, coins, and plaques remaining at the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The floorperson assigned to the gaming table shall record the amounts of the value chips, coins and plaques counted on the Table Inventory Slip, and the original copy of the Table Inventory Slip shall be signed by the dealer or boxperson who counted the table inventory and by the floorperson who observed the dealer or boxperson count the contents of the table inventory.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After the original copy of the Table Inventory Slip has been signed as required under <cite path="36|05|03|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the dealer or boxperson shall immediately deposit the original copy of the Table Inventory Slip in the table game drop box attached to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After the original copy of the Table Inventory Slip has been deposited in the table game drop box attached to the gaming table, the dealer or boxperson shall place the duplicate copy of the Table Inventory Slip and the value chips, coins and plaques remaining at the gaming table in the container required under <cite path="|36|05|03|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>, after which the floorperson shall lock the table inventory container and cause it to be transported directly to the cage by a security department member or secured to the gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the locked table inventory containers are transported to the cage, a cage supervisor shall determine that all locked containers have been returned.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the locked table inventory containers are secured to the gaming table, a pit manager or above shall verify that all the containers are locked.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Table Inventory for a Poker Table.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the requirements in Regulations .02, .03, .06, and .07 of this chapter, a facility operator may establish procedures for the issuance of table inventories that are maintained by poker dealers on an impress basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission the procedures developed under <cite path="36|05|03|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> as part of the facility operator's internal controls.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Table Inventory Counts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements in Regulations .03, .07, and .08 of this chapter for opening a table game, conducting a drop during an open game, and closing a table game, a facility operator may establish procedures for the use of a three-compartment drop box.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The use of a three-compartment drop box requires the preparation of a Table Inventory Slip for each shift that the table was open at least once each gaming day.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission the procedures developed under <cite path="36|05|03|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> as part of the facility operator's internal controls.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Match Play Coupons and Direct Bet Coupons.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may use Match Play Coupons and Direct Bet Coupons.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A coupon may not be issued by a facility operator or used in a facility until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The design specifications of the proposed coupon are submitted to and approved by the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A system of internal procedures and administrative and accounting controls governing the inventory, distribution and redemption of the coupon is submitted to and approved by the Commission as part of the facility operator’s internal controls.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A coupon issued by a facility operator shall contain at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name or logo of the facility operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The value of the coupon, which can be identified when viewing the coupon through the facility operator’s surveillance system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A sequential serial number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any restrictions regarding redemption, including the type of game or wager on which the coupon may be used; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The expiration date of the coupon.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Match Play Coupons shall contain an area designated for the placement thereon of the required gaming chips that does not obscure the visibility of the denomination of the coupon.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Administration of Coupon Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The accounting department and the marketing department, or other department as specified in the facility operator’s internal controls, shall be responsible for administering the coupon program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The marketing department shall be responsible for distributing the coupon to a player.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The accounting department shall be responsible for maintaining the coupon ledger and administering the coupon accounting procedures set forth in <cite path="36|05|03|.11|N.">§N of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A shipment of coupons received from a manufacturer or contractor, or those coupons produced by the facility operator, in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.11|Q.">§Q of this regulation</cite> shall be opened and examined by at least one member of the accounting department and one member of the marketing department, who shall report any deviation between the invoice accompanying the coupon and the actual coupon received to a supervisor from the accounting department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>After checking a coupon received from a manufacturer or contractor, or produced by the facility operator, an accounting department supervisor shall record the following information in the coupon ledger:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date a coupon was received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The quantity and denomination of coupons received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The beginning and ending serial number of the coupons received; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name, signature and license number of the individuals who checked the coupons.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A marketing department supervisor shall estimate the number of coupons needed for each gaming day or promotion and complete a requisition document which contains the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date the requisition was prepared;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date for which the coupons are needed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The denomination and quantity of coupons requested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name, signature, and license number of the marketing department supervisor completing the requisition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The name, signature and license number of the accounting department supervisor authorizing the requisition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of the requisition document, the accounting department supervisor shall record in the coupon ledger the following information before issuing the coupons to the marketing department supervisor:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The beginning and ending serial number of the coupons to be issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The denomination and quantity of coupons to be issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name, signature and license number of the accounting department supervisor who will be issuing the coupons; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A record and explanation of coupons that were voided.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A coupon that is not issued to the marketing department shall be controlled by an accounting department supervisor or above and stored in a secured and locked area approved by the Commission, as designated in the facility operator’s internal controls the location of the approved storage area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The marketing department shall maintain a daily Coupon Reconciliation Form which shall contain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The beginning and ending serial numbers of the coupons received from the accounting department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The denomination and quantity of coupons the marketing department has to distribute to players;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The denomination and quantity of coupons the marketing department distributed to players;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The denomination, quantity, and serial numbers of coupons remaining;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The serial numbers of coupons that were voided and the reason the coupons were voided;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any discrepancy discovered in the accounting for coupons and an explanation of the discrepancy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The name, signature and license number of the marketing department supervisor completing the form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Undistributed Coupons.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the end of the gaming day or promotional period, a copy of the Coupon Reconciliation Form and all coupons that were not distributed to players shall be returned to the accounting department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The marketing department may keep for use during the next gaming day all coupons that were not distributed to players if the coupons are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stored in a secured and locked area approved in advance by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recorded on the daily Coupon Reconciliation Form for the next gaming day.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All expired coupons shall be returned to the accounting department on a daily basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When unused and expired coupons are returned to the accounting department, an accounting department supervisor shall record the following information in the coupon ledger:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date the coupons were returned;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The beginning and ending serial numbers of the coupons returned;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The denomination and quantity of coupons returned;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The serial numbers of any coupons that were voided and the reason the coupons were voided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The name, signature, and license number of the marketing department supervisor returning the unused coupons; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The name, signature, and license number of the accounting department supervisor who received the unused coupons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>All documentation, voided coupons, redeemed coupons, and coupons that were not distributed to players shall be forwarded daily to the accounting department where the coupons shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Counted and examined for proper calculation and recording;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reviewed for the propriety of signatures on the documentation and cancelled;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reconciled by total number of coupons given to the marketing department for distribution to players, returned for reissuance, voided, distributed to players and redeemed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recorded, maintained, and controlled by the accounting department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>At least once every month, a facility operator shall inventory all coupons that are not distributed to players and record the result of the inventory in the coupon ledger in accordance with the inventory procedures that the Commission approved as part of the facility operator’s internal controls.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall prepare and submit to the Commission a quarterly report that lists the total value of the coupons redeemed by players.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator’s Commission-approved internal controls include its production and subsequent reconciliation of coupons, a facility operator may internally manufacture or print coupons.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Production of Coupons. If a facility operator’s Commission-approved internal controls include the production of coupons by a manufacturer or contractor, a facility operator may authorize a manufacturer or contractor to print and mail coupons directly to players in accordance with the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The coupons shall comply with the requirements in §§B and C of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall supply the manufacturer or contractor, through electronic means, a list of the following information for each player to whom the coupon shall be mailed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The player’s name and address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The denomination of the coupon;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The expiration date of the coupon; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A serial number on each coupon;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The coupon issued shall include a magnetic strip or bar code that will enable the facility operator’s computer system to identify the information required under <cite path="36|05|03|.11|R.|(2)">§R(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The information in <cite path="36|05|03|.11|R.|(2)">§R(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be provided to the accounting department, which shall maintain the information for purposes of reconciliation as required under <cite path="36|05|03|.11|N.">§N of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prior to redemption of the coupon, a dealer shall verify the expiration date and confirm that the coupon has not expired;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>All coupons issued shall be electronically canceled in the facility operator’s computer system immediately upon redemption or during the counting of the table game drop boxes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall ensure that the manufacturer or contractor does not engage in a predatory marketing practice in violation of <cite path="36.03.03.08">COMAR 36.03.03.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may use a computerized system that complies with the requirements in this regulation if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The computerized system creates coupons that comply with the requirements in §§B and C of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The computerized system provides an audit trail and allows for the segregation of duties to satisfy the requirements in this section; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The facility operator includes in its internal controls procedures governing the production, recording, redemption, and reconciliation of computer-generated coupons.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Use of Match Play Coupons and Direct Bet Coupons.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A coupon may be redeemed only at a gaming table in which a player wagers against the house.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Redemption. The dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify the coupon is valid prior to accepting it as a wager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a coupon is placed on an authorized wager so that the value of the coupon is visible at all times; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Settle winning wagers in accordance with the terms and conditions of the coupon.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Whether the wager wins or loses, the dealer shall deposit the coupon into the drop box attached to the gaming table at the time the winning wager is paid or the losing wager is collected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The coupon shall remain in the event of a push.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Electronic, Electrical, and Mechanical Devices Prohibited.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A player, or an individual acting in concert with a player, may not use, or possess with the intent to use, at a table game a calculator, computer or other electronic, electrical, or mechanical device to assist in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Projecting an outcome at any table game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Tracking or analyzing cards that have been dealt;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Tracking the changing probabilities of a table game; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Developing or tracking a playing strategy to be used by a player.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A violation of <cite path="36|05|03|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may be the basis for immediate ejection from the facility, placement on the Commission’s mandatory exclusion list under <cite path="|36.03.07">COMAR 36.03.07</cite>, or other civil or criminal penalty.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Minimum and Maximum Wagers; Payout Odds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall establish minimum and maximum wagers for any authorized table game in a facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In accordance with <cite path="|36|05|03|.23">Regulation .23 of this chapter</cite>, a facility operator shall provide notice of the minimum and maximum wagers in effect at each gaming table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A wager accepted by a dealer that exceeds the current table maximum, or is lower than the current table minimum, shall be paid or lost in its entirety in accordance with the rules of the game.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator includes a wagering requirement in its rules of the game under <cite path="|36|05|03|.21">Regulation .21 of this chapter</cite> nothing in this regulation shall preclude a facility operator from establishing additional wagering requirements that are consistent with the rules of the game, including a requirement that wagers be made in specified increments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise specified in a Commission-approved paytable, the payout odds for wagers printed on a layout, signage, brochure or other publication distributed by the facility operator shall be stated through the use of the word "to" and may not be stated through use of the word "for".</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Table Game Taxes and Gross Table Game Revenue.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The tax on table game revenue shall be payable to the Commission within 2 business days, with the exception of Maryland State holidays, and must be based upon the gross table game revenue derived during a gaming day reported in the manner prescribed by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Gross table game revenue includes the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The net revenue from all banking table games;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The net revenue from nonbanking table games; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The net revenue from contests or tournaments.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Net revenue from banking table games must be the sum of the net revenue determined for each banking table game individually.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The net revenue for an individual banking table game must be equal to the total of §D(1)—(3) of this regulation, minus the total of §D(4)—(6) of this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The ending inventory of value chips, coins and plaques at the gaming table as reported on the Table Inventory Slip for a table game that remained open for gaming activity when the table was being dropped at the end of the gaming day or the Table Inventory Slip for a table game that was closed prior to the end of the gaming day;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The sum of all Credit Slips for the gaming table for that gaming day;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total of the currency, promotional instruments, and counter checks collected from the drop box for that gaming table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inventory of value chips, coins, and plaques at the gaming table as reported on the Table Inventory Slip for a table game that remained open for gaming activity when the table was being dropped at the end of the previous gaming day or the Table Inventory Slip for a table game that was opened during the gaming day;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The sum of all Fill Slips and payments for counter checks and markers made at the table for the gaming table for that gaming day; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The sum of all promotional instruments that are allowed to be excluded from taxable proceeds under <cite path="36.03.10.36">COMAR 36.03.10.36</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Net revenue from a nonbanking table game shall be the sum of the net revenue determined for each nonbanking table game individually, and the net revenue for an individual nonbanking table game shall be equal to the poker rake.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Net revenue from an electronic wagering system shall be determined through the Commission’s central monitor and control system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Net revenue from any contest or tournament shall be the sum of the net revenue determined for each contest or tournament individually.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The net revenue for an individual contest or tournament must be equal to the sum of all entry fees, buy-ins, re-buy-ins and administrative fees imposed by the facility operator on the contest or tournament participants, minus:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The cash paid by the facility operator to the contest or tournament winners as prizes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The actual cost paid by the facility operator for noncash prizes awarded to the contest or tournament winners.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If the net revenue from a contest or tournament results in a loss, that loss may not offset the net revenue from another contest or tournament and may not be deducted from the calculation of gross table game revenue.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Gross table game revenue may not include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Counterfeit cash or counterfeit value chips;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Coins or currency of other countries that is not readily convertible to cash; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cash taken in a fraudulent act for which the facility operator is not reimbursed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Approval of Table Game Layout, Signage, and Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall submit to the Commission for approval table game staffing plans, tournament schedules, dealer training programs, and schematics of gaming guides, table game layouts, signage and equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this chapter, schematics of table game equipment that shall be submitted to the Commission for review and approval include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cards;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pai gow tiles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Gaming chips;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Plaques;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Commemorative chips;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Pai gow and sic bo shakers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Big Six and roulette wheels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Envelopes and containers used to hold or transport table game equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Match Play Coupons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Direct Bet Coupons; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Table game equipment that are not otherwise required to be submitted to an independent certified testing laboratory for approval under <cite path="36.03.12.05">COMAR 36.03.12.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of written approval from the Commission of its submission under <cite path="36|05|03|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, a facility operator may implement a table game staffing plan, tournament schedule or dealer training program and may utilize a gaming guide, table game layout, signage or equipment in the licensed facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility operator’s equipment storage and destruction areas may not be used until their location and physical characteristics have been approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall obtain approval from the Commission for the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Alternative locations for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Equipment that is required to be on the gaming table, including drop boxes, shakers, shufflers, discard racks and tip boxes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The complete text of the rules of all authorized games as required under <cite path="|36|05|03|.24">Regulation .24 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amendments to the facility operator’s plan for the distribution and collection of slot cash storage boxes, table game drop boxes or bad beat boxes under <cite path="36.03.10.45">COMAR 36.03.10.45</cite> and Regulations .07 and .08 of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sample sets of gaming chips and plaques manufactured in accordance with approved design specifications as required under <cite path="36.05.02.02">COMAR 36.05.02.02</cite> and <cite path="36.05.02.09">COMAR 36.05.02.09</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The collection times for dice, cards, tiles and other table game equipment from the gaming floor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Employee Training by Facility Operators.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall develop a training program for its dealers which, at a minimum, includes training in each of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Procedures for opening and closing tables for gaming, including the proper security procedures regarding table chip inventories;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures for distributing and removing gaming chips and plaques from gaming tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Procedures for accepting cash at gaming tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures for the acceptance of tips and gratuities from players;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Procedures for shift changes at gaming tables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Procedures for the proper placement of wagers by players and the proper collection of losing wagers and payment of winning wagers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Training in recognizing problem and compulsive gamblers at table games and procedures for informing supervisory personnel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.18">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Table Test; Employee Personnel File.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before conducting a table game on the facility operator’s gaming floor, a prospective dealer shall pass a table test on the table games that the dealer will be conducting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A table test required under <cite path="36|05|03|.18|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall consist of the dealer demonstrating proficiency at the table game to the satisfaction of an employee of the facility operator who is a pit manager or higher.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall document the following in a dealer’s personnel file:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completion of the training program required under <cite path="|36|05|03|.17">Regulation .17 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of the table test required under <cite path="36|05|03|.18|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Table Games Rules Submissions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before offering a table game authorized under the standard rules, a facility operator shall submit to the Commission a rules submission that specifies which options the facility operator will use in the conduct of the table game.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may implement the provisions in a rules submission only after receipt of written notice of approval from the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall maintain the current version of each Commission-approved rules submission so that it is available in electronic form, through secure computer access, to the facility operator’s internal audit and surveillance department and the Commission’s compliance representatives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each page of a table game’s rules submission shall indicate the date on which it was approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall maintain a paper or electronic copy of any superseded rules submission for a minimum of 5 years from the date of Commission approval.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Request to Offer a New Table Game or Feature.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator that desires to offer a table game or feature that is not already in the standard rules, or to offer a new wager, paytable or other feature as part of table game that has been approved by the Commission, shall submit a written request to the Commission that contains at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A detailed description of the table game or new feature, including the rules of play and wagering for the new table game or feature;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Description of whether the game is a variation of an authorized game, a composite of authorized games, or a new game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide the true odds, the payout odds, and the house advantage for each wager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide a sketch or picture of the game layout, if any;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Provide sketches, pictures, or samples of the equipment used to play the game;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The reason for proposing the new table game or feature;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A list of other gaming jurisdictions where the new table game or feature is currently being offered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Whether the game, its name, or any of the equipment used to play the game is covered by any issued or pending copyrights, trademarks or patents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other information the Commission requests.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to submitting a change request with the Commission, a facility operator shall, at its expense, submit the new table game or new feature for review to an independent certified testing laboratory certified by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Following testing by the independent certified testing laboratory, the Commission will notify the facility operator whether the new table game or new feature has been approved, approved with conditions, or rejected.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.21">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Game Rules; Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall maintain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A list of all table games that have been approved by the Commission and the standard rules for each approved table game; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Records of a facility operator’s table game or feature rules that have been approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|05|03|.21|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a facility operator may not change the rules under which a particular table game is being operated unless the facility operator submits to, and receives written approval from, the Commission for an amendment to its rules submission under <cite path="|36|05|03|.19">Regulation .19 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may increase or decrease the permissible maximum wager or decrease the permissible minimum wager at a table game:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If no players are playing at the table, at any time; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>While players are playing the game if the facility operator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provides at least 30 minutes advance notice of the change;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Posts a sign at the gaming table advising players of the change and the time that it will go into effect; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Announces the change to players who are at the table.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.22">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Player Access to Game Rules; Gaming Guide.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall maintain, at its security podium or other location approved in advance by the Commission, a printed copy of the complete text of the standard rules of all authorized games that shall be available to the public for inspection upon request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall make available to players upon request a gaming guide that contains, in a printed format, an abridged version of the complete text of the standard rules of all authorized games.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The gaming guide required under <cite path="36|05|03|.22|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> may not be issued, displayed or distributed by a facility operator until a sample of the gaming guide has been submitted to and approved by the Commission in accordance with <cite path="|36|05|03|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may display an approved gaming guide at any location in its licensed facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each facility operator shall make the approved gaming guide available on its web site.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.23">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Table Game Payouts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall use a table game payout document meeting the requirements of this regulation to pay a single payout event that requires the filing of a IRS Form W-2G, Certain Gambling Winnings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall prepare and timely file IRS Form W-2G, Certain Gambling Winnings, in accordance with IRS rules and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall pay a table game payout of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>$50,000 or more by check; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Less than $50,000 by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cash or check; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On the request of a player, any combination of cash, gaming ticket, check, or other methods of payment approved by the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall develop and include in the internal controls submitted to and approved by the Commission under <cite path="36.03.10.05">COMAR 36.03.10.05</cite> procedures addressing the payment of a table game payout event that requires the filing of an IRS Form W-2G, Certain Gambling Winnings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A facility operator's internal controls shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The use of a two-part computer generated table game payout document initiated on the request of a dealer or above after verifying the winning combination of characters at the table game and the amount of the payout.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A requirement that, if a single payout event that requires the filing of an IRS Form W-2G, Certain Gambling Winnings, is less than $50,000, a security department employee or floorperson or above sign the payout document after verifying the winning combination of characters at the table game and the amount of the payout.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A requirement that, if a single payout event that requires the filing of an IRS Form W-2G, Certain Gambling Winnings, is $50,000 or more, a pit manager or higher level gaming operations department employee other than the preparer of the document sign the table game payout document after verifying the winning combination of characters at the table game and amount of the payout.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A requirement that the following information be on a two-part computer generated table game payout document:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date and time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identification number of the table game on which the payout was registered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Winning combination of characters constituting the payout or a code corresponding to the winning combination of characters constituting the payout;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Amount to be paid;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Signature or identification code of the preparer of the document;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The signature or identification code of a verifying witness in accordance with this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The signature or identification code of the employee issuing the funds;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A requirement that the surveillance department:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be notified of a table game payout of $25,000 or more;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Log all notices regarding a table game payout in the surveillance log required under <cite path="36.03.10.12">COMAR 36.03.10.12</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Obtain and retain in accordance with <cite path="36.03.10.11">COMAR 36.03.10.11</cite> a photograph of the face of the player receiving the payout;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Details pertaining to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Payment of a payout at the table game;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The use of an accounting drop box; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Audit procedures to be performed by the facility operator's accounting department at the conclusion of each gaming day;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Procedures addressing unclaimed table game payouts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Details which establish the ability of the facility operator's video lottery system to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensure that a two-part computer generated table game payout document is not susceptible to change or deletion from the system after preparation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Process and document system overrides or adjustments to table game payouts including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Overrides or adjustments where the payout requested does not match the payout amount; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Identification of the level of employee having override authority; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Process voided table game payout documents; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Procedures utilized to issue a manual table game payout document which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Conform to the table game payout verification and signature requirements of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Involve use of a three-part serially pre-numbered manual table game payout document residing in a book, wiz machine, or functional equivalent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Require manual table game payout books or their functional equivalent to be maintained in a secured locked cabinet; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Require the key to the cabinet in <cite path="36|05|03|.23|E.|(9)|(c)">§E(9)(c) of this regulation</cite> to be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Controlled by the security department or the table games department in a manual key box or an automated key tracking system; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Limited to sign out by a floorperson or above.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.24">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Progressive Table Games.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A table game offering a progressive jackpot may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Stand alone;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be linked to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Other table games in a facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Table games in two or more facilities in or outside the State through a wide area progressive system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A manufacturer may not install in a facility, and a facility operator may not make available for play, table game equipment offering a progressive jackpot without written Commission approval of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A progressive proposal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Internal controls submitted addressing the payment of a progressive jackpot.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A manufacturer may not modify the terms of a progressive jackpot, and a facility operator may not make available for play, a table game or table game equipment that offers a progressive jackpot that differs from its approved progressive proposal without the approval in writing of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A table game may offer multiple progressive jackpots.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A progressive jackpot amount may be calculated and transmitted to a table game or table game device by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The operating system of a table game; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A separate progressive controller interfaced to a table game or table game equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A progressive controller shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Located in a restricted area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Secured:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In a dual key controlled compartment with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>One key controlled by a manufacturer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>One key controlled by the Commission; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By alternative means approved by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Capable of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Displaying an available progressive jackpot amount on a table game’s, or table game equipment’s:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Progressive meter; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Common progressive meter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Transmitting to a table game for metering purposes the amount of a progressive jackpot;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If linked to a common progressive meter in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.24|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>, displaying the Commission asset number of the table game on which a progressive jackpot is won;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If a progressive controller is servicing multiple table games, automatically resetting all table games connected to it to a pre-established reset amount; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If the progressive offers multiple jackpot levels, maintaining and displaying for each progressive level the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Number of progressive jackpots won;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Cumulative amount paid;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Maximum progressive payout;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Minimum amount or reset amount; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Rate of progression.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A table game offering a progressive jackpot shall be equipped, for each progressive jackpot offered, with the following mechanical, electrical, or electronic meters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A progressive meter which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May increase in value based upon wagers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Advises the player of the amount which may be won if the table game characters that result in the award of a progressive jackpot appear as a result of activation of play; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is visible from the table game through:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A meter display housed in the video lottery terminal; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A common progressive meter display unit;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A progressive payout meter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An attendant paid progressive jackpot meter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A cumulative progressive payout meter that continuously and automatically records the total value of progressive jackpots paid whether paid:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directly at the table game; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hand paid by a facility operator as a result of a progressive jackpot that exceeds the physical or configured capability of a table game or table game equipment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A table game linked to a common progressive meter for the purpose of offering the same progressive jackpot on two or more table games shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have the same probability of hitting the combination of characters that will award the progressive jackpot as every other table game linked to that common progressive meter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require each:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Player to wager the same amount to receive a chance at winning the progressive jackpot; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Wager to increment the progressive meter by the same rate of progression on every table game connected to the common progressive meter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the requirements of <cite path="36|05|03|.24|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>, table games linked to a common progressive meter for the purpose of offering the same progressive jackpot on two or more table games may be of different denominations or require different wagers, or both, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The probability of winning the progressive jackpot is directly proportional to the wager required to win a jackpot; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A notice indicating the proportional probability of hitting the progressive jackpot on the common progressive meter is conspicuously displayed in a manner specified by the Commission on each linked table game.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A manufacturer may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Set a limit for a progressive jackpot which exceeds the display capability of the progressive meter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Adjust a progressive meter without the prior approval of the Commission unless the adjustment is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Required as a direct result of table game equipment or meter malfunction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reported by the manufacturer in a form and in a time frame specified by the Commission to the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Commission; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Facility operator.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.25">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Table Game Statistical Data.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall maintain complete and accurate records that identify for each table game and type of game by daily, cumulative month-to-date, and cumulative year-to-date basis:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Statistical drop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Statistical win; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Statistical win-to-drop percentages.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prepare and distribute statistical reports to gaming facility management on at least a monthly basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using a 95 percent confidence interval, investigate fluctuations outside of the standard deviation from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The facility operator’s table game win-to-drop percentage for the previous business year; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In the initial year of operations, the previous month; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Document the results of the investigation required under <cite path="36|05|03|.25|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> in writing and submit a copy of the written investigation results to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Inspecting Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After receiving one or more decks of cards at the table, the dealer shall inspect the cards for any defects and a floorperson assigned to the table shall verify the inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After the cards are inspected, the dealer shall spread the cards out face up on the table, in horizontal fan shaped columns by deck according to suit and in sequence, for visual inspection by the first player to arrive at the table.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After the first player arriving at the table has been afforded an opportunity to visually inspect the cards, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Turn the cards face down on the table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Mix the cards thoroughly by washing them; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Stack the cards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After the cards have been stacked, the dealer shall shuffle them in accordance with <cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an automated card shuffling device is utilized and two decks of cards are received at the table, each deck of cards shall be spread for inspection, mixed, stacked, and shuffled in accordance with §§A—D of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the decks of cards received at the table are preinspected and preshuffled, §§A—E of this regulation do not apply.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.27">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Shuffling and Cutting the Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless the cards were preshuffled, the dealer shall shuffle the cards so they are randomly intermixed, manually or with an automated card shuffling device:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Immediately prior to commencement of play;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After each round of play has been completed; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When directed by a floorperson or above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may use an automated card shuffling device which inserts the stack of cards directly into a dealing shoe after shuffling is complete.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A deck shall be removed from the table if an automated card shuffling device:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is being used which counts the number of cards in the deck after the completion of each shuffle and indicates the number of cards present; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reveals that an incorrect number of cards are present.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon completion of the shuffle, the dealer or automated shuffling device shall place the decks of cards in a single stack, and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the cards were shuffled using an automated card shuffling device, deal the cards in accordance with Regulation .28, 29 or .30 of this chapter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the cards were shuffled manually or were preshuffled, cut the cards in accordance with the procedures in <cite path="36|05|03|.27|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a cut of the cards is required, the dealer shall perform the cut in accordance with the standard rules.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>After the cards have been cut and before any cards have been dealt, a floorperson or above may require the cards to be recut if the floorperson determines that the cut was performed improperly or in any way that might affect the integrity or fairness of the game.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If there is no gaming activity at a table which is open for gaming, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Remove the cards from the dealing shoe and discard rack;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless a player requests that the cards be spread face up on the table, spread out the cards on the table face down;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After the first player arriving at the table is afforded an opportunity to visually inspect the cards, complete the procedures in this section and <cite path="|36|05|03|.26">Regulation .26 of this chapter</cite> if there is no automated shuffling device in use; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If an automated shuffling device is in use, stack the cards and place them into the automated shuffling device to be shuffled, and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Remove the batch of cards already in the shuffler; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the automated card shuffling device stores a single batch of shuffled cards inside the shuffler in a secure manner, at a player’s request remove the batch of cards from the shuffler and spread the cards for inspection and reshuffle them prior to dealing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A facility operator may use a dealing shoe or other device that automatically reshuffles and counts the cards provided that the device is submitted to the Commission and approved prior to its use in the facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If a facility operator is using a device described in <cite path="36|05|03|.27|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>, §§E—G of this regulation do not apply.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.28">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Dealing Cards from a Manual Dealing Shoe.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements. If a manual dealing shoe is used, it shall be located on the table in a location approved by the Commission, and the following requirements shall be met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After the procedures required under <cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27 of this chapter</cite> have been completed, the stacked deck of cards shall be placed in the dealing shoe by the dealer or by an automated card shuffling device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prior to dealing any cards, the dealer shall announce “no more bets”.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Progressive Payout Wager is being offered, the dealer shall use the progressive table game system to prevent the placement of any additional Progressive Payout Wagers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a player has made a Progressive Payout Wager, the dealer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collect the Progressive Payout wager in accordance with the standard rules;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On the layout in front of the table inventory container, verify that the number of value chips wagered equals the number of Progressive Payout Wagers accepted by the progressive table game system; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Place the value chips into the table inventory container.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The dealer shall remove each card from the dealing shoe with the hand of the dealer that is closest to the dealing shoe and place the card on the appropriate area of the layout with the opposite hand.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The dealer shall deal the cards in accordance with the standard rules.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After dealing cards in accordance with the standard rules, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Remove the stub from the manual dealing shoe; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|05|03|.28|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, place the stub in the discard rack without exposing the cards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an automated card shuffling device described in <cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27 of this chapter</cite> is not being used, the dealer shall count the stub at least once every 5 rounds of play to determine if the correct number of cards required by the standard rules are still present in the deck.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Number of Cards. The dealer shall determine the number of cards in the stub as required under <cite path="36|05|03|.28|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> by counting the cards face down on the layout.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the count of the stub indicates that the correct number of cards is in the deck, the dealer shall place the stub in the discard rack without exposing the cards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the count of the stub indicates that the number of cards in the deck is not correct, the dealer shall determine if the cards were misdealt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If correct number of cards remain in the deck, but the cards were misdealt so that a player has more or less than the required number of cards or the dealer has more or less than the required number of cards, all hands are void and the dealer shall return all wagers to the players.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the cards were not misdealt as described in <cite path="36|05|03|.28|E.|(3)">§E(3) of this regulation</cite>, all hands are void and the dealer shall return all wagers to the players and remove the entire deck of cards from the table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.29">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.29</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Dealing Cards from the Hand.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements. If the cards are dealt from a dealer’s hand, the following requirements shall be met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An automated shuffling device shall be used to shuffle the cards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After the procedures required under <cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27 of this chapter</cite> have been completed, the dealer shall place the stacked deck of cards in either of the dealer’s hand.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After the dealer has chosen the hand in which to hold the cards, the dealer shall continue to use that hand while holding the cards during that round of play.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The cards held by the dealer shall be kept over the table inventory container and in front of the dealer at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Before dealing any cards, the dealer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Announce “no more bets”; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the Progressive Payout Wager is being offered, use the progressive table game system to prevent the placement of any additional Progressive Payout Wagers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If any Progressive Payout Wagers have been made, the dealer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On the layout in front of the table inventory container, collect the wagers in accordance with the standard rules;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Verify that the number of value chips wagered equals the number of Progressive Payout Wagers accepted by the progressive table game system; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Place the value chips into the table inventory container.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Deal each card by holding the deck of cards in the chosen hand;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use the other hand to remove the top card of the deck to place it face down on the appropriate area of the layout;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Deal the cards in accordance with the standard rules.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|05|03|.29|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, after dealing cards in accordance with the standard rules, place the stub in the discard rack without exposing the cards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an automated card shuffling device described in <cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27 of this chapter</cite> is not being used, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Count the stub at least once every five rounds of play to determine if the correct number of cards is still present in the deck in accordance with the standard rules; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determine the number of cards in the stub by counting the cards face down on the layout.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the count of the stub indicates that the correct number of cards is in the deck, the dealer shall place the stub in the discard rack without exposing the cards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the count of the stub indicates that the number of cards in the deck is not correct, the dealer shall determine if the cards were misdealt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the correct number of cards remains in the deck, but the cards were misdealt so that a player has more or less than the required number of cards or the dealer has more or less than the required number of cards, all hands are void and the dealer shall return all wagers to the players.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the cards were not misdealt as described in <cite path="36|05|03|.29|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, all hands are void and the dealer shall return all wagers to the players and remove the entire deck of cards from the table.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.30">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.30</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Dealing Cards from an Automated Dealing Shoe or Shuffler.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements. If cards are dealt from an automated dealing shoe, the following requirements shall be met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After the procedures required under <cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27 of this chapter</cite> have been completed, the dealer shall place the cards in an automated dealing shoe or shuffler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prior to the shoe or shuffler dispensing any stacks of cards, the dealer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Announce “no more bets”; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the Progressive Payout Wager is being offered, use the progressive table game system to prevent the placement of any additional Progressive Payout Wagers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If any Progressive Payout Wagers have been made, the dealer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On the layout in front of the table inventory container, collect the wagers in accordance with the standard rules;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Verify that the number of value chips wagered equals the number of Progressive Payout Wagers accepted by the progressive table game system; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Place the value chips into the table inventory container.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The dealer shall deal the cards in accordance with the standard rules.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After the cards has been dispensed and delivered in accordance with the standard rules, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Remove the stub from the automated dealing shoe; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|05|03|.30|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, place the cards in the discard rack without exposing the cards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the count of the stub indicates that the correct number of cards required by the standard rules is in the deck, the dealer shall place the stub in the discard rack without exposing the cards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the count of the stub indicates that the number of cards in the deck is not correct, the dealer shall determine if the cards were misdealt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the correct number of cards remains in the deck, but the cards were misdealt so that a player has more or less than the required number of cards or the dealer has more or less than the required number of cards, all hands are void and the dealer shall return all wagers to the players.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the cards were not misdealt as described in <cite path="36|05|03|.30|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, all hands are void and the dealer shall return all wagers to the players and remove the entire deck of cards from the table.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|05|03|.31">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.31</num>
    <heading>Mixing Tiles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After receiving a set of tiles at the table, the dealer shall sort and inspect the tiles and the floorperson assigned to the table shall verify the inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this section precludes a facility operator from cleaning the tiles prior to the inspection required in <cite path="36|05|03|.31|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A dealer shall inspect the tiles at the gaming table by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sorting a set of tiles into pairs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Placing each tile side by side to determine that all tiles are the same size and shading; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Examining the back and sides of each tile to ensure that it is not flawed, scratched, or marked, and if the dealer finds that a tile is unsuitable for use:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A floorperson or above shall bring another set of tiles to the table from the reserve in the pit stand; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The unsuitable set of tiles shall be placed in a sealed envelope or container, identified by table number, date and time and signed by the dealer and floorperson or above.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Following the inspection and verification of the tiles described in <cite path="36|05|03|.31|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Turn the tiles face up;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Place the tiles into 16 pairs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Arrange the tiles according to rank; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Leave the tiles in pairs for visual inspection by the first player to arrive at the table.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After the first player arriving at the table is afforded an opportunity to visually inspect the tiles, the dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Turn the tiles face down on the table;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Mix the tiles:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>With the heels of the hands;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In a circular motion with one hand moving clockwise and the other hand moving counterclockwise; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>With each hand completing at least eight circular motions to provide a random mixing; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Randomly pick up four tiles with each hand and place them side by side in stacks in front of the table inventory container, forming eight stacks of four tiles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The entire set of tiles shall be remixed if, during the stacking process described in <cite path="36|05|03|.31|E.|(2)">§E(2) of this regulation</cite>, a tile is turned over and exposed to the players.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>After each round of play has been completed, the dealer shall turn all of the tiles face down and mix the tiles in accordance with <cite path="36|05|03|.31|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If there is no gaming activity at the table, the dealer shall turn the tiles face up and place them into 16 pairs according to rank.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>After a player arrives at the table, the dealer shall follow the procedures in <cite path="36|05|03|.31|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-04, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-06-24">Regulations <cite path="|36|05|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|05|03|.24">.24</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 471); adopted permanently effective June 24, 2013 (40:12 Md. R. 1044)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-06"><cite path="|36|05|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective September 6, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|36|05|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 848)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-02-16"><cite path="|36|05|03|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 319)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-10-23"><cite path="|36|05|03|.03|H.">Regulation .03H</cite> amended effective October 23, 2017 (44:21 Md. R. 985)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-02-16"><cite path="|36|05|03|.05|P.">Regulation .05P</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 319)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|05|03|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597); September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|05|03|.11|L.">Regulation .11L</cite> amended effective October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|05|03|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|36|05|03|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-11-11"><cite path="|36|05|03|.15|A.">Regulation .15A</cite>, D amended as an emergency provision effective August 26, 2013 (40:19 Md. R. 1542); amended permanently effective November 11, 2013 (40:22 Md. R. 1879)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-09-26"><cite path="|36|05|03|.16|B.">Regulation .16B</cite> amended effective September 26, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.19">Regulation .19</cite> amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.20">Regulation .20</cite> amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.21">Regulation .21</cite> amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.22|A.">Regulation .22A</cite>, B amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|05|03|.23|C.">Regulation .23C</cite>, E amended effective October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-10-19"><cite path="|36|05|03|.23|E.">Regulation .23E</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 319); October 19, 2020 (47:21 Md. R. 905)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-08-17"><cite path="|36|05|03|.25">Regulation .25</cite> adopted effective August 17, 2015 (42:16 Md. R. 1056)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.26">Regulation .26</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.27">Regulation .27</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.28">Regulation .28</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.29">Regulation .29</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.30">Regulation .30</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|36|05|03|.31">Regulation .31</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1111)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
