<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Registration</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before offering services in connection with a fantasy competition to players physically located in Maryland, a fantasy competition operator shall register with the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator may not conduct an online fantasy competition unless registered to do so by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall register with the Commission every year not more than 365 days from the date of its previous registration, if it is offering services in connection with a fantasy competition in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person required to register shall provide, in the manner specified by the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and principal address of the fantasy competition operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a corporation, the state of incorporation and the full name and address of each officer, director, trustee, and principal salaried executive staff officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a foreign corporation, evidence of qualification to conduct business in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a partnership or joint venture, the name and address of each owner and officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the fantasy competition operator’s resident agent in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The place where and the date when the fantasy competition operator was legally established and the form of its organization;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Information concerning each fantasy competition offered by the fantasy competition operator as described in <cite path="|36|09|02|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Evidence satisfactory to the Commission that the fantasy competition operator has established and will implement procedures that prevent those individuals identified in <cite path="36.09.03.03">COMAR 36.09.03.03</cite> from participating in fantasy competitions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A plan that describes how the fantasy competition operator will maintain compliance with <cite path="|36.09.04">COMAR 36.09.04</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A responsible gaming plan required under <cite path="|36.09.05">COMAR 36.09.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Any additional information required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>For each fantasy competition operator registered under this chapter, the Commission shall issue a registration certificate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator registered under this chapter may operate fantasy competitions in accordance with this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Information provided by the fantasy competition operator shall be available for public review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>In the event that information provided by the fantasy competition operator is no longer accurate due to a change in circumstances, a fantasy competition operator shall provide the Commission with the corrected information within 10 work days.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Fantasy Competition Rules.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prior to conducting a new type of fantasy competition, a fantasy competition operator shall submit proposed fantasy competition rules to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator may offer minor variations of a fantasy competition without having to submit new fantasy competition rules to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Minor variations of a fantasy competition include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Offering a contest format for any sport, league, association, or organization previously offered for any fantasy competition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offering a fantasy competition only to employees of a fantasy competition operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The value of a fantasy competition and number of entries permitted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Nonmaterial changes to entry fee and prize structure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of athletes that a player selects to fill a roster when completing an entry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The fields that a player must fill in when completing an entry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Adjustments to a scoring system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Adjustments to a salary cap.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A registration fee of $100 shall be paid to the Commission to process a registration application of a fantasy competition operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fees paid under this regulation are nonrefundable.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Renewal Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless a registration is renewed, a fantasy competition operator’s registration expires 1 year from the last date of registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may renew a fantasy competition operator’s registration if, before the term of the registration expires, the fantasy competition operator:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applies for renewal no later than 45 days prior to the expiration of its current registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submits updated and current copies of all of the documents and information required under <cite path="|36|09|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays a renewal registration fee in the amount of $100 to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|03">03</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-05, Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 853, Acts of 2018</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.12">COMAR 36.09.01.12</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30">Regulations <cite path="|36|09|02|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|36|09|02|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); adopted permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
