<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>General Standards and Prohibitions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on Fantasy Competition Play.</heading>
    <text>Participation in a fantasy competition for which there is an entry fee is prohibited for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A minor, who is an individual under the age of 18;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A Commission member;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An officer or an employee of the Agency;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An individual who lives in the same principal residence as a Commission member or an officer or employee of the Agency and is the member’s, officer’s, or employee’s:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Spouse or domestic partner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sibling; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Parent or parent-in-law; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An individual who has asked to be excluded under <cite path="|36.09.05">COMAR 36.09.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on Fantasy Competition Kiosks.</heading>
    <text>Fantasy competitions may not be offered through a kiosk or machine physically located in the State.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|09|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Restrictions on Fantasy Competition Play by Individuals Associated with Operators.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|09|03|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> an employee, principal, officer, director, or contractor of a fantasy competition operator, or a member of that individual’s immediate family, is prohibited from participating in a fantasy competition offered by any fantasy competition operator; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exception. An individual associated with a fantasy competition operator may participate in a fantasy competition only if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Participation is for testing purposes and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual uses a clearly marked test account for testing purposes including evaluating a fantasy competition platform;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual fully discloses affiliation with a fantasy competition operator to each fantasy competition player in the fantasy competition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The individual is not eligible to win a prize; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The individual awards any prize won in a fantasy competition to the participant who would have won the prize if the individual associated with a fantasy competition operator had not participated; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The fantasy competition is a private fantasy competition that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clearly marked as a private fantasy competition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Limited by the fantasy competition operator to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Employees of the fantasy competition operator;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Immediate family members of an employee of the fantasy competition operator; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Friends of an employee of a fantasy competition operator; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contains a prominently displayed statement informing players that the fantasy competition may include players with specialized knowledge and expertise that could affect their odds of winning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on Fantasy Competition Play by Athletes and Others.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An athlete, sports agent, team employee, referee, or league official, or a member of that individual’s immediate family, is prohibited from entering fantasy competitions based on underlying sporting events in which the individual is a participant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An athlete, sports agent, team employee, referee, or league official, or a member of that individual’s immediate family, may not enter fantasy competitions based on underlying sporting events in which the individual is a participant through another person as a proxy.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|09|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Ensuring Fair Outcomes in Fantasy Competitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fantasy Competition Scripts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A fantasy competition operator may not permit the use of unauthorized scripts on a fantasy competition platform and shall use commercially reasonable efforts to monitor for and prevent use of such scripts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of <cite path="36|09|03|.05|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, scripts shall be treated as offering a competitive advantage if potential uses include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facilitating changes in many line ups at one time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Facilitating use of commercial products designed and distributed by third parties to identify advantageous game strategies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submitting entry fees or adjusting the athletes selected by a fantasy competition player; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Gathering information about the performance of others for the purpose of identifying or entering competitions against fantasy competition players who are less likely to be successful.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authorized scripts shall either be incorporated as a game feature or be prominently displayed and thereby made available to all fantasy competition players.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Beginner Games and Identification of Highly Experienced Players.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fantasy competition operators shall offer some fantasy competitions that are limited to beginner players and exclude highly experienced players.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fantasy competition operators shall clearly and prominently display that a highly experienced player is participating in a fantasy competition by attaching a symbol to the username of a highly experienced player, or by other easily visible means.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fantasy Competition Entries.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A fantasy competition operator shall disclose the number of entries a fantasy competition player may submit for each fantasy competition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A fantasy operator shall take reasonable steps to prevent fantasy competition players from submitting more than the allowable number of entries.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Limit on Number of Accounts. A fantasy competition operator may not permit a player to establish more than one account with a fantasy competition operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Disputes. Fantasy competition operators shall provide an opportunity for fantasy competition players to file a player dispute.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Data. Fantasy competition operators shall prominently display the source of the data utilized in determining results.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on Fantasy Competitions Based on Amateur Sports.</heading>
    <text>A fantasy competition operator may not offer a fantasy competition based on a sporting event featuring amateur athletes who are primarily under 18 years old.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Advertising.</heading>
    <text>Fantasy competition operator advertisements may not depict:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Minors, except professional athletes who may be minors;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Students;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Schools or colleges; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>School or college settings.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|03">03</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-05, Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 853, Acts of 2018</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.02">COMAR 36.09.01.02</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.03">COMAR 36.09.01.03</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.04">COMAR 36.09.01.04</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.05">COMAR 36.09.01.05</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.10">COMAR 36.09.01.10</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.13">COMAR 36.09.01.13</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.13">COMAR 36.09.01.13</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
