<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Financial Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Financial Account Protections.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall hold a fantasy competition player’s funds:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a segregated account that separates player funds from the operational funds of the operator; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In a special-purpose, segregated account that is maintained and controlled by a properly constituted corporate entity that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not the fantasy competition operator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a governing board that includes one or more corporate directors who are independent of the operator and of any corporation related to or controlled by the operator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requires a unanimous vote of all corporate directors to file for bankruptcy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has articles of incorporation that prohibit commingling of fantasy competition player funds with those of the fantasy competition operator, except as necessary to reconcile the accounts of fantasy competition players with sums owed to the fantasy competition operator by those fantasy competition players;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Is restricted from incurring debt other than to fantasy competition players pursuant to the fantasy competition operator’s rules governing the accounts of its fantasy competition players;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Is restricted from taking on obligations of the fantasy competition operator other than obligations to its fantasy competition players pursuant to the fantasy competition operator’s rules governing the accounts of its fantasy competition players; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Other than a special purpose corporate entity established by another fantasy competition operator that meets the requirements of this subtitle, may not dissolve, merge, or consolidate with another company while there are unsatisfied obligations to fantasy competition players.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall comply with all applicable State and federal requirements for data security.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|09|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Limits on Deposits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to season-long fantasy competitions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="36|09|04|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a fantasy competition player may not deposit more than $5,000 in a single calendar month with a fantasy competition operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exception. A fantasy competition player may request a fantasy competition operator to temporarily or permanently increase a deposit limit above $5,000 per calendar month only if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The fantasy competition operator has established and prominently displayed procedures for considering a request from a fantasy competition player to increase the deposit level;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedures for considering a request from a fantasy competition player to increase a deposit level include evaluation of information, including evidence of income or assets, sufficient to confirm the financial ability of a fantasy competition player to afford losses which may result from fantasy competition play at the deposit level requested by the fantasy competition player; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After a temporary or permanent deposit level increase has been approved, the fantasy competition player undergoes an annual evaluation by the fantasy competition operator of information sufficient to confirm the continued financial ability of the fantasy competition player to afford losses that may result from fantasy competition play at the increased deposit level.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on Extensions of Credit.</heading>
    <text>A fantasy competition operator may not extend credit to a fantasy competition player.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|09|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Financial Auditing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator that conducts competitions that require an entry fee and that generates gross annual revenues of $250,000 or more in Maryland shall ensure that a financial audit is performed annually by a certified public accountant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The certified public accounting firm that conducts the financial audit shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with generally accepted accounting principles; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit the financial audit report to the Commission within 180 days of the fantasy competition operator’s fiscal year end.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The financial audit does not preclude any State or federal agency from conducting an audit of a fantasy competition operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Auditor Exception.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The same certified public accountant may not perform more than five consecutive financial audits for a fantasy competition operator unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The fantasy competition operator requests and obtains preapproval of the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A different audit partner manages the audit after 5 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a different audit partner cannot be assigned, a fantasy competition operator shall advise the Agency prior to the beginning of the audit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the Commission deems it necessary, the Commission may require a fantasy competition operator that is not otherwise required by <cite path="36|09|04|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> to have a financial audit performed by a certified public accountant.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Taxation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall retain 85 percent of its proceeds from players in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall pay 15 percent of its Maryland player proceeds to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reporting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fantasy competition operators shall report fantasy competition prize payouts larger than $600 to the Comptroller of Maryland and the Internal Revenue Service in accordance with applicable tax laws.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall provide a 1099 MISC. tax form to players that receive a prize payout larger than $600.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Tax Laws and Disclosures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall comply with all applicable tax laws and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fantasy competition operator shall disclose tax reporting and withholding requirements to fantasy competition players before the fantasy competition begins and again at the time of award of any prize in excess of $600.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|03">03</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-05, Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 853, Acts of 2018</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.11">COMAR 36.09.01.11</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.07">COMAR 36.09.01.07</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.08">COMAR 36.09.01.08</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended and recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.13">COMAR 36.09.01.13</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); adopted permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30">Regulation.06 adopted as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); adopted permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30"><cite path="|36|09|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> recodified from <cite path="36.09.01.14">COMAR 36.09.01.14</cite> as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); amended permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
