<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Local Government Investment Guidelines and Reporting Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter requires local government units to adopt policies to be followed when investing public funds, to submit the adopted policies to the State Treasurer for acceptance, and certain local government units to submit periodic reports on investment activities to the State Treasurer.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accepted policy” means an adopted policy that has been accepted by the State Treasurer in accordance with <cite path="|25|03|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Adopted policy” means a local government investment policy which has been properly adopted by the local government unit in accordance with the requirements of both local law, and <cite path="|25|03|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Bankers’ acceptances” means an order to pay a sum certain on a certain day to the holder which is drawn on and accepted by the bank that assumes responsibility to make payment to the holder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Board of education” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|1-101">Education Article, §1-101(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Board of library trustees” means those boards established pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 23, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Certificate of deposit” means an interest-bearing negotiable instrument of fixed maturity issued by a commercial bank.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Chief Executive” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Commercial paper” means an unsecured promissory note with a fixed maturity of 270 days or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Community college” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Direct federal obligation” means a security issued by the United States Treasury, the principal and interest of which are guaranteed by the full faith and credit of the United States.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Federal agency obligation” means securities issued by entities that are United States government agencies or by a federal instrumentality created by Congress to advance federal policy through the issuance of securities, such as the Government National Mortgage Association, the Federal National Mortgage Association, the Federal Home Loan Bank, the Federal Farm Credit Bank, and the Student Loan Marketing Association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“GFOA” means the Government Finance Officers Association of the United States and Canada.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Governing body” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Investment manager” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Local government investment pool” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22G">Article 95, §22G, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Local government unit” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Marked to market” means the price at which a security is trading.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Money market mutual funds” means a mutual fund registered with the Securities and Exchange Commission under the Investment Company Act of 1940, 15 U.S.C. §80(A), as amended, and operated in accordance with Rule 2A-7 of the Investment Company Act of 1940, 17 CFR §270.2A-7, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Municipal securities” means debt issued by state and local governments and their agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Municipal Treasurer's Association” means the Municipal Treasurers' Association of the United States and Canada.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Net asset value” means the bid price of a mutual fund share.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Public funds” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Repurchase agreement” means an investment in which an investor buys a security from a broker for a specified period at an agreed rate of interest and the broker agrees to repurchase the security at a specific time for the original purchase price plus the interest accrued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Reverse repurchase agreement” means a method of borrowing using a security as collateral for a loan when the owner sells the security for a stated term with an agreement to repurchase the security at the sales price and an agreed-upon interest rate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“State Treasurer” means the Treasurer of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Requirements for Adoption of Local Government Investment Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The governing body of each local government unit shall adopt by resolution a written investment policy that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complies with State and local law, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|6-222">State Finance and Procurement Article, §6-222, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets or exceeds standards published by nationally recognized financial management organizations recognized by the State Treasurer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The State Treasurer recognizes the standards published by the following nationally recognized financial management organizations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>GFOA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Municipal Treasurer’s Association.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The board of education and the board of library trustees of a county need not adopt a written investment policy but shall invest in compliance with the accepted policy of the county.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>State Law Requirements for Adoption of Local Government Investment Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At a minimum, each adopted policy shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Allow local government units to invest in only those types of securities authorized by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|6-222">State Finance and Procurement Article, §6-222(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Article 95, §§22—22N, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require that investments made by local government units comply with the standards of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|6-222">State Finance and Procurement Article, §6-222(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prohibit the borrowing of money for the sole purpose of investment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Require that the local government unit's investment manager not invest public funds of the local government unit in a manner inconsistent with its adopted policy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A local government unit may include additional requirements in its adopted policy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to §§A and B of this regulation, the adopted policy of a board of education or a board of library trustees shall comply with the provisions of the adopted policy for the county in which the board of education or board of library trustees is located.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Adoption of Local Government Investment Policy and Submission for Acceptance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>By September 1, 1995, the governing body of each local government unit shall adopt by resolution a written local government investment policy that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complies with the requirements of local and State law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Satisfies the requirements of Regulations .03 and .04 of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the individual needs of the local government unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days following adoption, the governing body of each local government unit shall send a certified copy of its adopted policy and its adopting resolution to the State Treasurer for acceptance.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Check by State Treasurer of Local Government Investment Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt, the State Treasurer shall have each adopted policy checked for compliance with this chapter and <cite path="|25.03.04">COMAR 25.03.04</cite>, and shall either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the governing body of the local government unit that its adopted policy has been accepted; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Return the adopted policy to the governing body of the local government unit for revision and readoption.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An adopted policy returned by the State Treasurer shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Revised promptly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Readopted by the governing body of the local government unit in accordance with <cite path="|25|03|03|.05|A.">Regulation .05A of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Resubmitted to the State Treasurer in accordance with <cite path="|25|03|03|.05|B.">Regulation .05B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Amendment of Accepted Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An accepted policy may be amended by submitting to the State Treasurer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The proposed language of the amendment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certified copy of the adopting resolution of the local government unit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certified copy of the revised local government investment policy which shall contain the amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The State Treasurer shall consider each amendment in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="|25|03|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State Treasurer shall notify a local government unit to seek compliance if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Local government unit has not sent the State Treasurer an adopted policy in accordance with <cite path="|25|03|03|.05|B.">Regulation .05B of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State Treasurer determines that the adopted policy is not an accepted policy in accordance with <cite path="|25|03|03|.06|A.">Regulation .06A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The State Treasurer periodically shall send a written list of the local government units which have failed to comply with this chapter to the Joint Committee on the Management of Public Funds, which may take further action in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="95|22F">Article 95, §22F, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Article 95, §22F; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|6-222">State Finance and Procurement Article, §6-222</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-01">Regulations <cite path="|25|03|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|25|03|03|.09">.09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 1, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1310); emergency status expired February 1, 1996</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-02-26">Regulations <cite path="|25|03|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|25|03|03|.09">.09</cite> adopted effective February 26, 1996 (23:4 Md. R. 274)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, B amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> repealed as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-14"><cite path="|25|03|03|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective December 14, 1998 (25:25 Md. R. 1835)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-19"><cite path="|25|03|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> repealed effective February 19, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 207)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-19"><cite path="|25|03|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective February 19, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 207)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-25"><cite path="|25|03|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 2024 (51:11 Md. R. 577); emergency status expired October 22, 2024</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
