<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Forest and Woodland Protection</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Policies.</heading>
    <text>In developing and updating its Critical Area program, a local jurisdiction shall follow all of these policies in regard to forest and developed woodland protection:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maintain and increase the forest and developed woodland vegetation of the Critical Area;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conserve forests and developed woodlands and provide for expansion of forested areas;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provide that the removal of trees associated with development activities is minimized and, where appropriate, mitigated; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Recognize that forests are a protective land use to be managed so that maximum values for water quality, wildlife, timber, recreation, and other resources are maintained, recognizing that, in some cases, these uses may be mutually exclusive.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Criteria.</heading>
    <text>In developing and updating its Critical Area program, a local jurisdiction shall use all of the following criteria:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Where forests or developed woodlands occur within a local jurisdiction, the local  jurisdiction shall develop a forest preservation plan as part of its Critical Area program. These plans are to be developed in cooperation with the Department of Natural Resources and other appropriate agencies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each forest preservation plan shall consist of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identification and mapping, or otherwise designating, forests and developed woodland occurring within the Critical Area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identification of those forest areas and developed woodlands which include habitat protection areas in <cite path="|27.01.09">COMAR 27.01.09</cite>; and which also may include forest areas that are periodically flooded within the State wetlands boundary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Programs to provide incentives for the conversion of other land uses to forested conditions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Where forests or developed woodland occur within the local jurisdiction's Critical Area, local policies and programs for tree cultural operations in the Critical Area shall include all of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A forest management plan shall be required for all timber harvesting occurring within any 1-year interval and affecting 1 or more acres in forests and developed woodland in the Critical Area. The plans shall be prepared by a registered professional forester and be reviewed and approved by the Department of Natural Resources through the district forestry boards and the project forester, and filed with an appropriate designated agency within their local jurisdiction. Plans shall include measures to protect surface and ground water quality and identify whether the activities will disturb or affect habitat protection areas as identified in <cite path="|27.01.09">COMAR 27.01.09</cite>, and incorporate protection measures for these areas as specified by the local jurisdictions. To provide for the continuity of habitat, the plans shall address mitigation through forest management techniques which include scheduling size, timing and intensity of harvest cuts, afforestation, and reforestation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sediment control plan shall be required for all harvests of at least 5,000 square feet of disturbed area in the Critical Area, including harvesting on agricultural lands. This plan shall be developed according to the State guidelines entitled: “Standard Erosion and Sediment Control Plan for Forest Harvest Operations.” The operations shall be implemented in accordance with specifications set out by the Department of Natural Resources and enforced by the Department of Natural Resources or the local jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The cutting or clearing of trees within the buffer, as described in <cite path="|27.01.09">COMAR 27.01.09</cite>, shall be in accordance with that chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-1806">8-1806</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-1808">8-1808</cite>(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 1986 (12:24 Md. R. 2352)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container"><cite path="|14.15">COMAR 14.15</cite> became effective upon the enactment of Resolution No. 37 (SJ 9), Acts of 1986.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container"><cite path="|14.15.05">COMAR 14.15.05</cite> recodified to <cite path="|27.01.05">COMAR 27.01.05</cite> in August, 1992</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-08" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective March 8, 2010 (37:5 Md. R 428)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-20"><cite path="|27|01|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 1, 2010 (37:22 Md. R. 1555); January 20, 2025 (52:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-20"><cite path="|27|01|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective January 20, 2025 (52:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
