<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|01|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this title, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Agency” means the State Lottery and Gaming Control Agency and, unless the context dictates otherwise, includes the Director and Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cash.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Cash” means coins, U.S. currency, money orders, debit cards, and checks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Cash” does not include credit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the State Lottery and Gaming Control Commission and, unless the context dictates otherwise, may include staff of the Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“County” means any county in the State of Maryland and the City of Baltimore.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Director” means the Director of the Agency and includes the Director’s designees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Final action on a license denial” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If, after the Director sends written notice of license denial or recommendation of license denial, an applicant fails to timely request a reconsideration meeting, the date of the written notice of the Director’s written notice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If, after a reconsideration meeting, an applicant fails to timely request a Commission hearing, the date of the Director’s written notice after the reconsideration meeting; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the Commission holds or delegates a hearing on an appeal of the Director’s license denial or reconsideration of license denial, the date of the Commission’s or the Office of Administrative Hearings’ written decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Final action on a sanction” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If after the Director sends a deficiency notice under <cite path="|36.02.02">COMAR 36.02.02</cite>, <cite path="|36.03.04">36.03.04</cite>, <cite path="|36.06.05">36.06.05</cite>, <cite path="|36.07.02">36.07.02</cite>, <cite path="|36.03.03">36.03.03</cite> or <cite path="|36.10.08">36.10.08</cite>, a licensee fails to submit a timely, acceptable corrective action plan, and the Commission adopts as final the Director’s deficiency notice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the Commission holds a hearing on the Director’s recommendation to impose a sanction, the date of the Commission’s written decision; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If a licensee seeks judicial review of the Commission’s sanction, the most recent date of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The decision of the Office of Administrative Hearings;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A final judgement under Maryland Rule 2-601; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The entry of a mandate under Maryland Rule 8-606.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Gaming Activity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Gaming activity” means play of a game or machine that is regulated by the Agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Gaming activity” includes activities described in <cite path="|36.06">COMAR 36.06</cite> — <cite path="|36.10">COMAR 36.10</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Gaming law” means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Lottery”, “Maryland Lottery”, or “State Lottery” means the Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Lottery law” means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Player” means a person who participates in lottery or gaming activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Person.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Person” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|1-101">State Government Article §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Person” within <cite path="|36.02">COMAR 36.02</cite>, may include a group of two or more individuals that are playing or claiming together.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Prize” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A monetary award;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Merchandise; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An experiential award, such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A trip; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An outing; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A designated activity involving personal participation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Retailer” or “Lottery retailer” means a business or person who has been licensed by the Agency to sell lottery tickets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Sports wagering” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article §9-1</cite>E-01, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="36.10.01.02">COMAR 36.10.01.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Sports wagering law” means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1E, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Submit" means to deliver a document:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In a manner that ensures its receipt by the party to whom it is addressed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Which is considered complete only upon actual receipt by that party.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“State obligation” means moneys owed pursuant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|11-616">Criminal Procedure Article, §11-616(b) </cite>or 11-618, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-113">Family Law Article, §10-113</cite>.1(a), Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|3-307">State Finance and Procurement Article, §3-307, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Table games” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Roulette, baccarat, blackjack, craps, big six wheel, poker, pai gow, and sic bo shakers, pai gow tiles, any variation and composites of such games, and other games that the Commission has approved for play in a video lottery facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Gaming tournaments in which players compete against one another in one or more of the games authorized under <cite path="36|01|01|.01|B.|(147|(a)">§B(147(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Ticket” or “lottery ticket” means a ticket that a lottery retailer or the Agency makes available for sale.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Video lottery” means gaming or betting conducted using a video lottery terminal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Video lottery facility” means a facility at which players play video lottery terminals and table games.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Video Lottery Terminal.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Video lottery terminal” means any machine or other device that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On insertion of a bill, coin, token, voucher, ticket, coupon, or similar item, or on payment of any consideration is available to play or simulate the play of any game of chance in which the results, including the options available to the player, are randomly determined by the machine or other device; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>By the element of chance, may deliver or entitle the player who operates the machine or device to receive cash, premiums, merchandise, tokens, or anything of value, whether the payout is made automatically from the device or in any other manner.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Video lottery terminal” includes a machine or device that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Does not directly dispense money, tokens, or anything of value to winning players; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Uses an electronic credit system making the deposit of bills, coins, or tokens unnecessary.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Video Lottery terminal” means each single position or seat available for use by a player;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>“Video lottery terminal” does not include an authorized electronic gaming device operated by an eligible organization under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr">Criminal Law Article, Title 12, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Voluntary exclusion program” means the Voluntary Exclusion Program established under <cite path="|36.01.03">COMAR 36.01.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Winnings” means the amount won from a sports wager that is not reduced by a loss.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Work day” means when Maryland State government offices are open for business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Rules of Construction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Gender and Number. In interpreting and applying this title, the following rules of construction shall apply:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Words denoting one gender include and apply to the other gender as well; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The singular includes the plural and vice versa.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Time Computations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Computation of time after an act, event, or default applies the following rules:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In computing any period of time prescribed by this title, the day of the act, event, or default after which the designated period of time begins to run is not included;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the period of time allowed is more than 7 days, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays are counted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the period of time allowed is 7 days or less, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays are not counted; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The last day of the period so computed is included unless it is a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday, in which event the period runs until the end of the next day that is a work day.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Computation of time before a day, act, or event applies the following rules:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In determining the latest day for performing an act that is required by this title to be performed a prescribed number of days before a certain day, act, or event, all days preceding that day, including intervening Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays, are counted in the number of days so prescribed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The latest day is included in the determination unless it is a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday, in which event the latest day is the first preceding day that is a work day.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Lottery and Gaming Control Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Overview of Commission.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission is included in the Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may advise the Director on the administration and operation of the Agency in accordance with the lottery law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>With the assistance of the Agency, the Commission shall regulate the operation of video lottery terminals and table games in accordance with the gaming law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Operational Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meetings.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Commission shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Determine the times and places of its meetings;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Set its procedures for frequency, notice, and conduct of meetings; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Annually elect a chair from among its members.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commission may annually elect a vice chair from among its members.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Commission may not act unless at least four members concur.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Minutes.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Director is the Secretary of the Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Commission shall, as soon as practicable after the Commission meets, prepare minutes of the meeting and make them available to the public as required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|3-306">§3-306 of the General Provisions Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Powers of Commission. The Commission may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue subpoenas to compel attendance of witnesses at any place within the State in the course of any investigation or hearing conducted under the gaming law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Administer oaths and require testimony under oath before the Commission in the course of any investigation or hearing conducted under the gaming law and lottery law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Serve or cause to be served its process or notices in a manner provided for service of process in civil actions under the Maryland Rules; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Propound written interrogatories.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Lottery and Gaming Control Director.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Duties. The Director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervise and administer the operation of the Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide assistance to the Commission in the performance of its duties; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advise the Commission about any changes needed to improve the operation or administration of the Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Powers of Director.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director has all those powers conferred under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Make determinations on all issues relating to the Agency and all of the Agency’s games, promotions, and special activities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine that a game ticket is void and if the game ticket shall be paid; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Establish and announce special purchase options which reduce the purchase price of a game for a specified period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director may determine, and change:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The number of prize categories;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The allocation of prize money among prizes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The price of games;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The probability or odds of winning a game; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any other aspect of game play, payment, and implementation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Director may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Authorize the Agency to substitute a prize of equivalent value or higher for a prize; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approve a winner’s request to receive a cash equivalent value or other substitute prize for a merchandise or experiential prize.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Director may determine that a type of ticket shall be cancelled, including an instant ticket, a multi-jurisdictional ticket, and a draw game ticket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Director may disqualify a game ticket if a player violates an Agency law or regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Director may delegate to another individual the performance of any activity, function, or service in connection with the operation of the Lottery.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Limitations on Gaming Activity.</heading>
    <text>Gaming activity may not be engaged in by, and a prize, jackpot, or winnings may not be paid to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Commission member;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An officer or an employee of the Agency; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who lives in the same principal residence as a Commission member or an officer or employee of the Agency and is the officer’s, member’s or employee’s:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Spouse or domestic partner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sibling; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Parent or parent-in-law; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person whose name appears on a Voluntary Exclusion Program list under <cite path="|36.01.03">COMAR 36.01.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Agency shall conduct periodic reviews to ensure compliance with this Regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Code of Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agency employee" means an employee of the Agency who is designated as a public official under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|15-103">State Government Article, §15-103, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Complaint" means the submission of a communication to the Agency or the Commission alleging a violation of a law, regulation, or the code of conduct established by the Director.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Conflict of interest" means a situation in which a personal interest of a Commission member or an Agency employee may be contrary to the public interest in an anticipated Commission action or decision.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"Ex parte communication" means a direct or indirect communication between a Commission member or Agency employee and another person regarding an issue in a matter that is pending before the Commission, if the communication is made outside the presence of an opposing person.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Recusal" means nonparticipation of a Commission member in a specific matter before the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establishment and Compliance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall establish a code of conduct for members of the Commission and Agency employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Members of the Commission and Agency employees shall comply with the code of conduct.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Recusal of Commission Members.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Commission member may not participate in a Commission proceeding in matters in which the member:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has a conflict of interest; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cannot participate fairly and impartially.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Commission member’s familiarity with a person does not, of itself, require recusal of the Commission member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Commission member who is recused from a matter before the Commission may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Participate in the Commission's discussion or vote on the matter; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Discuss the matter or the Commission's review of the matter with members of the Commission or another person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A Commission member who is recused shall physically leave the room during hearings, discussion, or voting on the matter to ensure nonparticipation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall document the recusal of the Commission member in the minutes of the Commission meeting from which the member was recused.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Complaints.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Commission member against whom a complaint is filed shall follow §C(3) and (4) of this regulation for Commission discussion and voting related to the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a complaint, the Commission may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Direct the Agency to investigate; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Refer the complaint to appropriate unit of State government.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An Agency employee who has a conflict of interest pertaining to the Commission member who is the subject of the complaint may not participate in an investigation of the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commission member who is the subject of the complaint may not participate in any Commission activity until the complaint is resolved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Confidentiality.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Commission member or Agency employee may not discuss confidential matters with a person other than:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Commission member;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An Agency employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Attorney General's Office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A witness; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Another person authorized by law to be involved in the case.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the case of an ex parte communication, the Commission member shall follow the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-219">State Government Article, §10-219, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-101">9-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-111">9-111</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-116">9-116</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-123">9-123</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|01">01</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|02">02</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|24">24</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-205">10-205</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-29">Effective date: April 29, 2013 (40:8 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13"><cite path="|36|01|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); amended permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-02-16"><cite path="|36|01|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 319)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13"><cite path="|36|01|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 5, 2021 (48:18 Md. R. 690); amended permanently effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
