<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Voluntary Exclusion and Responsible Gaming</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This chapter establishes a mechanism by which an individual may request to be placed on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List of individuals with gambling problems who have requested to self-exclude themselves from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Video lottery facilities in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lottery play in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Instant bingo facilities under <cite path="|36.07">COMAR 36.07</cite> with more than 10 instant bingo machines;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Participating in fantasy competitions offered by fantasy competition operators registered under <cite path="|36.09">COMAR 36.09</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Participating in sports wagering offered by a sports wagering licensee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any combination of the five.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless context or the individual regulation dictates otherwise, in this chapter the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>”Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List” means the list established by the Commission as a measure to reduce or mitigate the effects of problem gambling that allows individuals with gambling problems to request to be excluded from participating in certain lottery and gambling activities for a specified period of time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>”Direct exclusion” means the ability of a person to make a request directly to a fantasy sports competition operator or a sports wagering licensee for exclusion from their online services.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>”Sports wagering licensee” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Sports wagering facility licensee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Mobile sports wagering licensee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Sports wagering facility operator licensee; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Online sports wagering operator licensee.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for individuals who have requested to be excluded from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Video lottery facilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lottery play in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Instant bingo facilities with more than 10 instant bingo machines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Fantasy competitions offered by registered fantasy competition operators; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Participating in sports wagering offered by sports wagering licensees; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establish measures to reduce and mitigate the effects of problem gambling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Application for Placement on the Commission's Voluntary Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application for placement on the Commission's Voluntary Exclusion List shall be available through:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each licensed video lottery facility upon request to Commission staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each licensed instant bingo facility with more than 10 instant bingo machines; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Information about applications for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List shall be available through:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each licensed video lottery facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each registered fantasy competition operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each sports wagering licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each licensed instant bingo facility with more than 10 instant bingo machines; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual may request to be excluded from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The places and activities described in <cite path="|36|01|03|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> by submitting a completed application for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List to Commission staff; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An instant bingo facility with more than 10 instant bingo machines by submitting a completed application form to instant bingo facility staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An application for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sufficient information to identify and exclude the individual, including the individual’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name, including any nickname or alias;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Residential address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Date of birth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Valid, unexpired, government-issued identification that includes a photograph of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Social Security number or other government-issued identification number, if applicable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Gender;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Physical description, including any birthmarks, scars, or tattoos;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Race or ethnic origin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Signature, which may include the use of a Commission-approved secure electronic means; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Signature; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Any other information about the individual that the Commission requires;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The length of time requested for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List, which shall be for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 2 years; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Life;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Information pertaining to problem gambling programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Acknowledgment that certain problem gambling programs may contact the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A signed statement by which the individual declares that the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has a gambling problem and is unable to gamble responsibly;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is sober and informed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Releases and holds harmless the State of Maryland, the Commission, the Agency, and their members, employees, and agents from any liability that may arise from the application or the individual’s placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Acknowledges that the Commission is collecting information from the individual that the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Individual may request to inspect or correct under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-502">General Provisions Article, §4-502, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Commission will maintain as sociological information under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-330">General Provisions Article, §4-330, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Commission or its licensees may share with entities as provided in <cite path="|36|01|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Authorizes the release of information to the persons specified in <cite path="|36|01|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Acknowledges that the individual will be, for the entire term of the requested period of exclusion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Prohibited from entering a video lottery facility and playing table games or a video lottery terminal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Prohibited from playing a lottery game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Prohibited from playing an instant bingo machine at an instant bingo facility with more than 10 instant bingo machines;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Prohibited from participating in a fantasy competition offered by a fantasy competition operator registered under <cite path="|36.09">COMAR 36.09</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Prohibited from participating in sports wagering offered by a sports wagering licensee under <cite path="|36.10">COMAR 36.10</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Any combination of the five;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Acknowledges that if the requested period of placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List was 2 years, the individual will not be removed from the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List unless the Commission grants the individual’s request for removal under <cite path="|36|01|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Acknowledges that the individual may be subject to criminal charges if, during the period of exclusion, the individual enters a video lottery facility in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Acknowledges that the individual may be, for the entire term of the requested period of exclusion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Banned by a video lottery facility from any of its affiliated facilities in Maryland or other jurisdictions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Removed or precluded from utilizing a video lottery facility’s associated sports wagering platform;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Banned from video lottery facilities that offer sports wagering;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Even if accessed from a different state, removed or precluded from joining or participating in a fantasy competition operator’s online platform;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Banned by a sports wagering facility from any of its affiliated facilities in Maryland or other jurisdictions; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Even if accessed from a different state, removed or precluded from joining or participating in a mobile sports wagering licensee’s online platform;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Otherwise acknowledges that the individual understands the individual’s responsibilities and possible consequences associated with being placed on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Is voluntarily applying.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a completed application for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List, assigned Commission staff may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Interview the individual in order to ascertain that the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is voluntarily applying for exclusion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is sober and informed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Confirms the information provided in the application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is fully informed of the consequences of being placed on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Decide whether to accept the request for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List and place the individual on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Deliver to the individual by regular U.S. mail a written notice of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Denial of the application requesting placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Notice to Individual Placed on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Agency’s notice to an individual of placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for video lottery facilities, shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement from each video lottery facility informing the individual not to enter the video lottery facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notice that, if the individual enters a video lottery facility, the individual may be subject to criminal charges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Notice that the individual may be banned by a video lottery facility from any of its affiliated facilities in Maryland or other jurisdictions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Notice that the individual may be unable to participate in sports wagering offered by a sports wagering facility operator or online sports wagering operator affiliated with a video lottery facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Agency’s notice of an individual’s placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for exclusion from participating in fantasy competitions in the State shall include notice that the individual may be excluded from participating in fantasy competitions offered by fantasy competition operators in another jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Agency’s notice of an individual’s placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for exclusion from sports wagering in the State shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice that the individual is not permitted in the sports wagering-related areas of a sports wagering facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notice that the individual may be excluded from participating in sports wagering offered by a sports wagering licensee in any of its affiliated facilities or platforms in other jurisdictions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Notice that, if the individual enters a video lottery facility that offers sports wagering, the individual may be subject to criminal charges.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Direct Exclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registered Fantasy Competition Operator.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registered fantasy competition operator may, on request of an individual, directly exclude the individual from participating in fantasy competitions through its platform.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request for direct exclusion from a fantasy competition operator’s platform:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not an application for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List under this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Will not result in placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is not a record that is maintained by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Does not prevent the person from using another fantasy competition platform in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mobile Sports Wagering Licensee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A mobile sports wagering licensee through its sports wagering platform or its online sports wagering operator’s platform may, on request of an individual, directly exclude the individual from participating in sports wagering on its platform.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request for direct exclusion from a mobile sports wagering licensee’s platform operated by its online sports wagering operator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not an application for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Will not result in inclusion on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is not a record that is maintained by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Does not prevent the person from using another mobile platform in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Voluntary Surrender.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. “Unredeemed item”:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Means a token, voucher, check, ticket, chip, coupon, or similar item that has monetary value, and that a player has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Won by playing a video lottery terminal or table game;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Inserted into a video lottery terminal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Played at a table game;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Received by converting cash, check or wire transfer at a video lottery facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Won by participating in a fantasy competition offered by a fantasy competition operator registered under <cite path="|36.09">COMAR 36.09</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Received by converting cash, check, wire transfer, points, tickets, coupons, or similar item or monetary equivalent through a registered fantasy competition operator’s system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Won by participating in sports wagering;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Inserted into sports wagering equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Received by converting cash, check, wire transfer, or points through sports wagers placed with a sports wagering licensee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Obtained while playing a lottery game in the State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Won by playing an instant bingo machine at an instant bingo facility with more than 10 instant bingo machines.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not include cash.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who applies to be placed on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List contractually agrees to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Redeem or liquidate an unredeemed item with monetary value that the individual has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In their possession since being placed on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Received from a fantasy competition, if the individual entered the fantasy competition after placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designate that the proceeds of the item be redeemed and contributed to the Problem Gambling Fund established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33(b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>The Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List.</heading>
    <text>The Commission shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establish and maintain a list of individuals:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From whom it has received a completed application requesting to be excluded as provided in <cite path="|36|01|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whose request for placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List has been accepted under <cite path="|36|01|03|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Provide the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for video lottery facilities to a video lottery facility, with periodic updates, to assist the video lottery facility in identifying excluded individuals;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Enter the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for lottery play into the Agency’s control system to ensure that an excluded individual’s prizes over $600 on a ticket will be surrendered under <cite path="|36|01|03|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Provide the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for individuals who have self-excluded from instant bingo to an instant bingo facility with more than 10 instant bingo machines, with periodic updates, to assist the facility in identifying excluded individuals;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Provide the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for individuals who have self-excluded from participating in fantasy competitions in the State to a registered fantasy competition operator, with periodic updates, to assist the fantasy competition operator in identifying excluded individuals; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Provide the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for individuals who have self-excluded from participating in sports wagering in the State to sports wagering facility licensees and mobile sports wagering licensees, with periodic updates, to assist them in identifying excluded individuals.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|01|03|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Removal from the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After an individual has been on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List for at least 2 years, the individual may request that the Commission remove the individual from the list.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual shall submit their request under <cite path="36|01|03|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> in writing to the Commission accompanied by documentation that the individual has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A problem gambling treatment or prevention program approved by the Commission; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A healthy decision-making program that is sponsored or approved by the Commission, with a licensed professional counselor or other person approved by the Commission;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Executed an authorization and release to be removed from the voluntary exclusion list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complied with any requirements deemed necessary by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission is not required to hold a hearing in order to review the request for removal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Grants the request, it shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Deliver to the individual by email or regular mail a notice of removal from the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the State’s video lottery facilities, instant bingo facilities with more than 10 instant bingo machines, registered fantasy competition operators, sports wagering facility licensees, and mobile sports wagering licensees, or update the Agency’s central system with the individual’s removal from the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Denies the request, it shall deliver to the individual by email or regular mail a notice that the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Request was denied; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual shall remain on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Access to the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All records pertaining to an individual’s placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List are sociological information under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-330">General Provisions Article, §4-330, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Access to records pertaining to an individual’s placement on the Commission’s Voluntary Exclusion List shall be limited to disclosures authorized under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, <cite path="|36.03.06">COMAR 36.03.06</cite>, and <cite path="|36|01|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|01|03|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Responsible Gaming Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may establish a responsible gaming program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A responsible gaming program established by the Commission under <cite path="36|01|03|.08|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be designed to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reduce or mitigate the effects of problem gambling in the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maximize the access of individuals who have a gambling problem to problem gambling resources.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|12-301">12-301</cite>.1 and 12-308; State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-110">9-110</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|24">24</cite>(e), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>D-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|05">05</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>E-11; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-29">Effective date: April 29, 2013 (40:8 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-22"><cite path="|36|01|03|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective February 3, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 93); October 22, 2018 (45:21 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-01"><cite path="|36|01|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective February 3, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 93); February 1, 2016 (43:2 Md. R. 129)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite>, D amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-02-03"><cite path="|36|01|03|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective February 3, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 93)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-01-14"><cite path="|36|01|03|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-05-30" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2021 (49:3 Md. R. 137); revised permanently effective May 30, 2022 (49:11 Md. R. 610)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
