<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Compensation to Individual Erroneously Convicted, Sentenced, and Confined</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter supplements the procedures for adjudicating a request for order of eligibility for compensation and a petition for supplemental compensation as required by law.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability. This chapter applies to a request for an order of eligibility for compensation and a petition for supplemental compensation made in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter shall be construed to ensure the fair and expeditious review of each request or petition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The adjudication of a request for order of eligibility for compensation or a petition for supplemental compensation is a contested case proceeding subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the Rules of Procedure found in <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“ALJ” means an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appointed by the Chief Administrative Law Judge under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1604">State Government Article, §9-1604, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Designated by the Chief Administrative Law Judge under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1607">State Government Article, §9-1607, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Application” means a written application for reasonable attorney’s fees and expenses under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(c)(3) </cite>or (d)(1)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Chief Judge” means the Chief Administrative Law Judge of the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Claimant” means an individual who files a request for an order of eligibility under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Filed” means that a document is postmarked or received in accordance with Regulation <cite path="28.02.01.04|D.">28.02.01.04D</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Office” means the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Other benefits” means those services provided by a State service provider identified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Petition for supplemental compensation” means a request for an order of supplemental compensation under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(c)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Petitioner” means an individual who files a petition for supplemental compensation under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(c)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Request” means a request for order of eligibility for compensation under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Filing and Service of a Request for Order of Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A claimant requesting an order of eligibility shall file the request with the Office as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(b)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, <cite path="28.02.01.04|D.">COMAR 28.02.01.04D</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The request shall be captioned “In the Matter of the Wrongful Conviction of (Claimant(s)) v. Board of Public Works.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The request shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name of the county where the alleged erroneous judgment of conviction for a felony was entered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name of the current State’s Attorney in the county where the alleged erroneous judgment of conviction for a felony was entered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The conviction date; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The duration of the alleged erroneous confinement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A claimant may initiate a request for order of eligibility by filing a form substantially similar to that in Appendix A of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A request for order of eligibility shall be served on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The current State’s Attorney in the county where the alleged erroneous judgment of conviction for the felony was entered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Office of the Attorney General.</text>
        <text>
          <cite path="28|05|01|attachments|28.05.01.04-appendix-A">FORM AT END OF CHAPTER</cite>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Filing and Service of a Petition for Order of Supplemental Compensation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A petitioner requesting an order of supplemental compensation shall file the petition with the Office as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(c)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, <cite path="28.02.01.04|D.">COMAR 28.02.01.04D</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The petition shall be captioned: “In the Matter of the Wrongful Conviction of (Claimant(s)) v. Board of Public Works.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The petition shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date or dates on which the previous compensation was awarded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount of the previous compensation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The conviction date; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The duration of the alleged erroneous confinement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A petitioner may initiate a request for order of supplemental compensation by filing a form substantially similar to that in Appendix B of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A petition for order of supplemental compensation shall be served on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The current State’s Attorney in the county where the alleged erroneous judgment of conviction for the felony was entered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Office of the Attorney General.</text>
        <text>
          <cite path="28|05|01|attachments|28.05.01.05-appendix-B">FORM AT END OF CHAPTER</cite>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Prehearing Conference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a request or a petition, the Office will schedule a prehearing conference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Office will send to all parties:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice of the prehearing conference;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instructions for the prehearing conference; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An identification of benefits form substantially similar to that in Appendix C of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The prehearing conference may address any issue set out in <cite path="28.01.02.17|C.">COMAR 28.01.02.17C</cite> and shall address the following matters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Scope of any evidentiary hearing, including the application of a clear and convincing burden of proof;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Stipulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Subpoenas duces tecum for records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Participation of each party in each stage of the proceedings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Motions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>For a request, identification of the asserted factual basis for eligibility under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(b)(1)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>For a petition, identification of the asserted factual basis for eligibility under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(c)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Identification of any requested benefit and State service provider under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Scheduling of any post-hearing process, as necessary, to determine requested benefits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Applications for reasonable attorney’s fees and expenses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Alternative dispute resolution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Scheduling; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Any other matter that will promote the order and prompt resolution of the request or petition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Conduct.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All parties shall participate in the prehearing conference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The ALJ shall record the prehearing conference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ALJ shall issue a prehearing conference order setting forth the actions taken or to be taken regarding the matters addressed at the prehearing conference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The prehearing order shall be part of the case record.</text>
        <text>
          <cite path="28|05|01|attachments|28.05.01.06-appendix-C">FORM AT END OF CHAPTER</cite>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Application for Reasonable Attorney’s Fees and Expenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 15 days of the conclusion of the evidentiary hearing, the claimant may file a written request for reasonable attorney’s fees and expenses under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(c)(3) </cite>or (d)(1)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The claimant shall submit supporting documentation, including time records, with the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The claimant shall serve the application and supporting documentation on all parties to the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A party may file a response to the application within 15 days after the date the application was filed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the ALJ determines that the record is insufficient for review of the application, the ALJ may order the claimant or petitioner to supplement the record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The ALJ shall include a ruling on the application in the final order pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(d)(1)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Only one attorney will be compensated unless the participation of more than one attorney is justified for a specific purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The ALJ may consider the following factors when awarding attorney’s fees:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The time and labor required;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The novelty and difficulty of the questions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The skill required to perform the legal service properly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether acceptance of the case precluded other employment by the attorney;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The customary fee for similar legal services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any time limitations imposed by the client or the circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The amount of compensation involved and the results obtained;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The experience, reputation, and ability of the attorneys;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The undesirability of the case;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The nature and length of the professional relationship with the client; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Awards in similar cases.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Guidelines regarding hourly rates are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Lawyers admitted to the bar for less than or equal to 8 years: $125—$225.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lawyers admitted to the bar for 9—14 years: $165—$300.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lawyers admitted to the bar for 15 years or more: $200—$400.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Paralegals and law clerks: $75—$100.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Final Decisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an ALJ finds that the claimant or petitioner has proven the elements required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the ALJ shall issue a decision finding the individual eligible for compensation and benefits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The ALJ shall include in the decision:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The monetary award;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reasonable attorney’s fees and expenses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Benefits to be awarded; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the ALJ determines that it is in the interests of the claimant or petitioner, a recommendation for an expedited payment schedule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Office shall deliver the decision to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each party or party representative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board of Public Works; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any State agency or State service providers ordered to provide benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The ALJ’s decision is the final agency decision for the purpose of judicial review.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-501">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-501, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13">Regulations <cite path="|28|05|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|28|05|01|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 16, 2021 (48:17 Md. R. 666); emergency provision expired effective December 13, 2021</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13">Regulations <cite path="|28|05|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|28|05|01|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <attachments>
    <attachment name="28.05.01.04-appendix-A" url="./28.05.01.04-appendix-A.pdf"/>
    <attachment name="28.05.01.05-appendix-B" url="./28.05.01.05-appendix-B.pdf"/>
    <attachment name="28.05.01.06-appendix-C" url="./28.05.01.06-appendix-C.pdf"/>
  </attachments>
</container>
