<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions and General Provisions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this title, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Allowance" means a benefit that is payable in equal monthly installments for the life of the recipient, except as otherwise provided for an optional form of an allowance under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-403">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §21-403, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Beneficiary" means a person other than a retiree, in receipt of a benefit under State Personnel and Pensions Article, Division II, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Board of Trustees" means the Board of Trustees for the State Retirement and Pension System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Creditable Service" means the service credit of a member that is recognized for computing a benefit under State Personnel and Pensions Article, Division II, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Earnable Compensation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Earnable compensation" means 1/12 of a member's annual salary rate payable for working the normal time in the member's position, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The employer pickup contribution provided for in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-313">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §21-313, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A contribution made under a salary reduction or supplemental retirement plan in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp">State Personnel and Pensions Article, Title 35, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Longevity pay;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>For a member of the State Police Retirement System, flight pay; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>For a member of the Teachers' Retirement System or the Teachers' Pension System, the compensation paid to the member for performing the member's regular job responsibilities during the period of the member's mandatory assignment that extends beyond the member's 10-month assignment in accordance with the standards and guidelines adopted by the State Superintendent of Schools.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Earnable compensation" does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Bonuses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Overtime;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Summer school salaries;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Adult education salary;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Additional temporary payments from special research projects;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Honorariums;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Vehicle stipends; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Other payments that the Board of Trustees determines are not part of the normal salary for working the normal time in the member's position.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Electronic signature" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|21-101">Commercial Law Article, §21-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Eligibility service" means the service credit of a member that is recognized for determining eligibility for a benefit under State Personnel and Pensions Article, Division II, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Executive Director" means the Executive Director of the Retirement Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Fiscal year" means the year beginning July 1 and ending June 30.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Participant" means a beneficiary, designated beneficiary, former member, member, or retiree who is or may become eligible to receive a benefit of any type from the several systems.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Participating employer" means the employer of an individual who, because of the employment relationship, is eligible for membership in a State system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Retirement Agency" means the State Retirement Agency established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-117">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §21-117, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Secure access participant portal" means the Retirement Agency’s internet website that participants may access only after completing the registration and authentication requirements specified by the Retirement Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Service credit" means the basic unit of eligibility service or creditable service, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Several systems" means the State systems specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-102">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §21-102, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"State system" means a retirement or pension system that is included in the State Retirement and Pension System under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-102">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §21-102, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Submission of Forms through the Secure Access Participant Portal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation applies only to forms that the Retirement Agency permits a participant to submit in an electronic format to the Retirement Agency through the secure access participant portal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Retirement Agency may establish a secure access participant portal and specify the registration and authentication requirements that participants must satisfy in order to access and use the secure access participant portal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A participant may submit a form through the secure access participant portal by properly completing submission and affixing an electronic signature in the manner and format required by the Retirement Agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except when Division II of the State Personnel and Pensions Article requires notarization, and notwithstanding any other provision of this title, a participant who submits a form through the secure access participant portal and satisfies its authentication requirements is not required to have the form acknowledged by a notary public.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-108">21-108</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-110">21-110</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1996 (22:26 Md. R. 2031)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective January 1, 1996, all of Title 22 was repealed and completely new regulations adopted. Codification and organization of the title were also completely changed. Consequently, the administrative histories of the revised Title 22 do not reflect regulatory activity before January 1, 1996. Refer to the old version of Title 22 or contact the Maryland State Archives for assistance.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-12-10"><cite path="|22|01|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective November 30, 1998 (25:24 Md. R. 1774); September 6, 1999 (26:18 Md. R. 1377); December 10, 2001 (28:24 Md. R. 2130)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|22|01|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 108)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11"><cite path="|22|01|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed and new Regulation .02 adopted effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 108)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
