<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Proof of Date of Birth</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definition.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, "alternate payee" means a former spouse named in an eligible domestic relations order that the Retirement Agency has accepted for administration pursuant to a notice of administration issued in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-502">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §21-502, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="22.01.03.04">COMAR 22.01.03.04</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Proof of Birth.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Individuals Required to Submit Proof of Birth.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When an individual enrolls as a member of a State system, the individual shall submit documentation to verify the individual's date of birth to the Retirement Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On the request of the Retirement Agency, an individual who applies for an allowance shall submit documentation to verify the individual’s date of birth and the date of birth of any designated beneficiaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On the request of the Retirement Agency, a participant or alternate payee who is or may become eligible to receive a benefit of any type under State Personnel and Pensions Article, Division II, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall submit documentation to the Retirement Agency to verify the individual’s date of birth.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual who is a United States citizen shall submit any one of the following documents to verify the individual’s date of birth:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Birth certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Adoption record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Statement of age card from the county health department or United States Bureau of Vital Statistics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>United States passport;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Naturalization records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Census record from the United States Bureau of the Census;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Military documentation from any branch of the United States Armed Forces;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Hospital birth record, certified by the custodian of the record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Unexpired driver's license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Unexpired Maryland Identification Card, formerly called Maryland Age of Majority Card, issued by the Maryland State Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who is not a United States citizen shall submit a resident alien registration receipt card to verify the individual's date of birth.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Retirement Agency shall accept a photostatic, facsimile, or electronically imaged copy of any one of the documents listed in §B or C of this regulation, but reserves the right to require the individual to submit the original document from which the copy was made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an individual cannot obtain any of the documents listed in §B or C of this regulation, the Retirement Agency may determine an alternate form of documentation to verify the individual’s date of birth.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-110">State Personnel and Pensions Article, § 21-110, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1996 (22:26 Md. R. 2031)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective January 1, 1996, all of Title 22 was repealed and completely new regulations adopted. Codification and organization of the title were also completely changed. Consequently, the administrative histories of the revised Title 22 do not reflect regulatory activity before January 1, 1996. Refer to the old version of Title 22 or contact the Maryland State Archives for assistance.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|22|01|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulation .01 adopted effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 109)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11"><cite path="|22|01|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 109)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
