<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Refund of Accumulated Contributions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes procedures for the refund of the accumulated contributions of each member or former member of a State system who separated from employment for a reason other than death or retirement.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Application for Withdrawal of Accumulated Contributions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A member or former member who has separated from employment with a participating employer for a reason other than death or retirement and is not employed by any other participating employer may request a refund of accumulated contributions by properly completing the appropriate form that the Retirement Agency provides and filing it with the Retirement Agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A form to request a refund of accumulated contributions is properly completed if it is completed in accordance with the form’s instructions and signed and dated by the member or former member.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Refund of Accumulated Contributions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Retirement Agency shall pay an applicant the accumulated contributions of the applicant within a reasonable time after receipt by the Retirement Agency of a properly completed application for refund form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an applicant files a photocopy, electronically transmitted copy, or facsimile copy of the application for refund form with the Retirement Agency, the applicant shall retain any original to provide to the Retirement Agency at the request of the Retirement Agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When requesting a refund of accumulated contributions, an applicant may request to have all or a portion of the refund that constitutes an eligible rollover distribution paid to an eligible retirement plan in a direct rollover in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp">State Personnel and Pensions Article, Title 21, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> and <cite path="22.07.02.05">COMAR 22.07.02.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-110">21-110</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|21-603">21-603</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|29-501">29-501</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|29-502">29-502</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1996 (22:26 Md. R. 2031)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-01">Effective January 1, 1996, all of Title 22 was repealed and completely new regulations adopted. Codification and organization of the title were also completely changed. Consequently, the administrative histories of the revised Title 22 do not reflect regulatory activity before January 1, 1996. Refer to the old version of Title 22 or contact the Maryland State Archives for assistance.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|22|01|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 109)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11"><cite path="|22|01|08|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 109)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11"><cite path="|22|01|08|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 109)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
