<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Security and Decorum</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“ALJ” means an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appointed as an Administrative Law Judge pursuant to the requirements established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1604">State Government Article, §9-1604(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Designated pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1607">State Government Article, §9-1607, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Chief ALJ” means the individual appointed as head of the Office pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1603">State Government Article, §9-1603, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dangerous or Toxic Item.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Dangerous or toxic item” means an object or substance that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is capable of causing physical harm, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Otherwise poses a threat to health or safety.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Dangerous or toxic item” includes, but is not limited to, chemicals and sharp objects.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Firearm” means a device capable of propelling a projectile by gunpowder or other means, including, but not limited to, a rifle, shotgun, or handgun.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Office” means the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Office facility” means a building in which a hearing, mediation, or other Office proceeding takes place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Office proceeding” means any type or stage of legal process scheduled by the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Police officer” means an individual who is authorized to make arrests in an official governmental capacity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Weapon.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Weapon” means a device capable of inflicting bodily injury or destroying property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Weapon” includes, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A firearm, crossbow or longbow, knife, club, razor, box cutter, nunchaku, or stun gun;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Metal knuckles, pepper spray, or mace; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any other device or object designed to be, or capable of being, used to inflict pain or cause injury.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="28|01|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Items or Substances and Weapons Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Dangerous or toxic items and weapons. Except as provided in <cite path="28|01|02|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dangerous or toxic items and weapons are prohibited at Office proceedings and facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dangerous or toxic items and weapons brought into an Office proceeding or facility may be confiscated; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a prohibited item or weapon is brought into an Office proceeding or facility:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The proceeding may be suspended or rescheduled; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual involved may be removed from the Office proceeding or facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Weapons Exceptions. Subject to <cite path="28|01|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the following individuals may possess a weapon in an Office proceeding or facility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Police officers acting in their official capacity who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have been summonsed to appear at an Office proceeding; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Are representing their employer in an Office proceeding; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individuals employed to provide security services at an Office proceeding or facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Police officers authorized to possess a weapon in an Office proceeding under <cite path="28|01|02|.02|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> who are carrying a concealed weapon shall notify the Office prior to the beginning of the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Illegal Substances.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Illegal substances are prohibited in Office proceedings and facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an illegal substance is brought into an Office proceeding or facility:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The illegal substance may be confiscated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The proceeding may be suspended or rescheduled; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The individual involved may be removed from the Office facility or proceeding.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Decorum and Security.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Parties, their authorized representatives, witnesses, and other persons present at an Office proceeding shall conduct themselves in a manner consistent with the standards of decorum commonly observed in a court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disrespectful, disorderly, disruptive, contemptuous, vulgar, or violent conduct or language, refusal to comply with directions, or continued use of dilatory tactics constitutes grounds for immediate exclusion from an Office proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person who presents a threat to safety or who is disrupting Office operations or an Office proceeding may be removed from the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Office proceeding;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Office facility; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Premises.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1604">State Government Article, §9-1604, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24">Effective date: April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 407)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-10"><cite path="|28|01|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective January 10, 2020 (46:26 Md. R. 1168)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-10"><cite path="|28|01|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective January 10, 2020 (46:26 Md. R. 1168)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-10"><cite path="|28|01|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 10, 2020 (46:26 Md. R. 1168)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
