<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Video Lottery Terminal Machines</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purchase or Lease of Video Lottery Terminals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A facility operator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Purchase or lease video lottery terminals for use in its facility; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintain control over the video lottery terminals that it has purchased or leased.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before placing a video lottery machine into operation in a facility, a facility operator shall obtain written authorization from Agency staff for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operating the video lottery terminal on the gaming floor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As required under <cite path="36.03.11.05">COMAR 36.03.11.05</cite>, any corresponding change to the facility gaming floor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="36|04|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Authorized Video Lottery Terminals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. A facility operator:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is authorized to operate the maximum number of video lottery terminals that is specified on its video lottery facility operation license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to <cite path="36|04|02|.02|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>, may operate less than the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall submit written notification to Agency staff at least 21 days before temporarily decreasing the number of video lottery terminals on its gaming floor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Request for Reduction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may submit one request each calendar year to reduce the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its video lottery facility operation license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An operator seeking to reduce the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license shall submit to Agency staff a written request for reduction no later than December 1 of a calendar year and specify the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reason for the request;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Number of video lottery terminals requested to be taken off the license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For each video lottery terminal subject to the request:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Device asset number;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Proposed reconfiguration of the facility’s floor plan after the reduction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Proposed date by which the reduction would be implemented; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Projected analysis of the impact of the reduction on the facility’s gaming revenue.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Agency Staff may approve or deny a request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Agency staff shall notify the operator in writing of the effective date of an approved request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Implementation of Approved Request for Reduction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No later than December 31 following the effective date of an approved reduction request, the operator shall remove the subject video lottery terminals from its gaming floor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agency staff shall implement an approved reduction by issuing the operator an amended license certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The operator for which a request for reduction was approved may operate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A maximum of the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Less than the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The facility operator shall pay all costs incurred by the Commission associated with reducing the number of authorized video lottery terminals from the operator’s license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A facility operator for which a reduction was approved may not be credited or refunded any portion of the initial license fee paid under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-36, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>For each authorized video lottery terminal on its license, a facility operator shall pay the annual fee of $425 required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise specified, a reduction in the number of authorized video lottery terminals does not change any other applicable requirement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Request to Increase Number of Authorized Video Lottery Terminals on a License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A facility operator may submit a written request to the Commission to increase the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license up to and including the allocation limit for its location specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-36(i)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written request under <cite path="36|04|02|.02|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> shall include the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reason for the request;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Number of video lottery terminals to be added to the license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proposed reconfiguration of the facility’s floor plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Proposed date by which the increase would be implemented; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Projected analysis of the impact of the increase on the facility’s gaming revenues.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission may approve or deny a request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To implement an approved request for an increased number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license, the operator shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pay a nonrefundable license fee of $6,000 for each additional video lottery terminal on the license, to accrue to the Education Trust Fund;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At its own expense, purchase or lease, and maintain, the additional video lottery terminals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pay all costs incurred by the Commission associated with increasing the number of authorized video lottery terminals on the operator’s license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Meet all applicable Commission requirements for placing the additional authorized video lottery terminals on the gaming floor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For each authorized video lottery terminal on its license, a facility operator shall pay the annual fee of $425 required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-33, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Agency staff shall implement an approved increase by issuing the operator an amended license certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The operator for which a request for increase was approved may operate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A maximum of the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Less than the number of authorized video lottery terminals on its license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a request for an increased allocation of video lottery terminals under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">State Government Article, §9-1</cite>A-36(i), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|04">04</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1">9-1</cite>A-21, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-29">Regulations <cite path="|36|04|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|36|04|02|.02">.02</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 470); adopted permanently effective April 29, 2013 (40:8 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-26"><cite path="|36|04|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective May 26, 2014 (41:10 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|04|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); amended permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-05-27"><cite path="|36|04|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed and new Regulation .02 adopted as an emergency provision effective December 12, 2023 (50:26 Md. R. 1130); adopted permanently effective May 27, 2024 (51:10 Md. R. 529)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
