<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>2 + 2 Transfer Scholarship Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship Program is to assist and encourage community college graduates to transfer to a 4-year institution within the State.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <text>To be eligible for assistance under the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship Program, an applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be a Maryland resident;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be currently enrolled at a community college in Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Maintain a minimum cumulative 2.5 grade point average on a 4.0 scale while a student at a community college in Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Have earned an associate’s degree from a community college in Maryland by the end of the semester in which the applicant plans to transfer;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Be accepted for admission to a degree program at a public senior higher education institution or a private nonprofit institution of higher education in Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Intend to enroll in a public senior higher education institution or a private nonprofit institution of higher education in Maryland in order to complete a bachelor’s program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>On or after the fall semester of 2014, enroll as a full-time, degree-seeking student in a public senior higher education institution or a private nonprofit institution of higher education in Maryland by the fall semester following completion of the associate’s degree;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>In the case of an individual who is required to register with the Selective Service System, have complied with the registration requirement;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Timely file the Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA) form; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Have demonstrated financial need.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be considered for the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship, students shall submit the application and all documents required by the Office for Student Financial Assistance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Students applying for the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship shall provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed online application form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A completed FAFSA application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A current official transcript from a community college in the State reflecting the applicant’s grade point average;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon graduation, an official transcript from a community college in the State reflecting that an Associate’s Degree has been conferred; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Documentation the student has registered with the Selective Service System, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Students should file a FAFSA by March 1 each year for priority consideration. Applications will be accepted after the March 1 date and awards will be made with available funds</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each student shall agree to provide any information or documentation requested by OSFA for the purpose of administering this program and, if requested, to sign an authorization for the release of information to OFSA for the purpose of administering this program. The student’s failure or refusal to provide requested information or a signed release may result in a determination of ineligibility and the cancellation of an award.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Award Amount.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="13B|08|01|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the annual award amount shall be $1,000.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The annual award amount shall be $2,000 for a student who enrolls in a science, teaching, engineering, computer science, mathematics, or nursing program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The scholarship may be used for tuition and mandatory fees for 3 years of study or 6 semesters of study, whichever is longer.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Selections of Recipients and Award Notification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligible applicants shall be ranked on the basis of cumulative grade point average.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Grades for credits earned as a community college student shall be used to calculate the cumulative grade point average.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Awards shall be made to applicants based on cumulative grade point average ranked highest to lowest. Awards shall be issued until the total funds appropriated for the program have been depleted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Recipients shall be notified in writing of the scholarship award. A recipient shall provide written acceptance of the award to the Office of Student Financial Assistance by the date specified in the award notice or the award will be forfeited.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Verification and Payment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance has the authority to verify information concerning applicants and recipients for the purpose of administering this program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At the request of OSFA, schools are required to verify the following using federal standards:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Taxable and nontaxable income of student and parents (if a dependent student);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enrollment status (undergraduate or graduate);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dependency status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Transaction number of ISIR used.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Schools shall provide updated and verified data to OSFA by the date established each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Information verified by the institutions will be used to update OSFA records. Awards for students with corrections and errors shall be recalculated and adjusted as specified in <cite path="|13B|08|01|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> or canceled accordingly.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each semester, eligible institutions shall certify on billing rosters provided by the Office of Student Financial Assistance that the recipient is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland resident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enrolled for 12 or more hours as a degree-seeking undergraduate student; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Making satisfactory academic progress toward a degree.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Renewal and Continuation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A 2+2 Transfer Scholarship may be renewed for a total of 3 years of study, or 6 semesters of study, whichever is longer, if the recipient:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Remains a resident of the State of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continues to be enrolled full-time as an undergraduate student in a degree program at a public senior higher education institution or a private nonprofit institution of higher education in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintains a cumulative 2.5 grade point average on a 4.0 scale each academic year the recipient is enrolled at a public senior higher education institution or a private nonprofit institution of higher education in the State or provides evidence satisfactory to the administration of extenuating circumstances as specified under <cite path="|13B|08|01|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Maintains the standards of the institution attended by the recipient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Certification of Grade Point Average.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Following the spring semester, the Office of Student Financial Assistance shall request the postsecondary institution to provide a certified cumulative grade point average for the academic year for the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship recipients attending that institution. The grade point average shall be computed using the procedures in use by the institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>OSFA also may ask the school to verify the recipient's grade point average by submitting an official transcript.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The institution's calculation of the grade average is final. OSFA does not round any reported grade point averages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the institution cannot compute a cumulative grade point average for the academic year, it shall submit a grade point average for each semester the student was enrolled during the academic year. If either semester average is below a 2.5, the institution shall report the number of hours attempted and the number of hours completed for the semesters in which the student is enrolled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the reported calculation is below a 2.5 grade point average, the recipient's 2+2 Transfer Scholarship will not be renewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A recipient whose award has been canceled may request reinstatement of the scholarship if the student’s academic performance in summer school courses taken immediately following that academic year raises the cumulative grade point average to 2.5 or above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Nonrenewal of Award.</heading>
    <text>The 2+2 Transfer Scholarship will not be renewed if the student fails to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maintain the academic standards of the institution;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maintain Maryland residency;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Maintain a cumulative 2.5 grade point average; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Enroll as a full-time degree-seeking student taking at least 12 credit hours each semester.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Basis of Appeal. An appeal may be filed only on the basis of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failure to maintain full-time enrollment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to maintain a 2.5 cumulative grade point average; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Changed financial circumstances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Appeal Based on Full-Time Enrollment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Full-time” means enrollment for at least 12 semester hours of courses each semester or its equivalent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To be considered full-time, the actual time spent in the classroom, lab, supervised activity, or clinic shall equal 180 clock hours or more in a regular semester.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Students enrolled for at least 6 credit hours but less than 12 credits can appeal to receive the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship if they are participating in a specific course or activity (such as an internship or a practicum) that is required by the institution to complete their academic program. The student may appeal by submitting documentation, in addition to the appeal form, from the student’s department chair that describes and confirms the program requirements for that semester, along with a catalog description of the program and classes involved. The documentation shall also list the number of clock hours required for each activity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Appeal Based on Grade Point Average.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a student fails to meet the grade point average requirement, the student may appeal on the basis of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A serious illness or injury of the student;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A serious illness of a member of the student’s immediate family;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Serious emotional difficulties experienced by the student;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The death of a member of the student’s immediate family; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other serious personal circumstances.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student’s appeal information shall clearly demonstrate that one or more of the factors in <cite path="13B|08|01|.09|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite> prevented the student from achieving the required grade point average.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The student’s appeal shall be supported by documentation from an appropriate professional, such as a treating physician, psychologist, or health professional, sufficient to substantiate the student’s claim.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Appeal Based on Changed Financial Circumstances.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A student may appeal if the student’s financial circumstances change, after the filing of the student’s application under Regulation .03, as a result of one of the following reasons:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The student’s parent or spouse dies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The student or the student’s parents’ divorce or separate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The student, student’s parent (if dependent), or student’s spouse (if independent) as defined by FAFSA becomes involuntarily unemployed for at least 10 consecutive weeks in the current year; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The student or the student’s parent(s) loses, as a result of the student reaching the age of majority, benefits from Social Security, AFDC, or child support.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student’s appeal shall be supported by appropriate documentation sufficient to substantiate the student’s claim, including, but not limited to, copies of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A death certificate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A divorce decree or separation agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A notice of job termination or layoff;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Federal tax transcript or W-2; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A copy of a termination notice of unemployment benefits.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If OSFA sustains a student’s appeal, OSFA shall provide the following relief:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the appeal was based on the death of the student’s parent or spouse, OSFA shall adjust the student’s FASFA income information to exclude the income of the deceased;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the appeal was based on the student or the student’s parents’ divorce or separation, OSFA shall adjust the student’s FASFA income information to exclude the income of the affected parent or spouse;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the appeal was based on the student, student’s parent (if dependent), or student’s spouse (if independent) becoming involuntarily unemployed for at least 10 consecutive weeks in the current year, OSFA shall calculate the student’s family contribution and total family income using an estimated income for the current calendar year; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If the appeal was based on the student or the student’s parent losing, as a result of the student reaching the age of majority, benefits from Social Security, TNAF, or child support, OSFA shall calculate the student’s family contribution and total family income using an estimated income for the current calendar year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Appeal Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An appeal may only be filed by the submission of a completed appeal form to the Director of Student Financial Assistance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An appeal shall be received by OSFA within 45 days of the date the student is notified that the scholarship award has been nonrenewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In completing the appeal form, the student shall document the conditions upon which the appeal is based as specified in <cite path="13B|08|01|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>. Upon receipt of the appeal, the documentation shall be reviewed and a decision shall be rendered. The student shall be notified of the outcome of the appeal in writing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Funding.</heading>
    <text>The funding for the 2+2 Transfer Scholarship shall be as provided in the annual State budget. All awards are contingent upon the annual appropriation of funding.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite>(u), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-204">18-204</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-2501">18-2501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-2507">18-2507</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-10">Effective date: December 10, 2015 (42:24 Md. R. 1505)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-07"><cite path="|13B|08|01|.02|J.">Regulation .02J</cite> amended effective August 7, 2023 (50:15 Md. R. 682)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
