<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Charles W. Riley Firefighter and Ambulance and Rescue Squad Member Scholarship Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the Charles W. Riley Firefighter and Ambulance and Rescue Squad Member Scholarship Program (Riley Scholarship) is to encourage members of the fire-fighting, ambulance, and rescue organizations serving Maryland communities to pursue credited courses that lead to a degree in fire service technology, emergency medical technology, fire service management, or public safety administration with a minor or concentration in fire service technology or fire service management.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, “actively engaged” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A career member who has worked a minimum of 1000 hours as part of a fire, ambulance, or rescue squad in the tax year prior to the award year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A volunteer member:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within a county or municipality that operates a Length of Service Award Program (LOSAP), who has recorded at least 50 LOSAP points as part of a fire, ambulance, or rescue squad in the tax year prior to the award year, and the points have been earned in at least two different categories; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within a county or municipality that does not operate a LOSAP, who has recorded at least 50 points under the point system established by the county or municipality to identify active members as part of a fire, ambulance, or rescue squad in the tax year prior to the award year, and the points have been earned in at least two different categories.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for a Riley Scholarship, an individual shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A resident of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Actively engaged as a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Career firefighter or ambulance or rescue squad member in an organized fire department or ambulance or rescue squad in the State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Volunteer firefighter or ambulance or rescue squad member in an organized fire department or ambulance or rescue squad in the State; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accepted for admission or enrolled as a full-time (12 or more credits per semester) or part-time (6—11 credits per semester) student in a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Regular undergraduate program at an eligible institution (public or private nonprofit institution of higher education in the State that possesses a certificate of approval from the Commission); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>2-year terminal certificate program in which the course work is acceptable for transfer credit toward an accredited baccalaureate degree program in an eligible institution.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Students applying for the Riley Scholarship shall submit the following materials to the Office for Student Financial Assistance (OSFA):</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed online application form, by March 1;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proof of official acceptance into a program of fire service technology, emergency medical technology, fire service management, or public safety administration with a minor or concentration in fire service technology or fire service management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A notarized statement from an eligible employer confirming active employment or volunteer service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Individuals may submit applications beginning January 1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each applicant shall agree to provide any information or documentation requested by OSFA for the purpose of administering this program and, if requested, to sign an authorization for the release of information to OFSA for the purpose of administering this program. The applicant’s failure or refusal to provide requested information or a signed release may result in a determination of ineligibility, the cancellation of an award, and the denial of a request for the deferment or waiver of a service obligation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Award Amount.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Office for Student Financial Assistance shall determine each recipient’s scholarship award as provided in <cite path="13B|08|03|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An annual award shall be at least 50 percent of the student’s actual annual tuition and mandatory fees at an eligible institution, but may not exceed the annual tuition and mandatory fees of a resident undergraduate student at the 4-year public institution of higher education within the University System of Maryland, other than the University of Maryland University College and the University of Maryland, Baltimore, with the highest annual expenses for a full-time resident undergraduate for courses credited toward a degree in fire service technology, emergency medical technology, fire service management, or public safety administration with a minor or concentration in fire service technology or fire service management.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Selection of Recipients and Award Notification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligible applicants who are renewals shall be given priority over initial applicants. Within these groups, applicants shall be ranked and awarded according to the submission date of their completed online application form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Recipients shall be notified in writing of a scholarship award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A recipient shall provide written acceptance of the award to the Office of Student Financial Assistance by the date specified in the award notice or the award shall be forfeited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applicants who are not selected shall be placed on the waitlist pending the availability of funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Applicants not selected in an academic year may reapply for consideration in a subsequent academic year, and shall be ranked according to the submission date of their completed online application form.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Verification and Payment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) has the authority to verify information concerning applicants and recipients for the purpose of administering this program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each semester, eligible institutions shall certify on billing rosters provided by OSFA that each recipient is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland resident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintaining a grade point average of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Enrolled either full-time or part-time in an eligible academic program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Making satisfactory academic progress toward a degree; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintaining the standards of the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An award shall be automatically renewed on an annual basis, pending the annual submission of a Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA) application, up to a maximum of 5 years of full-time study or 8 years of part-time study if sufficient funding is available and the student:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Continues to meet all of the eligibility requirements set forth in <cite path="|13B|08|03|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintains satisfactory academic progress at the institution attended; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintains a grade point average of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An award shall be canceled if the recipient fails to meet and maintain each eligibility requirement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A recipient who is academically ineligible shall forfeit the award and may reapply as an initial applicant in a subsequent award year if they meet and maintain each eligibility requirement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A student transferring from one institution to another may continue to receive the award if the student meets all of the scholarship eligibility requirements.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An appeal of a decision of ineligibility or cancellation of an award shall be filed with the Director of the Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An appeal shall be in writing and state clearly the basis for the appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An appeal shall be submitted within 30 days of notice of ineligibility or cancellation of award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director of OSFA shall review each appeal and issue a decision no later than 60 days after receiving the appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All decisions of the Director of OSFA are final.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Service Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A recipient shall serve for 1 year after completion of an eligible program as a volunteer or career firefighter or ambulance or rescue squad member, in a full-time or part-time capacity, of an organized fire department or ambulance or rescue squad in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each applicant offered an award shall sign and return a promissory note agreeing to begin fulfillment of the service obligation within 1 year of completing the degree for which they received assistance. The service obligation begins after completion of the degree program and cannot be fulfilled prior to completion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a recipient holds a Riley Scholarship along with any other State award requiring a service obligation, the service obligations shall be served in consecutive years.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Default in Service Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a recipient fails to carry out their service obligation, the recipient shall be in default and shall repay the State the portion of the scholarship not forgiven.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repayment may be prorated if the recipient partially fulfills the obligation, as determined by the Office of Student Financial Assistance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Interest on the funds advanced shall accrue at an interest rate equal to the interest rate established by the United States Department of Education for the Federal Stafford Loan on the first day of July of each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Interest shall begin accruing as of the date of a recipient’s graduation or termination from an institution of higher education.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Service Obligation Deferment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A recipient may request that their service obligation be deferred during the time that the recipient is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enrolled in a full-time (12 or more credits per semester) or part-time (6—11 credits per semester) undergraduate course of study;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enrolled in a full-time (9 or more credits per semester) or part-time (6—8 credits per semester) graduate course of study at an institution of higher education in a degree granting program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On a temporary leave of absence from required employment as a career or volunteer firefighter or ambulance or rescue squad member approved by the employer for a period not to exceed 12 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Temporarily disabled in a manner that substantially impairs the recipient’s ability to perform the service obligation, for a period not to exceed 3 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unable to secure employment for a period not to exceed 12 months because they must care for a spouse or child who is disabled;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Assigned military duty outside of the State, not to exceed 3 years without filing an appeal; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Married to a spouse assigned military duty outside of the State, not to exceed 3 years without filing an appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A recipient’s deferment request shall include satisfactory supporting documentation. Such documentation shall consist of the following, as appropriate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification by the office of the registrar that the recipient has returned to a full-time or part-time course of study at an eligible institution of higher education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certification by the employer that the recipient is on an approved temporary leave of absence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A sworn affidavit by a qualified physician that the recipient is temporarily disabled in a manner that substantially impairs the recipient’s ability to perform the service obligation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A sworn affidavit by a qualified physician that the recipient is unable to find employment because they must care for a spouse or child who is disabled;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A certified statement including a list of possible eligible employers, with their addresses and telephone numbers, to which application has been made if the recipient has been unable to find full-time employment as required as a career or volunteer firefighter or ambulance or rescue squad member; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A copy of military orders.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) shall review all documentation and determine if the deferment conditions have been met and, if so, determine the deferment period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before a deferment based on an inability to find employment or volunteer service is granted, OSFA shall review the recipient’s documentation and other available information and determine if the recipient has sought employment aggressively in all regions of the State in which opportunities exist.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A recipient need not make scholarship repayments and interest does not accrue during the period of an approved deferment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The OSFA shall, on a case-by-case basis, review an appeal from a recipient assigned military duty outside the State, or from a recipient married to an individual assigned military duty outside the State, that exceeds the 3-year deferral limit. An appeal must be in writing and include a copy of the military orders.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Waiver of Service and Repayment Obligations.</heading>
    <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance shall waive a recipient's service and repayment obligations if it determines:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On the basis of sworn affidavits by two qualified physicians that the recipient is physically unable to fulfill any of the possible service obligations on a full-time or part-time basis because of a permanent impairment; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On the basis of a death certificate or other evidence of death that is conclusive under State law that the recipient has died.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite>(u), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-204">18-204</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-603">18-603</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-08-28">Effective date: August 28, 2017 (44:17 Md. R. 836)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-29"><cite path="|13B|08|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 642)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
