<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Educational Excellence Awards Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Program of Educational Excellence Awards is to provide need-based financial assistance to students in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 18, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As used in this chapter, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Academic year” means the fall, spring, and summer semesters and any semester shorter in length than the term of a regular semester.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Educational Assistance Grant” or “EA Grant” means the Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Educational Assistance Grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Educational Excellence Award” or “EEA” means the Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Program of Educational Excellence Awards, which consists of Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Guaranteed Access Grants and Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Educational Assistance Grants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Eligible for in-State tuition” means an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determined by a public institution of higher education to qualify for in-State tuition under the institution’s policies and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determined by a nonpublic institution of higher education within the State to meet the criteria for in-State tuition under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Eligible institution” means an institution of higher education within the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“FAFSA” means the Free Application for Federal Student Aid.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Full-Time Student.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Full-time student” means a student enrolled in at least 12 credit hours, or the equivalent of 12 credit hours, as determined by OSFA:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In a regular undergraduate program leading to a degree or diploma from an eligible institution; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In a 2-year associate degree program in which the course work is acceptable for transfer credit to an accredited baccalaureate program at an eligible institution.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A semester hour or equivalent that does not lead towards a degree or diploma in a student’s educational program shall not be counted for purposes of determining whether the student is full-time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“GED” means a high school diploma by examination under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-808">Labor and Employment Article, §11-808 Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Guaranteed Access Grant” or “GA Grant” means the Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Guaranteed Access Grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Maryland State Financial Aid Application (MSFAA)” means the financial aid application form prescribed by the Office for individuals who are eligible for in-State tuition and ineligible to complete the FAFSA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“OSFA” or “Office” means the Office of Student Financial Assistance within the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Higher Education for the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Successfully Completed Course.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Successfully completed course” means a course in which a student received any grade higher than an “F” regardless of any school or program policy.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Successfully completed course” does not include a course that is retaken by a student more than once.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Title IV” means Title IV of the federal Higher Education Act of 1965.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|10|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for financial assistance under the Educational Excellence Award program, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be a Maryland resident or be eligible for in-State tuition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annually file the FAFSA or MSFAA by March 1;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be accepted for admission, or enrolled as a full-time student, in a regular undergraduate program leading to a degree or diploma at an eligible institution, or be enrolled full-time in a 2-year associate degree program in which the course work is acceptable for transfer credit to an accredited baccalaureate program at an eligible institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate financial need based upon the formula set forth in <cite path="|13B|08|10|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Agree to provide, by the deadline established by OSFA, any supplemental information or documentation requested by OSFA or an institution for the purpose of administering or verifying eligibility for the EEA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If requested, sign an authorization for the release of information to OSFA or an institution for the purpose of administering or verifying eligibility for the EEA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant’s failure or refusal to provide to OSFA requested information, or a signed authorization for the release of information, by the deadlines established by OSFA may result in a determination of ineligibility, the cancellation of an award, or the denial of an appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for a Guaranteed Access Grant, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Satisfy the requirements of <cite path="13B|08|10|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="13B|08|10|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, have an annual total family income as reported on the FAFSA or MSFAA that is at or below 130 percent of the federal poverty level or, if program funding allows, that is at or below 150 percent of the federal poverty level, for 2 years prior to the academic year for which the student is being reviewed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Begin enrollment at an eligible institution within 1 year of completing high school or within 1 year of obtaining a GED with a passing score of at least 165 per module or, if failing to do either, provide documentation satisfactory to OSFA of extenuating circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be younger than 22 years old at the time of receiving the first award, except as provided in <cite path="13B|08|10|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have obtained a GED with a passing score of at least 165 per module; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have successfully completed a college preparatory program in high school that is designed to prepare students for college level work;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have obtained a GED with a passing score of at least 165 per module; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have completed high school with an unweighted cumulative grade point average of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent at the end of the first semester of the senior year in high school and have completed high school or, failing to do so, on the recommendation of the recipient’s high school principal provide evidence satisfactory to the Commission of extenuating circumstances;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §C(3) and (6) of this regulation, be a senior in high school at the time of initial application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §C(3) and (6) of this regulation, submit a completed high school certification form and a high school transcript reflecting the first semester of the applicant’s senior year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Whether applying for the first time or as a renewal recipient, submit all supplemental documentation requested by OSFA or the institution (other than the FAFSA or MSFAA, which are due on March 1) no later than the deadline established by OSFA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Meet any other requirements adopted by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>OSFA may not consider an earned income credit under §32 of the Internal Revenue Code in determining the annual family income eligibility of an applicant for a Guaranteed Access Grant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Prior to award year 2022—2023, an individual may be younger than 26 years old at the time of receiving the first GA award, but beginning in award year 2022—2023, an individual shall be younger than 22 years old at the time of receiving the first GA award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="13B|08|10|.03|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, a student in grade 7 or grade 8 who applies and prequalifies for a Guaranteed Access Grant on the basis of financial need, as established by the Office, shall agree in writing, as a secondary and undergraduate student, to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Satisfy the attendance policy of the applicable school;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refrain from substance abuse;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide information required by the Commission or the Maryland State Department of Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Apply for admission to an institution of higher education during the student’s senior year of high school;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Participate in the Next Generation Scholars of Maryland Program until the student graduates from high school and matriculates at an institution of higher education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Maintain an unweighted cumulative grade point average of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Satisfy any other program requirements set by OSFA, the Commission, the Maryland State Board of Education, or the Maryland State Department of Education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A student in grade 9 or grade 10 shall prequalify for a Guaranteed Access Grant, to be used at the time of enrollment in an institution of postsecondary education, if the student:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="13B|08|10|.03|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is eligible for free or reduced price meals; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Attends a school that participates in the United States Department of Agriculture Community Eligibility Provision and is identified by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Direct certification; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Income information provided to the local school system, by the family of the student, on an alternative form developed by the Maryland State Department of Education.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|10|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Award Amounts and Credit Completion Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Educational Excellence Award program award amounts shall be determined by OSFA in accordance with this regulation and <cite path="|13B|08|10|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Educational Assistance Grant Award Amounts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Educational Assistance Grant award amounts shall range between $400 and $3,000 and be awarded in $100 increments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount of an Educational Assistance Grant made to a student in the student’s first 2 academic years of enrollment may not be less than $400 or more than $3,000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the student enrolled in an eligible institution on or after August 31, 2015, and has received the EA Grant for at least 2 years, then beginning with the 2018—2019 award year, and in each academic award year thereafter, the student shall successfully complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 30 credits in the prior academic year, in order for the EA award amount to not be less than $400 or more than $3,000; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 24 but fewer than 30 credits in the prior academic year, in order for the EA award amount to be equal to the amount the student would have otherwise received under <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|B.|(3)|(a)">§B(3)(a) of this regulation</cite> multiplied by the ratio of the number of credits successfully completed divided by 30.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the student’s prorated award amount under <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|B.|(3)|(b)">§B(3)(b) of this regulation</cite> is less than $400, the student shall not be awarded an Educational Assistance Grant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Guaranteed Access Grant Award Amounts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Guaranteed Access Grant award amounts shall range from $400 up to a maximum award not to exceed the equivalent annual expenses of a full-time resident undergraduate at the 4-year public institution of higher education within the University System of Maryland, other than the University of Maryland University College and the University of Maryland Baltimore, which is calculated by OSFA to have the highest annual expenses for a full-time resident undergraduate, in $100 increments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount of a Guaranteed Access Grant made to a student in the student's first 2 academic years of enrollment shall be equal to 100 percent of the student's adjusted financial need as determined by OSFA, subject to the requirements of <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the student has enrolled in an eligible institution on or after August 31, 2015, and has received the GA Grant for at least 2 years, then beginning with the 2018—2019 award year, and each academic award year thereafter, the student shall successfully complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 30 credits in the prior academic year, in order for the award amount to be equal to 100 percent of the amount calculated under <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 24 but fewer than 30 credits in the prior academic year, in order for the award amount to be equal to 100 percent of the amount calculated under <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> multiplied by the ratio of the number of credits successfully completed divided by 30.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the student’s prorated award amount under <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|C.|(3)|(b)">§C(3)(b) of this regulation</cite> would be less than $400, the student shall not be awarded a Guaranteed Access Grant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, if the student fails to complete at least 24 credits at the end of the student’s second academic year of receiving the grant, the student shall not be awarded either the Guaranteed Access Grant or the Educational Assistance Grant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A student described in <cite path="13B|08|10|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> may be awarded the grant if, subsequent to the second year of receiving the grant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student completes 24 credits within an academic year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reapplies for and qualifies for the grant the following year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The award recipient shall continue to meet the criteria established by this chapter for the duration of the award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Students may hold other State scholarships or grants in addition to an EEA, but shall meet all conditions for all awards, and may not receive an amount combined from all State programs that exceeds the maximum amount established by OSFA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A student who has been approved through an appeal under <cite path="|13B|08|10|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite> to receive an EEA while taking fewer than 12 credits in a term may not receive a part-time grant from OSFA during that same term.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Use of Award Out-of-State.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Guaranteed Access Grant or Educational Assistance Grant may be used at an institution of higher education in another state or the District of Columbia only if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following conditions are met:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The attendance is pursuant to a reciprocal agreement for applicants that are deaf or hearing impaired at an institution of higher education that makes special provisions for deaf and hearing impaired students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Comparable special provisions are not available at an in-State institution of higher education; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The institution is accredited by accrediting body recognized by the U.S. Department of Education; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The attendance is pursuant to a reciprocal agreement under Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-305">18-305</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-308">18-308</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>OSFA may not award more than 10 percent of the funds available for each of the types of grant awarded through the Guaranteed Access Grant program and Educational Assistance Grant program to students attending schools located in another state or the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Financial Need Calculation and Award Formulas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Determination of Financial Need.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office shall calculate an applicant’s adjusted financial need using the following formula:</text>
        <text>Adjusted Financial Need =</text>
        <text>Cost of Attendance</text>
        <text>- Expected Family Contribution Plus/Minus Regional Cost of Living Adjustment</text>
        <text>- Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant or Economic Development Student Assistance Grant</text>
        <text>- Estimated Pell Grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Expected Family Contribution shall be determined using the same methodology used by the U.S. Department of Education to determine expected family contribution for purposes of federal student aid.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Regional Cost of Living Adjustment shall be determined annually by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Cost of Attendance shall be calculated as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For a student living with parents, tuition and mandatory fees plus an allowance established by OSFA, with a minimum value of $3,200;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a student living off-campus, tuition and mandatory fees plus an allowance established by OSFA, with a minimum value of $5,100; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For a student living on-campus, tuition and mandatory fees, room and board, plus an allowance established by OSFA, with a minimum value of $900.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Determination of EEA Award Amounts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amounts of EEA program awards shall be calculated using data from the FAFSA or the MSFAA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>EA Grant Formulas. Subject to the requirements of <cite path="|13B|08|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An EA award for a student attending a 4-year institution shall be calculated using the following formula: Adjusted Financial Need x 40% = Educational Assistance Grant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An award for a student attending a community college shall be calculated using the following formula: Adjusted Financial Need x 60% = Educational Assistance Grant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>GA Grant Formulas. Subject to the requirements of <cite path="|13B|08|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, Guaranteed Access Grants shall be calculated using the following formula: Adjusted Financial Need x 100% = Guaranteed Access Grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Award amounts shall be calculated on an annual basis and rounded to the nearest $100.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Awards that are made for the fall and spring semesters in the academic year are evenly split between the two semesters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If a student’s award amount is determined to be below $400, the student shall not receive the award.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Errors on a FAFSA or MSFAA that are corrected by a student after the deadline may be considered by OSFA. Changes in award amounts as a result of a correction shall be handled as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For EA Grants and GA Grants, if a correction results in a decrease in an award amount, the award shall be adjusted and the student notified of the change. If a correction results in an increase in an award, the increase shall be funded only if OSFA determines that funds are available.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For GA Grants only, if a correction in family income or family size results in the student no longer being eligible for a GA Grant, the student's GA award shall be canceled and, if funding is available in OSFA’s determination, the student may be awarded as an EA Grant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Awarding Priorities and Distribution of Funds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On an annual basis, the Secretary shall establish awarding priorities for making awards under the Educational Excellence Awards Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The awarding priorities shall be based upon projections using the estimated funding level for the program, and shall take into consideration funds necessary to award Guaranteed Access Grants at 100 percent of need, with the remainder of the funds being awarded as Educational Assistance Grants.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As its first awarding priority, and subject to the requirements of Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-304">18-304</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-307">18-307</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Office shall strive to award recipients at the percent of need and maximum award established for the prior award year, adjusting for tuition and fee increases.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>As its second awarding priority, and subject to the requirements of Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-304">18-304</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-307">18-307</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Office shall strive to maintain the overall number of awards in the EEA program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Selection of Recipients.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for the GA Grant who files the FAFSA or MSFAA after March 1 may not be considered for an award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A renewal applicant for the GA Grant shall meet all the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13B|08|10|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> to be considered for a renewal award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>GA Grant applicants who have completed the FAFSA or MSFAA by March 1 shall be selected for the award in the following priority:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewal applicants who submit all supplemental information or documentation requested by OSFA or an institution by April 1;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial applicants who submit all supplemental information requested by OSFA or an institution by April 1; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Renewal and initial applicants and initial applicants who submit all supplemental information requested by OSFA or an institution after April 1 but no later than May 15.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All applicants for the EA Grant shall be selected and awards made based upon a Statewide ranking of each student's Expected Family Contribution (EFC) and need, with the lowest EFC and greatest need awarded first, in the following priority:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewal applicants for EA Grants shall be awarded first provided that the requirements of <cite path="|13B|08|10|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> are met; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Remaining funds shall be awarded to all other eligible applicants until all funds are depleted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Award Notification and Acceptance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recipients shall be notified by OSFA through the Maryland College Aid Processing System (MDCAPS) of the awards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An initial EA or GA Grant recipient shall log on to MDCAPS in order to accept an award, except that, in extenuating circumstances as determined by the Director of OSFA, a student may accept an award by providing written acceptance to the Office.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|10|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Award Renewal and Continuation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An Educational Assistance Grant may be renewed if the recipient:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Files a FAFSA or MSFAA by March 1;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstrates financial need;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is enrolled as a full-time student in an eligible institution or community college;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At the end of the student’s second academic year and thereafter of receiving the grant, completed at least 24 credits in the prior academic year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is making satisfactory progress according to institutional standards in compliance with federal Title IV program regulations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Is a resident of the State or eligible for in-State tuition, as verified by the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A Guaranteed Access Grant may be renewed if the recipient:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Files a FAFSA or MSFAA by March 1 and, if requested by OSFA or the institution, submits all required verification documentation by the deadline established by OSFA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has an annual total family income as reported on the FAFSA or MSFAA which is at or below 150 percent of the federal poverty level;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is enrolled as a full-time student in an eligible institution or community college;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At the end of the student’s second academic year and thereafter of receiving the grant, completed at least 24 credits in the prior academic year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is making satisfactory progress according to institutional standards in compliance with federal Title IV program regulations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Is a resident of the State or eligible for in-State tuition, as verified by the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A renewal applicant for a GA Grant who does not meet the requirements of <cite path="13B|08|10|.10|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be considered for an EA Grant, if the recipient satisfies the requirements of <cite path="13B|08|10|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, meets the EFC requirements based upon the Statewide ranking of greatest need, and <cite path="|13B|08|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Award Cancellation or Adjustment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An award shall be canceled if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A recipient of an EA Grant or GA Grant fails to accept the award within the time specified in the award notification to the recipient;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A recipient of an EA Grant or GA Grant fails to satisfy all verification requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A recipient of a GA Grant fails to submit all requested supplemental information or documentation to OSFA or an institution by the deadline established by OSFA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An institution reports on the billing roster that the recipient is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Not enrolled at that institution in a regular program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not enrolled as a full-time student;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Not meeting the required number of successfully completed credits under <cite path="|13B|08|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Not making satisfactory academic progress;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Not a resident of the State or not eligible for in-State tuition; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>In default of a Title IV loan or owes a refund of Title IV assistance; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An institution reports on the credit roster that the recipient is not meeting the required number of successfully completed credits under <cite path="|13B|08|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An award shall be adjusted in accordance with <cite path="|13B|08|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> if an institution reports on the billing roster that a recipient who received the grant for 2 prior years has completed a minimum of 24 credits but fewer than 30 credits.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Payment of Awards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>OSFA shall make an award payment to the institution for each semester that the eligible recipient is granted the award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The institution shall certify to OSFA all recipients, on a semester basis, on or before:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>December 15, for the fall semester; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May 15, for the spring semester.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An institution who fails to certify all recipients on a semester basis by the prescribed deadline will not be able to certify recipients for subsequent semester. At the beginning of each semester, institutions shall review billing rosters provided by OSFA to certify, by a deadline determined by OSFA, that the recipients meet the requirements described in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In order for funds to be disbursed to the institution, the institution at which the student is enrolled shall maintain the student’s FAFSA information on file. OSFA will maintain the applications for students who complete the MSFAA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Institutions shall be responsible for disbursing the funds on behalf of awarded students in a timely fashion.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|10|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Verification of Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In-House Verification by OSFA.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>OSFA annually shall verify a percentage of all new Educational Excellence Award applications to determine if they contain accurate information.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>OSFA shall verify Educational Excellence Award applications for recipients identified by OSFA, or by institutions, based upon:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whether the information contained in the application has discrepancies from the information contained in the FAFSA or MSFAA; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether the applicant misreported dependency status, State residency status, or status related to eligibility for in-State tuition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>OSFA may randomly select applications for verification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An applicant who filed a MSFAA and is selected for verification may only be verified by OSFA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Selected recipients are required to provide documentation of financial data and to verify dependency and State residency or eligibility for in-State tuition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>OSFA annually shall verify the eligibility status of at least 25 percent of GA Grant award recipients.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Initial GA Grant applicants shall submit a high school transcript or documentation of GED scores.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Initial and renewal GA Grant recipients shall provide documentation of financial data to verify eligibility as requested by OSFA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>OSFA shall notify a student who has been selected for verification in writing, and shall advise the student that the student is required to provide the following documents within the time specified in the notification:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Maryland Office of Student Financial Assistance Dependent or Independent Verification Form to verify:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Number of individuals in the household who will attend or are enrolled in college;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Household size; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Other untaxed income;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As applicable, the Maryland State tax return, IRS tax transcript, federal tax return, or IRS data retrieved through the FAFSA, W-2 forms, 1099, or Schedule C of the student, student’s parents, and student’s spouse, to verify:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Adjusted gross income;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Income taxes paid;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Untaxed portions of IRA distributions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Untaxed portions of pensions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Tax exempt interest income;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Education credits; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>State residency or eligibility for in-State tuition; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If deemed necessary by OSFA, a Non Tax Filer Statement for the student, student’s parents, or student’s spouse.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Awards may not be issued for students who fail to provide the requested information by the deadline established by OSFA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Students who provide the requested documentation shall be verified in accordance with the procedures established by OSFA. Awards for students with errors shall be recalculated and adjusted or canceled in accordance with this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>OSFA annually shall perform an independent review for a select percentage of GA Grant recipients that were verified in-house. This process shall occur between July 1 and December 1. If a discrepancy is found during the review process, OSFA reserves the right to make necessary adjustments to a student’s award and shall notify the student in writing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Institutional Verification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The institutions annually shall verify application information for a percentage of all new Educational Excellence Award recipients to determine if students are submitting accurate financial data.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>OSFA shall select a minimum of 25 percent of all students who have received an EA Grant and were flagged for federal verification. Lists of the selected students shall be submitted to the institutions the students are attending.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After students are selected for EA Grant verification under <cite path="13B|08|10|.13|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, each applicable institution shall use the U.S. Department of Education’s Title IV financial aid rules and regulations to verify the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Taxable and non-taxable income of the student and, if a dependent student, the student’s parents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Household size;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Number of individuals in the household that will attend or are enrolled in college;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Enrollment status (undergraduate or graduate);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Housing status;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Dependency status;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Expected Family Contribution; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Transaction number of Institutional Student Information Report used.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Institutions shall provide updated and verified data to OSFA by the date established by OSFA annually.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Information verified by the institutions shall be used to update OSFA records.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Awards for students with corrections and errors shall be recalculated and adjusted or canceled as specified in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A public institution of higher education in the State or a private nonprofit institution of higher education that is eligible for State aid under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|17-103">Education Article, §17-103, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may, in accordance with §§B(8)—(18) of this regulation, verify the eligibility of a GA Grant applicant who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Filed a FAFSA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is an admitted student at or has applied for admission to the institution for the next academic year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>An institution that may verify the eligibility of a GA grant applicant under <cite path="13B|08|10|.13|B.|(7)">§B(7) of this regulation</cite> shall elect to do so by notifying OSFA each year by the deadline established by OSFA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Portability of Institutional Verification.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has been verified by an institution that elects to verify GA Grant eligibility is not obligated to attend the institution performing the verification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A verification obtained by an applicant under this regulation may be used at any institution at which a GA Grant may be used under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-305">Education Article, §18-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of the GA Grant awarded to an applicant may be adjusted in accordance with the cost of attendance at the institution at which the applicant uses the award.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>An institution that elects to verify GA Grant eligibility shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Verify that an applicant qualifies for a GA grant under this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluate the applicant’s income eligibility criteria, as established by the Office, using the V1 standard Title IV financial aid verification process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For all applicants verified, regardless of their enrollment status at the institution, maintain all verification records for a period of 5 years after the end date of the award year associated with the applicant’s last award;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>As part of and in accordance with the regulations for the institution’s annual EEA Program audit submitted under COMAR 13B.08.19, provide the Commission with an audit of the institution’s verification process, to assess:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Accuracy of award eligibility determination performed by the institution;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Compliance with the requirements of the V1 standard Title IV financial aid verification process;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Accuracy of reporting by the institution to the Office in the Institutional Student Information Record; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Compliance with §§B(7)—(18) of this regulation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Meet any other requirements established by the Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Annually between October 1 and March 1 prior to the award year, OSFA will provide a list to participating institutions that identifies applicants who must submit supplemental documentation in the following categories:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Initial applicants who must verify that their high school GPA or GED scores meet the threshold in <cite path="|13B|08|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Initial applicants who must verify that their high school GPA or GED scores meet the threshold in <cite path="|13B|08|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> and who have been selected for verification of income eligibility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Renewal applicants who have been selected for verification of income eligibility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>An institution shall verify, as applicable:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For all applicants, FAFSA completion date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For applicants who have obtained their GED, GED scores;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For applicants in high school:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>That the applicant is in their senior year; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The applicant’s unweighted cumulative high school GPA at the end of their first semester of senior year; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For applicants selected for income verification:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Number of people in applicant’s household; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>All criteria required by the federal VI standard financial aid verification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>A participating institution shall establish a communication process to notify, in writing, applicants who are required to submit supplemental information or documentation for verification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>An institution may use their own institutional forms to collect supplemental information or documentation required for verification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>After verification and as applicable, an institution shall report to OSFA, by the deadline established by OSFA:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant’s unweighted GPA or GED scores; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Institutional Student Information Record the institution used to complete an applicant’s federal V1 verification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>An institution’s failure to timely report an applicant’s information as required under <cite path="13B|08|10|.13|B.|(15)">§B(15) of this regulation</cite> may cause the applicant to become ineligible for the GA Grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>In the event that an applicant is verified by more than one institution, the information most recently reported under <cite path="13B|08|10|.13|B.|(15)">§B(15) of this regulation</cite>, at the time awards are made, shall be used by OSFA to select applicants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>In the event that an applicant is verified by both an institution and OSFA, the information obtained by OSFA shall be used by OSFA to select applicants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|10|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Late Awards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>OSFA shall consider students for late GA and EA Grants if funds become available after initial awards have been made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter, consideration for a late award shall be given in the following descending order to students who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Were previously awarded and have requested reinstatement of a canceled award;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applied on time and filed an appeal based on changes in financial circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Applied on time and were eligible for an award but were not funded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Were late in applying, appealed for consideration, and were placed on the waiting list; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Applied after the deadline.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Selection of Recipients.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If funds are available to make late awards, OSFA shall fund GA and EA Grant applicants as specified in <cite path="13B|08|10|.14|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, and shall notify recipients and institutions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If funds become available after commencement of the fall semester and are sufficient to issue late awards, OSFA shall require the institution to verify the eligibility of applicants before making awards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Appeals of Eligibility Decisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An EA or GA Grant applicant or recipient may appeal an award eligibility decision, and OSFA may grant or deny an appeal of eligibility, pursuant to this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Appeals of Full-time Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant or recipient may appeal a determination that the applicant or recipient is not enrolled full-time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To be considered full-time, the actual time spent in the classroom, lab, supervised activity, or clinic shall equal at least 180 clock hours in a regular semester.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant or recipient enrolled for at least 6 credit hours, but fewer than 12 credit hours, may appeal on the basis that the individual is participating in a specific course or activity (such as an internship or a practicum) that is required by the institution to complete the academic program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Appeals to Receive Fifth or Third Year Awards. A student may appeal to hold an award for an additional year on the basis that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of baccalaureate programs, the institution confirms that the student is enrolled in an academic program that requires 5 years to complete; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student provides to OSFA evidence of extenuating financial, academic, or other circumstances that prevent the student from completing the academic program in 4 years for a baccalaureate program, or 2 years for an associate degree program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Appeals Based Upon Special Financial Circumstances. Subject to the availability of funds, OSFA shall make adjustments, as follows, based upon adequate documentation, that the student has experienced special financial circumstances that directly reduce the family contribution:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the student's parent or spouse dies on or after January 1 of the of the corresponding award year, OSFA shall adjust the FAFSA income information to exclude the income of the parent(s) or spouse affected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the student or the student's parents divorce or separate on or after January 1 of the corresponding award year, OSFA shall adjust the FAFSA income information to exclude the income of the parent or spouse affected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the student, student's parent, if dependent, or student's spouse, if the student is married and independent, becomes completely or involuntarily unemployed for at least 10 consecutive weeks in the prior or current year, OSFA shall calculate the student's family contribution and total family income using an estimated income for the current calendar year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the student or the student's parent loses, as a result of the student reaching the age of majority, benefits from Social Security, TANF, or child support, OSFA shall calculate the student's family contribution and total family income using an estimated income for the current calendar year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Appeals of GA Grant Eligibility. A GA applicant or recipient may appeal an eligibility determination, in addition to the other grounds set forth in this regulation, on the grounds that the applicant or recipient:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Did not complete high school or did not attain an unweighted grade point average of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent at the end of the first semester of the senior year in high school due to evidence of extenuating circumstances satisfactory to the Office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Did not begin college within 1 year of high school graduation or GED attainment due to extenuating circumstances, if demonstrated by evidence satisfactory to the Office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is a renewal student who no longer is eligible for the GA Grant program because the applicant’s annual family income rises above the 150 percent poverty level; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Did not complete the FAFSA or MSFAA by the March 1 deadline due to extenuating circumstances, if demonstrated by evidence satisfactory to the Office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Appeals of Credit Completion Requirement. A student who has received an EEA grant for at least 2 academic years and fails to complete at least 24 credits in the prior academic year may appeal an eligibility decision on the basis that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student completed at least 18 credit hours in the prior academic year and participated in a specific course or activity, such as an internship, practicum, or study abroad program, that is required by the institution to complete the student’s academic program and that, when combined with the 18 credit hours, is the equivalent of 24 credit hours in OSFA’s determination; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student is an individual with disabilities who completed fewer than 24 credit hours due to a disability.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Appeal Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual shall file an appeal under this regulation by submitting to OSFA a completed appeal form prescribed by OSFA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to the appeal form, the individual shall submit to OSFA the following documentation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is of an ineligibility decision due to the student’s lack of full-time status, documentation from the student’s department chair describing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The program requirements for that semester;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The catalog summary of the program and classes; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The number of clock hours required for the student’s activity;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is based upon requiring a fifth year to complete a baccalaureate program, or a third year to complete an associate degree program, documentation, as applicable, consisting of a death certificate, or statement from an attending physician, psychologist, mental health professional, guidance counselor, social worker, or the Dean of Students or other officer at the student's institution confirming the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Serious illness or injury of the student;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Serious illness of a member of the student's immediate family;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Serious emotional difficulties of the student;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Death of a member of the student's immediate family;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Existence of other serious personal circumstances; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The institution’s confirmation that the student’s baccalaureate program requires a fifth year to complete;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is based upon special financial circumstances, copies, as applicable, of a death certificate, separation agreement or divorce decree, notice of job termination or layoff, federal tax returns and W-2 forms, termination notices, or unemployment benefits from relevant agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is based upon the student not meeting the required GPA in his or her senior year of high school:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A letter from the student explaining the extenuating circumstances that caused the student not to obtain the required GPA;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An unofficial transcript to verify the student’s GPA;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supporting documentation describing the circumstances that prohibited the student from obtaining the required GPA; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A letter of recommendation from the student’s high school principal;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is from an applicant who was deemed ineligible for not beginning college within 1 year of high school graduation or GED attainment:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A letter from the student explaining the extenuating circumstances that caused the student to not begin college within 1 year of high school graduation or GED attainment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A letter of reference from an employer, teacher, or organization that the applicant is affiliated with describing the applicant’s commitment to attending college and earning a degree;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is from a student who was found to be no longer eligible for the GA program because the student’s annual family income rises above 150 percent of the poverty level, supporting documentation identifying the change in income level that resulted in the family income exceeding the 150 percent poverty threshold and extenuating circumstances demonstrating why the income should be omitted from the award calculation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is from a student who did not file the FAFSA or MSFAA by March 1 due to extenuating circumstances, a letter from the student explaining the extenuating circumstances that caused the student to miss the deadline;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>If the appeal is of a determination that the student failed to complete 24 credit hours in the prior academic year:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A letter from the student’s department chair that describes and confirms the program requirements for the applicable semester and describes the number of clock hours required for each activity, along with a catalog description of the program and classes involved; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Documentation from the student’s medical doctor that confirms that the student is an individual with disabilities, and that the student completed fewer than 24 credits due to disability; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>If the individual appeals a determination that an individual failed to complete high school:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A letter to OSFA documenting the extenuating circumstance that prevented the student from graduating high school;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A copy of the student’s high school transcript;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>If applicable, a copy of the student’s GED; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A letter of recommendation from the recipient’s high school principal.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Adjustment of Awards. Subject to the availability of funds, the following adjustment of awards shall be made for appeals that are granted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If an appeal is granted prior to awards being made for the upcoming year, the student's amount of an award shall be based upon the information provided in connection with the appeal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the student has not been awarded an award and submits the appeal after awards has been made for the upcoming year and the appeal is granted, the student shall be placed on the waiting list for an award;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the student already has been awarded an award and submits an appeal and the appeal is granted, the student shall be placed on a waiting list for any additional funds for which the student may be eligible; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If a student’s appeal based upon 12-credit-hour equivalency is granted, the student shall receive 75 percent of the original award if enrolled in 9 to 11 credits, and 50 percent of the original award if enrolled for 6 to 9 credits.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a completed appeal, the documentation shall be reviewed and a decision rendered by OSFA within 45 days, and the student shall be notified in writing of the outcome.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>OSFA’s grant or denial of an appeal under this regulation is final and not subject to further administrative or judicial review.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Documentation Required for a Dependency Override.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An institution that overrides a dependency determination for an EA applicant shall submit to OSFA for final award determination:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Updated Institutional Student Information Record data for the student; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Certification of Independent Status Form for the student.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An institution that overrides a dependency determination for a GA applicant who is selected for verification by OSFA shall submit to OSFA for final award determination:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Certification of Independent Status Form for the student; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All supporting documentation used by the institution to complete the override for the student.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Campus-Based Awards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall allocate funds to institutions of higher education to make awards to students who applied for Educational Excellence Awards after the March 1 deadline or who have other extenuating circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Funds shall be awarded to institutions based upon the proportion of full-time Pell Grant eligible Maryland residents enrolled at the institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Funds shall be awarded by institutions to students who meet the eligibility criteria for EA Grant awards in <cite path="|13B|08|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite> but who did not apply by the March 1 deadline or who have other extenuating circumstances. These students may be eligible for a Pell Grant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Awards shall be made in the amounts and the manner described in this chapter, including the same minimum amount ($400), maximum amount (established annually), required percent of need (established annually), and requirement of rounding awards to the nearest $100 increment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The amount of a Campus Based Educational Assistance Grant shall be determined in accordance with this chapter, including but not limited to <cite path="|13B|08|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An institution may not award a Delegate Howard P. Rawlings Campus-Based Educational Assistance Grant to a recipient of a Guaranteed Access or Educational Assistance Grant awarded by OSFA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Each institution of higher education that participates in the Campus-based Educational Assistance Grant program shall submit to OSFA:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By October 15, a report of all initial awards for the academic year that includes for each award the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Student’s name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Student’s Social Security number, if required by the office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Institutional cost of attendance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Expected Family Contribution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Amount of Pell Grant disbursed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Amount of Campus-based EA Grant awarded;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Pell I.D. and transaction number from the Institutional Student Information Report used for awarding; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Number of credits the student successfully completed for students enrolled in their second academic year and thereafter;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By January 15, a report of subsequent awards for the academic year that includes for each award the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Student’s name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Student’s Social Security number, if applicable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Institutional cost of attendance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Expected Family Contribution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Amount of Pell Grant disbursed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Amount of Campus-based EA grant awarded; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Number of credits the student successfully completed for students enrolled in their second academic year and thereafter; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>By June 15, a final end-of-year report that provides:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A final cumulative list of recipients that includes for each award the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Student’s name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Student’s Social Security number, if applicable; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Award amount;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The total number of students receiving an award;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The total number of students eligible for an award;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The total number of credits successfully completed for student enrolled in their second academic year and thereafter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The following demographic information provided in the aggregate:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The distribution of awards by class year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The distribution of awards by income;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The distribution of awards by age;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The distribution of awards by gender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The distribution of awards by independent vs. dependent status; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The number of recipients registering for the following year or transferring to a 4-year institution.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite>(u), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-204">18-204</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-301">18-301</cite> et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-03-25">Effective date: March 25, 2019 (46:6 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, C amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-25"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective July 25, 2022 (49:15 Md. R. 738)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-25"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite> adopted effective July 25, 2022 (49:15 Md. R. 738)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite>, C amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite>, B amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.12|D.">Regulation .12D</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite>, C amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|13B|08|10|.15|E.">Regulation .15E</cite>, G amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 509)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
