<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Richard W. Collins III Leadership with Honor Scholarship Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Program Established.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Richard W. Collins III Leadership with Honor Scholarship Program, which is administered by the Office pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-605">Education Article, §18-605, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A purpose of the program is to further the State’s compelling interests in educating diverse student bodies and in achieving diversity in ROTC programs.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Director” means the Executive Director of the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Education expenses” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tuition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Mandatory fees; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Costs of room and board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Eligible institution” means Bowie State University, Coppin State University, Morgan State University, or University of Maryland Eastern Shore.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Full-time” means enrollment at an eligible institution in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 12 credits per semester in a certificate or undergraduate degree program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 9 credits per semester in a graduate certificate, graduate degree, or doctoral degree program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Minority student or a student who is a member of another group historically underrepresented in Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC) programs”:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Means a student designated by the institution, based upon the institution’s holistic review of the applicant, as a student who contributes to diversity within ROTC programs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May include a student of any race, ethnicity, disability, national origin, religion, gender, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, or geographic representation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Office” means the Office of Student Financial Assistance within the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Part-time” means enrollment at an eligible institution in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 6 credits but fewer than 12 credits per semester in a certificate or undergraduate degree program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 6 credits but fewer than 9 credits per semester in a graduate certificate, graduate degree, or doctoral degree program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Higher Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Scholarship” means a Richard W. Collins III Scholarship under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Student Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to the State budget, the Office annually shall determine a student’s eligibility to receive a scholarship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant is eligible for a scholarship if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is enrolled full-time or part-time at an eligible institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is a member of a ROTC program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has been identified by the institution as a minority student or a student who is a member of another group historically underrepresented in Reserve Officer Training Corp (ROTC) programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has been determined to be eligible for in-State tuition by the institution; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Timely files an application and any required supporting documentation with the Office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A student shall apply annually to the Office to be eligible for a scholarship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall apply and submit a Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA) by June 15.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the applicant is ineligible to submit a FAFSA, but qualifies for in-State tuition under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the applicant shall submit a Maryland State Financial Aid Application (MSFAA) in lieu of the FAFSA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A student shall submit documentation to the Office confirming that the student is a member of a ROTC program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A student shall submit to the Office an institutional certification form, completed by the applicant’s institution, by a deadline established by the Office, confirming that the applicant is a minority student or a student who is a member of another group historically underrepresented in ROTC programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An application and FAFSA or MSFAA received by the Office after June 15 may not be considered for an award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the Office requests additional information from the applicant in order to determine the applicant’s eligibility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office shall notify the applicant of the deadline to submit such information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall submit the information by the deadline established by the Office; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Information received by the Office after the deadline may not be considered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Scholarship Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to <cite path="|13B|08|11|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, an applicant shall be eligible to renew a scholarship for a subsequent year if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Timely submits an application under <cite path="|13B|08|11|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continues to meet the requirements of <cite path="|13B|08|11|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Continues to maintain satisfactory academic progress standards as defined by the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A recipient may receive a scholarship for a maximum of 4 years.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Amount of Scholarship.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An annual scholarship award shall be in the amount prescribed by the Director, which may not exceed the recipient’s education expenses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The minimum scholarship award amount may not be less than $500 per semester and $1,000 for the academic year.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Selection of Recipients.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Priority of Scholarship Awards. The Office shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Give priority to awarding scholarships to applicants with the greatest financial need;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Award at least 25 percent of its total annual scholarship budget to students at Bowie State University; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Award the remaining amount of its total annual scholarship budget to students at other eligible institutions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant’s financial need shall be based upon the Expected Family Contribution (EFC) as reported on the FAFSA or MSFAA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant’s ranking shall be based on greatest financial need starting with the lowest EFC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Priority for scholarships in the subsequent years shall be given to prior year recipients who remain eligible under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Award Notification and Acceptance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recipients shall be notified by the Office through the Maryland College Aid Processing System (MDCAPS) of the awards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A recipient shall log on to MDCAPS in order to accept an award, except that, in extenuating circumstances as determined by the Director, a student may accept an award by providing written acceptance to the Office.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|11|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Payment of Awards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Office shall make an award payment to the institution for each semester that the eligible recipient is granted the award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The institution shall certify to the Office, and request payment for all recipients, on a semester basis, on or before:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>December 15, for the fall semester; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May 15, for the spring semester.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An institution that fails to certify and request payment for all recipients on a semester basis under <cite path="13B|08|11|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> may not certify recipients for the subsequent semester.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite>(u), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-204">18-204</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-605">18-605</cite>(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2019-11-18">Effective date: November 18, 2019 (46:23 Md. R. 1066)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-19"><cite path="|13B|08|11|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 642); April 19, 2021 (48:8 Md. R. 310)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-19"><cite path="|13B|08|11|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective April 19, 2021 (48:8 Md. R. 310)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-10-18"><cite path="|13B|08|11|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 18, 2021 (48:21 Md. R. 890)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-19"><cite path="|13B|08|11|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, E amended effective April 19, 2021 (48:8 Md. R. 310)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-10-18"><cite path="|13B|08|11|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective October 18, 2021 (48:21 Md. R. 890)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
