<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program is to help meet the State’s need for well-trained and highly skilled workers in shortage areas. Students who perform well academically and agree to use their training in eligible programs may qualify for scholarship assistance.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|14|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A recipient of assistance under this program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be a Maryland resident (if the recipient is a dependent student, the parent claiming the student as dependent shall be a Maryland resident as well);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have achieved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the applicant has completed 12 or more college credits, a cumulative college GPA of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the applicant has completed less than 12 college credits:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A cumulative, unweighted high school GPA of at least 2.5 on a 4.0 scale; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A GED with a passing score of at least 165 per module.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Enroll in an eligible major as specified in <cite path="|13B|08|14|.08">regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After completing studies in an eligible program, perform the service obligation as specified for each field in which there is a critical shortage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Sign a letter of intent to enroll in at least 6 credits per semester at an institution of higher education in Maryland as a degree-seeking undergraduate or graduate student.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Audited courses may not be used to reach the minimum credit hours for full-time or part-time status under <cite path="13B|08|14|.02|A.|(5)">§A(5) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Award Amount.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Grants shall be awarded in accordance with the minimum and maximum award ranges specified in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, “cost of attendance (COA)” means the annual expenses of a full-time resident undergraduate at the 4-year public institution of higher education within the University System of Maryland with the highest annual expense for a full-time resident undergraduate as determined by the Maryland Higher Education Commission, other than the University of Maryland University College and University of Maryland, Baltimore.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The minimum and maximum award ranges are:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th data-vertical-align="middle">Enrollment</th>
              <th data-vertical-align="middle">Community College Award Range</th>
              <th data-vertical-align="middle">4-Year Institution Award Range</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Full-time</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">$2,000 to 25 percent of COA</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">$4,000 to 50 percent of COA</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Part-Time</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000 to 12.5 percent of COA</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">$2,000 to 25 percent of COA</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) shall establish the award amount annually when program funding and the number of demand occupations to be incorporated into the program are known.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a student takes courses over a summer session to meet the minimum number of credit hours for full-time or part-time status, the award amount shall be divided equally between the fall, spring, and summer sessions, as appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A student who is enrolled in an academic program that includes mandatory summer sessions as part of the approved curriculum may receive an additional award not to exceed $1,000 per calendar year, if funds are available. A student shall apply for summer funding in writing by April 1 of that academic year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The grant award may be used at any eligible institution for educational expenses as defined by OSFA, including tuition, mandatory fees, and room and board.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Advisory Council on Workforce Shortage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of Higher Education shall appoint an Advisory Council on Workforce Shortage (Advisory Council) to identify and recommend workforce shortage fields to be included in the Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Advisory Council shall meet as necessary to make recommendations on occupations to be included in the program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At a minimum, the Advisory Council shall make recommendations every 2 years on occupations to be included in the program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Public Good or Benefit</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this section, "public good or benefit" means service to low-income or underserved residents or areas of the State in an occupation in the public sector or service in an organization, institution, association, society, or corporation that is exempt from taxation under §501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In establishing recommendations, the Advisory Council shall take into consideration whether the occupation provides a public good or benefit to the citizens of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Advisory Council’s recommendations shall be submitted to the Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) for approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Department of Labor shall provide data and analysis on demand occupations and supply to be used by the Advisory Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>OSFA shall allocate funds for each specific demand occupation within the program, based on the level of critical need. Renewals shall also be considered when determining allocations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Majors and occupational areas associated with the scholarship and tuition assistance programs listed below are included in the Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hattie N. Harrison Memorial Scholarship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ida G. and Leonard Ruben Scholarship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ruth M. Kirk Social Work Scholarship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Physical and Occupational Therapists and Assistants Scholarship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Sharon Christa McAuliffe Memorial Teacher Education Award;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Nursing Scholarship and Living Expenses Grant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>William Donald Schaefer Scholarship; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Parren J. Mitchell Public Service Scholarship.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Allocation of Funds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A specified amount of funds shall be allocated each year to each eligible occupational areas based on critical need as determined by the Advisory Council on Workforce Shortage. These funds shall be used to make awards to students majoring in specific programs leading to employment in these occupational areas.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As funding permits, the intent of the program is to incrementally address waiting lists for those occupations already incorporated into the grant program while new occupations are being included. In addition, a balanced approach shall be implemented to ensure the programs address demand in all occupations, including those currently in the program as well as new public good and economic development occupations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As the Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program expands, the determination of occupation allocations should consider the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gap analysis resulting from the workforce model;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Number of applications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Number of awards made in each eligible occupation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Number of students on a waiting list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be considered for the Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program, an applicant shall, no later than July 1:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete and file the Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit a completed application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the applicant has completed 12 or more college credits, submit an official transcript from the current or more recent institution of postsecondary education the applicant is attending or has attended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the applicant has earned less than 12 college level credits, submit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An official high school transcript; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of their GED examination;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If applying as a nursing major, submit proof of acceptance into a nursing program at the institution; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Submit any additional documentation that may be required by the Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) based on the applicant’s major.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each applicant shall agree to provide any information or documentation requested by OSFA for the purpose of administering this program and, if requested, shall sign an authorization for the release of information to OFSA for the purpose of administering this program. An applicant’s failure or refusal to provide requested information or a signed release may result in a determination of ineligibility, revocation of an award, denial of service credit, imposition of repayment obligations, or denial of a deferment or waiver request.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Selection of Recipients.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Priority for awards shall be given to prior year recipients who remain eligible for the award under <cite path="|13B|08|14|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Initial applicants shall be selected for awards based on greatest financial need, as demonstrated on the Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA).</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Eligible Majors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Advisory Council on Workforce Shortage shall identify eligible majors and occupational fields biennially based on Statewide workforce shortages.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligible majors are grouped by service areas that correspond with the service areas in <cite path="|13B|08|14|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligible Majors by Service Area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Service Area A, the Hattie M. Harrison Scholarship.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child development; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Early childhood education.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service Area B, the Ida G. and Leonard Ruben Scholarship.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Human services degree programs, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Aging services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Disability services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Mental health;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Nursing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Occupational therapy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Physical therapy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Psychology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Rehabilitation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Special education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Supported employment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Vocational rehabilitation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any other concentration in the healing arts or in programs providing support services to individuals with special needs, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Child welfare and juvenile justice; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The alcohol and drug workforce.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Service Area C, the Sharon Christa McAuliffe Scholarship.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approved teacher education programs leading to certification in a critical shortage field, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Chemistry (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Computer science (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Dance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Earth/space science (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>English for speakers of other languages (ESOL) (Pre-K—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Health occupations (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Latin (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Mathematics (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Physical science (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Physics (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Reading specialist;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Spanish (grades 7—12);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Special education, generic: infant/primary (birth—grade 3);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>Special education, generic: elementary/middle (grades 1—8);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Special education, generic: secondary/adult (grades 6—adult);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvi)</num>
            <text>Special education — hearing impaired;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvii)</num>
            <text>Special education — severely and profoundly disabled;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xviii)</num>
            <text>Special education — visually impaired;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xix)</num>
            <text>Speech language pathology (educational service area); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xx)</num>
            <text>Technology education (grades 7—12).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Elementary education is not a critical shortage field.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service Area D.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Physical therapy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Physical therapy assistant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Occupational therapy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Occupational therapy assistant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Service Area E, the William Donald Schaefer Scholarship — Law — Designed to prepare individuals to provide legal services to low-income residents in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Service Area F, the Ruth M. Kirk Public Social Work Scholarship — Social Workers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Service Area G, the Parren J. Mitchell Public Service Scholarship — Nursing and Other.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recipients shall be graduates of nursing programs and other majors designed to prepare individuals for careers in public service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recipients shall be employed in a public or nonprofit sector under §501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 in service areas where there is a shortage of qualified practitioners for low-income or underserved residents or areas of the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Payment.</heading>
    <text>Each semester, eligible institutions shall certify on billing rosters provided by the Office of Student Financial Assistance that the recipient is:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Maryland resident;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Enrolled for the required number of credits;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Enrolled in an eligible academic program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Making satisfactory academic progress towards a degree; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Maintaining the standards of the institution.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Renewal and Continuation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The award shall be automatically renewed on an annual basis up to a maximum of 5 years if the student continues to meet all of the eligibility requirements and meet the satisfactory academic progress standards of the institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The award may not be renewed if the original award was canceled because the recipient took an ineligible number of credits per semester or because of the student’s failure to maintain satisfactory academic progress.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A recipient who is academically ineligible shall forfeit the award for 1 academic year. The award may be reinstated, if funds are available, for the following academic year upon proof of meeting the standards of the institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A student transferring from one institution to another may continue to receive an award as long as the student meets all of the eligibility requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A renewal student wishing to continue receiving the award for an advanced degree shall contact the Office of Student Financial Assistance in order to determine if they are eligible for the award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A grant recipient in a workforce shortage field that is removed from the grant program may continue to receive renewal awards under the program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Service Obligation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicants offered an award shall sign and return a promissory note agreeing to begin fulfillment of the service obligation in the area/field for which the award was received within 1 year of completing the degree for which they received assistance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The service obligation begins after completion of the degree program and may not be fulfilled prior to completion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a recipient holds a Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant with any other State award requiring a service obligation, the obligations shall be served in consecutive years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a recipient works full-time, the service obligation shall be fulfilled at a rate of 1 year for each year that the award was received, even if the student was enrolled on a part-time basis for some semesters.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a recipient works part-time, the obligation shall be fulfilled at a rate of 2 years for each year the scholarship was received, even if the student was enrolled on a part-time basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Full-time employment is at least 35 hours per week, and part-time employment is at least 20 hours per week.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If a student receives a degree in a major that falls into more than one specified service area, the student may fulfill the service obligation in either area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Eligible Employment by Service Area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Service Area A. The recipient shall be employed in the State of Maryland as a director or senior staff member in a licensed Maryland childcare center or as a licensed family day care provider in Maryland. The recipient may not work as an elementary school teacher to fulfill this obligation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service Area B.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed in a Maryland community-based program that is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Licensed by the Developmental Disabilities Administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Approved by the Mental Hygiene Administration; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Certified by the Office of Health Care Quality;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed in a residential program that is licensed by the Department of Human Services or the Department of Juvenile Justice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be a direct service employee or provide first-line supervision of employees who provide habilitation, rehabilitation, residential, or related community support services to individuals:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>With developmental disabilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>With mental health disorders; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Who are dependent on alcohol or drugs;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be a direct service employee or provide first-line supervision of employees who serve children in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The custody of a local department of social services; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any residential childcare program licensed by the Department of Human Services or the Department of Juvenile Justice;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed by a State or local government entity in Maryland as a direct care service employee or provide first-line supervision of employees who provide habilitation, rehabilitation, residential, or related community support services to individuals:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>With developmental disabilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>With mental health disorders; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Who are dependent on alcohol or drugs; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed by a State or local government entity in Maryland as a direct care service employee or provide first-line supervision of employees who serve children in the custody of a local residential childcare program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Service Area C.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall become a certified teacher in Maryland:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In the certification area applied for and awarded, and be employed in a Maryland public or private elementary or secondary school as a teacher in that area; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In any teaching field if the individual commits to working in a Title I school or a school designated for improvement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance shall forgive a teacher recipient of a Workforce Shortage Student Assistant Grant for their service obligation for up to 2 years if the recipient has failed the teacher certification examination, approved by the Maryland State Board of Education, in 2 consecutive years and the recipient fails to pass the teacher certification examination within the time period specified by the Office of Student Financial Assistance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service Area D.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed as a therapist or therapy assistant to children with disabilities in a public school in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed as a therapist or therapy assistant to children with disabilities placed in an approved nonpublic education program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be employed as a therapist or therapy assistant to provide physical or occupational therapy in a State therapeutic hospital determined by the Secretary of Health to have a severe shortage of physical or occupational therapists.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Service Area E.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recipient shall be engaged in eligible employment in Maryland in public service to assist in providing legal services to low-income residents in the State.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Eligible employment is defined as employment in government at any level, public interest organization, public school, or nonprofit organization under §501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Service Area F. The recipient shall be employed as a social worker in the public or nonprofit sectors under §501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 in which there is a shortage of qualified practitioners for low-income or underserved residents or areas of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Service Area G. The recipient shall be employed as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A nurse in a Maryland licensed hospital, adult day care center, nursing home, public health agency, home health agency, an eligible institution of postsecondary education that awards nursing degrees or diplomas, or another organization authorized by the Secretary of Health; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A nurse in the public or nonprofit sectors under §501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 in which there is a shortage of qualified practitioners to low-income or underserved residents or areas of the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Repayment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a recipient fails to meet the required obligations under the Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant Program, the recipient shall repay the State the portion of the scholarship not forgiven.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Interest on the funds advanced shall be charged at an interest rate equal to the interest rate established by the United States Department of Education for the Federal Stafford Loan on the first day of July of each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Interest may not accrue prior to notification to the Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) of a recipient’s graduation or termination from an institution of higher education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Repayment may be prorated if the recipient partially fulfills their obligation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>OSFA shall waive the repayment of a grant award at a rate of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>1 year for each year that the recipient performs the service obligation on a full-time basis; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>6 months for each year that the recipient performs the service obligation on a part-time basis.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this regulation, repayment shall be made to the State within 6 years after the repayment period begins and shall follow a repayment schedule established by OSFA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|14|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Deferment of the Service Obligation and Repayment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recipients shall seek eligible employment aggressively within a 60-mile radius of their residence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A recipient may request that their service obligation be deferred during the time the recipient is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enrolled in a full-time (12 or more credits per semester) or part-time (6—11 credits per semester) undergraduate course of study, or a full-time (9 or more credits per semester) or part-time (6—8 credits per semester) graduate course of study at an institution of higher education in a degree-granting program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On a temporary leave of absence approved by the employer in the required employment field for a period not to exceed 12 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Temporarily disabled in a manner that substantially impairs the recipient’s ability to perform the service obligation, for a period not to exceed 3 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unable to maintain employment for a period not to exceed 12 months because they must care for a spouse or child who is disabled;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Assigned military duty outside of the State, not to exceed 3 years without filing an appeal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Married to a spouse assigned military duty outside of the State, not to exceed 3 years without filing an appeal; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Aggressively seeking and unable to secure employment, as required in <cite path="13B|08|14|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, for a single period not to exceed 12 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A recipient’s deferment request shall include satisfactory supporting documentation, consisting of the following, as appropriate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification by the office of the registrar that the recipient has returned to a full-time or part-time course of study at an eligible institution of higher education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certification by the employer that the recipient is on a temporary approved leave of absence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A sworn affidavit by a qualified physician that the recipient is temporarily disabled in a manner that substantially impairs the recipient’s ability to perform the service obligation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A sworn affidavit by a qualified physician that the recipient is unable to maintain employment because they must care for a spouse or child who is disabled;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A notarized statement including a list of possible eligible employers, including their addresses and telephone numbers, to which application has been made if the recipient has been unable to find full-time employment as required; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A copy of military orders.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) shall review all documentation and determine if the deferment conditions have been met and, if so, determine the deferment period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Before a deferment based on an inability to find employment is granted, OSFA shall review the recipient’s documentation and other available information and determine if the recipient has sought employment aggressively in all required areas of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>During the period of an approved deferment, a recipient need not make scholarship repayments and interest does not accrue.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>OSFA shall, on a case-by-case basis, review appeals from individuals assigned military duty outside the State, and from the spouse of an individual assigned military duty outside the State, that exceed the 3-year deferral limit. Appeals shall be in writing and include a copy of the military orders.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Waiver of the Service Obligation and Repayment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) shall waive a recipient's service and repayment obligations if it determines:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On the basis of a sworn affidavit of two qualified physicians, that the recipient is physically unable to fulfill any of the possible service obligations on a full-time or part-time basis because of a permanent impairment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On the basis of a death certificate or other evidence of death that is conclusive under State law that the recipient has died.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>OSFA shall forgive a recipient of a Workforce Shortage Student Assistance Grant, Service Area C, for up to 2 years of an award if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The recipient has taken the teacher certification examination, approved by the Maryland State Board of Education, in 2 consecutive years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The recipient fails to pass the teacher certification examination within the time period specified by OSFA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Special Financial Circumstances Appeals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A student may appeal if the student’s financial circumstances change, after the filing of the student’s application, as a result of one of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student’s parent or spouse dies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student or the student’s parents divorce or separate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The student, student’s parent (if dependent), or student’s spouse (if independent) as defined by the Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA) becomes involuntarily unemployed for at least 10 consecutive weeks in the current year; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The student or the student’s parent loses, as a result of the student reaching the age of majority, benefits from Social Security, Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF), or child support.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The student’s appeal shall be supported by appropriate documentation sufficient to substantiate the student’s claim including, but not limited to, a copy of a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Death certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Divorce decree or separation agreement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice of job termination or layoff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Federal tax transcript or W-2; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Termination notice of unemployment benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Office of Student Financial Assistance (OSFA) sustains a student’s appeal, OSFA shall provide the following relief:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the appeal was based on the death of the student’s parent or spouse, OSFA shall adjust the student’s FASFA income information to exclude the income of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the appeal was based on the student or the student’s parents’ divorce or separation, OSFA shall adjust the student’s FASFA income information to exclude the income of the affected parent or spouse;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the appeal was based on the student, student’s parent (if dependent), or student’s spouse (if independent) becoming involuntarily unemployed for at least 10 consecutive weeks in the current year, OSFA shall calculate the student’s family contribution and total family income using an estimated income for the current calendar year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the appeal was based on the student or the student’s parent losing, as a result of the student reaching the age of majority, benefits from Social Security, TANF, or child support, OSFA shall calculate the student’s family contribution and total family income using an estimated income for the current calendar year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite>(u), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-204">18-204</cite> (c), and 18-708, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-08-28">Effective date: August 28, 2017 (44:17 Md. R. 837)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-07"><cite path="|13B|08|14|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective August 7, 2023 (50:15 Md. R. 683)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-07"><cite path="|13B|08|14|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective August 7, 2023 (50:15 Md. R. 683)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-07"><cite path="|13B|08|14|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective August 7, 2023 (50:15 Md. R. 683)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
