<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>22</num>
  <heading>Teaching Fellows for Maryland Scholarship Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Program Established.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Teaching Fellows for Maryland Scholarship Program, which is administered by the Office pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 18, Subtitle 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The purpose of the Program is to provide scholarships to students who pledge to work as public school or public prekindergarten teachers in the State.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Director” means the Executive Director of the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Eligible Institution.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Eligible institution” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-2201">Education Article, §18-2201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Eligible institution” does not include a private nonprofit institution of higher education that has not timely submitted a Participation Agreement to the Office under this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Extenuating Circumstances.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Extenuating circumstances” means the occurrence of an extraordinary event or condition that prevents a recipient from fulfilling a scholarship requirement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Extenuating circumstances” may include, but are not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Disability;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Serious illness of the student;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Pregnancy or adoption;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Extreme financial hardship of the students or student’s immediate family;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Fulfillment of military service; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Serious illness or death of an immediate family member.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Full-time” means enrollment in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 12 credits per semester in an undergraduate certificate or degree program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 9 credits per semester in a graduate certificate or degree program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Initial participation year” means the academic year following the submission of a Participation Agreement under <cite path="|13B|08|22|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“MDCAPS” means the Maryland College Aid Process System maintained by the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Nonresident student” means a student that resides in housing that is privately owned.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Office” means the Office of Student Financial Assistance within the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Part-time” means enrollment in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 6 credits, but fewer than 12 credits, per semester in an undergraduate certificate or degree program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 6 credits, but fewer than 9 credits, per semester in a graduate certificate or degree program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Resident student” means a student who resides in housing that is owned by the institution in which they are enrolled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Higher Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Scholarship” means a Teaching Fellows for Maryland Scholarship under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Teaching Assistant.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Teaching assistant” means an individual who, regardless of job title, is employed at least 10 hours a week by a school or prekindergarten program to provide instructional assistance to a teacher in a classroom setting.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Teaching assistant” does not include a volunteer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Private Eligible Institutions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Participation Agreements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A private nonprofit institution of higher education that is an eligible institution under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-2201">Education Article, §18-2201(b)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall annually notify the Commission of its agreement to provide matching grants to students, pursuant to <cite path="13B|08|22|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, by submitting a Participation Agreement to the Office pursuant to this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Participation Agreement in <cite path="13B|08|22|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be in a form prescribed by the Office, which will be provided annually to all private nonprofit institutions of higher education in the State no later than February 1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Participation Agreements shall be submitted annually to the Office no later than March 1. A student at an institution that did not timely submit a Participation Agreement will not be considered for an initial award by the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The names of the institutions that timely submitted a Participation Agreement to the Office each year shall be displayed on the Commission website and the scholarship application form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Matching Grants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>During an initial participation year, an institution shall provide a matching grant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A student who receives an initial award from the Office for that year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A transfer student who receives a renewal award for that year, if it is the student’s first year attending the institution.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a student received a matching grant during an initial participation year, the institution shall provide a matching grant to the student for each year in which the student:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Remains enrolled at the institution; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Receives a renewal award under this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A matching grant under <cite path="13B|08|22|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be provided regardless of whether the institution has submitted a Participation Agreement for that year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The amount of a matching grant shall be equal to the amount of the initial or renewal award received by the student from the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Repayment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An institution is not prohibited from requiring repayment of a matching grant if the student fails to meet any scholarship requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 18, Subtitle 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An institution shall notify a student of all institutional repayment requirements prior to the student’s acceptance of a scholarship award under this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An institution shall be solely responsible for administration of any repayment obligation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Use and Amount of Award.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A scholarship shall be used solely for tuition, mandatory fees, and room and board for the fall and spring semester following the award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For a student using the scholarship at a public eligible institution, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-2201">Education Article, §18-2201(b)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the scholarship awarded by the Office shall be in an amount equal to 100 percent of the annual tuition, mandatory fees, and room and board of a resident undergraduate or graduate student, as appropriate, for the fall and spring semesters at the public eligible institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For a student using the scholarship at a private nonprofit institution of higher education that is an eligible institution under this chapter, the scholarship awarded by the Office shall be in an amount equal to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For tuition and fees, the lesser of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>100 percent of the annual tuition and mandatory fees of a resident undergraduate or graduate student, as appropriate, for the fall and spring semesters at the University of Maryland, College Park campus; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>50 percent of the annual tuition and mandatory fees of a resident undergraduate or graduate student, as appropriate, for the fall and spring semesters at the private nonprofit institution of higher education; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For room and board, 100 percent of the room and board of a resident undergraduate or graduate student, as appropriate, for the fall and spring semesters at the private nonprofit institution of higher education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Subject to the availability of funds, the award amount of a nonresident undergraduate or graduate student at a public or private nonprofit eligible institution may include an allowance for room and board costs, in an amount determined by the Office, but not more than 100 percent of the room and board of a resident undergraduate or graduate student at the institution, as appropriate.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Initial Awards — Student Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to the State budget, the Office annually shall determine students’ initial eligibility to receive a scholarship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="13B|08|22|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an applicant is eligible for a scholarship if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Does not have a Maryland professional teacher’s certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is accepted for admission or currently enrolled at an eligible institution as a full-time or part-time undergraduate or graduate student pursuing a course of study or program in an academic discipline leading to a Maryland professional teacher’s certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is a Maryland resident or has graduated from a Maryland high school;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has achieved at least:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For a student currently enrolled in high school:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A cumulative unweighted grade point average (GPA) of at least 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent after completion of the first semester of the senior year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An overall GPA in the top 15 percent of the student’s grade after the completion of the first semester of the senior year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A combined reading and math score of at least 1100 on the SAT with a score of at least 500 on each of those portions; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A composite ACT score of at least 25;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a student who has graduated from high school and completed fewer than 12 college credits:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An overall unweighted high school GPA of at least 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A combined reading and math score of at least 1100 on the SAT with a score of at least 500 on each of those portions; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A composite ACT score of at least 25;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For a student who has completed at least 12, but fewer than 24, undergraduate credits:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A cumulative undergraduate GPA of at least 3.3 on a 4.0 scale and satisfactory progress toward a degree; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A combined reading and math score of at least 1100 on the SAT with a score of at least 500 on each of these portions, provided that the student has a cumulative high school GPA of at least 3.0 on a 4.0 scale and satisfactory progress toward a degree;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For a student who has completed 24 or more undergraduate credits and does not have a bachelor’s degree:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A cumulative undergraduate GPA of at least 3.3 on a 4.0 scale and satisfactory progress toward a degree; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A score of at least 50 percent on the GRE, provided that the student has a cumulative undergraduate GPA of at least 3.0 on a 4.0 scale and satisfactory progress toward a degree; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>For a student who has a bachelor’s degree:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An overall undergraduate GPA of at least 3.3 on a 4.0 scale; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A score of at least 50 percent on the GRE, provided that the student has a cumulative undergraduate GPA of at least 3.0 on a 4.0 scale and satisfactory progress toward a degree;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Has demonstrated an exceptional dedication to or aptitude for teaching; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Timely files an application and all supporting documentation required by the Office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant is exempt from §B(3)—(5) of this regulation if, at the time they are scheduled to matriculate at an eligible institution, they will have been employed as a teaching assistant at a public school or public prekindergarten program in the State for at least 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant’s career history or prior course of study at an institution of postsecondary education may not exclude the applicant from eligibility for the scholarship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A determination made by the Office that an applicant is ineligible for an initial award is final and not subject to further review or appeal.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Initial Awards — Application Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be considered for an initial award, a student shall submit to the Office, by the deadline established by the Office, an application form and all documentation required by this regulation. Untimely submission of any required materials shall disqualify an applicant from being awarded a scholarship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Application. Except for applicants who are eligible for the scholarship under <cite path="|13B|08|22|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite>, all applicants shall submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Teaching Fellows for Maryland Scholarship application form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written essay of at least 600 words detailing exceptional dedication to or aptitude for teaching;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation of GPA and standardized test score, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For an applicant currently in high school:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A high school transcript issued after the completion of the first semester of the senior year; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the transcript indicates a cumulative unweighted GPA of less than 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent, an SAT or ACT score report or documentation, in a form prescribed by the Office, of class rank;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For an applicant who has graduated from high school and completed fewer than 12 college credits, whether or not currently enrolled:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A final high school transcript; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the transcript indicates an overall unweighted high school GPA of less than 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent, an SAT or ACT score report;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For an applicant who has completed at least 12, but fewer than 24, undergraduate credits:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The most recent college transcript; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the transcript indicates a cumulative undergraduate GPA of less than 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent, an SAT or ACT score report;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For an applicant who has completed 24 or more undergraduate credits and has not earned a bachelor’s degree, whether or not currently enrolled:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The most recent college transcript; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the transcript indicates a cumulative undergraduate GPA of less than 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent, a GRE score report; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>For an applicant who has a bachelor’s degree, whether or not the applicant has completed graduate credits or earned a graduate degree:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A final undergraduate transcript; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the transcript indicates a cumulative undergraduate GPA of less than 3.3 on a 4.0 scale or its equivalent, a GRE score report; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other documents required by the Office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant who is not required to submit an SAT, ACT, or GRE score report under <cite path="13B|08|22|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> may submit the applicable test score report in addition to the applicant’s required materials.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Form of Application — Teaching Assistant Applicants. In lieu of the documents in <cite path="13B|08|22|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, applicants who are eligible for the scholarship under <cite path="|13B|08|22|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite> shall submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Teaching Fellows for Maryland Scholarship application form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An Employment Verification Form available from the Office; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other documents required by the Office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Office may request additional information or documentation from an applicant before determining eligibility for the award. Any requested information or documentation submitted after any deadline established by the Office will not be considered.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Renewal Awards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="13B|08|22|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an initial scholarship award under this chapter may be renewed annually for a maximum of three renewal awards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A student’s scholarship shall be eligible for renewal if the student:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Continues to be a resident of the State or graduated from a high school in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continues to be a full-time or part-time undergraduate or graduate student at an eligible institution pursuing a course of study or program in an academic discipline leading to a Maryland professional teacher’s certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="13B|08|22|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, has maintained a cumulative grade point average of at least a 3.3 on a 4.0 scale, as demonstrated by the student’s most recent undergraduate or graduate transcript;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is determined by their institution to be maintaining satisfactory progress towards a degree; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintains the disciplinary standards of the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Renewal of Award for Fifth Year.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a student is enrolled in a course of study or program that, as determined by the institution, requires 5 years to complete, an initial scholarship award may be renewed annually for a maximum of four renewal awards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student shall request renewal of the award for a fifth year by submitting to the Office:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Documentation from the institution that the course of study or program in which the student is enrolled requires 5 years to complete; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any other documents requested by the Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Determinations made by the Office under this section are final and not subject to further review or appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of GPA Requirement Based on Extenuating Circumstances.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A student who has not achieved the required GPA shall be eligible to receive a renewal award if the student provides the Office with documentation of extenuating circumstances and the Office determines that the documentation provides sufficient evidence of the extenuating circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student shall request a waiver by submitting to the Office:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A letter explaining the extenuating circumstances and why they prevented the student from achieving the required GPA;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any documentation of the occurrence of the extenuating circumstances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other relevant supporting documentation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other documents requested by the Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Waiver determinations made by the Office are final and not subject to further review or appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Selection of Recipients.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the number of applicants for awards exceeds the amount of funds available, eligible applicants will be selected pursuant to §§B—E of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Renewal Awards. Priority shall be given to applicants who are renewing an award under <cite path="|13B|08|22|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>High School and Undergraduate Students.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If funds remain after awards are made to students under <cite path="13B|08|22|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, priority shall be given to initial applicants who have not yet earned an undergraduate degree.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the number of applicants under this section exceeds the amount of funds available, applicants shall be ranked in descending order by GPA or the GPA equivalent, as established by the Office, of the applicant’s SAT, ACT, or GRE score, whichever is higher.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Teaching Assistants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If funds remain after awards are made to students under §§B and C of this regulation, priority shall be given to initial applicants who have applied as teaching assistants under <cite path="|13B|08|22|.06|D.">Regulation .06D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the number of applicants under this section exceeds the amount of funds available, applicants shall be ranked according to application submission date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Graduate Students.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If funds remain after awards are made to students under §§B—D of this regulation, awards shall be made to applicants who have already earned an undergraduate degree.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the number of applicants under this section exceeds the amount of funds available, applicants will be ranked in descending order by GPA or the GPA equivalent, as established by the Office, of the applicant’s GRE score, whichever is higher.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An eligible applicant who does not receive an award shall be notified and placed on a waiting list.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Award Notification and Acceptance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A recipient shall be notified by the Office of an award offer in writing, which may include electronic mail.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The recipient shall have 6 weeks from the date notification was sent by the Office to accept the award. A recipient who does not accept the award in that time period will not receive an award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A recipient shall log into MDCAPS in order to accept an award offer unless permitted by the Director to provide an alternative form of written acceptance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Additional Requirements for Receipt of Award.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To receive the award, a recipient shall, by the deadline established by the Office:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Execute the written agreement with the Commission described in <cite path="|13B|08|22|.11|B.">Regulation .11B of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sign the promissory note described in <cite path="|13B|08|22|.11|B.">Regulation .11B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A recipient who does not timely complete the requirements of this section will not receive an award.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Certification and Disbursement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Annual awards shall be disbursed in two installments, one per semester.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Certification of Initial Awards. Before an initial award is disbursed, eligible institutions shall certify, on billing rosters provided by the Office, that a recipient is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If applicable, a Maryland resident; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enrolled as a full-time or part-time undergraduate or graduate student, as applicable, pursuing a course of study or program in an academic discipline leading to a Maryland professional teacher’s certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Certification of Renewal Awards. Before a renewal award is disbursed, eligible institutions shall certify, on billing rosters provided by the Office, that a recipient:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If applicable, continues to be a Maryland resident;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continues to be enrolled as a full-time or part-time undergraduate or graduate student, as applicable, pursuing a course of study or program in an academic discipline leading to a Maryland professional teacher’s certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has maintained a cumulative GPA of at least 3.3 on a 4.0 scale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is maintaining satisfactory academic progress toward a degree; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is maintaining the disciplinary standards of the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An institution shall provide certification to the Office and request payment for all recipients on a semester basis no later than:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>December 15, for the fall semester; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May 15, for the spring semester.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An institution that fails to timely certify and request payment for all recipients under <cite path="13B|08|22|.10|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> may not certify recipients for the subsequent semester until all prior semester awards have been certified and disbursed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Scholarship Conditions and Repayment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recipient Obligations. A scholarship recipient shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain all scholarship eligibility requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 18, Subtitle 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Satisfy the degree requirements of the course of study or program for which the scholarship was received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After completion of the course of study or program for which the scholarship was received, perform a service obligation that meets the requirements of <cite path="|13B|08|22|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Become professionally certified to teach in the State of Maryland no later than 2 years after completion of the course of study or program for which the scholarship was received; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Satisfy any other criteria established by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Documents. A recipient shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enter into a written agreement with the Commission, in the form and manner prescribed by the Office, to meet the scholarship conditions in <cite path="13B|08|22|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sign a promissory note, in the form prescribed by the Office, to repay the award if the recipient does not perform the obligations set forth in the written agreement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Conversion of Scholarship to Loan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|13B|08|22|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>, if a recipient breaches the agreement or promissory note in <cite path="13B|08|22|.11|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the scholarship shall be converted to a student loan, payable to the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="13B|08|22|.11|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, the amount of the loan shall be equivalent to the total of the awards received by the recipient from the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The loan amount may be prorated based on partial fulfillment of the service obligation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Interest on the loan shall be charged at an interest rate equal to the interest rate established by the United States Department of Education for the Federal Stafford Loan on July 1st each year. Interest will not accrue prior to a recipient’s graduation or termination from an eligible institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Office shall establish a repayment schedule for the loan. Except as otherwise provided in this regulation, repayment shall be made to the State within 6 years after the repayment period begins.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Loan Forgiveness.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office shall partially forgive a recipient's repayment obligation, in an amount equal to 2 years’ awards, if it determines that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recipient has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Taken the teacher certification examination approved by the State Board of Education, in 2 consecutive years; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Failed to pass the teacher certification examination within 2 years after completion of the course of study or program for which the scholarship was received; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The recipient has provided to the Office satisfactory evidence of extenuating circumstances that prevented the recipient from becoming professionally certified to teach in the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Decisions of the Office regarding loan forgiveness are final and not subject to further review or appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13B|08|22|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Service Obligation Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Allowable Employment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Generally. Except as set forth in <cite path="13B|08|22|.12|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, the service obligation requirement in <cite path="|13B|08|22|.11|A.">Regulation .11A of this chapter</cite> shall be fulfilled by employment of at least 35 hours a week as a teacher at:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A public school in the State that has at least 50 percent of its students eligible for free or reduced price meals; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A public prekindergarten program in the State that has at least 50 percent of its students eligible for free or reduced price meals.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employment Unavailable.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If, after aggressively seeking employment for a position that meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="13B|08|22|.12|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, a recipient is unable to perform the service requirement in this section because there are no available positions that meet these requirements, the service obligation may take place in any public school or public prekindergarten program in the State.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A recipient described in <cite path="13B|08|22|.12|A.|(2)|(a)">§A(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall provide to the Office documentation that provides sufficient evidence, as determined by the Office, that there are no available positions that meet the requirements of <cite path="13B|08|22|.12|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The service obligation requirement may not be fulfilled by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employment as a teaching assistant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Volunteer service; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A fellowship or internship.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Duration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Undergraduate Students. For each year a recipient receives a scholarship for an undergraduate program, the recipient shall perform the service obligation for 1 year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Graduate Students. A recipient who receives a scholarship for a graduate program shall perform the service obligation for at least 2 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Deferment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A recipient may request that the service obligation be deferred during the time the recipient is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enrolled full-time or part-time in a graduate certificate or degree program in Education in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a temporary leave of absence of less than 12 months from an allowable employer under this regulation, approved by the employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Temporarily disabled in a manner that substantially impairs the recipient’s ability to perform the service obligation, for a period not to exceed 3 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Unable to maintain employment because the recipient must care for a spouse or child who is disabled, for a period not to exceed 12 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Assigned military duty outside of the State, for a period not to exceed 3 years unless the Director determines that special circumstances exist that warrant a longer period; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Married to a spouse assigned military duty outside of the State, for a period not to exceed 3 years unless the Director determines that special circumstances exist that warrant a longer period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A recipient’s deferment request shall include satisfactory supporting documentation, consisting of the following, as appropriate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certification by an institute in the State that the recipient is enrolled in a full-time or part-time graduate certificate or degree program in Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Certification by the employer that the recipient is on a temporary approved leave of absence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A sworn affidavit by a qualified physician that the recipient is temporarily disabled in a manner that substantially impairs the recipient’s ability to perform the service obligation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A sworn affidavit by a qualified physician that the recipient is unable to maintain employment because the recipient must care for a spouse or child who is disabled; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A copy of military orders.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Office shall review all documentation, determine if the deferment conditions have been met, and, if so, determine the deferment period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Decisions of the Office regarding deferment are final and not subject to further review or appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|11-105">11-105</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-204">18-204</cite> and Title 18, Subtitle 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-25">Effective date: July 25, 2022 (49:15 Md. R. 739)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
