<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Disposal Process</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>These regulations only apply to State-owned personal property that has been declared excess or surplus under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-502">State Finance and Procurement Article, §4-502, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. They do not apply to other State-owned personal property that is covered by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|10-305">State Finance and Procurement Article, §10-305</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Availability.</heading>
    <text>Serviceable excess property will be listed periodically in the Excess Property Bulletin, a Statewide Department of General Services publication, notifying State agencies, local governments, and nonprofit organizations of available excess property.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Inventory Management Division of the Department of General Services shall determine the method of property disposition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Excess property will be transferred to another State agency, whenever feasible, before other methods of disposal are considered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Excess property sales will be executed by competitive sealed bids or public auctions.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Utilization by a Local Jurisdiction or Nonprofit Organization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Excess property that is no longer needed by the State may be sold without obtaining competitive bids or donated to a local jurisdiction or nonprofit organization upon approval by the Secretary of General Services or the Secretary's designee at no lower than the Assistant Secretary's level.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A local jurisdiction or nonprofit organization obtaining donated property shall be required to sign a statement certifying the intended use of the property in the recipient's program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-204">4-204</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-501">4-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-508">4-508</cite>,<br/>Annotated Code of Maryland; <cite path="21.01.03.01|A.|(10)">COMAR 21.01.03.01A(10)</cite></annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-06-27">Effective date: June 27, 1988 (15:13 Md. R. 1551)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-01"><cite path="|04|03|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective May 1, 2000 (27:8 Md. R. 796)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
