<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Surplus Personal Property—Enterprise Activity</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Enterprise activity" means a State governmental operation that markets goods and related services intended to result in revenue after payment of all costs, overhead, and expenses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Inmate labor" means labor by individuals on work release from the Maryland Correctional System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"MSASP" means the Maryland State Agency for Surplus Property, a self-supporting division of the Department of General Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Qualified donee" means a unit of State government, a local governmental jurisdiction, or a nonprofit, tax-exempt organization, eligible to purchase surplus property from MSASP.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Refurbish" means the process of enhancing the marketability of property through operations including, but not limited to, cleaning, painting, assembling, repairing, reupholstering, adding, or replacing component parts, etc.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Surplus Property.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Surplus property" means federal surplus personal property as well as items of excess personal property, located at the MSASP Warehouse, that the Department of General Services declares as not needed by any unit of State government.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Surplus property" includes motor vehicles, machinery, office furniture, clothing, office machines, etc.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="04|03|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>MSASP Enterprise Activity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope and Purpose.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>MSASP is an unfunded, self-supporting agency that may engage in enterprise activity in order to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cover its operating expenses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Generate revenue for the State's General Fund;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employ and train qualified inmates in vocational skills; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provide quality, finished products to qualified donees at attractive prices.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>MSASP may market refurbished surplus property to qualified donees, together with incidental design, planning, installation, and delivery services on a project-by-project basis, including the marketing of complete modular office furniture systems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disposition of Funds. Money received from the sale of surplus property shall be handled in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-505">State Finance and Procurement Article, §4-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Accounting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>MSASP shall keep accurate accounts of all enterprise activity in a standardized form that is complete and subject to audit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accounts are to be kept on a project-by-project basis and include detailed entries for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Surplus property as well as purchased property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Services incidental to each enterprise agency project; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Payments received from a qualified donee customer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prerequisites to MSASP Enterprise Activity. After the initial consultation, planning, and estimating stages of an enterprise activity project, MSASP shall proceed with the project only if in good faith it can ensure that the materials to be used in the project will consist primarily of surplus or refurbished property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Materials. Whenever a good-faith estimate in <cite path="04|03|02|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> is made, MSASP may buy additional used or refurbished materials, or both, as well as a minimal amount of new material, as needed to complete the project, and shall obtain the best price in accordance with good business practices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Labor.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided, all enterprise activity labor, including marketing and customer service such as design, planning, estimating, installation, and delivery, shall be performed by MSASP employees and MSASP inmate labor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If, after the initial consultation, planning, and estimating stages, MSASP is unable to meet a project's labor requirements through its own employees and inmate labor, then MSASP may subcontract the remaining labor to State Use Industries.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If State Use Industries cannot perform the labor or cannot enter subcontracts because of time constraints, then MSASP may subcontract for labor with private organizations, subject to good business practices in obtaining the best competitive price.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-501">4-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-508">4-508</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-11-20">Effective date: November 20, 1995 (22:23 Md. R. 1799)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
