<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish procedures for the Department to carry out the responsibilities and goals of the Maryland Veterans Service Animal Program pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(h), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Eligible nonprofit training entity” means a nonprofit training entity that qualifies under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(d)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Eligible veteran” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Fund” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Nonprofit training entity” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(a)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Program” means the Maryland Veterans Service Animal Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Program participant” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(a)(6), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Service Dog</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Service dog” has the meaning stated in the Americans with Disabilities Act, 42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq., as amended.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Service dog” includes any dog that is individually trained to do work or perform tasks for the benefit of an individual with a disability, including a physical, sensory, psychiatric, intellectual, or other mental disability.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Service dog” does not include any other species of animal, whether wild or domestic, trained or untrained.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Successful program participant” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957(a)(7), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Support dog” means a dog that is individually trained and that serves as an emotional support animal or therapy animal that a medical professional, within the medical professional’s scope of practice, has determined provides benefit for an individual with a sensory, psychiatric, intellectual, or other disability.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Therapy horse” means a horse determined appropriate for interactions with veterans at a stable licensed by the State that is a Professional Association of Therapeutic Horsemanship, International (PATH, Intl.) member center or has Equine Assisted Growth and Learning Association (EAGALA) certified professionals who provide services to veterans.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Applicability.</heading>
    <text>These regulations apply to every expenditure by the Department of money from the Fund.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Program Outreach.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department will promote the program to eligible veterans using website announcements, social media sites, electronic newsletters, print media and brochures, and community outreach events.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department will encourage successful program participants to assist with program outreach and referral of eligible veterans.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Referral of Eligible Veterans to Selected Nonprofit Training Entities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligible nonprofit training entities must complete a Program application and submit any additional information or documentation requested by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nonprofit training entities must be registered and in good standing with the Office of the Secretary of State to be considered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department will publish a list of the selected nonprofit training entities on its website.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department will refer veterans to the list of entities and maintain a record of referrals made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The nonprofit training entity will screen a referred veteran for eligibility to become a program participant.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Donations to the Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department will accept online donations through its website.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department will allow donors to request anonymity before publishing an annual list of donors.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Disbursements from the Fund to Selected Nonprofit Training Entities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall review grant applications and award grant awards to approved nonprofit training entities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nonprofit training entities shall submit progress reports to the Department.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-957">State Government Article, §9-957, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-12-18">Effective date: Effective December 18, 2017 (44:251 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2024-01-08"><cite path="|35|06|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 10, 2020 (47:3 Md. R. 173); January 24, 2022 (49:2 Md. R. 79); January 8, 2024 (50:26 Md. R. 1133)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-10"><cite path="|35|06|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective February 10, 2020 (47:3 Md. R. 173)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|35|06|01|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 728)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-24"><cite path="|35|06|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> repealed and new Regulation .07 adopted effective January 24, 2022 (49:2 Md. R. 79)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
