<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Public Improvements Project Review</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="23|02|03|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="23|02|03|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, this chapter applies to all projects for the construction, maintenance, or repair of any building, structure, or other public work:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owned or constructed by the State or any unit of the State government, including the University of Maryland; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Acquired or constructed in whole or in part with State funds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to the construction, maintenance, or repair of any building, structure, or other public work by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department of Transportation or a unit within that Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any housing authority created under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="44A">Article 44A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Washington Suburban Sanitary Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Baltimore County Metropolitan District; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A county, municipal corporation, or unit of a county or municipal corporation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Power to Exempt.</heading>
    <text>The Board of Public Works may exempt specific projects for the construction, maintenance, or repair of any building, structure, or other public work by a unit of State government from the provisions of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Title 4, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, pursuant to the procedures set forth in Regulation .03, of this chapter.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Exemption Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Request for Exemption. A unit may request the Board of Public Works to exempt a specific project under Regulation .02, of this chapter, by filing an application with the Secretary to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Application. The application shall be in writing and shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The identity of the applicant and of the building, structure, or other public work that is the subject of the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the project and its purpose; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The reason why the exemption is sought.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Action of Board of Public Works.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As soon as practicable after submission, the Secretary to the Board shall place the application for exemption on the Board Agenda.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall consider the request and may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Grant the request if it finds that the exemption is in the best interests of the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deny the request; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Defer action, pending submission of additional information from the applicant, study by the Department of General Services, or any other action that the Board deems necessary or appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notification. The Secretary to the Board promptly shall notify the applicant in writing of the Board's action. If action on the application is deferred, the notice shall state the terms of the deferral.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-402">State Finance and Procurement Article, §4-402, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-05">Effective date: September 5, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2154)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
