<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Pictures of Abducted Children</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following words have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Agency" means the Department of General Services, the Department of Transportation, or the University System of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Center" means the Maryland Center for Missing Children, a unit of the Criminal Intelligence Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Facility.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Facility" means any single building or group of buildings in the same location under the control of or managed by an agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Facility" includes an office complex and an educational campus.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Superintendent" means the chief of operations of a facility or the designee of the chief of operations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="23|02|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Posting of Pictures in Facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each superintendent shall designate which building or buildings within a facility are appropriate for the display of pictures of missing children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In each designated building, the superintendent shall allocate space for the display of pictures of missing children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the space allocated under <cite path="23|02|05|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the superintendent shall display the pictures of children abducted in non-custody-related abductions, which the Center submits for display.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The superintendent may control the size and manner of a display, including the number of pictures and the length of time for which the pictures are to be displayed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In making a determination under §§A—D of this regulation, the superintendent may consider, at the superintendent's absolute discretion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The needs of the agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount of pedestrian traffic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The facility's resources; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other factor reasonably related to the determination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Duties of the Center.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Center is the central clearinghouse for distribution of pictures to facilities for display.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Center shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine which pictures of children abducted in non-custody-related abductions should be submitted for display;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Distribute current pictures to superintendents for display; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notify superintendents when a picture should no longer be displayed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Law enforcement agencies and nonprofit advocacy groups for abducted children shall work through the Center to submit pictures of missing children for display.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|4-209">State Finance and Procurement Article, §4-209, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-08-25">Effective date: August 25, 1997 (24:17 Md. R. 1217)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
