<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Petition for Declaratory Ruling</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Who May File.</heading>
    <text>Any interested person may file a petition with the Treasurer with respect to the applicability of any statute pertaining to the Office of the State Treasurer or the applicability of any regulation adopted by the Treasurer.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Form.</heading>
    <text>The petition shall be in writing and shall contain a detailed statement of the facts. It shall question the applicability of the State statute or regulation to these facts. The petition shall contain the name, address, and telephone number of the petitioner and a statement describing the petitioner's interest in making the request for the declaratory ruling. In addition, the petition shall contain a statement by the petitioner, under oath, that the facts contained in the petition are true to the best of his knowledge, information, and belief.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Submission, Consideration, and Disposition.</heading>
    <text>The petition for declaratory ruling shall be filed with the Treasurer. The Treasurer or the Treasurer's designee shall consider the petition and shall notify the petitioner in writing of its disposition, stating the reasons for the Treasurer's issuance or denial of the declaratory ruling requested. A written answer from the Treasurer or the Treasurer's designee to an inquiry may not be construed to be a declaratory ruling unless made in conformity with this regulation.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-304">State Government Article, §10-304, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-04-09">Effective date: April 9, 1984 (11:7 Md. R. 628)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-17"><cite path="|25|01|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 17, 1988 (15:21 Md. R. 2470)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-17"><cite path="|25|01|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 17, 1988 (15:21 Md. R. 2470)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
