<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Exception to Participation Restriction</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The Commission may grant an official or employee an exception to the participation restrictions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-501">General Provisions Article, §5-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, related to a business entity with which a qualifying relative is affiliated if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The official’s or employee’s agency or appointing authority supports the exception; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission finds that, based on the overall circumstances and relationships, granting an exception is not contrary to the purposes of the Public Ethics Law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Factors to Be Considered.</heading>
    <text>In determining whether to grant an exception under <cite path="|19A|02|03|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, the Commission shall consider:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The nature of the qualifying relative’s relationship with the business entity;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The nature of the relationship between the official or employee and the qualifying relative;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The geographical distance between the official or employee and the qualifying relative;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any prior issues related to the official’s or employee’s participation in the matter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Agency controls and safeguards;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Any involvement by the qualifying relative in the matter involving the official or employee; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The nature of the official’s or employee’s participation in the matter in relation to the official’s or employee’s overall duties.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-206">5-206</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-501">5-501</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1308)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
