<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Correction or Amendment of Personal Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>These regulations set out procedures for persons in interest to request the correction or amendment of personal records under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-625">State Government Article, §10-625, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In these regulations, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Act" means the Access to Public Records Act, State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">10-611</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-628">10-628</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Public Works.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Custodian" means a person employed by the Board of Public Works having personal custody and control of a public record of the office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Official custodian" means the Secretary to the Board of Public Works.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Person in interest" means a person or governmental unit that is the subject of a public record or a designee of the person or governmental unit, or, if the person has a legal disability, a parent or legal representative of the person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Personal record" means a public record that names or, with reasonable certainty, otherwise identifies an individual by an identifying factor such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A description;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A finger or voice print;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A number; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A picture.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Who May Request.</heading>
    <text>A person in interest may request the Board to correct or amend any personal record pursuant to §10-625 of the Act.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Contents of Request.</heading>
    <text>The request shall be in writing and shall state the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Name, address, and phone number of the person making the request;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Precise correction or amendment requested; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reason the correction or amendment is sought.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Filing The Request.</heading>
    <text>A request for correction or amendment of a record shall be filed with the Board by addressing it to the custodian of the record. If the custodian is unknown, the request may be addressed to the official custodian.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Return of Request.</heading>
    <text>If a request does not reasonably comply with Regulation .04, of this chapter, it shall be returned to the person in interest with an explanation and a statement that, upon completion, it may be refiled with the Board.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Response to Request.</heading>
    <text>Within 30 days after receipt of a proper request for correction or amendment the custodian shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Make the requested correction or amendment and inform the person in writing of the action;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inform the person in writing of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The refusal to make the requested correction or amendment, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for the refusal; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Inform the person in writing that the record will not be amended or corrected as requested because:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person is not a person in interest,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The record sought to be corrected or amended is not a personal record,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The person requesting the correction or amendment is not entitled to inspect the record under State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-615">10-615</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-619">10-619</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other reason that is authorized by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Statement of Disagreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Right to File. If the Board refuses the requested correction or amendment, the person in interest may file a concise statement of the reasons for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The requested correction or amendment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disagreement with the refusal of the Board to make the correction or amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Statements of Disagreement. The statement shall be filed on pages not exceeding 8-1/2 X 11 inches in size. Only one side of the page shall contain a statement. Not more than five pages will be accepted in connection with a single request for correction or amendment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Information Provided to Third Parties. When the Board discloses to a third party information from personal records about which a statement of disagreement has been filed, the Board shall furnish a copy of the statement to the third party.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Administrative and Judicial Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may seek administrative and judicial review in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if the person has been denied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request to change a personal record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The right to file a statement of disagreement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The right to have a statement of disagreement forwarded to a third party pursuant to Regulation .08C.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for administrative review of a decision of the Board to deny a request to change a personal record shall be filed within 30 days of the date of the decision.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-625">State Government Article, §10-625, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-05">Effective date: September 5, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2153)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
