<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Administrative Disqualification Hearings — Food Supplement and Family Investment Programs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish the procedures to be used by the Administration to disqualify individuals for the Food Supplement Program or Family Investment Programs, when there is sufficient evidence to substantiate the decision that the individual has committed an intentional violation of the Food Supplement Program or Family Investment Program regulations.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Family Investment Administration of the Department of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Administrative disqualification hearing" means a hearing held by an administrative law judge (ALJ) of the Office of Administrative Hearings to determine if an intentional program violation has occurred.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Caretaker relative" means an individual related by blood or marriage who is the parent or is acting on behalf of the parent of a dependent child.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Hearing" means a contested case hearing as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-202">State Government Article, §10-202(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Intentional program violation" means an intentional:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>False or misleading statement or misrepresentation, concealment, or withholding of facts:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Concerning food supplement; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For the purposes of establishing or maintaining the assistance unit's eligibility for TCA or for increasing or preventing a reduction of the amount of TCA; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Act that constitutes a violation of the Food Stamp Act, the Food Supplement Program regulations, or any State statute relating to the use, presentation, transfer, acquisition, receipt, or possession of food supplement benefits or electronic benefit transfer (EBT) card.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Local department" means a department of social services in a county or Baltimore City, or the Montgomery County Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH)" means the unit within the Executive Branch established by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1602">State Government Article, §9-1602, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Program Fraud Division” means the unit of the Office of the Inspector General’s Bureau of Investigative Services that provides investigative resources for local departments in the investigation of suspected fraud in Department programs including but not limited to TCA, the Office of Home Energy Programs (OHEP), and food supplement benefit application, redetermination, and open cases.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Temporary cash assistance (TCA)" means benefits received under <cite path="|07.03.03">COMAR 07.03.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notification to an Applicant Household.</heading>
    <text>The local department shall inform the household, in the case of food supplement benefits and TCA, of the disqualification penalties for intentional program violations in clear, prominent, and boldface lettering on the application form each time the household or individual applies for food supplement benefits or TCA.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Local Department Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When information is received that an individual may have committed an intentional program violation, the local department shall refer the information to the Office of the Inspector General which shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct an investigation of the suspected intentional program violators;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prepare a report on the completed investigation showing the methods used to obtain information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make the report available to the director of the local department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The local departments for OHEP shall refer the information to the OHEP central office for review and investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When the local department decides that there is sufficient documentary evidence that an individual has committed an intentional program violation, the local department shall refer the individual to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Local State's attorney if the alleged facts in the case meet the guidelines established by the State's attorney for prosecution; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>OAH for an administrative disqualification hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the local State's attorney decides that a case does not warrant prosecution, the local department may refer that case to OAH for an administrative disqualification hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the local State's attorney does not act on a referred case within a reasonable period of time, the local department shall formally withdraw the referral and refer the case to OAH for an administrative disqualification hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The local department may refer an individual for an administrative disqualification hearing regardless of the current eligibility of the individual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The local department may not initiate an administrative disqualification hearing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Against an individual whose case is being referred by the State's attorney for prosecution; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After the State's attorney or a court of appropriate jurisdiction has taken any action against the individual in a case arising out of the same or related circumstance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Waiver of Administrative Disqualification Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The local department may allow an individual who is accused of an intentional program violation to waive the individual's right to an administrative disqualification hearing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supervisory Review. Before providing advanced written notification that the individual may waive the individual's right to an administrative disqualification hearing, the local department shall ensure that someone other than the eligibility worker assigned to the accused individual's household or assistance unit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reviews the evidence against the household member or individual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determines that the evidence warrants scheduling of a disqualification hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Advance Notification. When the local department decides to allow an individual to waive the individual's right to an administrative disqualification hearing, the local department shall notify the individual in writing. The notice shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A summary of the charge against the individual and the evidence to support it;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Information regarding the administrative disqualification hearing including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement that the individual may waive the right to an administrative disqualification hearing,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date, not later than 20 days after the mailing of the notice, after which the local department will refer the case to OAH for a hearing if the local department has not received the signed waiver,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The requirement that, for charges the head of household shall also sign the waiver if the individual is not the head of household,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A statement that the individual has the right to remain silent and that anything the individual says or signs concerning the charge may be used in future administrative or judicial proceedings,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A statement that signing the waiver will result in disqualification and  reduce or terminate benefits for the household or assistance unit;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An opportunity for the individual to admit to the facts presented by the local department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A statement that the disqualified individual and remaining household or assistance unit members are responsible for repayment of any overissued benefits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A statement that a hearing does not preclude the State or federal government from prosecuting the individual for the intentional program violation in a civil or criminal court; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The name and telephone number of the person to contact for additional information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Imposition of Disqualification Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the local department receives a signed waiver of the right to an administrative disqualification hearing before the hearing, the local department shall apply the disqualification penalty in accordance with <cite path="|07|03|10|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The signing of the waiver of the right to an administrative disqualification hearing terminates the administrative process to establish an intentional program violation. The disqualification penalty may not be changed by a subsequent OAH decision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The individual may request a hearing if the individual disagrees with the amount of the overissued benefits or the method of repayment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Referral for Disqualification Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the local department does not receive a signed waiver of the right to an administrative disqualification hearing within 20 days of providing advance notification in accordance with <cite path="|07|03|10|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite>, the local department shall refer the individual to OAH for a hearing in accordance with <cite path="|07.01.04">COMAR 07.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The referral shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identifying case information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A summary of the alleged intentional program violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Copies of the local department's supporting documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Documentation that the individual has been:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Previously disqualified for an intentional program violation, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Convicted by a court of fraud involving food supplement or TCA.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Effect of Pending Disqualification Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pending disqualification hearing does not affect the individual's, the household's, or the assistance unit's right to be certified and participate in the program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The local department shall terminate or reduce the household's benefits if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is documentation to support the action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The household fails to request a hearing and continuation of benefits after notice of termination or reduction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|03|10|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Disqualification Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Food Supplement Program and Family Investment Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual who has waived the right to an administrative hearing, or was found to have committed an intentional program violation, is ineligible to participate in the specified Program, as described in <cite path="07|03|10|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> and <cite path="07.03.03.19">COMAR 07.03.03.19</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The disqualification period begins for Food Supplement and Family Investment Program, with the first month following the month in which the household receives written notification of the disqualification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Once a disqualification penalty has been imposed, the period of disqualification continues uninterrupted until the disqualification period is completed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual disqualified for an IPV is ineligible for the following period of time:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One year for the first violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two years for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Second violation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>First finding by a court of the trading of Program benefits for an illegal drug;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Permanently for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Third violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Second finding by a court of the trading of Program benefits for an illegal drug;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>First finding by a court of the trading of Program benefits for firearms, ammunition, or explosives; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>First finding by a court of trafficking Program benefits of $500 or more; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ten years if an individual is found guilty of making a fraudulent statement or misrepresentation with respect to the individual’s identity or residence to receive multiple benefits at the same time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The local department shall disqualify only the individual in the household found to have committed an IPV or who signed the waiver of the right to an administrative hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The disqualification period begins with the first month following the month in which the individual receives written notification of the decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Once a disqualification penalty has been imposed, the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Period of disqualification shall continue uninterrupted until completed regardless of the eligibility of the disqualified member’s household; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disqualified member’s household shall continue to be responsible for the repayment of the overissuance resulting from the disqualified member’s IPV regardless of the household’s eligibility for program benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>When an individual is disqualified, the local department shall send the household a demand letter for restitution. This letter shall inform the household of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount owed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for the claim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The period of time the claim covers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any offsetting done to reduce the claim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The ways in which the claim may be paid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The household’s right to a fair hearing if the household disagrees with the amount of the claim, except if the household already had a fair hearing on the amount of the claim as a result of consolidation of the administrative disqualification hearing with the fair hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The household’s right to request renegotiation of any agreed to repayment schedule if the household’s economic circumstance change; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The requirements to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Indicate by signature the household’s agreement to make restitution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Select the method of repayment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Return the repayment notice within 30 days of the date of the notice.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The local department shall provide written notice:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Of the effective disqualification date to the household or assistance unit before imposing the sanction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To the remaining household members, if any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of the benefit they will receive during the period of disqualification; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That they may reapply because the certification period has expired.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An OAH finding of an intentional program violation may not be reversed by a subsequent OAH decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>When a household or assistance unit has been sanctioned, the local department shall send the assistance unit or household a demand letter for restitution which includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount owed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for the claim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The period of time covered by the claim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any offsetting done to reduce the claim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The ways in which the claim can be paid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The right to a hearing if the household or assistance unit disagrees with the amount of the claim, unless the household or assistance unit has already had a hearing on the amount of the claim as a result of the consolidation of an administrative disqualification hearing with another hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The right to request renegotiation of any repayment schedule if the household's or assistance unit's economic circumstances change; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The requirement to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sign the repayment notice to indicate agreement to make restitution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Select the method of payment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Return the repayment notice within 30 days of the date of the notice.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Human Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|5-207">5-207</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|5-501">5-501</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|5-604">5-604</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Agency Note: Federal Regulatory Reference—7 CFR §273.16</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-02-02">Chapter, Work Incentive Program/Income Maintenance Units (WIN/IMU), adopted effective February 2, 1977 (4:3 Md. R. 143)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-02-22"><cite path="|07|03|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 22, 1980 (7:4 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-12-20"><cite path="|07|03|10|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective April 3, 1981 (8:7 Md. R. 641); June 7, 1982 (9:11 Md. R. 1126); August 2, 1982 (9:15 Md. R. 1513); December 20, 1982 (9:25 Md. R. 2479)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-07">Regulations .05B and .06B, C amended effective March 7, 1980 (7:5 Md. R. 472)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1982-04-26">Regulations .05 and .06C amended effective April 26, 1982 (9:8 Md. R. 820)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-03-28"><cite path="|07|03|10|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective March 28, 1983 (10:6 Md. R. 554)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-01">Chapter repealed effective May 1, 1984 (11:8 Md. R. 713)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-04-22" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|07|03|10|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|07|03|10|.11">.11</cite> adopted effective April 22, 1985 (12:8 Md. R. 801)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|07|03|10|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 908)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|07|03|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 908)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-05-06"><cite path="|07|03|10|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 1, 1996 (23:4 Md. R. 267); amended permanently effective May 6, 1996 (23:9 Md. R. 669)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|07|03|10|.07|D.">Regulation .07D</cite> amended effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 908)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|07|03|10|.09|C.">Regulation .09C</cite> and J amended effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 908)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|07|03|10|.10|F.">Regulation .10F</cite> amended effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 908)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-05-06"><cite path="|07|03|10|.10|G.">Regulation .10G</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 1, 1996 (23:4 Md. R. 267); amended permanently effective May 6, 1996 (23:9 Md. R. 669)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1996-05-06"><cite path="|07|03|10|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 1, 1996 (23:4 Md. R. 267); amended permanently effective May 6, 1996 (23:9 Md. R. 669)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-22"><cite path="|07|03|10|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1339)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-01-02"><cite path="|07|03|10|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective January 2, 1995 (21:26 Md. R. 2184)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|07|03|10|.11|C.">Regulation .11C</cite> and G amended effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 908)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1396); May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08"><cite path="|07|03|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-06"><cite path="|07|03|10|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, B amended effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1396)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08"><cite path="|07|03|10|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-12"><cite path="|07|03|10|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 520)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-06"><cite path="|07|03|10|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1396)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08"><cite path="|07|03|10|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
