<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>24</num>
  <heading>Citizenship Promotion Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The Citizenship Promotion Program provides funding to nonprofit organizations or accredited educational institutions for naturalization-related programs and activities for eligible legal permanent residents seeking to become United States citizens. The Maryland Office for New Americans (MONA) in the Family Investment Administration administers the funding.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Citizenship services provider" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A nonprofit organization that provides immigration services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An accredited educational institution that provides instruction in English as a second language, or civics, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Grantee" means a citizenship services provider who is a recipient of a Citizenship Promotion Program grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Legal permanent resident" means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has established legal residence in the United States (U.S.); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is legally eligible to apply to become a naturalized U.S. citizen.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Office" means the Maryland Office of New Americans (MONA) of the Family Investment Administration in the Department of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the Citizenship Promotion Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Programs and Activities Funded.</heading>
    <text>The Office shall allocate Program funds through grants for the following activities:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Outreach and community organizing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Citizenship application assistance;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Immigration counseling;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Instruction in English as a second language;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Civics and U.S. history classes; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Support services such as child care and transportation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Grant Application Procedures.</heading>
    <text>The Office shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prepare and distribute not later than 30 days before proposals are due an annual request for proposals (RFP) to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Community-based organizations and agencies that provide immigration-related services to the foreign-born,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ethnic organizations, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Educational institutions;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inform the following of the availability of the RFP:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ethnic media outlets,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Governor's Office of Asian Pacific American Affairs,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Governor's Commission on Hispanic Affairs,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Governor's Commission on Migratory and Seasonal Farm Labor, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Local government agencies in jurisdictions with a significant immigrant presence;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Convene an evaluation committee, consisting of at least three members who have knowledge of the naturalization process or immigrant populations, or both;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hold a prebid conference to familiarize potential grant applicants with the requirements of the RFP;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reserve the right to make site visits to potential grantees before deciding on the final awards;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Provide written notice of its award decisions to all grant applicants; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Inform grantees of the amounts of their program awards and the names of the other grantees.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Selection of Grantees.</heading>
    <text>In allocating grant funds to applicants, the Office shall consider:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant's status as either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nonprofit agency, as defined by 26 U.S.C. §501(c)(3); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An educational institution accredited or approved by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland Department of Education,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland Higher Education Commission, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Accrediting Council for Continuing Education and Training;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant's demonstrated expertise in immigration law;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The applicant's demonstrated effectiveness in providing outreach or educational activities to immigrants;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Whether the applicant's capacity and internal controls are adequate to meet grant requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The number of immigrants who reside in the applicant's jurisdiction of residence; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The applicant's stated measurable objectives.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Grantees' Fiscal Records.</heading>
    <text>Grantees shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maintain financial records according to generally accepted standards of accounting;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Retain documentation of all income and expenditures related to the grant for 3 years from the date of receipt of the grant; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon 7 days notice, present all books, records, and documents relating to the grant for inspection by State auditors or others authorized to monitor the performance of the Program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="07|03|24|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Grant Management Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The grantee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide one or more of the citizenship promotion activities specified in <cite path="|07|03|24|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Keep records on Program participants that include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Photocopies of both sides of the participant's Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) Alien Registration Receipt Form (1-55 or "green card"), and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The participant's address and telephone number at the time of completion of Program participation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit quarterly a narrative report to the Office that accurately reflects the accomplishment of the measurable objectives stipulated in the applicant's proposal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit a final narrative report which includes the information specified in <cite path="07|03|24|.07|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Office shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reserve the right to require the grantee to lower a fee to a level the Office considers to be reasonable; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Serve as a clearinghouse for citizenship service providers for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information on naturalization and citizenship, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Timely information on revisions of INS regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Office may monitor grantee performance by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review of statistical and narrative reports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Site visits; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Both §C(1) and (2) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|6-706">Human Services Article, §6-706, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-26">Effective date: June 26, 2000 (27:12 Md. R. 1137)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|07.06.21">COMAR 07.06.21</cite> to <cite path="|07.03.24">COMAR 07.03.24</cite>, effective June, 2009</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
