<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Administrative Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As used in the Maryland Securities Act and in this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Maryland Securities Commissioner or the designated agent of the Maryland Securities Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"CRD" means the Central Registration Depository System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Securities in the Office of the Attorney General.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Business Opportunities Sales Act" and "Business Opportunities Act" mean <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law" and "Maryland Franchise Law" mean <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Securities Act" means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"NASAA" means the North American Securities Administrators Association, Inc.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"NASD" means the National Association of Securities Dealers, Inc.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"SEC" means the Securities and Exchange Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Self-regulatory organization" or "SRO" means a national securities or commodities exchange, or an association or clearing agency that is registered with the Securities and Exchange Commission or the Commodity Futures Trading Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Administrative Files.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Public Inspection. Except for materials accorded confidential treatment under <cite path="02|02|01|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, all registration statements, applications for registration, and reports filed with the Division are available for public inspection during regular business hours at the offices of the Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Confidential Materials. The following materials contained in the registration files of the Division are not available for public inspection:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Materials containing trade secrets or other confidential information if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, do not require disclosure of the trade secrets or confidential information, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Commissioner finds that disclosure of the trade secrets or confidential information is not necessary for the protection of investors;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Financial statements of broker-dealers that are required by <cite path="|02.02.02">COMAR 02.02.02</cite> and that are accorded confidential treatment under 17 CFR §240.17a-5(d) (SEC Rule 17a-5(d), Annual Filing of Audited Financial Statements), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Requests for Confidential Treatment. A registrant who desires confidential treatment under <cite path="02|02|01|.02|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall submit a request for confidential treatment in a letter which shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State the basis for the request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include a copy of the document for which confidential treatment is sought.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Petition for Adoption of Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Petition. An interested person may petition the Commissioner to adopt, amend, or repeal a regulation within the Commissioner's authority under the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland Securities Act;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maryland Business Opportunities Sales Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Petition. The petition shall be submitted in writing and may be in the form of a letter addressed to the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Content of Petition. The petition shall state, clearly and concisely, the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Language of the proposed regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reasons why the petitioner believes the Commissioner should adopt the proposed regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Nature of the petitioner's interest in the proposed regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Authority of the Commissioner to take the action requested by the petitioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Disposition. The Commissioner shall consider the petition and shall notify the petitioner within 60 days of the Commissioner's disposition of the petition.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Fines and Civil Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation applies to fines and civil penalties imposed under the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-417">11-417</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-701">11-701</cite>.1(b)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Amount of Fine or Civil Penalty. For the purpose of determining the amount of a fine or civil penalty to be imposed for a violation of any provision of the Maryland Securities Act, or any regulation or order under the Maryland Securities Act, the Commissioner shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The circumstances, nature, frequency, seriousness, magnitude, persistence, and willfulness of the conduct constituting the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The scope of the violation, including the number of persons in and out of Maryland affected by the conduct constituting the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The level of restitution or compensation the violator has made;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Past and concurrent conduct of the violator that has given rise to any sanction or judgment imposed by, or plea of guilty or nolo contendere or settlement with, the Commissioner or a state securities administrator, a court of competent jurisdiction, the SEC, any other federal or state agency, or a self-regulatory organization; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other factor the Commissioner finds appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of investors and within the purposes fairly intended by the policy and provisions of the Maryland Securities Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Interpretive Opinions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Filing of Request. A request for an interpretive opinion or a no action position under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-206">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-206(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be filed with the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Request. A request for an interpretive opinion or a no action position shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An original and one copy of the letter requesting the interpretive opinion or no action position; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two copies of any supporting documentation or materials.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Content of Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request shall state the names of any issuer, individual, or entity involved. Requests concerning unnamed issuers, individuals, or entities, or hypothetical situations, are not acceptable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request shall indicate in a prominent manner the specific subsections of the statute or regulation to which the request pertains.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A request shall be limited to a particular fact situation and shall contain a legal analysis indicating why the requesting party believes that it is appropriate, given the language, meaning, and intent of the pertinent statutes and regulations, and the interests of investor protection, that the Commissioner should take a particular position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A request shall contain the name of the individual to be contacted by the Division if additional information is required. The designated individual shall be fully versed in the facts and legal analysis underlying the request for the interpretive opinion or no action position.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Request for Confidential Treatment. If a person requesting an interpretive opinion or no action position seeks to keep all or part of the request confidential, the person shall submit, together with the request for an interpretive opinion or no action position, a separate letter that states why the person believes that confidential treatment is appropriate or necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Payment of Fee. A request for an interpretive opinion or a no action position shall be accompanied by the fee set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-206">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-206(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The filing fee is nonrefundable.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Consent to Service of Process.</heading>
    <text>A person required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-802">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-802, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to appoint the Commissioner as agent for service of process shall file a Form U-2 (Uniform Consent to Service of Process) with the Commissioner.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Payment of Fees and Fines.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Payee. Checks for fees required by the Maryland Securities Act, the Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law, or the Maryland Business Opportunities Sales Act, or for fines or civil penalties imposed by the Commissioner, shall be made payable to "Office of the Attorney General".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Overpayment of Fees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Division discovers an overpayment in an amount of $35 or greater in a fee paid directly to the Division, the Division shall notify the person submitting the fee that the person may be entitled to a refund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refund Request.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person that wishes to obtain a refund of an overpayment shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Advise the Division that the person wishes to receive a refund; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide the Division with the person's federal tax identification number.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A request for a refund of an overpayment shall be made within 90 days after the overpayment or the mailing of any notice given by the Division.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Processing Refund Request. The Division shall forward a request for a refund and the person's tax identification number to the Fiscal Division of the Office of the Attorney General for processing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Application of Overpayment to Fees for Subsequent Years. An overpayment of a fee may not be applied to fees due for subsequent years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Place of Filing.</heading>
    <text>A registration application, pleading, correspondence, or other document required to be filed with or served upon the Commissioner shall be addressed to the Securities Commissioner, Office of the Attorney General, 200 St. Paul Place, Baltimore, Maryland 21202-2020.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Senior or Retiree Designations and Credentials.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>It shall constitute a violation of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-305">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and a dishonest or unethical business practice under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">11-302</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|3">3</cite>) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-412">11-412</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|7">7</cite>), Annotated Code of Maryland, to use, in a way that misleads or would mislead any person, a senior-specific certification or designation that indicates or implies that the user has special certification or training in advising or servicing senior citizens or retirees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The prohibited use of a certification or professional designation includes, but is not limited to, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use of a certification or professional designation by a person who has not actually earned or is ineligible to use the certification or designation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use of a nonexistent or self-conferred certification or professional designation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Use of a certification or professional designation that indicates or implies a level of occupational qualifications obtained through education, training, or experience that the user does not have; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use of a certification or professional designation that was obtained from a designating or certifying organization that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is primarily engaged in the business of instruction in sales, marketing, or sales and marketing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not have reasonable standards or procedures for assuring the competency of its designees or certificants;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Does not have reasonable standards or procedures for monitoring and disciplining its designees or certificants for improper or unethical conduct; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Does not have reasonable continuing education requirements for its designees or certificants in order to maintain the designation or certification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>There is a rebuttable presumption that a designating or certifying organization is not disqualified solely for purposes of <cite path="02|02|01|.09|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite> if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The organization has been accredited by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The American National Standards Institute; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The National Commission for Certifying Agencies; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The organization is on the United States Department of Education's list entitled "Accrediting Agencies Recognized for Title IV Purposes" and the issued designation or credential does not primarily apply to sales, marketing, or sales and marketing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The following factors shall be considered when determining whether a combination of words, or an acronym standing for a combination of words, constitutes a certification or professional designation indicating or implying that a person has special certification or training in advising or servicing senior citizens or retirees:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use, in the name of the certification or professional designation, of one or more words such as "senior", "retirement", "elder", or similar terms, combined with one or more words such as "certified", "registered", "chartered", "adviser", "specialist", "consultant", "planner", or similar terms; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Manner in which the words described in <cite path="02|02|01|.09|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> are combined.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Exceptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For purposes of this regulation, a certification or professional designation does not include a job title within an organization that is licensed or registered by a state or federal financial services regulatory agency, when that job title:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Indicates seniority or standing within the organization; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specifies an individual's area of specialization within the organization.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For purposes of this section, financial services regulatory agency includes, but is not limited to, an agency that regulates broker-dealers, investment advisers, or investment companies as defined under the Investment Company Act of 1940.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation limits the Securities Commissioner's authority to enforce existing provisions of law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">11-203</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">11-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-305">11-305</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-412">11-412</cite>; Business Regulation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-106">14-106</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-206">14-206</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1962-06-01">Effective date: June 1, 1962</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|02|02|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 16, 1990 (17:5 Md. R. 633); adopted permanently effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1340)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-13"><cite path="|02|02|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective May 13, 1991 (18:9 Md. R. 1007)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-01-17" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|01|.06">.06</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|02|02|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|01|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective January 17, 1994 (21:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|02|02|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 5, 2009 (36:22 Md. R. 1721); adopted permanently effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 175)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
