<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Broker-Dealer Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Initial Registration as Broker-Dealer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation governs applications for initial registration as a broker-dealer in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>National Association of Securities Dealers (NASD) Members. An applicant that is already a member of, or has applied for membership in, the NASD shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File with the Central Registration Depository System (CRD) the information required by Form BD (Uniform Application for Broker-Dealer Registration) and the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File with the Commissioner other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Non-NASD Members.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant that is not a member of, or has not applied for membership in, the NASD shall file with the Commissioner an application upon Form BD (Uniform Application for Broker-Dealer Registration).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A financial statement prepared in accordance with 17 CFR §240.17a-5(d) (SEC Rule 17a-5(d), Annual Filing of Audited Financial Statements), which is incorporated by reference, as of a date within 90 days of the date on which the statement is filed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the applicant is a corporation, a resolution authorizing the filing of the application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A statement or certificate showing compliance with, or exemption from, the examination requirement of <cite path="|02|02|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing. An application for initial registration as a broker-dealer is not considered filed for purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-405">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant has complied with the examination requirement of <cite path="|02|02|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The required fee and all required submissions have been received by the Commissioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the applicant is seeking membership in the NASD, the applicant is approved as a member of the NASD; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The applicant has submitted any other information the Commissioner has requested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Renewal Registration as Broker-Dealer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation governs applications for renewal registration as a broker-dealer in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>NASD Members. An applicant that is a member of the NASD shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File with the CRD the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File with the Commissioner other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Non-NASD Members.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant that is not a member of the NASD shall file with the Commissioner an application upon Form 200 (Renewal of Registration of Non-NASD Broker-Dealer).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A financial statement prepared in accordance with 17 CFR §240.17a-5(d) (SEC Rule 17a-5(d), Annual Filing of Audited Financial Statements), which is incorporated by reference;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing. An application for renewal registration as a broker-dealer is not considered filed for purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-406">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, until the required fee and all required submissions have been received by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Mandatory Registration of an Agent.</heading>
    <text>A broker-dealer registered with the Commissioner shall register at least one agent with the Commissioner.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Initial Registration as Agent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation governs applications for initial registration as a broker-dealer agent in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Agents of NASD Members. An applicant for initial registration as an agent for a broker-dealer that is a member of the NASD shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File with the CRD the information required by Form U-4 (Uniform Application for Securities Industry Registration or Transfer) and the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File with the Commissioner other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Agents of Non-NASD Members.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for initial registration as an agent for a broker-dealer that is not an NASD member shall file an application with the Commissioner upon Form U-4 (Uniform Application for Securities Industry Registration or Transfer).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement or certificate showing compliance with or exemption from the examination requirement of <cite path="|02|02|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing. An application for initial registration as an agent is not considered filed for purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-405">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant has complied with the examination requirement of <cite path="|02|02|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the applicant has applied for registration with the NASD, the applicant is approved by the NASD as a representative; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant has submitted any other information the Commissioner has requested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Renewal Registration as Agent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation governs applications for renewal registration as a broker-dealer agent in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Agents of NASD Members. An applicant for renewal registration as an agent for a broker-dealer that is a member of the NASD shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File with the CRD the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File with the Commissioner other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Agents of Non-NASD Members.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for renewal registration as an agent for a broker-dealer that is not a member of the NASD shall file an application for renewal registration with the Commissioner upon Form 200a (Application for Renewal of Agents of Non-NASD Member Broker-Dealers).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing. An application for renewal registration as an agent is not considered filed for purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-406">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, until the required fee and all required submissions have been received by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Examination Requirement for Broker-Dealers and Agents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Examination Requirement. An applicant for registration as a broker-dealer or as a broker-dealer agent in Maryland shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pass, with a score of 70 percent or better, the appropriate examination designated in <cite path="02|02|02|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> within 2 years before the date of application; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Qualify for an exemption from the examination requirement under <cite path="02|02|02|.06|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>SRO Examinations. An applicant for initial registration as a broker-dealer or broker-dealer agent shall take the appropriate examination or examinations designated and administered by a self-regulatory organization.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exemption. An applicant for registration as a broker-dealer or broker-dealer agent is exempt from the examination requirement of this regulation if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a member firm or is a registered representative with the NASD; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has been continuously engaged in the securities business for a period of at least 2 years immediately preceding the date of application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Amendment of Documents Filed by Broker-Dealers and Agents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Time of Filing. An amendment to a broker-dealer or agent filing required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be filed within 30 days of the event that gave rise to the need to amend the filing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Place of Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Broker-Dealers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>NASD Members. A broker-dealer that is a member of the NASD shall file an amendment with the CRD.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Non-NASD Members. A broker-dealer that is not a member of the NASD shall file an amendment with the Commissioner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Broker-Dealer Agents.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>NASD Registered Representatives. A broker-dealer agent who is registered with the NASD shall file an amendment with the CRD.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Others. A broker-dealer agent who is not registered with the NASD shall file an amendment with the Commissioner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|02|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Financial Requirements for Broker-Dealers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined. For purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-409">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-409, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this regulation, the terms "net capital" and "aggregate indebtedness" have the meanings stated in 17 CFR §240.15c3-1 (SEC Rule 15c3-1, Net Capital Requirements for Brokers and Dealers), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Broker-Dealers Subject to §15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934. A broker-dealer that is registered in Maryland and that is subject to §15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 shall maintain the net capital required by 17 CFR §240.15c3-1 (SEC Rule 15c3-1 Net Capital Requirements for Brokers and Dealers), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Broker-Dealers Not Subject to §15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A broker-dealer that is registered in Maryland and that is not subject to §15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintain a net capital of not less than $15,000; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not permit its aggregate indebtedness to exceed 2000 percent of its net capital.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A registered broker-dealer that deals exclusively in securities exempt under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-601">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-601(1) </cite>or (2), Annotated Code of Maryland, is exempt from the requirement of <cite path="02|02|02|.08|C.|(1)|(b)">§C(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Exemption. The Commissioner by order may exempt a registered broker-dealer from the requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|02|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Financial Reporting Requirements for Broker-Dealers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Financial Reports. A broker-dealer registered in Maryland shall file financial reports with the Commissioner as required by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>NASD Members. Unless otherwise ordered by the Commissioner, a broker-dealer that is a member of the NASD may satisfy its obligations under this regulation and the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, by filing with the NASD an annual financial statement prepared in accordance with 17 CFR §240.17a-5(d) (SEC Rule 17a-5(d), Annual Filing of Audited Financial Statements), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Non-NASD Members. A broker-dealer that is not a member of the NASD shall file with the Commissioner an annual financial statement prepared in accordance with 17 CFR §240.17a-5(d) (SEC Rule 17a-5(d), Annual Filing of Audited Financial Statements), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Filing of Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Time for Filing. A broker-dealer required to file a financial statement under <cite path="02|02|02|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall file the financial statement within 45 days after the end of the broker-dealer's fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extensions of Time.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A broker-dealer may request an extension of time to file a financial statement. The request shall state the reason for the extension of time and shall contain an undertaking to file the statement on or before a specified date.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A request for an extension of time shall be considered granted unless the Commissioner, within 10 days after the receipt of the request, denies the request and notifies the broker-dealer of the denial.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If an extension of time for filing a financial statement is granted, the financial statement shall report the financial condition of the broker-dealer as of a date within 90 days of the date that the financial statement is filed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Book and Record-Keeping Requirements for Broker-Dealers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A broker-dealer registered or required to be registered in Maryland shall make and keep books and records as set forth in 17 CFR §240.17a-3 (SEC Rule 17a-3, Records to be Made by Certain Exchange Members, Brokers and Dealers), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A broker-dealer registered or required to be registered in Maryland shall preserve all records required to be made under this regulation as set forth in 17 CFR §240.17a-4 (SEC Rule 17a-4, Records to be Preserved by Certain Exchange Members, Brokers and Dealers), which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-203, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1965-06-01">Effective date: June 1, 19652</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-01-17">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|02|.06">.06</cite> and new Regulations <cite path="|02|02|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|02|.10">.10</cite> adopted effective January 17, 1994 (21:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite>, D amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|02|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, D amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|02|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite>, C amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
