<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Registration Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Prospectus.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Regulation. This regulation prescribes the form and content of the prospectus required to be filed as part of a registration statement for registration of securities by qualification or notification, and to be used in connection with the offering of securities so registered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Registration by Qualification. A prospectus filed as part of a registration statement for registration of securities by qualification shall contain all the information required by Schedule A.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Registration by Notification. A prospectus filed as part of a registration statement for registration of securities by notification shall contain the information required by Schedule A except that the information required by §§F(4), I(2), J, K, L, Q, S(1)(c), and S(2) may be omitted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Legibility of Prospectus. The prospectus may be printed, mimeographed, or typewritten, or prepared by any similar process which will result in clear, legible copies. If printed, it shall be set in clear Roman type at least as large as 10 point modern type, with financial data or other statistical or tabular matter at least as large as 8 point. All type shall be leaded at least 2 points.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Presentation of Information in Prospectus.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The prospectus shall contain the information called for by all items of Schedule A required to be answered, except that no reference need be made to inapplicable items, and negative answers to any item may be omitted. None of the other information or documents filed as a part of the registration statement need be included in the prospectus.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless clearly indicated otherwise, information set forth in any part of the prospectus need not be duplicated elsewhere in the prospectus. When it is deemed necessary or desirable to call attention to the information in more than one part of the prospectus, this may be accomplished by appropriate cross-references. Instead of restating information in the form of notes to the financial statements, references may be made to other parts of the prospectus where the information is set forth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The information required in the prospectus need not follow the order of the items in Schedule A. All information contained in the prospectus shall be set forth under appropriate captions or headings reasonably indicative of the principal subject matter set forth under it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Every prospectus shall include in its forepart a reasonably detailed table of contents showing the subject matter of the various sections or subdivisions and the page number on which each section or subdivision begins.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Date of Prospectus.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each prospectus used after the effective date of the registration statement shall be dated approximately as of the effective date, provided, however, that a revised or amended prospectus used after it need only bear the approximate date of its issuance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each supplement to a prospectus shall be separately dated with the approximate date of its issuance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Exchange Offers. If any of the securities being registered are to be offered in exchange for securities of any other issuer, the prospectus shall also include the information which would be required by §§F—O of Schedule A if the securities of an issuer were being registered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Preliminary Prospectus. A prospectus filed as part of a registration statement is a preliminary prospectus until the registration statement has become effective. Every preliminary prospectus shall bear on the outside front cover page the following caption underscored or in red ink, "Preliminary Prospectus", and the following statement, in type as large as that generally in the body of the prospectus:</text>
      <text>"A registration statement relating to these securities has been filed with the Division of Securities of the Department of Law of Maryland, but has not yet become effective. Information contained herein is subject to completion or amendment. These securities may not be sold, nor may offers to buy be accepted prior to the time the registration statement becomes effective."</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Required Legend. Every prospectus shall bear the following legend in capital letters on the outside front cover page:</text>
      <include>
        <text>"THESE SECURITIES ARE OFFERED FOR SALE IN THE STATE OF MARYLAND PURSUANT TO REGISTRATION WITH THE DIVISION OF SECURITIES OF THE DEPARTMENT OF LAW OF MARYLAND, BUT REGISTRATION IS PERMISSIVE ONLY AND DOES NOT CONSTITUTE A FINDING THAT THIS PROSPECTUS IS TRUE, COMPLETE, AND NOT MISLEADING, NOR HAS THE DIVISION OF SECURITIES PASSED IN ANY WAY UPON THE MERITS OF, RECOMMENDED, OR GIVEN APPROVAL TO THESE SECURITIES. ANY REPRESENTATION TO THE CONTRARY IS A CRIMINAL OFFENSE."</text>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Use of Prospectus.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It is a condition of registration of securities by qualification or notification that a prospectus satisfying the requirements of this regulation shall be sent or given to each person to whom an offer is made as required by §11-502(c) or 11-504(d) of the Maryland Securities Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a prospectus is used more than 9 months after the effective date of the registration statement, the information contained in it shall be as of a date not more than 16 months before the use, so far as the information is known to the user of the prospectus or can be furnished by the user without unreasonable effort or expense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In addition to the requirements of §J(2), if a prospectus becomes misleading or inaccurate in any material respect, its use shall be discontinued, and it shall be revised or supplemented in such a way that it may not be misleading or inaccurate in any material respect. Three copies of a revised or supplemented prospectus shall be promptly filed with the Commissioner. Nothing in this paragraph shall be taken to relieve any person from the requirements of §11-502(c) or 11-504(d) of the Maryland Securities Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this chapter, the following terms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Affiliate" of, or person "affiliated" with, a specified person, is a person who directly or indirectly through one or more intermediaries, controls, or is controlled by, or is under common control with, the person specified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Control" (including the terms "controlling," "controlled by" and "under common control with") means the possession, direct or indirect, of the power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of a person, whether through the ownership of voting securities, by contract, or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Director" means any director of a corporation or any person performing similar functions with respect to any organization whether incorporated or unincorporated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Equity security" means any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stock or similar security;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Security convertible, with or without consideration, into such a security, or carrying any warrant or right to subscribe to or purchase such a security; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Such warrant or right.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Material", when used to qualify a requirement for the furnishing of information as to any subject, limits the information required to those matters as to which an average prudent investor reasonably ought to be informed before purchasing the security registered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Officer" means a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer or principal financial officer, comptroller or principal accounting officer, and any other person performing similar functions with respect to any organization, whether incorporated or unincorporated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Predecessor" means a person, the major portion of the business and assets of which another person acquired in a single succession, or in a series of related successions, in each of which the acquiring person acquired the major portion of the business and assets of the acquired person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Promoter" includes any person who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Acting alone or in conjunction with one or more other persons, directly or indirectly takes initiative in founding and organizing the business or enterprise of an issuer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In connection with the founding and organizing of the business or enterprise of an issuer, directly or indirectly receives in consideration of services or property, or both services and property, 10 percent or more of any class of securities of the issuer or 10 percent or more of the proceeds from the sale of any class of securities. However, a person who receives the securities or proceeds either solely as underwriting commissions or solely in consideration of property may not be deemed a promoter within the meaning of this subsection if the person does not otherwise take part in founding and organizing the enterprise.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Significant subsidiary" means a subsidiary meeting any one of the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The assets of the subsidiary, or the investments in and advances to the subsidiary by its parent and the parent's other subsidiaries, if any, exceed 15 percent of the assets of the parent and its subsidiaries on a consolidated basis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The sales and operating revenues of the subsidiary exceed 15 percent of the sales and operating revenues of its parent and the parent's subsidiaries on a consolidated basis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The subsidiary is a parent of one or more subsidiaries and, together with the subsidiaries would, if considered in the aggregate, constitute a significant subsidiary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Subsidiary" of a specified person is an affiliate controlled by that person directly, or indirectly through one or more intermediaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Succession" means the direct acquisition of the assets comprising a going business, whether by merger, consolidation, purchase, or other direct transfer. The term does not include the acquisition of control of a business, unless followed by the direct acquisition of its assets. The terms "succeed" and "successor" have meanings correlative to the foregoing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Additional Information. In addition to the information expressly required to be included in a prospectus or a registration statement by this regulation, or both, there shall be added such further information, if any, as may be necessary in order to make the statements made in a prospectus or a registration statement, or both, in the light of the circumstances under which they are made, not misleading.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Guidelines. Registrants should consult releases issued by the Division of Securities from time to time respecting guidelines as to compliance with the procedural, form and contents requirements for a registration statement and a prospectus set forth in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <include>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Schedule A</strong>
      </text>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Information Required in Prospectus</strong>
      </text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Distribution Spread.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The information called for by the following table shall be given, in substantially the tabular form indicated, on the outside front cover page of the prospectus as to all securities being offered which are to be offered for cash (estimate, if necessary).</text>
          <text>
            <table class="layout-table">
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Price<br/>to<br/>Public</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Underwriting<br/>discounts and<br/>commissions</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Proceeds to<br/>issuer or<br/>other persons</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Per Unit</td>
                  <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">................................................................................</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Total</td>
                  <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">................................................................................</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any variation from the price set forth in the first column of the table at which any proportion of the offering is to be made to any person or class of persons other than the underwriters shall be disclosed following the table with a reference to it in the first column of the table. Specify the person or class and the proposed offering price to that person or class.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>"Commissions" means all cash commissions or discounts paid or to be paid, directly or indirectly, by the issuer or selling security holders to the underwriters in respect of the sale of the security to be offered. A commission paid or to be paid in connection with the sale of a security by a person in which the issuer has an interest or which is controlled or directed by, or under common control with, the issuer shall be deemed to have been paid by the issuer. Only commissions paid by the issuer or selling security holders are to be included in the table. Commissions paid by other persons shall be set forth following the table with a reference to it in the second column of the table.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>If securities, contracts, or anything else of value (other than cash) is to accrue to the underwriters in connection with the offering, the amount and nature of the considerations shall be set forth following the table with a reference to it in the second column of the table.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>If any finder's fees are to be paid in connection with the offering, the name and address of each recipient of it, together with the amount and nature of the fee, shall be set forth following the table with a reference to it in the second column of the table.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>If the underwriting discounts or commission are variable, set forth their maximum and minimum amounts in the second column of the table and set forth the maximum and minimum proceeds in the third column of the table. The basis of determining the discounts and commissions shall be set forth following the table with a reference to it in the second and third columns of the table.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>An estimate of the aggregate selling expenses (other than underwriting discounts and commissions and finder's fees) payable by the issuer or selling security holders shall be set forth following the table with a reference to it in the third column of the table. The estimate shall include printing, legal, engineering, accounting, and other charges.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>If it is impracticable to state the price to the public, the method by which it is to be determined shall be explained. In addition, if the securities are to be offered at the market, indicate the market involved and the market price as of the latest practicable date.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>If any of the securities being registered are to be offered for the account of security holders, refer on the outside front cover page of the prospectus to the information called for by §H.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Plan of Distribution.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>If the securities being registered are to be offered through underwriters, give the names and addresses of the underwriters, their relationship, if any, to the issuer and state briefly the nature of the underwriters' obligation to take the securities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instruction. All that is required as to the nature of the under writers' obligation is whether it is a "firm commitment" under which the underwriters must take and pay for all of the securities, if any are taken, or whether it is merely an agency or "best efforts" arrangement under which the underwriters are required to take and pay for only such securities as they may sell to the public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Outline briefly the plan of distribution of any securities being registered which are to be offered otherwise than through an underwriter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Use of Proceeds to Issuer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>State the principal purposes for which the net proceeds to the issuer from the offering are intended to be used, and the approximate amount intended to be used for each purpose.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Details of proposed expenditures are not to be given; for example, there need be furnished only a brief outline of any program of construction or addition of equipment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Include a statement as to the use of the actual proceeds if they are not sufficient to accomplish the purposes set forth and the order of priority in which they will be applied.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>If any material amounts of other funds are to be used in conjunction with the proceeds, state the amounts and sources of the other funds.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>If any material amount of the proceeds is to be used to acquire assets, otherwise than in the ordinary course of business, briefly describe the assets and give the names of the persons from whom they are to be acquired. State the purchase price of the assets, the names of any persons who have received or are to receive commissions in connection with the acquisition, the amounts of the commissions and any other expense in connection with the acquisition.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Sales Otherwise than for Cash. If any of the securities being registered are to be offered otherwise than for cash, state briefly the general purposes of the distribution, the basis upon which the securities are to be offered, the amount of compensation and other expenses of distribution, and by whom they are to be borne.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Capitalization and Long-Term Debt.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Furnish the information called for by the following table, in substantially the tabular form indicated, as to each class of securities of the issuer and each class of securities, other than those owned by the issuer or its totally-held subsidiaries, of all significant subsidiaries of the issuer.</text>
          <text>
            <table class="layout-table">
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center">Title<br/>of<br/>class</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center">Amount<br/>authorized<br/>or to be<br/>authorized</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Amount<br/>outstanding<br/>as of a<br/>specified<br/>date within<br/>90 days</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Amount to be<br/>outstanding<br/>if all<br/>securities<br/>registered<br/>are sold</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Securities held by or for the account of the issuer thereof are not to be included in the amount outstanding, but the amount so held shall be stated in a note to the table.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If any of the securities were issued within the last 2 years or will be issued for a consideration other than cash at least equal to par value, disclose in appropriate footnotes to the table the amount and kind of the consideration.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Financial Statements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Furnish in comparative columnar form a profit and loss statement and analysis of surplus for each of the last 3 fiscal years of the issuer (or for the life of the issuer and its immediate predecessors, if less) preceding the date of the balance sheet furnished and for any period subsequent to the latest of the fiscal years and the date of the balance sheet.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Registration of Securities by Notification.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>If the prospectus is filed as part of a registration statement for registration of securities by notification, instead of the profit and loss statement and analysis of surplus required in §(1), above, furnish in comparative columnar form a summary of earnings for each of the 2 fiscal years preceding the date of the balance sheet and for any period between the close of the last fiscal year and the date of the balance sheet, or for the period of the issuer's and any predecessor's existence if less than 2 years.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The summary shall cover a representative period and, subject to appropriate deviation to correspond to significant characteristics of the issuer, the following items shall be included:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Net sales or operating revenues;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Cost of goods sold or operating expenses (or gross profit);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>Interest charges;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Income taxes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>Net income;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <text>Special items;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vii)</num>
              <text>Net income and special items.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The summary shall reflect the retroactive adjustment of any material items affecting the comparability of the results.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Appropriate footnotes to the summary, including references to other parts of the prospectus, shall be furnished whenever necessary to reflect information or explanations of material significance to investors in appraising the results shown.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>If common stock is being registered, the summary shall be prepared to present earnings applicable to common stock.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Earnings per share and dividends declared for each year of the summary shall also be included when appropriate.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Furnish a balance sheet of the issuer as of a date within 4 months before the filing of the registration statement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>If any part of the proceeds of the offering is to be applied to the purchase of any business, furnish with respect to that business, the financial statements required in this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Organization of Issuer. With respect to the issuer and any significant subsidiary of the issuer, state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The year in which it was organized;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Its form or organization (such as "a corporation", "an unincorporated association" or other appropriate statement);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The name of the state or other jurisdiction under the laws of which it was organized; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The address of its principal executive offices.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Selling Security Holders. With respect to each person on whose behalf any part of the offering is to be made in a non-issuer distribution, provide the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>His name and address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The amount of securities of the issuer held by him as of the date of the filing of the registration statement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A statement of his reasons for making the offering.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Description of Business.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Briefly describe the business done and intended to be done by the issuer and its significant subsidiaries, and the general development of the business during the past 5 years. If the business consists of the production or distribution of different kinds of products or the rendering of different kinds of services, indicate, insofar as practicable, the relative importance of each product or service, or class of similar products or services, which contributed 15 percent or more to the gross volume of business done during the last fiscal year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The description may not relate to the powers and objects specified in the charter, but to the actual business done and intended to be done.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>In describing developments, information shall be given as to matters such as the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>The nature and results of any bankruptcy, receivership, or similar proceedings with respect to the issuer or any of its significant subsidiaries;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>The nature and results of any other materially important reorganization, readjustments, or succession of the issuer or any of its significant subsidiaries;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>The acquisition of any material amount of assets otherwise than in the ordinary course of business;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Any materially important changes in the types of products produced or services rendered by the issuer and its significant subsidiaries; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>Any materially important changes in the mode of conducting the business, such as fundamental changes in the methods of distribution.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Indicate briefly, to the extent material, the general competitive conditions in the industry in which the issuer and its significant subsidiaries are engaged or intend to engage, and the position of the enterprise in the industry. If several products or services are involved, separate consideration should be given to the principal products or services or classes of products or services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>J.</num>
        <text>Description of Property.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>State briefly the location and general character of the principal plants, mines, and other materially important physical properties of the issuer and its significant subsidiaries. If any such property is not held in fee or is held subject to any major encumbrance, so state and briefly describe how it is held.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instruction. The description should be limited to information essential to an investor's appraisal of the securities being registered. In the case of a manufacturing enterprise, for example, the answer should be limited to such over-all statements as will reasonably inform investors as to the suitability, adequacy, and productive capacity of the facilities used in the enterprise. In the case of an extractive enterprise, appropriate information should be given as to production and reserves. Detailed descriptions of the physical characteristics of individual properties, or legal descriptions by metes and bounds, are not required and should not be given.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>K.</num>
        <text>Organization Within 3 Years. If the issuer was organized within the past 3 years otherwise than as the successor to one or more predecessors, furnish the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>State the names, addresses, and principal occupations for the past 5 years of the promoters; state the nature and amount of anything of value (including money, property, contracts, options, or rights of any kind) received or to be received by each promoter directly or indirectly from the issuer, and the nature and amount of any assets, services, or other consideration therefore received or to be received by the issuer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>As to any assets acquired or to be acquired by the issuer from a promoter, state the amount at which acquired or to be acquired and the principle followed or to be followed in determining the amount. Identify the persons making the determination and state their relationship, if any, with the issuer or any promoter. If the assets were acquired by the promoter within 2 years before their transfer to the issuer, state the cost of it to the promoter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Describe any other material interest of a promoter in any material transaction with the issuer or any significant subsidiary effected or proposed to be effected.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>L.</num>
        <text>Pending Legal Proceedings.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Briefly describe any material pending legal proceedings, other than ordinary routine litigation incidental to the business, to which the issuer or any of its subsidiaries is a party, or of which any of their property is the subject. Include the name of the court in which the proceedings are pending, the date instituted and the principal parties to it. Include similar information as to any proceedings known to be contemplated by governmental authorities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>If the business ordinarily results in actions for negligence or other claims, an action or claim need not be described unless it departs from the normal kind of actions.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Information need not be given with respect to any proceeding which involves primarily a claim for damages if the amount involved, exclusive of interest and costs, does not exceed 15 percent of the current assets of the issuer and its subsidiaries on a consolidated basis. However, if any proceeding presents in large degree the same issues as other proceedings pending or known to be contemplated, the amount involved in the other proceedings shall be included in computing the percentage.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Notwithstanding §L(2)(a) and (b), any bankruptcy, receivership, or similar proceeding with respect to the issuer or any of its significant subsidiaries shall be described. Any proceeding in which any of the following persons has an interest adverse to the issuer of its subsidiaries shall also be described:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Any director, officer, or affiliate of the issuer;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Any security holder named in answer to §R; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>Any person having a material relationship with the director, officer, or security holder.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>M.</num>
        <text>Capital Stock Being Registered.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>If capital stock is being registered, state the title of the class and furnish the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Outline briefly:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Dividend rights;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Voting rights;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>Liquidation rights;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Pre-emptive rights;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>Conversion rights;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <text>Redemption provisions;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vii)</num>
              <text>Sinking fund provisions; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(viii)</num>
              <text>Liability to further calls or to assessment by the issuer.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If the rights of holders of a stock may be modified otherwise than by a vote of a majority or more of the shares outstanding, voting as a class, so state and explain briefly.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Outline briefly any restriction on the repurchase or redemption of shares by the issuer while there is any arrearage in the payment of dividends or sinking fund installments. If there is no restriction, so state.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Only a brief summary of the pertinent provisions from an investment standpoint is required. A complete legal description of the provisions referred to is not required and should not be given. Do not set forth the provisions of the governing instruments verbatim. Only a succinct resume is required.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If the rights evidenced by the securities being registered are materially limited or qualified by the rights of any other class of securities, include the information regarding such other securities as will enable investors to understand the rights evidenced by securities being registered. Information need not be given, however, as to any class of securities, all of which will be redeemed and retired, provided appropriate steps to assure the redemption and retirement will be taken before or upon delivery by the issuer of the securities being registered.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>N.</num>
        <text>Long-Term Debt Being Registered. If long-term debt is being registered, state the title of the issue and outline any of the following provisions that are relevant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Provisions with respect to interest, maturity, conversion, redemption, amortization, sinking fund, or retirement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Provisions with respect to the kind and priority of any lien, restricting the declaration of dividends or requiring the maintenance of any ratio of assets, the creation or maintenance of reserves, or the maintenance of properties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Provisions permitting or restricting the issuance of additional securities, the incurring of additional debt, the release or substitution of assets securing the issue, the modification of the terms of the security, and similar provisions;</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>Instruction. Provisions permitting the release of assets upon the deposit of equivalent funds, property no longer required in the business, obsolete property, or property taken by eminent domain, need not be described.</aftertext>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The name of the trustee and the nature of any material relationship with the issuer or any of its affiliates, the percentage of securities of the class necessary to require the trustee to take action, and what indemnification the trustee may require before proceeding to enforce the lien.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>Instruction. The instructions to §M shall also apply to this item.</aftertext>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>O.</num>
        <text>Other Securities Being Registered. If securities other than capital stock or long-term debt are being registered, outline briefly the rights evidenced by it. If subscription warrants or rights are being registered, state the title and amount of securities called for, the period during which and the prices at which the warrants or rights are exercisable.</text>
        <text>Instruction. The instructions to §M shall also apply to this item.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>P.</num>
        <text>Directors and Officers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>List the names and addresses of all directors and officers of the issuer and all persons chosen to become directors or officers. Indicate all positions and offices with the issuer held by each person named, and the principal occupations during the past 5 years of each officer and each person chosen to become an officer. State the amount and type of securities of the issuer held by each person named as of a specified date within 30 days of the filing of the registration statement, and the amount of the securities covered by the registration statement to which he has indicated his intention to subscribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instruction. If any person chosen to become a director or officer has not consented to act as such, so state.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>Q.</num>
        <text>Remuneration of Directors and Officers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>State the amount of the aggregate remuneration which the issuer (together with all predecessors, parents, subsidiaries, and affiliates) paid to, or set aside or accrued for the benefit of all directors and officers as a group during the past 12 months and estimate the remuneration for the next 12 months.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instructions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>This item applies to any person who was a director or officer of the issuer at any time during the fiscal year. However, remuneration is not to be included for any portion of the period during which the person was not a director or officer of the issuer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>To the extent that the remuneration is to be computed upon the basis of a percentage of profits, it will suffice to state the percentage without estimating the amount of profits to be paid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>State separately the total amount set aside or accrued during the periods pursuant to all pension, retirement or other deferred compensation plans for the benefit of directors or officers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>R.</num>
        <text>Principal Holders of Equity Securities.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Furnish the following information, in substantially the tabular form indicated, as to each person who owns of record, or beneficially if known, 10 percent or more of the outstanding shares of any class of equity security of the issuer as of a specific date within 30 days before the date of filing.</text>
          <text>
            <table class="layout-table">
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">4</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center">Name and Address</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Title of<br/>Class</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Type of<br/>Ownership</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Amount <br/>Owed</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Percent<br/>of Class</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Instruction. Indicate by footnotes the amount of the securities covered by the registration statement to which any person named in the table has indicated his intention to subscribe.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>S.</num>
        <text>Interest of Management and Others in Certain Transactions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Describe briefly, and where practicable state the approximate amount of any material interest, direct or indirect, of any of the persons specified below in any material transactions during the last 3 years, or in any material proposed transactions, to which the issuer or any of its subsidiaries was or is to be a party:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any director or officer of the issuer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Any security holder named in answer to §R;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Any person on whose behalf any part of the offering is to be made in non-issuer distribution;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Any person (other than the issuer or its subsidiaries) with whom any of the foregoing persons had a material relationship.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>State the dates of, the parties to, and the general effect of every management or other material contract made or to be made otherwise than in the ordinary course of business, if it is to be performed in whole or in part at, or after, the filing of the registration statement, or was made within the past 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>T.</num>
        <text>Options to Purchase Securities. Furnish the following information as to options to purchase securities from the issuer or any of its subsidiaries, which are outstanding as of a specified date within 30 days before the date of filing, or which are to be created in connection with the offering.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Describe the options, stating the material provisions including the consideration received, or to be received, by the grantor of it and the market value of the securities called for on the granting date. If, however, the options are "restricted stock options" as defined in §421 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1954 only the following is required:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>A statement to that effect;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A brief description of the terms and conditions of the options or the plan pursuant to which they were issued; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>A statement of the provisions of the plan or options with respect to the relationship between the option price and the market price of the securities at the date when the options were granted, or with respect to the terms of any variable price option.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>State:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The title and amount of the securities called for by the options;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The purchase prices of the securities called for and the expiration dates of the options; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The market value of the securities called for by the options as of the latest practicable date.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>State the amount of the options held or to be held by each of the following persons:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any director or officer of the issuer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Any security holder named in answer to §R;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Any promoter named in answer to §K;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Any person on whose behalf any part of the offering is to be made in a non-issuer distribution;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Any underwriter or recipient of a finder's fee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Any person who holds or will hold 10 percent or more in the aggregate of the options.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Instruction. The term "options" as used in this section includes all options, warrants, and rights other than those issued to security holders as such on a pro rata basis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </include>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Acceptability of Uniform Forms in Registration by Coordination.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner will permit the use of the Uniform Application Form adopted by the North American Securities Administrators Association and the Uniform Application to Register Securities (Form U-1) adopted by the Midwest Securities Commissioners Association in connection with the registration of securities by coordination, provided, however, that no instruction, undertaking, or other matter appearing in the forms shall be deemed to modify, or in any way affect, the application of the requirements of the Maryland Securities Act and of the rules and regulations under it to the registration.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Quarterly Reports on Registered Securities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="02|02|03|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, so long as a registration statement covering securities registered by notification or qualification is effective, the person who filed the registration statement shall file quarterly reports which shall keep reasonably current the information contained in the registration statement and disclose the progress of the offering, (see form SRQ-1, which is annexed hereto), and in addition, the reports shall contain a list of persons who have purchased securities within that given monthly period. This shareholder list shall include the name, the address and the telephone number of the purchaser and the number of units, shares, or beneficial interests purchased and the date of the purchase.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When an offering of securities registered by notification or qualification has been completed, the person who filed the registration statement may be relieved of the necessity of filing further reports pursuant to <cite path="02|02|03|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> by notifying the Commissioner in writing of the fact that the offering has been completed, and by submitting a final shareholder list and status of the offering report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The quarterly reports required by <cite path="02|02|03|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be filed with the Division of Securities within 7 days from the end of each quarterly period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Securities Commissioner may, by rule or order, further modify, condition, withdraw, or waive the conditions of this regulation when he deems it in the public interest.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Financial Statements Filed As Part of Registration Statements for Registration of Securities by Qualification Notification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All financial statements required to be filed as part of registration statements for registration of securities by qualification or notification shall be certified by independent public accountants.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner will not recognize any certified public accountant or public accountant as independent who is not in fact independent. For example, an accountant will be considered not independent with respect to any person or any of its parents or subsidiaries:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In whom he has, or had during the period of report, any direct, financial interest or any material indirect financial interest; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>with whom he is, or was during the period, connected as a promoter, underwriter, voting trustee, director, officer, or employee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Escrow Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner, in his discretion, shall have the right to require an escrow fund to be established and may, by regulation or order, require as a condition of registration by qualification that the proceeds from the sale of the registered securities be impounded until the issuer receives a special amount. The Commissioner may, by regulation or order, determine the conditions of any escrow or impounding required hereunder, but he may not reject a depository solely because of location in another state.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Accordingly, in any instance where he determines impounding of the proceeds of the sale of securities to be in the public interest and necessary for the protection of investors, the Commissioner will require, as a condition of registration, that the registrant deposit a specific percentage of the proceeds from the sale of the registrant's securities in an acceptable depository, pursuant to a written agreement between the registrant issuer and the depository, to be retained in it until a specific sum has been accumulated and the terms and conditions of the agreement have been performed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Registration by Coordination of Shelf Registrations Pursuant to SEC Rule 415.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Initial Registration. Securities which are qualified to be registered on SEC Form S-3 and which are to be offered in series or offered and sold on a continuous or delayed basis pursuant to SEC Rule 415, may be registered by coordination as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial Filing. On filing a Shelf Registration Statement with the SEC pursuant to Rule 415, the registrant shall file a Form U- 1 annexing the Shelf Registration Statement containing all of the information required for coordinated registrations pursuant to §11-503 of the Maryland Securities Act with the Maryland Division of Securities (the Division), along with the requisite filing fee based on the maximum amount to be sold.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pre-effective Amendments. If an amendment to the Shelf Registration Statement is required prior to SEC effectiveness, this amendment shall be filed with the Division.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Effectiveness of Registration. The Shelf Registration Statement automatically becomes effective in Maryland at the moment the federal registration statement becomes effective if all the following conditions are satisfied:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A stop order is not in effect and a proceeding is not pending under §§11-511—11-513 of the Maryland Securities Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The registration statement has been on file with the Commissioner for at least 10 days prior to the determination of effectiveness by the SEC; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A statement of the maximum and minimum proposed offering prices and the maximum underwriting discounts and commissions applicable to the shelf registration has been on file for 2 full business days or any shorter period which the Commissioner permits by rule or otherwise, and the offering is made within those limitations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Subsequent Takedowns. Thereafter, the securities registered under §A may be offered and sold in Maryland without, except as indicated below, any prior notification to or approval by the Division so long as these offerings are effected with no material changes from the terms provided in the Shelf Registration Statement:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Further Filings. The registrant shall furnish copies of prospectus supplements or post-effective amendments, or both, relating to particular offerings of securities registered by the Shelf Registration Statement to the Division at the same time these filings are made with the SEC.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pricing-Telegrams. The furnishing of pricing-telegrams with respect to particular offerings of securities registered by the Shelf Registration Statement is not required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conclusion of Offering. The registrant shall notify the Division in writing when the offering is concluded.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|03|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Filing of Sales and Advertising Literature.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Act" means the Maryland Securities Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Securities Commissioner of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Securities of the Office of the Attorney General.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Regulation" means this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Sales and advertising literature" includes any pamphlet, circular, form letter, advertisement or printed advertising communication, films, film strips, television and radio presentations, tape and cassette recordings, and any other public lecture addressed or intended for distribution to and/or delivered to prospective investors including clients or prospective clients of an agent or broker/dealer; provided, however, that "sales and advertising literature" may not include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any prospectus used in conjunction with an offer or sale, or both, of securities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any individual letter sent to a prospective investor where the issuer has filed a registration statement with the Division relating to the offer or sale, or both, of securities to which the letter relates, provided, however, that the letter shall direct the prospective investor to the prospectus or be accompanied by a copy of the prospectus;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Tombstone advertisements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Dividend notices, proxy statements and reports to shareholders, the content of which does not pertain to a current offering or sale, or both, of securities of the issuer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Literature disseminated in connection with the distribution of securities of an investment company registered under §8 of the Investment Company Act of 1940;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Literature relating to any securities, offer or sale, or both of securities, to which is applicable one or more of the exemptions from registration contained within §§11-601—11-604 of the Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Written or printed material relating to an offer or sale, or both, of securities pursuant to a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Qualified employee stock, or stock-option plan, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Merger, consolidation, exchange offer, reclassification of securities or sale of corporate assets in consideration of the issuance of securities of another issuer;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Written or printed material which is otherwise required to be filed under the registration provisions of the Act.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All sales and advertising literature relating to an offering of securities for which a registration statement has been filed with the Division pursuant to §11-502, 11-503, or 11-504 of the Act also shall be filed with the Division and have prominently displayed by legend or printed sticker on the front cover of the sales and advertising literature, in bold-face type, substantially the following statement:</text>
      <text>"THIS SALES AND ADVERTISING LITERATURE MUST BE READ IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE PROSPECTUS IN ORDER TO UNDERSTAND FULLY ALL OF THE IMPLICATIONS AND RISKS OF THE OFFERING OF SECURITIES TO WHICH IT RELATES. A COPY OF THE PROSPECTUS MUST BE MADE AVAILABLE TO YOU IN CONNECTION WITH THIS OFFERING."</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall review the sales and advertising literature required to be filed under <cite path="02|02|03|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> and, if 7 days after the filing of the material, he has not issued a stop-order or other order with respect to it, the material may be used in connection with the offering of securities to which it relates. If a stop-order or other order is issued, then the sales and advertising literature, and the use of it, shall comply in all respects with the order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may, by regulation or order, further modify, condition, withdraw, or waive the conditions of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Renewal of Registration Statement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Effective date" means the date that a registration statement is declared effective by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Expiration/renewal date" means the date that is 1 year from the effective date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Scope of Regulation. This regulation applies to registration statements filed pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland. Regulations concerning registration of securities of investment companies may be found in Regulation .10, below.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Filing Requirements. Subject to the provisions of the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-511">11-511</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-512">11-512</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-513">11-513</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, an effective registration statement that is registered pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-502">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-502, </cite>11-503, or 11-504, may be renewed for a successive 1-year period by submitting to the Division, within the 30 days before its expiration/renewal date, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A manually signed U-1 application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The appropriate registration fee in the amount and made payable in the manner specified in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-506">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-506(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All registration or offering documents that have been amended during the registration period that have not been previously filed with the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Retroactive Effectiveness. An application for renewal may not be given effectiveness retroactive to its expiration/renewal date for any reason, including, but not limited to, the late or deficient filing of any of the documents or materials specified in §C, above.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Termination. The registrant shall provide the Commissioner with written notification of the termination of the offering in this State.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|03|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Registration of Securities of Investment Companies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Filing Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to the registration provisions of the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-502">11-502</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-504">11-504</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, a registrant that files pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall pay a $100 filing fee with the initial application for registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A registrant that renews its registration statement pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1(b), shall pay a $100 filing fee in addition to any fee that is required to be paid pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1(b)(1) or (2).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registrant that files a registration statement for an indefinite amount of securities pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1, shall promptly notify the Commissioner of the registrant's fiscal year and of any subsequent changes to its fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A registrant that pays a fee pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1(b)(2), shall file a report of sales on Form USR-1, as approved by the North American Securities Administrators Association.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A registration statement filed pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1, shall cover only one class of securities. Multiple classes of securities offered by the same issuer shall be registered separately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Renewal. A registrant that renews its registration statement pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1(b), shall file with the Commissioner a current prospectus and statement of additional information or other offering document, as applicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Termination. The registrant shall provide the Commissioner with written notification of the termination of the offering in this State. Upon termination, the registrant shall pay a final sales fee pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1(b)(1) or (2), and comply with <cite path="02|02|03|.10|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, if applicable.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|03|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Initial and Renewal Registration as Issuer Agent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For purposes of this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agent" has the same meaning as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Issuer agent" means an agent, other than a broker-dealer agent, who represents an issuer in effecting or attempting to effect the purchase or sale of securities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Initial Registration. An applicant for initial registration as an issuer agent shall file with the Commissioner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application upon Form U-4 (Uniform Application for Securities Industry Registration or Transfer);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement or certificate demonstrating that the applicant has satisfied the examination requirement of <cite path="02|02|03|.11|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Examination Requirement. An applicant for initial registration as an issuer agent shall have passed, with a score of 70 percent or better, the Series 63 examination administered by the NASD unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant effects transactions exclusively in securities exempt under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-601">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-601</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Based upon the applicant's education, experience, or duties, the Commissioner waives the examination requirement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Renewal Registration. An applicant for renewal registration as an issuer agent shall file with the Commissioner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application on the form entitled Maryland Application for Renewal of Registration as an Issuer Agent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407(a)(2)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|03|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Small Corporate Offering Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registration by Qualification. An issuer may register securities by qualification under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-504">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-504, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, by using Form U-7 (Small Corporate Offering Registration Form) if the conditions set forth in this regulation and in the instructions to Form U-7 are satisfied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Small Corporate Offering Registration Form.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application to register securities under this regulation shall be prepared in accordance with the instructions set forth in Form U-7 (Small Corporate Offering Registration Form) adopted by the North American Securities Administrators Association, Inc., on April 29, 1989, which is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A completed Form U-7 that has been declared effective by the Commissioner shall serve as the prospectus for an offering registered under this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligibility of Issuer. To be eligible to register securities under this regulation, the issuer shall satisfy the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The issuer is a corporation organized under the laws of one of the states or possessions of the United States;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The issuer engages in, or proposes to engage in, a business other than petroleum exploration or mining or other extractive industries;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The issuer is not an investment company subject to the Investment Company Act of 1940, 15 U.S.C. §§80a-1—80a-52;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The issuer is not subject to the reporting requirements of §13 or 15(d) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. §§78m, 78o(d)).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Eligibility of Offering. To be eligible for registration under this regulation, an offering shall satisfy the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The aggregate offering price does not exceed $1,000,000 in any 12-month period, less the aggregate offering price for all securities sold within 12 months before the start of and during the offering of the securities under 17 CFR §230.504 (SEC Rule 504, Exemptions for Limited Offerings and Sales of Securities Not Exceeding $500,000) in reliance on any exemption under §3(b) or in violation of §5(a) of the Securities Act of 1933 (15 U.S.C. §§77c(b), 77e(a));</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The offering is not a "blind pool" offering or other offering for which the specific business or properties cannot be described at the time of the offering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The securities are to be offered and sold only on behalf of the issuer and not on behalf of any selling security holder;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the securities are common stock, the offering price equals or exceeds $5 per share;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the securities are options, warrants, or rights for common stock, the exercise price equals or exceeds $5 per share;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the securities are convertible into common stock, the conversion price equals or exceeds $5 per share; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The offering is exempt from registration with the SEC under 17 CFR §§230.501—230.508 (SEC Regulation D, Rules Governing the Limited Offer and Sale of Securities Without Registration under the Securities Act of 1933).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Disqualifications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Bases of Disqualification. An issuer may not register an offering under this regulation if the issuer, any of its officers, directors, beneficial owners of 10 percent or more of any class of its equity securities, any promoters currently connected with it in any capacity, any selling agents of the securities to be offered, or any officer, director, or partner of the selling agent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 5 years before the filing of the application for registration under this regulation, has filed a registration statement which is currently the subject of a stop order under any state's securities law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within 5 years before the filing of the application for registration under this regulation, has been convicted of any felony or misdemeanor in connection with the offer, purchase, or sale of any security or any felony involving fraud or deceit, including, but not limited to, forgery, embezzlement, obtaining money under false pretenses, larceny, or conspiracy to defraud;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is currently subject to any state administrative enforcement order or judgment:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>That was entered within 5 years before the filing of the application for registration under this regulation, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In which fraud or deceit, including untrue statements of material facts or omissions of material facts, was found;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is subject to any state administrative enforcement order or judgment that prohibits, denies, or revokes the use of any exemption from registration in connection with the current offer, purchase, or sale of securities; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Is currently subject to any order, judgment, or decree of any court of competent jurisdiction, entered within 5 years before the filing of the application for registration under this regulation, temporarily, preliminarily, or permanently restraining or enjoining the party from engaging in or continuing any conduct or practice in connection with the purchase or sale of any security or involving the making of any false filing with a state.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Limitation of Disqualification. The disqualifications set forth in §E(1)(a)—(c) and (e) of this regulation do not apply if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Person subject to the disqualification is licensed or registered to conduct securities-related business in the state in which the disqualifying administrative order or judgment was entered or the broker-dealer employing the person is registered in Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Form BD or Form U-4 filed with the Commissioner discloses the disqualifying event.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Waiver of Disqualification. The Commissioner, by order, may waive a disqualification set forth in <cite path="02|02|03|.12|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> if the Commissioner finds that the waiver is consistent with the public interest and within the purposes fairly intended by the policy and provisions of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Undertaking Not to Split Stock.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By execution and filing of a Form U-7, the issuer undertakes not to split its common stock, or declare a stock dividend, for 2 years after the effectiveness of the registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="02|02|03|.12|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite>, an issuer may apply to the Commissioner for approval to split its common stock or declare a stock dividend in connection with a subsequent registered public offering.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Filing Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for registration under this regulation shall be filed with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application for registration under this regulation shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All forms and exhibits required by the instructions in Form U-7;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the issuer does not make the offering through a registered broker-dealer, an application for issuer agent registration prepared in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|03|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The filing fee set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-506">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-506(a)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reports Filed with the Commissioner. The issuer shall file quarterly reports that shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contain the information required by <cite path="|02|02|03|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certify that no changes or amendments were made to Form U-7 or any sales or advertising materials other than changes or amendments filed with and declared effective by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Reports to Investors. The issuer shall deliver to each investor any:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reports required by Form U-7; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other reports that the Commissioner may require.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Sales and Advertising Literature. The issuer shall file sales and advertising literature with the Commissioner as required by <cite path="|02|02|03|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-203, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1962-06-01">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|03|.05">.05</cite> effective June 1, 1962</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-15"><cite path="|02|02|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed effective April 15, 1991 (18:7 Md. R. 770)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1968-12-01"><cite path="|02|02|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> effective December 1, 1968</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1972-12-01"><cite path="|02|02|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> effective December 1, 1972; repealed effective July 1,</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">1983 (10:6 Md. R. 551)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-07"><cite path="|02|02|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective May 7, 1984 (11:9 Md. R. 795)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1974-12-01"><cite path="|02|02|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> effective December 1, 1974</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|02|02|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01"><cite path="|02|02|03|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> adopted effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 684)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|02|02|03|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1853)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01"><cite path="|02|02|03|.10|D.">Regulation .10D</cite>—F amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 684)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-09"><cite path="|02|02|03|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective May 9, 1994 (21:9 Md. R. 749)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-09"><cite path="|02|02|03|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective May 9, 1994 (21:9 Md. R. 749)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-10-20"><cite path="|02|02|03|.21">Regulation .21</cite> adopted effective October 20, 1978 (5:21 Md. R. 1585)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|02|02|03|.21">Regulation .21</cite> repealed effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1853)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
