<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Investment Adviser Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As used in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Compensation" means a form of payment or consideration, whether direct or indirect or in the form of cash or other benefits, that is paid or conveyed to or for the benefit of the investment adviser in connection with the rendering of the investment advisory services described in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Engages in the business of advising others, either directly or through publications or writings, as to the value of securities or as to the advisability of investing in, purchasing or selling securities, or who, for compensation and as a part of a regular business, issues or promulgates analyses or reports concerning securities" has the same meaning as the identical phrase found in §202(a)(11) of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 and the rules, regulations, and interpretive releases promulgated under it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Engineer" means a person who is registered and in good standing with the State Board for Professional Engineers, as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo">Business Occupations and Professions Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or its equivalent licensing and regulatory agency in a state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Insurance producer" means an insurance producer licensed by and in good standing with the Maryland Insurance Administration, as set forth in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Investment Advisers Act of 1940" means the federal act of that name, as amended, set forth in 15 U.S.C. §§80b-1—80b-21.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Investment Company Act of 1940" means the federal act of that name, as amended, set forth in 15 U.S.C. §§80a-1—80a-52.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Lawyer" means a person who is admitted to practice before the bar of any state and is in good standing with it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Securities Exchange Act of 1934" means the federal act of that name, as amended, set forth in 15 U.S.C. §§78a—78jj.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Solely incidental to the practice of his profession" has the same meaning as the identical phrase found in §202(a)(11) of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 and the rules, regulations, and interpretive releases promulgated under it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Teacher" means a person who possesses a valid license or certificate of qualification to teach in an educational institution in a state, or a person who is employed in a teaching or research capacity by a college, university, or other accredited educational institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notwithanding the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the term "investment adviser representative", as it applies to an individual who is employed by or associated with a federal covered adviser, only includes an individual who has a "place of business" in this State, as that term is defined in rules or regulations promulgated under §203A of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940, and who is either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An "investment adviser representative" as that term is defined in rules or regulations promulgated under §203A of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not a "supervised person" as that term is defined in rules or regulations promulgated under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940, and solicits, offers, or negotiates for the sale of or sells investment advisory services on behalf of a federal covered adviser.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Indirect Consideration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The antifraud provisions of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, apply to a person who receives consideration indirectly from another person for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advising the person as to the value of securities or their purchase or sale; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Acting as an investment adviser or investment adviser representative.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this regulation and the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a person receiving indirect consideration may include a person, including officers, directors, and investment adviser representatives of an investment adviser, who receives compensation from an individual or entity that renders investment advice to a client even though the person does not receive compensation directly from the client.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Dishonest or Unethical Practices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Affiliate" has the meaning stated in §2(a)(3) of the Investment Company Act of 1940.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Found" means determined or ascertained by adjudication or consent in a final court action, administrative proceeding, or SRO proceeding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Investment-related or financially related" means pertaining to investment advisory or financial planning services, counseling or consulting activities, securities, commodities, banking, insurance, real estate, or accountancy, including, but not limited to, acting as or being associated with a broker-dealer, investment company, investment adviser, government securities broker or dealer, municipal securities dealer, insurance company or agent or broker, bank, savings institution, trust company, credit union, or savings and loan association, or fiduciary, or an entity or person required to be registered under the Commodity Exchange Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Involved" means acting or aiding, abetting, causing, counseling, commanding, inducing, conspiring with, or failing reasonably to supervise another in doing an act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Management person" means a person with power to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Exercise, directly or indirectly, a controlling influence over the management or policies of an investment adviser; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine the general investment advice given to clients.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Practices. An investment adviser is a fiduciary and has a duty to act primarily for the benefit of its clients. While the extent and nature of this duty varies according to the nature of the relationship between an investment adviser and its clients and the circumstances of each case, an investment adviser may not engage in unethical business practices, including the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommending to a client to whom investment supervisory, management, or consulting services are provided the purchase, sale, or exchange of a security without reasonable grounds to believe that the recommendation is suitable for the client on the basis of information furnished by the client after reasonable inquiry concerning the client's investment objectives, financial situation and needs, and any other information known or acquired by the investment adviser after reasonable examination of the client's financial records.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Placing an order to purchase or sell a security for the account of a client without having obtained, in advance, the authority to do so.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Placing an order to purchase or sell a security for the account of a client upon instruction of a third party without first having obtained a written third-party trading authorization from the client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Exercising discretionary power in placing an order for the purchase or sale of securities for a client without obtaining written discretionary authority from the client within 10 business days after the date of the first transaction placed under oral discretionary authority, unless the discretionary power relates solely to the price at which, or the time when, an order involving a definite amount of a specified security shall be executed, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Inducing trading in a client's account that is excessive in size or frequency in view of the financial resources, objectives, and character of the account.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Borrowing money or securities from a client unless the client is a broker-dealer, an affiliate of the investment adviser, or a financial institution engaged in the business of loaning funds or securities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Loaning money to a client unless the investment adviser is a financial institution engaged in the business of loaning funds or a broker-dealer engaged in the management of margin accounts, or unless the client is an affiliate of the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Misrepresenting to an advisory client or prospective advisory client the qualifications of the investment adviser, or an investment adviser representative employed by or associated with the investment adviser or an employee of the investment adviser, or misrepresenting the nature of the advisory services being offered or fees to be charged for that service, or omitting to state a material fact necessary to make the statements made regarding qualifications, services, or fees, in light of the circumstances under which they are made, not misleading.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Providing a report or recommendation to an advisory client prepared by a person other than the investment adviser without disclosing that fact, except that this prohibition does not apply to a situation in which the investment adviser uses published research reports or statistical analyses to render advice or a situation in which an adviser orders these reports in the normal course of providing services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Charging a client an unreasonable advisory fee in light of the fees charged by other investment advisers providing essentially the same services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Failing to disclose to clients in writing before advice is rendered a material conflict of interest relating to the investment adviser or any of its affiliates or employees that could reasonably be expected to impair the rendering of unbiased and objective advice, including conflicts that may arise from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Compensation arrangements connected with advisory services to clients that are in addition to compensation from the clients for these services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Charging a client an advisory fee for rendering advice when a commission for executing securities transactions pursuant to the advice will be received by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The investment adviser;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any affiliate of the investment adviser;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any investment adviser representative employed by or associated with the investment adviser; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Any employee of the investment adviser.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Guaranteeing a client that a certain or specific result will be achieved, for example, gain or no loss, as a result of the advice that will be rendered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Publishing, circulating, or distributing an advertisement that does not comply with 17 CFR §275.206(4)-1 (SEC Rule 206(4)-1, Advertisements by Investment Advisers).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Disclosing the identity, affairs, or investments of a client to a third party without the consent of the client, unless required by law to do so.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Taking an action, directly or indirectly, with respect to those securities, instruments, or funds in which a client has a beneficial interest, when the investment adviser has custody or possession of the securities or funds when the investment adviser's action is subject to and does not comply with the safekeeping requirements of 17 CFR §275.206(4)-2 (SEC Rule 206(4)-2, Custody or Possession of Funds or Securities of Clients).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Entering into, extending, or renewing an investment advisory contract unless the contract is in writing and discloses, in substance:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The services to be provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The term of the contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The advisory fee or the formula for computing the fee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The amount of prepaid fee to be returned in the event of contract termination or nonperformance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Whether the contract grants discretionary power to the investment adviser; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>That an assignment of the contract may not be made by the investment adviser without the consent of the other party to the contract.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to Disclose.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It shall constitute a dishonest and unethical business practice within the meaning of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for an investment adviser to fail to disclose to a client or prospective client all material facts with respect to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A financial condition of the adviser that is reasonably likely to impair the ability of the investment adviser to meet contractual commitments to the client, if the investment adviser has discretionary authority, whether express or implied, or custody over the client's funds, instruments, or securities, or requires prepayment of advisory fees of more than $500 from the client at a time more than 6 months in advance of performance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal or disciplinary event that is material to an evaluation of the investment adviser's integrity or ability to meet contractual commitments to clients.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Investment advisers may disclose the information required by this section in their "brochure", the Form ADV-Part II written disclosure statement that is required to be made to clients under the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">11-302</cite>(d) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">11-411</cite>(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|02|02|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, if the delivery of the brochure satisfies the timing of disclosure requirements described in <cite path="02|02|05|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Timing of Disclosure. The information required to be disclosed by <cite path="02|02|05|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall be disclosed to clients promptly, and to prospective clients not less than 48 hours before entering into a written or oral investment advisory contract, or not later than the time of entering into a contract if the client has the right to terminate the contract without penalty within 5 business days after entering into the contract.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Material Events. There shall be a rebuttable presumption that the following legal or disciplinary events involving the investment adviser or a management person of the adviser (any of these being referred to after this as "person") that were not resolved in the person's favor or subsequently reversed, suspended, or vacated, are material within the meaning of <cite path="02|02|05|.03|C.|(1)|(b)">§C(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> for a period of 10 years from the time of the event:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A criminal or civil action in a court of competent jurisdiction in which the person was:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Convicted of, or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to, a felony or misdemeanor, or is the named subject of a pending criminal proceeding or indictment (any of these referred to after this as "action"), and the action involved an investment-related or financially related business, fraud, false statements or omissions, wrongful taking of property, bribery, forgery, counterfeiting, or extortion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Found to have been involved in a violation of an investment-related or financially related statute or regulation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The subject of an order, judgment, or decree permanently or temporarily enjoining or otherwise limiting the person from engaging in an investment-related or financially related activity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Administrative proceedings before the Commissioner, the SEC, other federal regulatory agency, or other state ("agency") in which the person was found to have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Caused an investment-related or financially related business or entity to lose its license or authorization to do business; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Been involved in a violation of an investment-related or financially related statute or regulation and was the subject of an order by the agency denying, suspending, or revoking the license or authorization of the person to act in, or barring or suspending the person's association with, an investment-related or financially related business, entity, or individual, or otherwise limiting significantly the person's investment-related or financially related activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Self-regulatory organization proceedings in which the person was found to have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Caused an investment-related or financially related business or entity to lose its license or authorization to do business; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Been involved in a violation of the SRO's rules and was the subject of an order by the SRO barring or suspending the person from membership or from association with other members, or expelling the person from membership, fining the person more than $2,500, or otherwise significantly limiting the person's investment-related or financially related activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Calculating Time Period. For purposes of calculating the 10-year period during which events are presumed to be material under <cite path="02|02|05|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, the date of a reportable event shall be the date on which the final order, judgment, or decree was entered, or the latest date on which a right of appeal from a preliminary order, judgment, or decree lapsed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Other Conduct and Obligations. The conduct set forth in §§B—F of this regulation is not inclusive. Engaging in other conduct such as nondisclosure, incomplete disclosure, or deceptive practices shall be considered an unethical business practice. Compliance with this regulation does not relieve an investment adviser from any obligations under any other disclosure requirement of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order promulgated under it, or any other state or federal law, rule, or regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Custody of Client Funds or Securities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Conditions of Custody. As provided in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, it is unlawful for an investment adviser to take or have custody of securities or funds of a client unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The investment adviser notifies the Commissioner in writing that the investment adviser has or may have custody, which notification may be given on Form ADV;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The securities of each client are segregated, marked to identify the particular client having the beneficial interest in those securities, and held in safekeeping in a place reasonably free from risk of destruction or other loss;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All client funds are deposited as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In one or more bank accounts containing only clients' funds,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The account or accounts are maintained in the name of the investment adviser as agent or trustee for the clients, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser maintains a separate record for each account showing the name and address of the bank where the account is maintained, the dates and amounts of deposits in and withdrawals from the account, and the exact amount of each client's beneficial interest in the account;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Immediately after accepting custody or possession of funds or securities from a client, the investment adviser notifies the client in writing of the place and manner in which the funds and securities will be maintained and subsequently, if or when there is a change in the place or manner in which the funds or securities are maintained, the investment adviser gives written notice to the client;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At least once every 3 months, the investment adviser sends to each client an itemized statement showing the client's funds and securities in the investment adviser's custody at the end of the period, and all debits, credits, and transactions in the client's account during that period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>At least once each calendar year, an independent certified public accountant or public accountant ("accountant") verifies all client funds and securities by an actual examination, which shall be made at a time chosen by the accountant without prior notice to the investment adviser. A report stating that the accountant has made an examination of the client funds and securities in the custody of the investment adviser, and describing the nature and extent of the examination, shall be filed with the Commissioner within 30 days after each examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exception for Certain Broker-Dealers. This regulation does not apply to an investment adviser that is also registered as a broker-dealer under §15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 if the broker-dealer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is subject to and in compliance with 17 CFR §240.15c3-1 (SEC Rule 15c3-1, Net Capital Requirements for Brokers or Dealers); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is a member of an exchange whose members are exempt from 17 CFR §240.15c3-1 (SEC Rule 15c3-1, Net Capital Requirements for Brokers or Dealers) under the provisions of paragraph (b)(2) of that rule, and the broker-dealer is in compliance with all rules and settled practices of the exchange that impose requirements with respect to financial responsibility and the segregation of funds or securities carried for the accounts of customers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Information to be Furnished to Clients ("Brochure Rule").</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise provided in this regulation, an investment adviser may fulfill the disclosure requirements of the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">11-302</cite>(d) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">11-411</cite>(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, by complying with the provisions of §204 of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 and the rules, regulations, and interpretive releases promulgated under it with respect to Form ADV. Taken together, these requirements may be known as the "brochure rule".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As provided in the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">11-302</cite>(d) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">11-411</cite>(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, the Commissioner may impose on an investment adviser, or a class or group of investment advisers, requirements relating to the disclosure of information to clients that are in addition to those set forth in <cite path="02|02|05|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>. These additional requirements may be imposed as appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of investors and clients.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall relieve an investment adviser from any obligations under any other provision of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order promulgated under it, or any other state or federal law, rule, or regulation that requires the disclosure of information to clients or prospective clients not specifically required by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Agency Cross Transactions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition. For purposes of this regulation, "agency cross transaction for an advisory client" means a transaction in which a person acts as an investment adviser in relation to a transaction in which the investment adviser, or a person controlling, controlled by, or under common control with the investment adviser, including an investment adviser representative, acts as a broker-dealer for both the client and another person on the other side of the transaction. When acting in this capacity, the person is required to be registered as a broker-dealer in this State unless excluded from the definition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conditions of Compliance. An investment adviser effecting an agency cross transaction for an advisory client shall be in compliance with the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The advisory client executes a written consent prospectively authorizing the investment adviser to effect agency cross transactions for the client;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Before obtaining written consent from the client, the investment adviser makes full written disclosure to the client that, with respect to agency cross transactions, the investment adviser will act as broker-dealer for, receive commissions from, and have a potentially conflicting division of loyalties and responsibilities regarding both parties to the transactions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At or before the completion of each agency cross transaction, the investment adviser or other person relying on this regulation sends to the client a written confirmation including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement of the nature of the transaction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date the transaction took place;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An offer to furnish, upon request, the time when the transaction took place; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The source and amount of any other remuneration the investment adviser received or will receive in connection with the transaction;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the case of a purchase, if the investment adviser was not participating in a distribution, or, in the case of a sale, if the investment adviser was not participating in a tender offer, the written confirmation may state whether the investment adviser has been receiving or will receive other remuneration and that the investment adviser will furnish the source and amount of the remuneration to the client upon the client's written request;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At least annually, and with or as a part of a written statement or summary of the client's account provided by the investment adviser, the investment adviser or another person relying on this regulation sends the client a written disclosure statement identifying:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The total number of agency cross transactions during the period for the client since the date of the last statement or summary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The total amount of all commissions or other remuneration the investment adviser received or will receive in connection with agency cross transactions for the client during the period;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Each written disclosure and confirmation required by this regulation shall include a conspicuous statement that the client may revoke the written consent required under <cite path="02|02|05|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> at any time by providing written notice of the revocation to the investment adviser; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An agency cross transaction may not be effected in which the same investment adviser recommended the transaction to both a seller and a purchaser.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Duties to Clients. Nothing in this regulation shall be construed to relieve an investment adviser or investment adviser representative from acting in the best interests of the client, including fulfilling the duty with respect to the best price and execution for the particular transaction for the client, nor shall it relieve an investment adviser or investment adviser representative of any obligations under any other disclosure requirement of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order promulgated under it, or any other state or federal law, rule or regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Exemption from the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a)(4), for Certain Broker-Dealers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Publicly distributed written materials" means written materials that are distributed to 35 or more persons who pay for those materials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Publicly made oral statements" means oral statements made simultaneously to 35 or more persons who pay for access to those statements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exemption from §11-302(a)(4). An investment adviser registered as a broker-dealer under §15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 shall be exempt from the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, in connection with a transaction in relation to which the broker-dealer acts as an investment adviser:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Solely by means of publicly distributed written materials or publicly made oral statements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Solely by means of written materials or oral statements not purporting to meet the objectives or needs of specific individuals or accounts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Solely through the issuance of statistical information containing no expressions of opinion as to the investment merits of a particular security; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Through a combination of the items or services enumerated in §B(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The exemption in <cite path="02|02|05|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall apply only if the materials and oral statements disclose that, if the purchaser of the advisory communication uses the investment adviser's services in connection with the sale or purchase of a security that is a subject of the communication, the investment adviser may act as principal for its own account or as agent for another person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Compliance by the investment adviser with the disclosure in <cite path="02|02|05|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> does not relieve it of any obligations under any other disclosure requirement of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order promulgated under it, or any other state or federal law, rule, or regulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Exemption from the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(e)(1)(i) for Performance-Based Compensation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Affiliate" has the meaning stated in §2(a)(3) of the Investment Company Act of 1940.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Client's independent agent" means a person who agrees to act as an investment advisory client's agent in connection with the contract, but does not include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser relying on this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An affiliate of the investment adviser or an affiliate of an affiliate of the investment adviser, including an investment adviser representative;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An interested person of the investment adviser;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A person who receives, directly or indirectly, compensation in connection with the contract from the investment adviser, an affiliate of the investment adviser, an affiliate of the affiliate of the investment adviser, or an interested person of the investment adviser; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A person having the benefit of a material relationship between or among himself (or an affiliate of that person) and the investment adviser (or an affiliate of the investment adviser) that exists, or has existed at any time during the past 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Company.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except for the companies listed in <cite path="02|02|05|.08|A.|(3)|(b)">§A(3)(b) of this regulation</cite>, "company" means a corporation, partnership, association, joint stock company, trust, or any organized group of persons, whether incorporated or not, or a receiver, trustee in a case under Title 11 of the United States Code, or similar official or a liquidating agent for any of the above, in his capacity as such.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unless each of the equity owners of the companies listed below, other than the investment adviser entering into the contract, is a natural person as described in <cite path="02|02|05|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> or is a company as defined in <cite path="02|02|05|.08|A.|(3)|(a)">§A(3)(a) of this regulation</cite>, "company" does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A company required to be registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 but that is not so registered;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A private investment company that, for purposes of this paragraph, means a company that would be defined as an investment company under §3(a) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 but for the exception from that definition provided by §3(c)(1) of that act;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A business development company, as defined in §202(a)(22) of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Interested person" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A member of the immediate family of a natural person who is an affiliate of the investment adviser;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person who knowingly has a direct or indirect beneficial interest in, or who is designated as trustee, executor, or guardian of a legal interest in, a security issued by the investment adviser or by a controlling person of the investment adviser if that beneficial or legal interest exceeds:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>One-tenth of 1 percent of any class of outstanding securities of the investment adviser or a controlling person of the investment adviser; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Five percent of the total assets of the person seeking to act as the client's independent agent; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person or partner or employee of a person who, at any time during the past 2 years, has acted as legal counsel for the investment adviser.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exemption from the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(e)(1)(i)</cite>. Notwithstanding the prohibitions of the Maryland Securities Act, Corporation and Associations Article, §11-302(e)(1)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland, an investment adviser may enter into, extend, or renew an investment advisory contract that provides for compensation to the investment adviser on the basis of a share of capital gains upon or capital appreciation of the funds or a portion of the funds of the client if the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The client entering into the contract is a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Natural person or a company that, immediately after entering into the contract, has at least $500,000 under the management of the investment adviser; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Person who the investment adviser and its investment adviser representatives reasonably believe, immediately before entering into the contract, is a natural person or a company whose net worth, at the time the contract is entered into, exceeds $1,000,000. The net worth of a natural person may include assets held jointly with that person's spouse.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The compensation paid to the investment adviser with respect to the performance of securities over a given period shall be based on a formula with the following characteristics:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the case of securities for which market quotations are readily available within the meaning of 17 CFR §270.2a-4(a)(1) (SEC Rule 2a-4(a)(1), Periodic Calculation of Net Asset Value of Redeemable Security), the formula shall include the realized capital losses and unrealized capital depreciation of the securities over the period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In the case of securities for which market quotations are not readily available within the meaning of  17 CFR §270.2a-4(a)(1) (SEC Rule 2a-4(a)(1), Periodic Calculation of Net Asset Value of Redeemable Security), the formula shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The realized capital losses of securities over the period; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the unrealized capital appreciation of the securities over the period is included, the unrealized capital depreciation of the securities over the period; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The formula shall provide that compensation paid to the investment adviser under this regulation is based on the gains less the losses (computed in accordance with §B(2)(a) and (b) of this regulation) in the client's account for a period of not less than 1 year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Before entering into the advisory contract and in addition to the requirements of Form ADV, the investment adviser shall disclose in writing to the client or the client's independent agent all material information concerning the proposed advisory arrangement, including the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That the fee arrangement may create an incentive for the investment adviser to make investments that involve more risk and are more speculative than would be the case in the absence of a performance-based fee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When relevant, that the investment adviser may receive increased compensation with regard to unrealized appreciation as well as realized gains in the client's account;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The time periods that will be used to measure investment performance throughout the contract and their potential significance in the computation of the fee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The nature of an index that will be used as a comparative measure of investment performance, the potential significance of the index, and the reasons the investment adviser believes that the index is appropriate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>When the investment adviser's compensation is based in part on the unrealized appreciation of securities for which market quotations are not readily available within the meaning of 17 CFR §270.2a-4(a)(1) (SEC Rule 2a-4(a)(1), Periodic Calculation of Net Asset Value of Redeemable Security), the method by which the securities will be valued and the extent to which the valuation will be independently determined.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The investment adviser, and any investment adviser representative who enters into the contract, shall reasonably believe, immediately before entering into the contract, that the contract represents an arm's-length arrangement between the parties and that the client (or in the case of a client that is a company as defined in <cite path="02|02|05|.08|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>, the person representing the company), alone or together with the client's independent agent, understands the proposed method of compensation and its risks. The representative of a company may be a partner, director, officer, or an employee of the company or the trustee when the company is a trust, or other person designated by the company or trustee, but shall satisfy the definition of client's independent agent set forth in <cite path="02|02|05|.08|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person entering into or performing an investment advisory contract under this regulation is not relieved of any obligations under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any other applicable provision of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order promulgated under it, or any other state or federal law, rule, or regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall relieve a client's independent agent from any obligation to the client under applicable law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Transactions Considered Not to be Assignments.</heading>
    <text>For purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-302(e)(1)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a transaction that does not result in a change of actual control or management of an investment adviser is not an assignment.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Electronic Filing with Designated Entity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Designation. Pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-405">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-405(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Commissioner designates the web-based Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD) operated by the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority to receive and store filings and collect related fees from investment advisers and investment adviser representatives on behalf of the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Use of the IARD. Unless otherwise provided, all investment adviser and investment adviser representative applications, amendments, reports, notices, related filings, and fees required to be filed with the Commissioner pursuant to the regulations promulgated under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be filed electronically with and transmitted to the IARD.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Electronic Filing Conditions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Electronic Signature. When a signature or signatures are required by the particular instructions of any filing to be made through the IARD, a duly authorized officer of the investment adviser or the investment adviser, as required, shall affix the individual's electronic signature to the filing by typing the individual's name in the appropriate fields and submitting the filing to the IARD. Submission of a filing in this manner shall constitute irrefutable evidence of legal signature by any individual whose name is typed on the filing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completion of Filing. Applications for initial and renewal registration as an investment adviser may not be considered filed until the required fee and all required submissions have been received by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Electronic Filing—When Not Required. Notwithstanding <cite path="02|02|05|.10|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the electronic filing of any particular document and the collection of related processing fees may not be required until the IARD provides for receipt of such filings and fees and 30 days notice is provided by the Commissioner. Any documents required to be filed with the Commissioner that are not permitted to be filed with or cannot be accepted by the IARD shall be filed in paper directly with the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Hardship Exemptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Temporary Hardship Exemption.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State who experiences unanticipated technical difficulties that prevent submission of an electronic filing to the IARD may request a temporary hardship exemption from the requirements to file electronically.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To request a temporary hardship exemption, an investment adviser shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>File Form ADV-H-State, Application for a Temporary or Continuing Hardship Exemption, in paper format with the Commissioner where the investment adviser's principal place of business is located, not later than 1 business day after the filing that is the subject of the Form ADV-H-State is due; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Submit the filing that is the subject of the Form ADV-H-State in electronic format to the IARD not later than 7 business days after the filing is due.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Effective Date Upon Filing. The temporary hardship exemption will be considered effective upon receipt by the Commissioner of the complete Form ADV-H-State. Multiple temporary hardship exemption requests within the same calendar year may be disallowed by the Commissioner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continuing Hardship Exemption.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Criteria for Exemption. A continuing hardship exemption may be granted only if the investment adviser is able to demonstrate that the electronic filing requirements of this regulation are prohibitively burdensome.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To apply for a continuing hardship exemption, an investment adviser shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>File Form ADV-H-State, Application for a Temporary or Continuing Hardship Exemption, in paper format with the Commissioner at least 20 business days before a filing is due; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If a filing is due to more than one Commissioner, file Form ADV-H-State with the Commissioner where the investment adviser's principal place of business is located.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Decision and Effective Date. The Commissioner who receives the application shall grant or deny the application within 10 business days after the filing of Form ADV-H-State. An exemption is effective upon approval by the Commissioner. The time period of the exemption may not be longer than 1 year after the date on which the Form ADV-H-State is filed. If the Commissioner approves the application, the investment adviser shall, not later than 5 business days after the exemption approval date, submit filings to the IARD in paper format along with the appropriate processing fees for the period of time for which the exemption is granted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Applications for Investment Advisers and Notice Filings for Federal Covered Advisers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application Form for Investment Adviser Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial Application. An application for initial registration as an investment adviser shall be made by completing Form ADV (Uniform Application for Investment Adviser Registration) in accordance with the form instructions and by filing the form with the IARD. The application for initial registration shall also include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Evidence of compliance by the applicant with or exemption from the examination requirements of <cite path="|02|02|05|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For those applicants subject to <cite path="|02|02|05|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>, a balance sheet prepared in accordance with the instructions to the Form ADV, and, if such balance sheet is as of a date more than 45 days from the date of filing of the application, an unaudited balance sheet prepared in accordance with the instructions to the Form ADV;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A sample copy of each investment advisory contract used by the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Renewal Application. An application for renewal registration as an investment adviser shall be made by filing with the IARD the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Updates and Amendments.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser shall file with the IARD, in accordance with the instructions in the Form ADV, any amendments to the investment adviser's Form ADV;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An amendment shall be considered to be filed promptly if the amendment is filed within 30 days of the event that requires the filing of the amendment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Within 90 days of the end of the investment adviser's fiscal year, an investment adviser shall file with the IARD an updated Form ADV.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Investment Adviser Representative Registration. Each investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State shall register at least one investment adviser representative with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Completion of Filing. An application for initial or renewal registration as an investment adviser will not be considered filed until the required fee and all required submissions have been received by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice Filing Requirements for Federal Covered Advisers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial Notice Filing. An initial notice filing for a federal covered adviser shall be made by filing with the IARD a completed Form ADV (Uniform Application for Investment Adviser Registration) and the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. An initial notice filing shall be considered filed when the fee required by Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the Form ADV are filed with and accepted by the IARD on behalf of this State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Renewal Notice Filing. A renewal notice for a federal covered adviser shall be made by filing with the IARD the fee required by Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The renewal notice filing shall be considered filed when the fee required by Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is filed with and accepted by the IARD on behalf of this State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Updates and Amendments. A federal covered adviser shall file with the IARD, in accordance with the instructions in the Form ADV, any amendments to the federal covered adviser's Form ADV.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Initial and Renewal Registration as Investment Adviser Representative.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Method of Filing. Until the IARD is capable of accepting applications to register investment adviser representatives, an application for initial or renewal registration as an investment adviser representative shall be submitted in accordance with <cite path="02|02|05|.12|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>. When the IARD is capable of accepting applications to register investment adviser representatives, an application for initial and renewal registration as an investment adviser representative shall be submitted in accordance with <cite path="02|02|05|.12|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Electronic Filings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial Application. An application for initial registration as an investment adviser representative shall be made by completing the Uniform Application for Securities Industry Registration or Transfer (Form U-4), in accordance with the form instructions and by filing the Form U-4 with the IARD. The application for initial registration also shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Evidence of compliance by the applicant with or exemption from the examination requirements of <cite path="|02|02|05|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annual Renewal. An application for renewal registration for an investment adviser representative registered in this State shall be made by filing with the IARD the fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Updates and Amendments.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser representative is under a continuing obligation to update information required by Form U-4 as changes occur.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser representative and the investment adviser shall file promptly with the IARD any amendments to the representative's Form U-4.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An amendment shall be considered to be filed promptly if the amendment is filed within 30 days of the event that requires the filing of the amendment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Paper Filings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for an individual specified in <cite path="02|02|05|.12|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, an application for initial registration as an investment adviser representative shall be filed with the Commissioner upon Form U-4 (Uniform Application for Securities Industry Registration or Transfer). The Form U-4 shall be manually executed by both the individual applicant and the investment adviser. The application also shall contain the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Evidence of compliance by the applicant with or exemption from the examination requirements of <cite path="|02|02|05|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual registered as an agent in this State for a registered broker-dealer that is also a registered investment adviser in this State or is the affiliate of the registered investment adviser shall file an application for initial registration as an investment adviser representative with the Commissioner. The application shall contain the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name and CRD number of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evidence of compliance by the applicant with or exemption from the examination requirements of <cite path="|02|02|05|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An application for renewal registration for an investment adviser representative registered in this State shall be filed by the investment adviser with the Commissioner. A renewal application will be accepted not earlier than 60 days before the December 31 expiration date and shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A list of the names and, when applicable, CRD numbers of the investment adviser representatives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Amendments of documents previously filed with the Commissioner that were not amended as required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A certification that, to the best knowledge, information, and belief of the investment adviser, there has been no change in the information contained in the investment adviser representatives' applications for registration currently in effect; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The fee required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-407">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-407, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applications for initial and renewal registration as an investment adviser representative will not be considered filed until the required fee and all required submissions have been received by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Investment Adviser Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State shall establish, maintain, and enforce written supervisory guidelines that are reasonably designed to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervise the activities of an investment adviser representative and associated person to achieve compliance with the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the regulations promulgated under it; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Achieve compliance by the investment adviser with the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the regulations promulgated under it.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State shall designate on the Form ADV one principal responsible for compliance with <cite path="02|02|05|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Examination Requirements for Investment Advisers and Investment Adviser Representatives.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Approved IAR continuing education credit" means the materials, written, oral, or otherwise, that have been approved by NASAA or its designee and that make up the educational program provided to an investment adviser representative (IAR) under this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Authorized provider" means a person that NASAA or its designee has authorized to provide continuing education content required by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Credit" means a unit that has been designated by NASAA or its designee as at least 50 minutes of educational instruction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Home state" means the state in which the investment adviser representative has its principal office and place of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"IAR ethics and professional responsibility content" means approved IAR continuing education content that addresses an investment adviser representative's ethical and regulatory obligations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"IAR products and practice content" means approved IAR continuing education content that addresses an investment adviser representative's continuing skills and knowledge regarding financial products, investment features, and practices in the investment advisory industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"NASAA" means the North American Securities Administrators Association or a committee designated by its Board of Directors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Reporting period" means one 12-month period as determined by NASAA. An investment adviser representative's initial reporting period with this State commences the first day of the first full reporting period after the individual is registered or required to be registered with this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Examination Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An investment adviser or investment adviser representative registered or required to be registered in this State shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Successfully pass the examination or examinations designated by the Commissioner;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Qualify for an exemption from the examination requirement under §D or E of this regulation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Receive a waiver of the examination requirement under <cite path="02|02|05|.14|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person who is designated a principal under <cite path="|02|02|05|.13|B.">Regulation .13B of this chapter</cite> shall fulfill the investment adviser's examination requirement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Designated principals and applicants for initial registration as investment adviser representative shall pass the following examinations administered by the FINRA:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Series 65 examination as adopted by the Commissioner on January 1, 2000; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Series 7 examination and the Series 66 examination as adopted by the Commissioner on January 1, 2000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="02|02|05|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> do not apply to a designated principal or an applicant for initial registration as an investment adviser representative, if the individual has earned a credential designated by the Commissioner including, but not limited to, the following, and at the time of application is in good standing with the organization that issued the credential:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certified Financial Planner (CFP) awarded by the Certified Financial Planner Board of Standards, Inc.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Chartered Financial Consultant (ChFC) awarded by the American College, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Personal Financial Specialist (PFS) awarded by the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Chartered Financial Analyst (CFA) awarded by the Institute of Chartered Financial Analysts; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Chartered Investment Counselor (CIC) awarded by the Investment Counsel Association of America, Inc.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Grandfathering Provisions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="02|02|05|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> do not apply to a designated principal or an applicant for initial registration as an investment adviser representative, if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual was approved by the Commissioner as the designated principal for a registered investment adviser as of January 1, 2000; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual was registered in any jurisdiction in the United States as an investment adviser representative or investment adviser as of January 1, 2000.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="02|02|05|.14|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Commissioner may require additional examinations for an individual found to have violated any state or federal law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Two-Year Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual who has not been registered in any jurisdiction for a period of 2 years shall be required to comply with the provisions of <cite path="02|02|05|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="02|02|05|.14|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Commissioner, by order or otherwise, may modify the 2-year requirement of this subsection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Based on a demonstration by an individual of relevant factors including, but not limited to, education and experience, the Commissioner shall consider an individual's request for a waiver of the examination requirements in accordance with the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-412">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-412(c)(6), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Continuing Education Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An investment adviser representative registered in this State shall complete the following continuing education requirements each reporting period:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>6 credits of IAR ethics and professional responsibility content approved by NASAA and offered by an authorized provider, with at least 3 credits covering the topic of ethics; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>6 credits of IAR products and practice content approved by NASAA and offered by an authorized provider.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An investment adviser representative who is registered as an agent of a FINRA member broker-dealer and is in compliance with FINRA's continuing education requirements is considered to be in compliance with the provisions of <cite path="02|02|05|.14|H.|(1)|(b)">§H(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> for each applicable reporting period if, as determined by NASAA:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>FINRA's continuing education content focuses on compliance, regulatory, ethical, and sales practices standards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>FINRA's continuing education content is derived from state and federal investment advisory statutes, rules and regulations, securities industry rules and regulations, and accepted standards and practices in the financial services industry; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>FINRA's continuing education content requires that its participants demonstrate proficiency in the subject matter of the educational materials.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Credentialing Organization Continuing Education Compliance. Credits of continuing education completed by an investment adviser representative who was awarded and currently holds a credential that qualifies for an examination waiver under <cite path="02|02|05|.14|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> shall satisfy the requirements of <cite path="02|02|05|.14|H.|(1)">§H(1) of this regulation</cite> provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser representative completes the credits of continuing education as a condition of maintaining the credential for the relevant reporting period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The credits of continuing education completed during the relevant reporting period by the investment adviser representative are mandatory to maintain the credential; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The continuing education content provided by the credentialing organization during the relevant reporting period is approved IAR continuing education content.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Continuing Education Reporting. An investment adviser representative registered in this State shall be responsible for ensuring that the authorized provider reports the investment adviser representative's completion of the applicable IAR continuing education requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>No Carry-Forward. An investment adviser representative who completes credits of continuing education in excess of the amount required for a reporting period may not carry forward excess credits to a subsequent reporting period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Failure to Complete or Report Continuing Education.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser representative who fails to comply with §H(1) or (4) of this regulation by the end of a reporting period shall be considered "CE inactive".</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The registration of an investment adviser representative who is "CE inactive", but otherwise qualifies for renewal, shall be renewed in this State at the end of the calendar year in which the investment adviser representative becomes "CE inactive".</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser representative shall remain "CE inactive" until the investment adviser representative completes and reports all required IAR continuing education credits for all reporting periods as required by this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser representative who is "CE inactive" at the close of the next calendar year is not eligible for investment adviser representative registration or renewal of an investment adviser representative registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may, in the Commissioner's discretion, waive any requirements of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Home State. An investment adviser representative registered or required to be registered in this State who is registered as an investment adviser representative in the individual's home state is considered to be in compliance with <cite path="02|02|05|.14|H.">§H of this regulation</cite> provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser representative's home state has continuing education requirements that are at least as stringent as <cite path="02|02|05|.14|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser representative is in compliance with the home state's investment adviser representative continuing education requirements.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Unregistered Periods. An individual applying for investment adviser representative registration who was previously registered as an investment adviser representative in this State must complete IAR continuing education for all reporting periods that occurred during the period the individual was not registered in this State as an investment adviser representative unless the individual takes and passes the examination required under <cite path="02|02|05|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> or receives an examination waiver under <cite path="02|02|05|.14|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Financial Requirements for Certain Investment Advisers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Net assets" means the excess of assets over liabilities, as determined by generally accepted accounting principles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Net capital" has the meaning stated in 17 CFR §240.15c3-1 (SEC Rule 15c3-1, Net Capital Requirements for Brokers and Dealers).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Tangible net assets" means the net assets of an investment adviser registered or required to be registered reduced by the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prepaid expenses, except as to items properly classified as current assets under generally accepted accounting principles;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deferred charges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Goodwill, franchise rights, organizational expenses, patents, copyrights, marketing rights, unamortized debt discount and expense, and all other assets of intangible nature; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Homes, furnishings, and automobiles and personal items not readily marketable, in the case of an individual, or advances or loans to stockholders and officers, in the case of a corporation, or advances or loans to partners, in the case of a partnership.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State that has custody of client funds, assets, or securities, or requires payment of advisory fees more than 6 months in advance and in excess of $500 per client, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain at all times a minimum net capital of $20,000, or minimum tangible net assets of $35,000; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be bonded in the amount of $10,000 by a bonding company qualified to do business in this State, or deposit cash or any other equivalent form of security as the Commissioner may permit in the amount of $10,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State shall notify the Commissioner by the close of business on the next business day if the investment adviser's total net capital or tangible net assets falls below the minimum required net capital or minimum required tangible net assets as required by <cite path="02|02|05|.15|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>. After transmitting the notice, the investment adviser shall, by the close of business on the following business day, file with the Commissioner a report of its financial condition, including the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A trial balance of all ledger accounts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A computation of net capital or tangible net assets as defined in <cite path="02|02|05|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A statement of all client funds, securities, or assets that are not segregated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A computation of the aggregate amount of client ledger debit balances; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A statement of the number of client accounts.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For an investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State that maintains a minimum tangible net assets requirement as required by <cite path="02|02|05|.15|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>, rather than the minimum net capital requirement, submission to the Commissioner of a current appraisal may be required in order to establish the worth of an asset being calculated under the tangible net asset formulation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Record-Keeping Requirements for Investment Advisers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An investment adviser registered or required to be registered in this State shall maintain and preserve the following books, ledgers, and records:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A journal or journals, including cash receipts and disbursements records, and any other records of original entry forming the basis of entries in any ledger.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>General and auxiliary ledgers (or other comparable records) reflecting asset, liability, reserve, capital, income, and expense accounts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A memorandum of each order given by the investment adviser for the purchase or sale of a security or asset, of an instruction received by the investment adviser from the client concerning the purchase, sale, receipt, or delivery of a particular security or asset, and of a modification or cancellation of an order or instruction. These memoranda shall show the terms and conditions of the order, instruction, modification, or cancellation, shall identify the person connected with the investment adviser who recommended the transaction to the client and the person who placed the order, and shall show the account for which entered, the date of entry, whether the order was entered pursuant to the exercise of discretionary power and, when appropriate, the bank, broker-dealer, or other entity or person by or through which the transaction was effected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All check books, bank statements, cancelled checks, and cash reconciliations of the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All bills or statements, or copies thereof, paid or unpaid, relating to the business of the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>All trial balances, financial statements, and internal audit working papers relating to the business of the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Originals of all written communications received, and copies of all written communications sent, by the investment adviser relating to a recommendation made or proposed to be made and advice given or proposed to be given, a receipt, disbursement, or delivery of funds, securities, or assets, or the placing or execution of an order to purchase or sell a security or asset, except that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The investment adviser is not required to keep any unsolicited market letters and other similar communications of general public distribution not prepared by or for the investment adviser; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the investment adviser sends a notice, circular, or other advertisement offering a report, analysis, publication, or other investment advisory service to more than 10 persons, the investment adviser is not required to keep a record of the names and addresses of the persons to whom it was sent, except that if the notice, circular, or advertisement is distributed to persons named on a list, the investment adviser shall retain with a copy of the notice, circular, or advertisement a memorandum describing the list and its source.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A list or other record of all accounts in which the investment adviser is vested with discretionary power with respect to the funds, securities, assets, or transactions of a client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Copies of originals of all powers of attorney and other evidences of the granting of discretionary authority by a client to the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>All written agreements, or copies, entered into by the investment adviser with a client or otherwise relating to the business of the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>A copy of each notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin, or other communication that the investment adviser circulates or distributes, directly or indirectly, to 10 or more persons, other than persons connected with the investment adviser, and, if the notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin, or other communication recommends the purchase or sale of a specific security or asset, and does not state the reasons for this recommendation, a memorandum of the investment adviser indicating the reasons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Records of Securities or Asset Transactions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A record of every transaction involving either an asset about which advice is given or a security, in which the investment adviser or any of those persons described in §A(12)(b) and (c) of this regulation has, or by reason of the transaction acquires, any direct or indirect beneficial ownership, except transactions effected over which neither the investment adviser nor any of those persons described in §A(12)(b) and (c) of this regulation has any direct or indirect influence or control, and transactions in securities that are direct obligations of the United States.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Records of transactions shall include the transactions of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A partner, officer, or director of the investment adviser;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An employee who makes any recommendation, who participates in the determination of which recommendation shall be made, or whose functions or duties relate to the determination of which recommendation shall be made;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An employee who, in connection with the employee's duties, obtains  information concerning which securities are being recommended before the effective dissemination of the recommendations or of the information concerning the recommendations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Any of the following persons who obtain information concerning securities recommendations being made by the investment adviser before the effective dissemination of the recommendations or of the information concerning the recommendations: a person in a control relationship to the investment adviser, an affiliated person of the controlling person, and an affiliated person of the affiliated person.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Control" has the same meaning as set forth in §2(a)(9) of the Investment Company Act of 1940, as amended.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The record shall state the title and amount of the security or asset involved, the date and nature of the transaction (that is, purchase, sale, or other acquisition or disposition), the price at which it was effected, and the name of the broker-dealer, bank, or other entity or person with or through which the transaction was effected.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A transaction shall be recorded not later than 10 days after the end of the calendar quarter in which the transaction was effected.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The record also may contain a statement declaring that the reporting or recording of the transaction will not be construed as an admission that the investment adviser or investment adviser representative has any direct or indirect beneficial ownership in the security or asset.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser will not be considered to have violated the provisions of this subsection by the investment adviser's failure to record securities or asset transactions of any of those persons described in §A(12)(b) and (c) of this regulation if the investment adviser establishes that it instituted adequate procedures and used reasonable diligence to obtain promptly reports of all transactions required to be recorded.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Records of Transactions in Securities or Assets Involving Direct or Indirect Beneficial Ownership.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding the provisions of <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.|(12)">§A(12) of this regulation</cite>, when the investment adviser is primarily engaged in a business other than advising registered investment companies or other advisory clients, a record shall be maintained of every transaction involving either an asset about which advice is given or a security, in which the investment adviser or any of those persons described in §A(13)(b) and (c) of this regulation has, or by reason of the transaction acquires, any direct or indirect beneficial ownership, except transactions effected in any account over which neither the investment adviser  nor any of those persons described in §A(13)(b) and (c) of this regulation has any direct or indirect influence or control, and transactions in securities that are direct obligations of the United States.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Records of transactions shall include the transactions of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A partner, officer, director, or employee of the investment adviser who makes a recommendation, who participates in the determination of which recommendation shall be made, or whose functions or duties relate to the determination of which recommendation shall be made, or who, in connection with his duties, obtains information concerning which securities are being recommended before the effective dissemination of the recommendations or of the information concerning the recommendations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any of the following persons who obtain information concerning securities recommendations being made by the investment adviser before the effective dissemination of the recommendations or of the information concerning the recommendations: a person in a control relationship to the investment adviser, an affiliated person of the controlling person, and an affiliated person of the affiliated person.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Control" has the same meaning as set forth in §2(a)(9) of the Investment Company Act of 1940, as amended.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The record shall state the title and amount of the security or asset involved, the date and nature of the transaction (that is, purchase, sale, or other acquisition or disposition), the price at which it was effected, and the name of the broker-dealer, bank, or other entity or person with or through which the transaction was effected.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A transaction shall be recorded not later than 10 days after the end of the calendar quarter in which the transaction was effected.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The record may also contain a statement declaring that the reporting or recording of the transaction will not be construed as an admission that the investment adviser or investment adviser representative has any direct or indirect beneficial ownership in the security or asset.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser is "primarily engaged in a business or businesses other than advising registered investment companies or other advisory clients" if, for each of its three most recent fiscal years or for the period of time since organization, whichever is less, the investment adviser derived from the other business or businesses, on an unconsolidated basis, more than 50 percent of both its total sales and revenues and its income (or loss) before income taxes and extraordinary items.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>An investment adviser will not be considered to have violated the provisions of this subsection by its failure to record securities or asset transactions of any of those persons described in §A(13)(b) and (c) of this regulation if the investment adviser establishes that it instituted adequate procedures and used reasonable diligence to obtain promptly reports of all transactions required to be recorded.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>A copy of each written statement, and each amendment or revision of each written statement, given or sent to a client or prospective client of the investment adviser in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="|02|02|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, and a record of the dates that each written statement, and each amendment or revision of each written statement, was given, or offered to be given, to a client or prospective client who subsequently became a client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>All accounts, books, internal working papers, and other records or documents that are necessary to form the basis for or demonstrate the calculation of the performance or rate of return of all managed accounts or securities or assets recommendations in any notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin, or other communication that the investment adviser circulates or distributes, directly or indirectly, to 10 or more persons, other than persons connected with the investment adviser. With respect to the performance of managed accounts, the retention of all account statements, if they reflect all debits, credits, and other transactions in a client's account for the period of the statement, and all worksheets necessary to demonstrate the calculation of the performance or rate of return of all managed accounts, shall be considered to satisfy the requirements of this subsection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an investment adviser subject to <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> has custody or possession of securities, assets, or funds of a client, the records required to be made and kept under <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A journal or other record showing all purchases, sales, receipts, and deliveries of securities (including certificate numbers) and other assets (including identifying or descriptive materials as appropriate) for these accounts, as well as all other debits and credits to the accounts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A separate ledger account for each client showing all purchases, sales, receipts, and deliveries of securities or assets, the date and price of each purchase and sale, and all debits and credits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Copies of confirmations of all transactions effected by or for the account of each client; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A record for each security or asset in which each client has a position or ownership interest, which record shall show the name of the client having the position or interest, the amount of the position or interest, and the location of each security or asset.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An investment adviser subject to <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> that renders an investment supervisory or management service to a client shall, with respect to the portfolio being supervised or managed and to the extent that the information is reasonably available to or obtainable by the investment adviser, make and keep the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>True, accurate, and current records showing separately for each client the securities or assets purchased and sold, and the date, amount, and price of each purchase and sale; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For each security or asset in which a client has a current position, true, accurate, and current information from which the investment adviser can promptly furnish the name of each client, and the current amount or interest of the client.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Books or records required by this regulation may be maintained by the investment adviser in a manner such that the identity of a client to whom the investment adviser renders investment advisory services is indicated by numerical or alphabetical code or some similar designation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Time Period.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Books and records required to be made under the provisions of §§A—C(1), inclusive, of this regulation, except for books and records required to be made under the provisions of §A(11) and (15) of this regulation, shall be maintained and preserved in an easily accessible place for a period of not less than 5 years from the end of the fiscal year during which the last entry was made on the record, and for the first 2 years shall be maintained in an appropriate office of the investment adviser.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Partnership articles and amendments to the partnership articles, articles of incorporation, charters, minute books, and stock certificate books of the investment adviser and of any predecessor, shall be maintained in the principal office of the investment adviser and preserved until at least 3 years after termination of the enterprise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Books and records required to be made under the provisions of §A(11) and (15) of this regulation shall be maintained and preserved in an easily accessible place for a period of not less than 5 years, the first 2 years in an appropriate office of the investment adviser, from the end of the fiscal year during which the investment adviser last published or otherwise disseminated, directly or indirectly, the notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin, or other communication.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Before ceasing to conduct or discontinuing business as an investment adviser, an investment adviser subject to <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall arrange for and be responsible for the preservation of the books and records required to be maintained and preserved under this regulation for the remainder of the period specified herein, and shall notify the Commissioner in writing of the exact address at which the books and records will be maintained during this period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Preservation and Maintenance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The records required to be maintained and preserved under this regulation may be immediately produced or reproduced by photograph on film or, as provided in <cite path="02|02|05|.16|G.|(2)">§G(2) of this regulation</cite>, on magnetic disk, tape, or other computer storage medium, and be maintained and preserved for the required time in that form. If records are produced or reproduced by photographic film or computer storage medium, the investment advisor shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Arrange the records and index the films or computer storage medium so as to permit the immediate location of a particular record;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be ready at all times to provide, and promptly provide, any facsimile enlargement of film or computer printout or copy of the computer storage medium that the Commissioner may request;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Store separately from the original one other copy of the film or computer storage medium for the time required;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>With respect to records stored on computer storage medium, maintain procedures for maintenance and preservation of, and access to, records to reasonably safeguard records from loss, alteration, or destruction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>With respect to records stored on photographic film, at all times have available for examination of its records under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, facilities for immediate, easily readable projection of the film and for producing easily readable facsimile enlargements.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="02|02|05|.16|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite>, an adviser may maintain and preserve on computer tape or disk or other computer storage medium records that, in the ordinary course of the adviser's business, are created by the adviser on electronic media or are received by the adviser solely on electronic media or by electronic data transmission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A book or other record made, kept, maintained, and preserved in compliance with 17 CFR §240.17a-3 (SEC Rule 17a-3, Records to be Made by Certain Exchange Members, Brokers and Dealers), that is substantially the same as the book or other record required to be made, kept, maintained, and preserved under this regulation shall be considered to be made, kept, maintained, and preserved in compliance with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A record made and kept under any provision of <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, that contains all the information required under any other provision of <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, need not be maintained in duplicate in order to meet the requirements of the other provision of <cite path="02|02|05|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Financial Reporting Requirements for Certain Investment Advisers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A registered investment adviser that has custody of client funds or securities, or requires payment of advisory fees 6 months or more in advance and in excess of $500 per client, shall file with the Commissioner an audited balance sheet as of the end of the investment adviser's fiscal year. Each balance sheet filed under this regulation shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Audited by an independent certified public accountant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prepared in conformity with generally accepted accounting principles; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accompanied by a note stating the principles used to prepare it, the basis of included securities or assets, and any other explanations required for clarity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The financial statements required by this regulation shall be filed with the Commissioner within 90 days following the end of the investment adviser's fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Correction of Documents Filed by Investment Advisers and Investment Adviser Representatives.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation governs amendment filings for investment advisers and investment adviser representatives that have not yet transitioned onto the IARD. Investment advisers and investment adviser representatives that have transitioned onto the IARD shall comply with Regulations .11A(3) and .12A(3) of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An amendment to an investment adviser's filings required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be filed with the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An amendment to an investment adviser representative's filings required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be filed with the Commissioner upon Form U-4.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An amendment required by the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Filed within 30 days of the event giving rise to the amendment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Marked to indicate clearly the changes on the filing that is being amended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Withdrawal of Investment Adviser and Investment Adviser Representative Registrations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Investment Adviser. An application for withdrawal of registration or of an application to register as an investment adviser shall be made by completing Form ADV-W (Notice of Withdrawal from Registration as Investment Adviser) in accordance with the form instructions and by filing the form with the IARD.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Investment Adviser Representative. An application for withdrawal of registration or of an application to register as an investment adviser representative shall be made by completing Form U-5 (Uniform Notice of Withdrawal of Securities Industry Registration) in accordance with the form instructions and by filing the form with the IARD.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Filings required by §A or B of this regulation shall be filed within 30 days of the event giving rise to the filing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Exemption from the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(i)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland, for Certain Individuals.</heading>
    <text>Under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(i)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an investment adviser representative does not include:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual broker-dealer agent who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In conjunction with the agent's employment or affiliation with a broker-dealer, holds out to the public, as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1)(ii)</cite>3, Annotated Code of Maryland, by use of the title "financial consultant", "financial adviser", or similar title or designation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner hold out as an investment adviser or representative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner act or perform as an investment adviser or representative as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is registered and in good standing in this State as the agent of a broker-dealer that is registered and in good standing in this State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Has passed, with a score of 70 percent or better, the Series 7 examination administered by the FINRA, or a combination of examinations that the Commissioner determines is the substantial equivalent of the Series 7 examination;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual insurance producer who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Falls within the definition of "investment adviser" under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, solely by incident of holding out to the public, as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1)(ii)</cite>3, Annotated Code of Maryland, by use of the registered trademark "ChFC", "Chartered Financial Consultant", "NAIFA", "National Association of Insurance and Financial Advisers", or any state or local affiliate of NAIFA whether by name or acronym, in the context of representing, acting as an agent or employee of, or otherwise indicating an affiliation with, an insurance company, producer, or agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner hold out as an investment adviser or representative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner act or perform as an investment adviser or representative as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Holds a valid license as an insurance producer with the Maryland Insurance Administration, as provided in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Does not, in any other manner, act or perform as a broker-dealer agent as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual officer, director, or other administrative employee of an insurance company, producer, agency, or trade association who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Falls within the definition of "investment adviser" under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, solely by incident of holding out to the public, as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1)(ii)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, by use of the registered trademark "ChFC", "Chartered Financial Consultant", "NAIFA", "National Association of Insurance and Financial Advisers", or any state or local affiliate of NAIFA whether by name or acronym;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner hold out as an investment adviser or representative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner act or perform as an investment adviser or representative as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is regulated by the Maryland Insurance Administration, as provided in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, with respect to business or professional conduct;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Uses the registered trademark "ChFC", "Chartered Financial Consultant", "NAIFA", "National Association of Insurance and Financial Advisers", or any state or local affiliate of NAIFA whether by name or acronym, only in the context of acting as an officer, director, or other administrative employee of an insurance company, producer, agency, or trade association; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Does not, in any other manner, act or perform as a broker-dealer agent as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An individual who falls within the definition of "investment adviser" under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, solely by incident of holding out to the public, as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1)(ii)</cite>3, Annotated Code of Maryland, but who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Uses the registered trademark "ChFC", "Chartered Financial Consultant", "CFP", or "Certified Financial Planner" solely in the context of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Acting as a teacher or researcher at an accredited college or university,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Employment in the employee benefits, pension, personnel, or similar unit of a business entity that is not an investment adviser, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employment by an agency of municipal, state, or local government;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner hold out as an investment adviser or representative; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not in any other manner act or perform as an investment adviser or representative as set forth in the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Exemption from the Maryland Securities Act, Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(2)(iii)3, Annotated Code of Maryland, for Certain Individuals.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(h)(2)(iii)</cite>3, Annotated Code of Maryland, a certified public accountant or certified public accounting firm (CPA) is not considered to "hold out" as an investment adviser if the CPA limits his or her holding out as an investment adviser to the following and does not in any other manner hold out as an investment adviser:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Enumerating financial or investment planning, counseling, consulting, or similar types of advising or consulting as a service of the practice of the CPA in brochures or similar materials used for internal client purposes only;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Enumerating financial or investment planning, counseling, consulting, or similar types of advising or consulting as a service of the practice of the CPA under the heading or caption "Certified Public Accountants" in a classified telephone book advertisement or listing, or in a directory of professional services, provided that the services are enumerated among the other services that are offered by the CPA.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|05|.22">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Cancellation of Investment Adviser and Investment Adviser Representative Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Abandonment of Application. For purposes of this regulation and the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-414">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-414, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an application is considered abandoned if the applicant has failed to pursue the application for initial registration in a diligent manner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice of Proposed Cancellation. Before the Commissioner cancels an application for initial registration because the applicant has abandoned the application, the Commissioner shall send the applicant notice of the proposed cancellation at least 15 days before issuing an order of cancellation. The notice shall be sent by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the last known address of the applicant as specified in the application or correspondence with the Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Request for Time to Complete Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant that receives a notice of proposed cancellation under <cite path="02|02|05|.22|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> may request, before the date of the proposed cancellation, that the application remain pending so that the applicant may complete the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant that has requested that an application remain pending shall complete the application within 30 days of the date of the request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Final Action.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an applicant does not make a timely request for additional time to complete an application after the Commissioner has issued a notice of proposed cancellation under <cite path="02|02|05|.22|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Commissioner may cancel the application as abandoned.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an applicant that has requested additional time under <cite path="02|02|05|.22|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> fails to complete the application within 30 days, the Commissioner may cancel the application as abandoned.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">11-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">11-203</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-302">11-302</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-25">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|05|.09">.09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 25, 1989 (16:16 Md. R. 1733); emergency status expired December 22, 1989</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-04-16">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|05|.09">.09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 23, 1989 (17:1 Md. R. 63); adopted permanently effective April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 845)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-01"><cite path="|02|02|05|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended and Regulations <cite path="|02|02|05|.10">.10</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|05|.18">.18</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 1, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1845)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-12-01"><cite path="|02|02|05|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended and new Regulations <cite path="|02|02|05|.10">.10</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|05|.18">.18</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 1, 1990 (17:26 Md. R. 2972)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-03-18">Regulations .05A, B amended effective March 18, 1991 (18:5 Md. R. 592)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-03-18">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|05|.10">.10</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|05|.18">.18</cite> adopted effective March 18, 1991 (18:5 Md. R. 592)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Regulations .10B, .11C, and .13D amended as an emergency provision effective September 23, 1991 (18:20 Md. R. 2197); emergency status extended at 18:26 Md. R. 2826; adopted permanently effective February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 152)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-12-07">Regulations .19 and .20 adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 1992 (19:17 Md. R. 1602); emergency status extended at 19:24 Md. R. 2123; adopted permanently effective December 7, 1992 (19:24 Md. R. 2125)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-09" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 9, 1994 (21:9 Md. R. 749)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-04" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective February 4, 2002 (29:2 Md. R. 94)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-27"><cite path="|02|02|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective December 27, 2021 (48:26 Md. R. 1109)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-27"><cite path="|02|02|05|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective December 27, 2021 (48:26 Md. R. 1109)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-27"><cite path="|02|02|05|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective December 27, 2021 (48:26 Md. R. 1109)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
