<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Procedures for Administrative Hearings</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter contains procedures for administrative hearings before the Maryland Securities Commissioner which are conducted under the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> ("the Maryland Securities Act");</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Business Opportunities Sales Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> ("the Business Opportunities Act"); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> ("the Maryland Franchise Law").</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This chapter does not apply to investigations instituted by the Commissioner under the Maryland Securities Act, the Business Opportunities Act, or the Maryland Franchise Law. <cite path="|02.02.07">COMAR 02.02.07</cite> contains regulations governing investigations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Regulations <cite path="|02|02|06|.08">.08</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|06|.22">.22</cite> of this chapter do not apply to contested cases that are delegated under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-205">State Government Article, §10-205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to the Office of Administrative Hearings to conduct a hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administrative law judge" means a person authorized to conduct hearings in contested cases under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 16, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Maryland Securities Commissioner or the designated agent of the Maryland Securities Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Contested case" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-202">State Government Article, §10-202(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and in this chapter refers to a proceeding before the Commissioner under the Maryland Securities Act, Business Opportunities Act, or the Maryland Franchise Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Securities in the Office of the Attorney General.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Business Opportunities Sales Act" and "Business Opportunities Act" mean <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law" and "Maryland Franchise Law" mean <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Securities Act" means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Party" means a respondent in the proceeding and the Division.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Person" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|1-101">Business Regulation Article, §1-101(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Respondent" means a person against whom a show cause order or summary order has been issued under the Maryland Securities Act, the Business Opportunities Act, or the Maryland Franchise Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Show Cause Order.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Show cause order" means an order issued by the Commissioner that alleges facts that constitute a violation of, or a failure to comply with, the law by the respondent and that directs the respondent to explain why the Commissioner should not issue a final order against the respondent based upon the alleged facts.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Show cause order" includes orders to show cause concerning:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A cease and desist order under the Business Opportunities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-110">Business Regulation Article, §14-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A cease and desist order under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-210">Business Regulation Article, §14-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A denial, suspension, or revocation of investment adviser or investment adviser representative registration under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-412">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-412, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A denial, suspension, or revocation of broker-dealer or broker-dealer agent registration under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-412">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-412, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A denial, suspension, or revocation of effectiveness of a securities registration statement under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-511">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-511, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>A denial or revocation of a securities registration exemption under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-603">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-603, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>An order to cease and desist violations of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-301">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-301</cite>—11-304, 11-401, 11-402, or 11-501, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Summary Order.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Summary order" means an order issued by the Commissioner that alleges facts that constitute a violation of, or failure to comply with, the law by the respondent and that directs the respondent immediately to take certain actions or to refrain from certain actions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Summary order" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A summary cease and desist order issued under the Business Opportunities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-110">Business Regulation Article, §14-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A summary cease and desist order issued under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-210">Business Regulation Article, §14-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A stop order issued under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A summary postponement or suspension of investment adviser or investment adviser representative registration under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-413">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-413, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A summary postponement or suspension of broker-dealer or broker-dealer agent registration under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-413">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-413, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>A summary postponement or suspension of the effectiveness of a securities registration statement under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-512">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-512, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>A summary denial or revocation of a securities registration exemption under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-603">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-603, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>A summary cease and desist order for violation of the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-701">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-701</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Time and Place of Filing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Place of Filing. Papers required or permitted to be filed under this chapter, or any provision of applicable law, shall be filed with the Office of the Attorney General, Division of Securities, 200 St. Paul Place, 20th Floor, Baltimore, MD 21202-2020, or such other places as the Commissioner may designate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Date of Filing. A paper is filed when it is received by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Computation of Time. Unless otherwise specifically provided by law or these regulations, computation of any time period prescribed by these regulations or by an order of the Commissioner begins with the first day following the act or event that initiates the time period. The last day of the time period so computed is included unless it is a Saturday, Sunday, State holiday, or any other day on which the Division is closed, in which event the period runs until the end of the next business day.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Additional Time After Service by Mail. If a notice or other filing is served by mail and the party served is entitled or required to take some action within a prescribed time period after service:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date of mailing is the date of service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>3 days are added to the prescribed time period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Form of Papers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Caption. A pleading or other paper filed by a party with the Commissioner shall contain a caption that sets forth:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name of the first listed respondent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The file number assigned to the case by the Division; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A brief descriptive title of the pleading.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Signature. A pleading or other paper filed with the Commissioner shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be signed by the party or the party's representative or attorney; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the business address and telephone number of the person by whom it is signed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Certificate of Service. The original of any pleading or other paper shall be filed with the Commissioner, and a copy shall be served upon each party or party's attorney of record. A certificate of service attesting to the date and manner of service shall be filed with the pleading.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Initiation of Contested Case.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Service of Summary Order or Show Cause Order. The Division shall promptly serve a copy of a summary order or a show cause order upon each respondent named in the order. Service may be made by personal service or by registered or certified mail. If appropriate, service may be made upon the Commissioner as the respondent's attorney for service of process in accordance with the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-802">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-802, </cite>or in accordance with an appointment made pursuant to the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-216">Business Regulation Article, §14-216(c)(26), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice of Right to Hearing. In addition to any contents required by statute, a summary order or show cause order shall advise the respondent of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Respondent's right to a hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Time period within which the respondent must request a hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Respondent's obligation to file an answer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Effect of a failure to file an answer and to request a hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Answer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Time for Filing. A respondent shall file with the Commissioner a written answer to a show cause or summary order within 15 days of service of the order and within 7 days of service of any amended order. The parties may agree to extend the time for filing the answer up to 30 days. Any additional extension of time may only be granted by order of the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Response to Factual Allegations. The answer shall admit or deny each factual allegation in the show cause or summary order and shall set forth affirmative defenses, if any. A respondent without knowledge or information sufficient to form a belief as to the truth of an allegation shall so state.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Request for Hearing. The answer shall indicate whether the respondent requests a hearing concerning the show cause or summary order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to File Answer. If a respondent fails to file a timely answer, the Commissioner may issue a proposed or final decision adverse to that respondent.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Delegation of Hearing Authority.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Delegation. The Commissioner may delegate authority to conduct a hearing to the Office of Administrative Hearings or to another person designated in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-205">State Government Article, §10-205(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Scope of Delegation. The Commissioner shall indicate in a written notice of delegation whether the Office of Administrative Hearings or other designated hearing officer is to issue proposed or final findings of fact, proposed or final conclusions of law, and a proposed or final decision. The Commissioner shall serve the notice of delegation on all parties and on the Office of Administrative Hearings or other designated hearing officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Revocation of Delegation. The Commissioner may revoke all or part of a delegation of a contested case to the Office of Administrative Hearings or other designated hearing officer if the case:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Involves novel or unanticipated factual or legal issues;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has significant social or fiscal consequences;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Involves policy issues of general applicability; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is likely to have precedential value.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures for Revocation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may revoke a delegation of a contested case at any time before a ruling on a substantive issue by the hearing officer or administrative law judge, or the taking of oral testimony from the first witness, whichever is earlier.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall issue a written notice of revocation that states briefly the reason for the revocation and specifies whether all or part of the delegation has been revoked. If only part of the delegation has been revoked, the Commissioner shall specify in the notice of revocation the portions of the contested case for which the delegation has been revoked.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall serve the notice of revocation on all parties and the Office of Administrative Hearings or other designated hearing officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A decision issued by the Commissioner shall reflect the revocation of delegation, and a copy of the revocation notice shall be included as part of the record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Withdrawal of Delegation with Consent of Parties. The Commissioner may withdraw all or part of a delegation of a contested case as to a respondent at any time with the consent of that respondent and the Division.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Notice of Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Advance Written Notice. If a respondent requests a hearing, or if the Commissioner otherwise determines that a hearing concerning a summary order or a show cause order is appropriate, the Commissioner shall give the parties reasonable advance written notice of the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Content of Notice. The notice of the hearing shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date, time, place, and nature of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The legal basis for the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A brief statement of the issues;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A summary of the rights and restrictions concerning representation set forth in <cite path="|02|02|06|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A statement that each respondent may present evidence and may cross-examine witnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A statement that each respondent may request the issuance of subpoenas in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|06|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A copy of the hearing procedures set forth in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A statement that failure by a respondent to appear at the hearing may result in adverse action against that respondent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A statement that the parties may agree to the evidence and that a respondent may waive the right to appear at the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hearings under the Maryland Franchise Law. If a respondent named in a cease and desist order issued under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-210">Business Regulation Article, §14-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or in a stop order issued under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, submits a written request for a hearing, the Commissioner shall schedule the hearing to begin within 15 business days after the Commissioner receives the request, unless the respondent consents to a later date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certain Hearings under the Maryland Securities Act. If a respondent named in a summary order issued pursuant to the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-413">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-413, </cite>11-512, or 11-603, Annotated Code of Maryland, submits a written request for a hearing, the Commissioner shall, within 15 days after receipt of the request, set a date for a hearing.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Representation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may appear on the individual's own behalf.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A party may be represented by an attorney authorized to practice law in Maryland or, when authorized by law, appear through a representative who is not an attorney. An attorney who is not a member of the Maryland Bar, but is a member in good standing of the Bar of another state, may represent a party if the attorney is specially admitted in accordance with Rule 14 of the Rules Governing Admission to the Bar of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An attorney who appears in a representative capacity shall enter an appearance by filing a pleading or written notice of appearance setting forth the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name, business address, and telephone number of the attorney; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name and address of the party represented.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each party and any representative of a party shall promptly notify the Commissioner in writing of any change of address or telephone number.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A party's representative of record shall be copied on all notices, pleadings, or other correspondence relating to the contested case.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Addition, Deletion, and Substitution of Parties.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner may, upon motion of a party, order the addition, deletion, or substitution of parties.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Consolidation of Cases.</heading>
    <text>If separate proceedings involve a common question of law or fact, the Commissioner may consolidate the proceedings in whole or in part.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Discovery.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Document Requests. A party may serve a written document request on any other party requiring that party to produce, within 15 days, for inspection and copying, any documents or tangible items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Relevant to the subject matter of the case; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not privileged.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Filing and Service. The party making the document request shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File the written request with the Commissioner not later than 20 days before the date set for the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Serve a copy of the request on all other parties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Copies of Documents.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Copies of requested documents shall be made at the expense of the party making the request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The charge for copying documents may be waived by the Division in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-621">State Government Article, §10-621, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or other applicable law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Subpoenas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Issuance of Subpoenas. Upon the request of any party, the Commissioner may issue subpoenas requiring the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of documents and tangible items in the possession or under the control of the witness.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications for Subpoenas. An application for issuance of a subpoena shall be made in writing to the Commissioner and shall state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the person to be subpoenaed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If production of documents or tangible items is sought, a particular description of the documents or tangible items sought; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of the party requesting the subpoena.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Service of Subpoenas. A subpoena may be served by personal service or by registered or certified mail. The party requesting the subpoena shall be responsible for, and bear the cost of, service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Return of Service. A party shall promptly file a return of service with the Commissioner including an affidavit by the person making service and, if the subpoena was served by mail, the return receipt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Objections to Subpoenas. A person who has been served with a subpoena may object to the subpoena by filing a motion to quash with the Commissioner within 10 days of service of the subpoena or by the date of the hearing, whichever is earlier.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Enforcement of Subpoenas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a person under subpoena fails to appear as required by the subpoena, or fails to produce the documents or tangible items set forth in the subpoena, a party may apply to the Commissioner for enforcement of the subpoena.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application to the Commissioner for enforcement of a subpoena shall be made immediately upon the failure to comply with the subpoena or within such other time period as the Commissioner may set.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon a timely request by a party for enforcement of a subpoena, the Commissioner may apply to the circuit court in the county in which the person under subpoena resides to enforce the subpoena.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Prehearing Conferences.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scheduling of Conference. The Commissioner, upon request of a party or when the Commissioner otherwise believes it appropriate, may require the parties to appear at a specified date, time, and place for a prehearing conference before the date set for hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Agenda. A prehearing conference may be held to address the following matters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Simplification of issues;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Admissions or stipulations of fact;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Requests for official notice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Discovery disputes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Preliminary motions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Admissibility of evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Order of presentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Limitation of the number of witnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Exchange of prepared testimony and exhibits between the parties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Scheduling; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Other matters that will promote the orderly and prompt conduct of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Conduct of Prehearing Conference. The Commissioner may conduct the prehearing conference by telephone. Upon notice to the participants, all or part of the prehearing conference may be recorded.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Record of Prehearing Conference. The Commissioner shall make any action taken at a prehearing conference part of the record.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Failure to Appear.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Conduct of Hearing in Party's Absence. If a party, after receiving notice of a prehearing conference or hearing, fails to appear at the conference or hearing, the Commissioner may proceed to hold the conference or hearing in that party's absence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Default. The Commissioner may also hold the absent party in default and may issue a proposed or final decision and order against the defaulted party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Request for Reconsideration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A party defaulted as a result of a failure to appear at a prehearing conference or hearing may file a written motion requesting reconsideration by the Commissioner and stating the grounds for the request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A motion for reconsideration shall be filed within 15 days after service of a default order, or such lesser time as the Commissioner may direct.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Motions—Generally.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Form and Content. Unless otherwise permitted by these regulations or by the Commissioner, motions shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be made in writing, unless otherwise permitted by the Commissioner during the course of a hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State concisely the question to be determined and be accompanied by any necessary supporting documentation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Filing and Service. A party shall file a motion not later than 15 days before the date of the hearing and shall serve a copy of the motion on each party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Response to Motion. A response to a written motion shall be filed on the earlier of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>10 days after receipt of the motion; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Oral Argument. The Commissioner may allow oral argument if it appears necessary to a fuller understanding of the issues presented.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Effect of Filing of Motion. The filing or pendency of a motion does not alter or extend any time limit.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Motions for Summary Decision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Time for Filing. A party may move at any time for summary decision as to any substantive issue in the case.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standard. The Commissioner may issue a summary decision if the Commissioner finds that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact, and that the moving party is entitled to prevail as a matter of law.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Hearings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Presiding Officer. The Commissioner shall preside at all hearings unless the Commissioner has delegated authority to conduct a hearing to the Office of Administrative Hearings or other hearing officer designated in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-205">State Government Article, §10-205(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Order of Proceedings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall call the hearing to order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall explain briefly the purpose and nature of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may allow the parties to present preliminary matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The parties may make opening statements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall state the order of presentation of evidence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Witnesses shall be sworn or put under affirmation to tell the truth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The parties may present closing summations and argument.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Function of Presiding Officer. During the hearing, the Commissioner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall administer the oath or affirmation to each witness;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall rule on the admissibility of evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall maintain order and take such action as necessary to avoid delay in the conduct of the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May question any witness as to any matter that the Commissioner considers relevant and material to the proceeding.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Presentation by Parties. On a genuine issue relevant to the determination of a contested case, each party may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Call witnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offer evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cross-examine any witness called by another party; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Make opening and closing statements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Telephone Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consent of Parties. If each party consents and has an opportunity to participate in the entire proceeding, the Commissioner may conduct all or part of the hearing by telephone, video, or other electronic means.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentary Evidence. A party shall mail copies of all documentary evidence to be offered during a telephone hearing to all parties and the Commissioner at least 5 days before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Default. The following conditions may be considered a failure to appear and grounds for default, if the conditions exist for more than 10 minutes after the scheduled time for a telephone hearing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Failure of a party to answer the telephone;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Failure of a party to free the telephone for a hearing; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Failure of a party to be ready to proceed with the hearing as scheduled.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Right to Appear at Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A party may waive the right to appear personally at the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A waiver shall be in writing and filed with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A waiver may be withdrawn by a party by written notice filed with the Commissioner not later than 7 days before the scheduled hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A party who has filed a timely written waiver may not be held in default for failing to appear at the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Public Hearings. All hearings are public unless all respondents request that the hearing be conducted privately and the Commissioner, for good cause shown, grants the request.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Submission of Case on Documentary Record.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner may elect not to hold a hearing if all parties agree to submit the case on the documentary record and waive their right to appear.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Evidence.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Standards of Admissibility. Evidence shall be admitted in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-213">State Government Article, §10-213, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Relevance. The Commissioner may admit evidence that reasonable and prudent individuals commonly accept in the conduct of their affairs, and give probative effect to that evidence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exclusion of Evidence. The Commissioner may exclude evidence that is incompetent, irrelevant, immaterial, or unduly repetitious.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hearsay. Evidence may not be excluded solely on the ground that it is hearsay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Stipulations. Parties may, by stipulation, agree on any facts relevant to the proceedings. The facts stipulated shall be considered proven for purposes of the proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Official Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may take official notice of a fact that is judicially noticeable or that is within the specialized knowledge of the Division.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Before taking official notice of a fact, the Commissioner shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify each party before or during the hearing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Give each party an opportunity to contest the fact.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Examination of Witnesses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Oath. Witnesses shall testify under oath or affirmation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Rules of Evidence. A party may conduct direct examination or cross-examination without strict adherence to formal rules of evidence in order to obtain a full and fair disclosure of facts relevant to matters in issue.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hostile Witnesses. If the Commissioner determines that a witness is hostile or unresponsive, the Commissioner may authorize the party calling the witness to proceed as if the witness were under cross-examination.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Sequestration of Witnesses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Request for Sequestration. Upon request by any party, the Commissioner may exclude witnesses other than parties from the hearing room when those witnesses are not testifying.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Representative of Party. A party that is not a natural person may designate an individual as its representative to remain in the hearing room, even though the individual may also be a witness.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Experts. An expert witness who is to render an opinion based upon the testimony given at the hearing may remain in the hearing room during the testimony.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prohibition of Disclosure. The Commissioner may order the witnesses, parties, their counsel, and any person under their direction not to disclose to any sequestered witness the substance of the testimony, exhibits, or other evidence introduced during the witness' absence.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|06|.23">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Ex Parte Communications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Prohibition. Except as provided in <cite path="02|02|06|.23|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, while a contested case is pending, the Commissioner may not communicate ex parte regarding the merits of any issue in the case with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A respondent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A representative or attorney for a respondent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Division staff or counsel involved in the investigation or presentation of the case; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An administrative law judge or other hearing officer who presided at an earlier stage of the case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Other Division Staff. The Commissioner may communicate regarding the merits of any issue in the case with the Division's staff or counsel who have not otherwise participated in the investigation or presentation of the case.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Disclosure. Ex parte communications received before a hearing in a contested case that would otherwise violate <cite path="02|02|06|.23|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be disclosed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-219">State Government Article, §10-219, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Proposed Decisions and Final Decisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Cases Heard by the Commissioner. The Commissioner shall prepare written findings of fact and conclusions of law, and shall promptly issue a final decision after the conclusion of any hearing held before the Commissioner. The final decision shall include rulings on any proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law submitted by the parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Cases Heard by an Administrative Law Judge.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When the Commissioner has delegated authority to hear a case to the Office of Administrative Hearings but has reserved final decision-making authority, the administrative law judge shall send a proposed decision, including proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law, to the parties and the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 15 days of receipt of the proposed decision, each party shall file with the Commissioner any exceptions to the proposed decision, any supporting memorandum, and any request to present argument to the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days of receipt of exceptions filed by an adverse party, a party may file a memorandum in opposition to those exceptions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall review the hearing record, the proposed decision of the administrative law judge, and any exceptions and memoranda filed by the parties, and shall permit the parties to present arguments, if they request an opportunity to do so. Before issuing a final decision, the Commissioner may require the submission of additional information or documentation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall issue a final decision that may adopt, modify, or reject the proposed findings of fact, proposed conclusions of law, or the proposed decision of the administrative law judge. The final decision shall include rulings on any exceptions filed by the parties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice of Appeal Rights. A final decision of the Commissioner shall advise each respondent that any appeal to the circuit court shall be filed within 30 days from the date the order is mailed by the Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Final Decision by Default. The Commissioner may enter a final decision as to any respondent who fails to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File a timely responsive answer; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appear for a hearing at the scheduled time and date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Service of Final Decision. A final decision of the Commissioner shall be in writing. A copy of the final decision shall be hand delivered or mailed, by certified or registered mail, to each party or its representative or attorney.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Correction of Final Decision. In the event of fraud, mistake, or irregularity, the Commissioner may correct a final decision at any time.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Record of Proceedings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recording of Oral Proceedings. The Division shall cause all oral proceedings, including testimony, to be recorded by a stenographer or by tape recorder or other device. The recording of the proceedings, which need not be transcribed, shall be maintained in the custody of the Division. In the event of an appeal from a decision of the Commissioner, the appellant shall pay the cost of transcription of the record. Other verbatim reports or recordings may not be made by any other person without the consent of the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The record of a contested case shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All pleadings, motions, orders, and related papers filed with the Commissioner or the Office of Administrative Hearings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All documentary and tangible evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A statement of matters officially noticed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recordings and any transcripts of oral proceedings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The findings of fact and conclusions of law proposed by each party;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any exceptions filed by the parties and the Commissioner's rulings on those exceptions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The findings of fact, conclusions of law, and decision of the Commissioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If a case has been delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings for a proposed decision:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The notice of delegation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any notice of revocation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The proposed decision, including proposed findings of fact and proposed conclusions of law, of the administrative law judge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any exceptions filed by the parties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Commissioner's rulings on any exceptions and proposed findings of fact or conclusions of law; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any additional information or documentation submitted to the Commissioner by the parties;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The final order, if any, of the Commissioner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Other documents or material placed in the record as required by law or at the discretion of the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Index of Record. The Division shall prepare an index of the record of proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Public Inspection. Upon compilation, the record shall be available for public inspection at the Division during normal business hours unless the contents are otherwise protected by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Copy of Record. The Division, upon request of a party, shall arrange for a copy of the record to be made, if the requesting party pays in advance to the Office of the Attorney General the Division's estimate of the reasonable cost of making the copy. The copy shall be certified by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Stay of Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Motion for Stay. After the Commissioner has issued a final decision that results in the entry of a final order against a party, the party may move for a stay of the Commissioner's order if the party has filed an appeal of the final decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Motion. A request for a stay shall be in writing and shall include a copy of the order for appeal filed in the circuit court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Criteria for Stay. The Commissioner may grant a stay of a final order for such period of time as the Commissioner considers appropriate, after considering:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The potential hardship caused by the order to the party requesting the stay;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The likelihood that the party will prevail on appeal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other reasons for a stay proffered by that party;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The interest of investor protection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The public interest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Disposition by Agreement.</heading>
    <text>At any time after initiation of a contested case, with the approval of the Commissioner, the parties may resolve a contested case without a final decision by stipulation, settlement, or consent order.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-203</cite>;<br/>Business Regulation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-106">14-106</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-206">14-206</cite>;<br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-206">State Government Article, §10-206</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-23">Effective date: May 23, 1994 (21:10 Md. R. 840)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended and D adopted effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite>, C amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.16|C.">Regulation .16C</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.23|B.">Regulation .23B</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|06|.24|B.">Regulation .24B</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
