<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Investigations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to investigations instituted by the Securities Commissioner under the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> (the Maryland Securities Act);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Business Opportunities Sales Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> (the Business Opportunities Act); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> (the Maryland Franchise Law).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to examinations of registrants conducted by the Securities Division under the Maryland Securities Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-411">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-411(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Document" means the original of a paper or other tangible item or material on which information is written or recorded and includes, by example, correspondence, memoranda, reports, circulars, announcements, financial statements or projections, books, ledgers, records, tabulations, maps, charts, photographs, mechanical transcriptions, electronic and computer media, and any other tangible recording.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Person" means an individual, partnership, corporation, limited liability company, limited liability partnership, business trust, estate, trust, fiduciary, representative of any kind, association, unincorporated organization, government, political subdivision, and any other legal or commercial entity, and includes all individuals and entities set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|1-101">Business Regulation Article, §1-101(g), </cite>and Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|1-101">1-101</cite>(p) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">11-101</cite>(n), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Subpoenas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Type of Subpoena. As part of an investigation, the Commissioner may issue a subpoena to any person to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Testify under oath;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Answer written interrogatories under oath;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Produce documents and tangible things; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Permit inspection and copying of documents.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Content of Subpoena. A subpoena shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Describe generally the nature of the investigation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the subpoena requires testimony under oath, specify the date, time, and place for the taking of testimony;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the subpoena requires answers to written interrogatories, contain a copy of the written interrogatories;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the subpoena requires the production of tangible things or documents:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Describe the things and documents to be produced with reasonable specificity, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specify a date, time, and place at which the things and documents are to be produced;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify the person to whom the subpoena is directed of the obligation to supplement responses under <cite path="|02|02|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Advise the person to whom the subpoena is directed that the person may be represented by counsel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Identify a member of the Securities Division who may be contacted in reference to the subpoena.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Subpoenas to Corporations and Other Entities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A subpoena directed to a corporation, partnership, or other entity that requires testimony under oath shall describe with reasonable particularity the subject matter of the testimony.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An entity that receives a subpoena to answer written interrogatories or to testify under oath shall designate one or more of its officers, agents, employees, or other authorized persons familiar with the subject matter specified in the subpoena to respond to the subpoena on its behalf.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The persons designated by an entity to respond to a subpoena on its behalf shall answer the interrogatories or testify as to all matters known or reasonably available to the entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A subpoena directed to an entity that requires testimony under oath or answers to written interrogatories shall advise the entity of its obligations under this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Service of Subpoena.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A subpoena may be served by personal service or by mail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person who serves a subpoena shall complete a certificate of service attesting to the method and date of service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Effect of Other Proceedings. The pendency or beginning of administrative or judicial proceedings against a person by the Commissioner does not relieve the person of its obligation to respond to a subpoena issued under this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Petition to Modify or Quash Subpoena.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person served with a subpoena under this regulation may request that the subpoena be modified or quashed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A petition to modify or quash a subpoena issued under this regulation shall be filed with the Commissioner within 10 days of service of the subpoena or by the date specified for compliance with the subpoena, whichever is earlier. The petition shall set forth good cause why the subpoena should be modified or quashed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Enforcement of Subpoena. If a person served with a subpoena under this regulation fails to appear as required by the subpoena, or fails to provide testimony, answers to written interrogatories, or documents and tangible things as required by the subpoena, the Commissioner may apply to the appropriate circuit court for enforcement of the subpoena.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Testimony Under Oath.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Presiding Officer. Testimony under oath shall be taken before the Commissioner or an officer designated by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Attendance at Testimony. A witness who testifies under oath in compliance with a subpoena may be accompanied and represented by counsel. Members of the Division involved in the investigation may be present during the taking of testimony. Other persons may not attend unless permitted in the discretion of the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Examination of Witness. The following individuals may ask questions of</text>
      <text>the witness:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attorneys representing the Division;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Counsel representing the witness.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Record of Testimony. Testimony shall be recorded by a stenographer or by tape recorder or other device. Any other recording is not permitted. The recording of the testimony shall be maintained in the custody of the Division.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Production of Things and Documents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Assertion of Privilege. If a person responding to a subpoena for production of things or documents withholds a record or document on the basis of a privilege, the person shall state, with respect to each document:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and title of the author of the document;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The names and titles of all persons to whom the document was addressed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The names and titles of all persons to whom copies of the document were sent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The date on which the document was written or otherwise produced and the date on which it was mailed, sent, or delivered to its addressee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of pages in the document;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A brief description of the nature or subject matter of the document;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The basis on which the document is being withheld; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The paragraph number of the subpoena to which the document is responsive.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Obligation to Supplement Responses. If a person has responded to a subpoena under this regulation and later discovers or obtains additional documents or things responsive to the subpoena, the person shall supplement the response as soon as reasonably possible.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Use and Confidential Treatment of Subpoenaed Materials.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Use of Subpoenaed Materials. The Division may use information, documents, and things obtained by subpoena in furtherance of an investigation conducted by the Division and of joint investigations conducted by the Division in cooperation with other state and federal agencies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Confidential Treatment. Information, documents, and things obtained by subpoena may be held confidential and are not subject to disclosure to the extent provided by the Public Information Act, State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">10-611</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-628">10-628</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">11-203</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-701">11-701</cite>;<br/>Business Regulation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-106">14-106</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-111">14-111</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-206">14-206</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-212">14-212</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-05">Effective date: December 5, 1994 (21:24 Md. R. 1986)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|02|02|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 15, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 944)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
