<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Franchise Registration and Disclosure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this chapter and of the Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as used in the Uniform Franchise Offering Circular, "affiliate" means a person that, directly or indirectly, controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with, another person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Securities Commissioner in the Office of the Attorney General or the designated agent of the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Securities in the Office of the Attorney General.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Earnings Claim.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Earnings claim" means information given to a prospective franchisee by, on behalf of, or at the direction of the franchisor or its agent, from which a specific level or range of actual or potential sales, cost, income, or profit from franchised or nonfranchised units may be ascertained.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Earnings claim" includes, but is not necessarily limited to, a chart, table, or mathematical calculation presented to demonstrate possible results based on a combination of variables such as multiples of prices and quantity to reflect gross sales.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Earnings claim" includes a representation of a franchise offering that is described in terms of the amount or value of revenue, sales, income, contracts, or business intended to be provided to a franchisee within a specified period of time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Franchise" has the meaning stated in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Franchise fee" has the meaning stated in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Franchise Offering Circular (MFOC)" means a document prepared in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law" and the "Maryland Franchise Law" mean <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 14, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Material change", for purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-220">Business Regulation Article, §14-220, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|02|02|08|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, includes, but is not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The termination, in any manner, of more than 10 percent of the franchises of the franchisor that are located in the State during any 3-month period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The termination, in any manner, of more than 5 percent of all franchises of the franchisor regardless of location during any 3-month period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A reorganization of the franchisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A change in control, corporate name, or state of incorporation of the franchisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The commencement of any new product, service, or model line requiring, directly or indirectly, additional investment by any franchisee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The discontinuation or modification of the marketing plan or system of any product or service of the franchisor which accounts for at least 20 percent of the annual gross sales of the franchisor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Person" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|1-101">Business Regulation Article, §1-101(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>For purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-203">Business Regulation Article, §14-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Maryland edition of a "publication" is considered a separate "publication" if the Maryland edition does not carry the same advertising as other editions of the publication.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Uniform Franchise Offering Circular (UFOC)" means the Uniform Franchise Offering Circular Guidelines adopted by the North American Securities Administrators Association, Inc., on April 25, 1993, which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|02|02|08|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Franchise.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. The Commissioner shall consider the factors set forth in this regulation in any determination as to whether a business relationship is a franchise as defined in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Marketing Plan. For purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(e)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, "marketing plan" means a plan or system concerning a material aspect of conducting business. Indicia of a marketing plan include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Price specification, special pricing systems, or discount plans;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sales or display equipment or merchandising devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sales techniques;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Promotional or advertising materials or cooperative advertising;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Training regarding the promotion, operation, or management of the business; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Operational, managerial, technical, or financial guidelines or assistance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prescription by Franchisor. For purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(e)(1)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whether a marketing plan or system is "prescribed in substantial part by the franchisor" depends upon consideration of a number of factors including, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the representations made by the franchisor in connection with the offer or sale of a franchise suggest, or any agreement executed in connection with the offer to sell or sale of a franchise requires, that the franchisee operate a business that purchases a substantial portion of its goods solely from sources designated or approved by the franchisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the representations made by the franchisor in connection with the offer or sale of a franchise suggest, or any agreement executed in connection with the offer to sell or sale of a franchise requires, that the franchisee follow an operating plan, standard procedure, or training manual, or its substantial equivalent, promulgated by the franchisor in the operation of the licensed business, violations of which may, under the terms of the agreement, permit the franchisor to terminate the agreement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the representations made by the franchisor in connection with the offer or sale of a franchise suggest, or any agreement executed in connection with the offer to sell or sale of a franchise requires, that the franchisee is limited as to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type, quantity, or quality of any product or service the franchisee may sell; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Persons or accounts to which the franchisee may sell the franchisor's product or service;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the provisions of the agreement permitting the franchisor to terminate the agreement, to buy back the franchisee or license rights assigned by the agreement, or to refuse to renew the grant of the franchisee or license rights are such as to operate or be exercisable substantially at the will of the franchisor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Whether the representations made by the franchisor or seller in connection with the offer or sale of a franchise suggest, or any agreement executed in connection with the offer or sale of a franchise requires, that the franchisor aid or assist the franchisee in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Training,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtaining locations or facilities for operation of the franchisee's business, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Marketing the franchisor's product or service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Association with Franchisor's Business. For purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(e)(1)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whether a marketing plan or system is "associated substantially with the trademark, service mark, trade name, logotype, advertising, or other commercial symbol that designates the franchisor or its affiliate" depends upon consideration of a number of factors, including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the identification of the franchisor's business or use of its trademark, service mark, trade name, logotype, advertising, or other commercial symbol is used either by the franchisor or the franchisee to enhance the chances of the franchisee's success in the business of dealing in, selling, or promoting the franchisor's product or service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the agreement provides for the franchisee to contribute a portion of its operating revenue to the franchisor for advertising expenses, or representations made by the franchisor or the franchisor's agents or employees otherwise suggest, require, or compel payment by the franchisee for advertising conducted, managed, or prescribed by the franchisor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may consider, in determining whether a business relationship is a franchise as defined in Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whether the relationship is described as or entitled a "franchise".</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Franchise Fee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. The Commissioner shall consider the factors set forth in this regulation in any determination as to whether a franchisee is required to pay a franchise fee, as defined in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form and Timing of Payment. A franchise fee includes, but is not limited to, a payment that is made before, upon, or after execution of an agreement to purchase, process, resell, or otherwise distribute a manufacturer's or franchisor's goods, services, equipment, inventory, or real estate, and that is made in the form of a lump sum, installments, periodic royalties, profits, or cash flow, or is or may be reflected in the price of goods, services, equipment, inventory, or real estate sold by the franchisor to the franchisee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Purchases at Wholesale Price. For purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-201">Business Regulation Article, §14-201(g)(3)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whether a transaction involves "the purchase of or agreement to purchase goods at a wholesale price" depends upon consideration of a number of factors, including but not limited to whether in connection with an agreement to process, resell, or otherwise distribute a manufacturer's or franchisor's product or service:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consideration paid by the buyer in purchase transactions is solely for the payment of goods, services, equipment, inventory, or real estate, and does not reflect the buyer's payment for the right to continue the purchase transactions or the business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The buyer's purchase of goods, services, equipment, inventory, or real estate is required by or in connection with the agreement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The cost to the seller of goods, services, equipment, inventory, or real estate is reasonably related to the price paid by the buyer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application for Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Form of Application. An application to register a franchise shall be prepared in accordance with the Uniform Franchise Offering Circular Guidelines adopted by the North American Securities Administrators Association, Inc., on April 25, 1993 (UFOC), which is incorporated by reference, with the modifications set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>. A copy of the UFOC may be obtained from the Division for a nominal fee and may also be found in Business Franchise Guide (CCH) §5200—5200.17.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Modifications to UFOC.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application shall include two copies of the proposed offering circular which complies with the instructions for the UFOC with the additions and modifications set forth in §B(2)—(4) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Item 11—Franchisor Obligations. In addition to the information required by the UFOC, the offering circular shall disclose in Item 11 how fees related to advertising are to be raised and spent, and how a franchisee may obtain an accounting of advertising expenditures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Item 17—Renewal, Termination, Transfer, and Dispute Resolution. If the agreement provides for termination of the franchise upon bankruptcy of the franchisee, the offering circular shall disclose in Item 17, in addition to the information required by the UFOC, that this provision may not be enforceable under federal bankruptcy law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Item 21—Financial Statements. In addition to the information required by the UFOC, the offering circular shall contain financial statements required under <cite path="|02|02|08|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Initial Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registration File Number.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of an application for initial registration, the Division shall assign a file number to the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Correspondents shall refer to the assigned file number in all subsequent related filings and correspondence with the Division.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An application for registration may include a stamped self-addressed envelope and a duplicate cover letter which the Division may stamp and return to the applicant as confirmation of receipt of the filing and notification of the registration file number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Undertaking. During an examination of an application for initial registration under the Maryland Franchise Law, the Commissioner may require that the applicant provide an undertaking that it has not offered or sold franchises in the State without being registered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>During an examination of an application for initial registration under the Maryland Franchise Law, the Commissioner may require the applicant to modify the application or to submit additional information to remedy deficiencies in the application. The Commissioner may require the applicant to make such other disclosures as the Commissioner determines are necessary in the public interest and for the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request by the Commissioner for modifications, additional information, or other disclosures may be communicated in any form to the applicant, or to the person filing the application on behalf of the applicant, within 30 business days after receipt of the initial application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An application for initial registration is considered filed for purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-218">Business Regulation Article, §14-218(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, only when the application fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-215">Business Regulation Article, §14-215, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and all modifications, information, and disclosures reasonably required by the Commissioner have been received by the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Abandonment of Application. If an applicant fails to provide information requested by the Commissioner or otherwise neglects to pursue an application for initial registration in a diligent manner, the Commissioner shall consider the application abandoned 6 months after the date of the last written communication from the applicant or any person on behalf of the applicant. An applicant who wishes to revive an abandoned application shall submit a new application, together with a new application fee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Amendment of Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When to File.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for amendment of a registration statement shall be promptly filed if there is a material change in the information that a registrant previously filed with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An amendment is not required if a particular franchise agreement is changed as a result of negotiations between the franchisee and the franchisor and the franchisor agrees to the change or a similar change only on an individual or isolated basis.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Amendment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for amendment of a registration statement, whether filed before or after the effective date of registration, shall be in the form set forth in <cite path="|02|02|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> and shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One complete clean copy of the amended MFOC; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One redlined copy of the MFOC that highlights all additions, deletions, and other changes by underlining, boldface or italic type, or such other symbols as to indicate clearly any alterations to the applicant's prior submission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each amendment shall be accompanied by a facing page which indicates that the filing is an amendment and which states the number of the amendment and the items of the offering circular which are affected by the amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Payment of Fee. An application to amend an effective registration statement shall be accompanied by payment for the fee set forth in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-220">Business Regulation Article, §14-220, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Status of Current Registration. During the pendency of an application to amend a registration statement, the current registration statement filed with the Commissioner remains in effect.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing. During examination of an application to amend an effective registration statement, the Commissioner may require the applicant to modify the application or to submit additional information to remedy deficiencies in the application. The Commissioner may require the applicant to make such other disclosures as the Commissioner considers necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Effective Date of Amendment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner does not require additional information from the applicant and does not issue a stop order or other order blocking effectiveness of the amendment, an amendment to an effective registration statement becomes effective 15 business days after receipt by the Commissioner of the application to amend, or at such earlier time as the Commissioner may determine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner requires that the applicant provide additional information, the amendment to the registration statement becomes effective 15 business days after receipt by the Commissioner of the information requested, unless the Commissioner issues a stop order or other order blocking the effectiveness of the amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Abandonment of Amendment. If an applicant fails to provide information requested by the Commissioner or otherwise neglects to pursue an application to amend an effective registration statement in a diligent manner, the Commissioner shall consider the application to amend the registration statement abandoned 6 months after the date of the last written communication from the applicant or any person on behalf of the applicant. An applicant who wishes to revive an abandoned application to amend an effective registration statement shall submit a new application to amend the registration statement, together with a new filing fee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Annual Effective Date. Notwithstanding the amendment of an effective registration statement, the effective date of the initial or renewal registration statement remains the date from which annual effectiveness is measured.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Time for Submitting Renewal Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application to renew a registration shall be submitted to the Division not less than 15 business days before the end of 1 year from the effective date of the registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a registrant submits an application to renew a registration less than 15 days before the expiration of the prior year's registration, but before the expiration of the prior year's registration, the Commissioner may consider the application as an application for renewal registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a registrant submits an application to renew a registration after the expiration of the prior year's registration, the Commissioner shall treat the application as an application for initial registration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Renewal Application. An application to renew a registration shall be in the form set forth in <cite path="|02|02|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> and shall be accompanied by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Two copies of the registrant's most recent MFOC which meets the requirements of <cite path="|02|02|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Financial statements that satisfy the requirements of <cite path="|02|02|08|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Payment for the renewal fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-219">Business Regulation Article, §14-219, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Completion of Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>During an examination of an application to renew a registration, the Commissioner may require the applicant to modify the application or to submit additional information to remedy deficiencies in the application. The Commissioner may require the applicant to make such other disclosures as the Commissioner considers necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request by the Commissioner for modifications, additional information, or other disclosures may be communicated in any form to the applicant, or to the person submitting the application on behalf of the applicant, within 15 business days after receipt of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An application for renewal registration is considered filed for purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-219">Business Regulation Article, §14-219(b)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, only when the application fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-219">Business Regulation Article, §14-219(b)(1)(iii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and all modifications, information, and disclosures reasonably required by the Commissioner have been received by the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Date of Effectiveness.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If no stop order or other order blocking effectiveness of the renewal is in effect, a renewal registration that was timely filed becomes effective at 12 noon of the day on which the prior registration expires, or at such earlier time as the Commissioner may determine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a renewal registration application is submitted less than 15 days before the expiration of the prior registration, and the Commissioner elects to treat it as a renewal registration application under <cite path="02|02|08|.07|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, the Commissioner shall notify the applicant of the date upon which the renewal registration becomes effective.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Extension of Current Registration. If a previous registration is about to expire and a renewal registration application is not yet considered filed, the Commissioner may extend the effective period of a registration subject to such conditions as the Commissioner may prescribe for the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Abandonment of Renewal Application. If an applicant fails to provide information requested by the Commissioner or otherwise neglects to pursue an application for renewal registration in a diligent manner, the Commissioner shall consider the application abandoned 6 months after the date of the last written communication from the applicant or any person on behalf of the applicant. An applicant who wishes to revive an abandoned application for renewal registration shall submit an initial application for registration, together with the application fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-215">Business Regulation Article, §14-215, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for an initial registration.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Escrow Condition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Imposition of Escrow Condition. At any time after the submission of a registration statement and upon a finding that it is necessary and appropriate for the protection of prospective franchisees or subfranchisors, the Commissioner may require a franchisor to escrow franchise fees and other funds paid by a franchisee or subfranchisor until the franchisor's obligations under the offering have been satisfied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Depositary. Funds subject to an escrow condition shall be placed in a separate trust account with a national bank located in Maryland or a Maryland bank or trust company.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Compliance with Escrow Condition. After the Commissioner imposes an escrow condition, the franchisor shall file with the Commissioner the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An original fully executed copy of the escrow agreement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written consent from the depositary agreeing to operate the escrow account under this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the depositary and the account number of the escrow account;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of an individual or individuals at the depositary who may be contacted by the Commissioner regarding the escrow account; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An amended franchise registration application reflecting, in both the franchise agreement and Item 5 of the offering circular, that the Commissioner has imposed the escrow conditions and the material terms of that escrow condition, including the name of the depositary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Operation of Escrow Condition. After the Commissioner imposes an escrow condition:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Franchisee and subfranchisor checks for franchise fees or other payments to the franchisor shall be made payable to the depositary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Franchise fees and all other funds to be paid to the franchisor by its franchisees or subfranchisors for any purpose shall be placed, within 48 hours of the receipt of those funds, with the depositary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Funds placed in the depositary shall remain escrowed until the Commissioner authorizes the release of the funds under <cite path="02|02|08|.08|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Release of Escrowed Funds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A franchisor may apply to the Commissioner for the release of escrowed funds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A franchisor's application to the Commissioner to authorize the release of escrowed funds to the franchisor shall be in writing, verified by an authorized officer of the franchisor and shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement by the franchisor that all proceeds from the sale of franchises have been placed with the depositary in accordance with the terms and conditions of the escrow condition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A statement of the depositary, signed by an appropriate officer, setting forth the aggregate amount of escrowed funds deposited with the depositary and the franchisor's account number with the depositary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A list of the franchisees and subfranchisors and the amount held in the escrow account for the account of each franchisee and subfranchisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>With respect to each franchisee for which the release of funds is sought, the amount of funds sought to be released and a written certification from the franchisee stating the amount of funds to be released and acknowledging that the franchisor has completely performed its obligations under the franchise agreement to provide real estate, improvements, equipment, inventory, training, or other items; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other information the Commissioner may reasonably require.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner finds that the franchisor has fulfilled its obligations under the franchise agreement to a specified franchisee or subfranchisor, the Commissioner shall authorize the depositary to release to the franchisor those amounts of the escrowed funds applicable to the franchisee or subfranchisor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Surety Bond in Place of Escrow.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Instead of the imposition of an escrow condition, a franchisor may post a surety bond in an amount required by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The bond shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In an amount not less than the initial franchise fee multiplied by the number of franchises the franchisor estimates it will sell in the State in the next year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Issued by a corporate surety authorized to transact business in Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Conditioned upon the completion by the franchisor of its obligations under the franchise agreement to provide real estate, improvements, equipment, inventory, training, or other items.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Deferral of Fees in Place of Escrow.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Instead of the imposition of an escrow condition, the Commissioner may, in appropriate circumstances, accept a franchisor's agreement to defer franchise fees and other initial payments owed by franchisees and subfranchisors until the franchisor has completed its initial obligations under the franchise agreement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The franchisor's agreement to defer franchise fees shall be reflected in the offering circular and the franchise agreement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Removal of Escrow Condition. At any time after the imposition of an escrow condition, the Commissioner may remove the escrow condition if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The franchisor posts a surety bond in accordance with <cite path="02|02|08|.08|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The franchisor agrees to defer franchise fees and other initial payments in accordance with <cite path="02|02|08|.08|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Based upon new information, the Commissioner finds that the escrow condition is no longer necessary and appropriate for the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Advertising.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Standards For Advertising.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An advertisement for a franchise offering may not refer to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The purchase or sale of a franchise as a safe investment, as free from risk of loss or default, or as a guarantee or assurance of earnings or profits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An earnings claim, unless otherwise permitted by the Commissioner; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An opinion of counsel without stating the name and address of the counsel.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advertising shall state the name and address of the person sponsoring the advertisement or making the offer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Review of Advertising. A copy of each advertisement to be used by or on behalf of a franchisor in the offer or sale of any franchise subject to registration shall be submitted to the Division of Securities for review at least 5 days before the date of its anticipated initial use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Videotape and Audiotape Advertising. Advertising submitted under this regulation that is in the form of videotapes or audiotapes shall be accompanied by a written transcript and description of the contents.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Basis of Exemption. Under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-214">Business Regulation Article, §14-214(b)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Commissioner has determined that the offers or sales described in §§B—G of this regulation are exempt from the registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law because the transactions are not within the purpose of the Maryland Franchise Law and registration of the transactions is not necessary or appropriate for the protection of investors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Out-of-State Sales.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law do not apply to an offer or sale of a franchise to a resident of a foreign state, territory, or country who is not a resident of Maryland to the knowledge of the seller.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exemption set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> may be claimed only if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The franchised business is not to be operated wholly or partially in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The sale of the franchise does not violate any law of the foreign state, territory, or country of which the offeree or buyer is a resident; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The sale of the franchise does not violate the antifraud provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nominal Franchise Fee. The registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law do not apply to an offer or sale of a franchise when the franchise fee does not exceed $100 on an annual basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Seasoned Franchisor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law do not apply to any offer or sale of a franchise when the franchisor has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A net equity, according to its most recently audited financial statements, of not less than:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>$10,000,000 on a consolidated basis, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>$1,000,000 and is at least 80 percent owned by a corporation or entity that has a net equity, on a consolidated basis, according to its most recently audited financial statements, of not less than $10,000,000, which 80 percent owner guarantees the performance of the franchisor's obligations; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had at least 25 franchisees conducting the same franchised business at all times during the 5-year period immediately preceding the offer or sale.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exemption set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> may be claimed only if the franchisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Files a Form F-1 Notice of Exemption:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Not later than 10 business days before the offer or sale of any franchise, which Notice of Exemption shall expire after a period of 1 year, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the franchisor intends to offer or sell for an additional period annually after that, at least 10 business days before the expiration of the previously filed Notice of Exemption;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Files a Consent to Service of Process naming the Commissioner as the franchisor's agent to receive process in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Files an undertaking by which it agrees to supply any additional information the Commissioner may reasonably request;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pays the filing fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-214">Business Regulation Article, §14-214(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Submits financial statements demonstrating compliance with the conditions set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|D.|(1)|(a)">§D(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Submits a representation that the franchisor complies with the condition set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|D.|(1)|(b)">§D(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Files one copy of its current offering circular.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Sophisticated Franchisee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law do not apply to any offer or sale of a franchise for which the franchisor requires an initial investment by the franchisee of more than $750,000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exemption set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> may be claimed only if the franchisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Files a Form F-1 Notice of Exemption:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Not later than 10 business days before the offer or sale of any franchise, which Notice of Exemption shall expire after a period of 1 year, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the franchisor intends to offer or sell for an additional period annually after that, at least 10 business days before the expiration of the previously filed Notice of Exemption;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Files a Consent to Service of Process naming the Commissioner as the franchisor's agent to receive process in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Files an undertaking by which it agrees to supply any additional information the Commissioner may reasonably request;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pays the filing fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-214">Business Regulation Article, §14-214(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Files one copy of its current offering circular.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Institutional Franchisee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law do not apply to an offer or sale of a franchise to a bank, savings bank, savings and loan association, trust company, insurance company, investment company, or other financial institution, or to a broker-dealer when the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Purchaser is acting for itself or in a fiduciary capacity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Franchise is not being purchased for the purpose of resale.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exemption set forth in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite> may be claimed only if the franchisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Files a Form F-1 Notice of Exemption at least 10 business days before each offer or sale of each franchise;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Files a Consent to Service of Process naming the Commissioner as the franchisor's agent to receive process in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Files an undertaking by which it agrees to supply any additional information as the Commissioner may reasonably request; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pays the filing fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-214">Business Regulation Article, §14-214(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Exemption by Order.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law do not apply to an offer or sale of a franchise or class of franchises not otherwise described in §§B—F of this regulation if the Commissioner, by order, determines that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The transaction or class of franchises is not one within the purpose of the Maryland Franchise Law; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Registration of the transaction or class of franchises is not necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of franchisees.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request for an order exempting the offer and sale of a franchise or class of franchises under this section shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be filed with the Commissioner;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contain a description of the transaction or class of franchises for which an exemption is sought and the reasons why an order of exemption is appropriate under the criteria described in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Include a representation that the person making the request shall provide any additional information the Commissioner requires.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A request for an order under this section may be made either by a franchisor or a franchisee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner's order exempting the offer and sale of a franchise or class of franchises shall include findings of fact and reasons why granting the exemption is appropriate under the criteria described in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unless the Commissioner orders otherwise, if the Commissioner finds that a franchise or class of franchises satisfies the criteria described in <cite path="02|02|08|.10|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite>, an exemption may be claimed only if the franchisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Files a Form F-1 Notice of Exemption, as set forth in <cite path="|02|02|08|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, not later than 10 business days before the offer or sale of any franchise, which Notice of Exemption shall expire after a period of 1 year, and if the franchisor intends to offer or sell for an additional period annually after that, at least 10 business days before the expiration of the previously filed Notice of Exemption;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Files a Consent to Service of Process naming the Commissioner as the franchisor's agent to receive process in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Files an undertaking by which it agrees to supply any additional information the Commissioner may reasonably require;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pays the filing fee required by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-214">Business Regulation Article, §14-214(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Files one copy of its current offering circular.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Disclosure Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless the Commissioner orders otherwise, if a franchisor relies upon any of the exemptions set forth in §D, E, F, or G of this regulation, the franchisor shall provide an offering circular, together with all proposed agreements relating to the sale of the franchise, to a prospective franchisee at the earlier of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The prospective franchisee's first personal meeting with the franchisor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>10 business days before the signing of the agreement or the payment of any consideration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instead of providing an offering circular prepared in accordance with the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-216">Business Regulation Article, §14-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|02|02|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, a franchisor may provide an offering circular that complies with the requirements of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Federal Trade Commission's trade regulation entitled "Disclosure Requirements and Prohibitions Concerning Franchising and Business Opportunity Ventures", 16 CFR 436;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Franchise disclosure law of another state; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>UFOC.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Franchisors filing a claim of exemption under §D, E, F, or G of this regulation shall include a self-addressed stamped envelope by which the Division may return to the franchisor confirmation of receipt of the filing and the exemption file number assigned. Correspondents shall refer to the assigned file number in all subsequent related filings and correspondence with the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Exemptions—Form F-1.</heading>
    <text>The following form shall be filed by franchisors claiming exemptions under Regulation .10D, E, F, or G of this chapter:</text>
    <include>
      <text class="center">FORM F-1</text>
      <text class="center">NOTICE OF EXEMPTION UNDER THE MARYLAND FRANCHISE REGISTRATION AND DISCLOSURE LAW</text>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite path="02.02.08.10">COMAR 02.02.08.10</cite></text>
      <text>This Notice of Exemption shall be accompanied by a filing fee of $250.00 payable by check to: Office of the Attorney General. This Notice shall be considered filed with the Division for purposes of <cite path="02.02.08.10">COMAR 02.02.08.10</cite> as of the date on which the Notice is received by the Division or, if received by the Division after the date on which it is due, as of the date prior to the due date on which it was mailed by means of United States registered or certified mail to the Maryland Division of Securities, Office of the Attorney General, 200 St. Paul Place, 20th Floor, Baltimore, Maryland 21202-2020.</text>
      <text>This form is being filed to claim the following exemption from the registration requirements of the Maryland Franchise Registration and Disclosure Law. (CHECK ONE)</text>
      <text>_______<cite path="02.02.08.10|D.">02.02.08.10D</cite>—SEASONED FRANCHISOR</text>
      <text>(If relying on this exemption, include with this filing the financial statements required by this regulation.)</text>
      <text>_______<cite path="02.02.08.10|E.">02.02.08.10E</cite>—SOPHISTICATED FRANCHISEE</text>
      <text>_______<cite path="02.02.08.10|F.">02.02.08.10F</cite>—INSTITUTIONAL FRANCHISEE</text>
      <text>_______<cite path="02.02.08.10|G.">02.02.08.10G</cite>—EXEMPTION BY ORDER</text>
      <text>(If relying on this exemption, include with this filing a copy of the Commissioner's order.)</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Franchisor Name:  Complete mailing address, telephone number, and facsimile number of Franchisor:   Mailing Address:</text>
        <text>Telephone:  ( )    Facsimile:  ( )</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Name of Correspondent to whom communications regarding this Notice should be directed:  Complete mailing address, telephone number and facsimile number of Correspondent:   Mailing Address:     Telephone:  ( )    Facsimile:  ( )</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Describe briefly the type of franchise being offered:</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Franchisor's type of business organization:            Corporation            Partnership            Other (describe)</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Name of Offeree (if applicable):</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Complete mailing address, telephone number, and facsimile number of Offeree:</aftertext>
      <aftertext>Mailing Address:_________________________</aftertext>
      <aftertext>Telephone: (___) ________________________</aftertext>
      <aftertext>Facsimile: (___) ________________________:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>In the event that(a) the Franchisor, (b) any of its officers, directors, or general partners, (c) any franchise broker offering or selling its franchises in Maryland, or (d) any salesperson offering or selling its franchises in Maryland, is or has been the subject of any of the following actions or events, please provide the detailed information requested (attach additional sheets):</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Pending administrative, civil, or criminal actions alleging a violation of any franchise law or regulation, fraud, embezzlement, fraudulent conversion, restraint of trade, unfair or deceptive practices, misappropriation of property or any comparable allegations:      NO    YES (ATTACH DETAIL)</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>During the 10-year period immediately preceding the date of the offering circular:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A conviction of a felony or a plea of nolo contendere to a felony charge or a finding of liability in a civil action if such felony or civil action involved a violation of any franchise law, fraud, embezzlement, fraudulent conversion, restraint of trade, unfair or deceptive practices, misappropriation of property, or any comparable violations of law:      NO   YES (ATTACH DETAIL)</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any consent judgment, decree, or order or assurance under a franchise, securities, antitrust, monopoly, trade practice, or trade regulation law:      NO   YES (ATTACH DETAIL)</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Any order of any national securities association or national securities exchange (as defined in the Securities Exchange Act of 1934) suspending or expelling such persons from membership in such association or exchange:  NO  YES  (ATTACH DETAIL)</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>With respect to each question above answered "Yes", state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The name of each person or entity involved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The court, agency, association, or exchange involved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A summary of the allegations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>If applicable, the date of the conviction, judgment, decree, or order or assurance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The penalty imposed, damages assessed and nature thereof, terms and conditions of the judgment, decree, or order or assurance.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>DATE  ________________________</aftertext>
        <aftertext>AUTHORIZED SIGNATURE  ___________________________</aftertext>
        <aftertext>PRINTED NAME OF SIGNATORY   Complete mailing address, telephone number, and facsimile number if different from item 2 above:   ( )</aftertext>
      </para>
    </include>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Denial, Suspension, or Revocation of Registration or Exemption.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner, with or without prior notice or hearing, may issue a cease and desist order and may deny, suspend, or revoke any registration, amendment, or claim of exemption set forth in <cite path="|02|02|08|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>, if the Commissioner finds that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The franchisor, or any of its officers, directors, agents, employees, or any other person related to the franchisor has violated or failed to comply with any provision of the Maryland Franchise Law, or any regulation or order of the Commissioner;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The franchisor, or any of its officers, directors, agents, or employees, or any other person related to the franchisor, is engaging or is about to engage in false, fraudulent, or deceptive practices in connection with the offer and sale of a franchise;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person identified in an application for registration, a claim of exemption, or any MFOC or other franchise offering circular has been convicted of an offense described in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-216">Business Regulation Article, §14-216(c)(8), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or is subject to an order or civil judgment as described in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-216">Business Regulation Article, §14-216(c)(9), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the involvement of the person in the business of the applicant or franchisor creates a substantial risk to franchisees or prospective franchisees.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Financial Statements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. The following financial statements shall be prepared in accordance with this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A financial statement required by the Maryland Franchise Law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A financial statement required by any regulation adopted under the Maryland Franchise Law, including the MFOC; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A financial statement used by or on behalf of a franchisor in connection with an offer, sale, or purchase of a franchise in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A financial statement specified in <cite path="02|02|08|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Financial statements of a franchise offering, for which registration is required under the Maryland Franchise Law, shall be audited and certified by an independent certified public accountant, except that this requirement:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Does not apply to interim financial statements unless otherwise required by the Commissioner in a particular case; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be waived by the Commissioner for good cause shown when a waiver would not be inconsistent with the purposes of the Maryland Franchise Law or contrary to the public interest or the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Content of Financial Statements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The financial statements that accompany an application for initial or renewal registration shall include comparative:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Balance sheets as of the end of the franchisor's last 2 fiscal years before the application date; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Statements of operations, or owners' equity, and of cash flows for the last 3 fiscal years before the application date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the date of the most recent audited financial statements precedes the date of the application by more than 90 days, the franchisor shall also include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An interim balance sheet as of a date within 90 days of the date of the application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Statements of operations for the period from the date of the most recent audited statement to the date of the interim balance sheet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a franchisor owns, directly or indirectly, a controlling interest in any other corporation or entity, the financial statements filed by the franchisor shall reflect, on a consolidated basis, the financial condition of the franchisor and each of the entities controlled by it.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Disclosure. A presentation of unaudited financial statements shall be accompanied by the following written disclosure, immediately adjacent to the financial statements:</text>
      <text>These Financial Statements Have Been Prepared Without An Audit. Prospective Franchisees Or Sellers of Franchises Should Be Advised That No Independent Certified Public Accountant Has Audited These Figures Or Expressed An Opinion with Regard to their Content Or Form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Failure to Submit Financial Statements. If a franchisor fails to submit audited financial statements which comply with the requirements of this regulation as part of an application for registration or renewal of registration, the Commissioner may deny the application.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Reports by Registrants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Time for Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A franchisor registered under the Maryland Franchise Law shall file a quarterly report with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The first report filed under this section shall be filed not later than 90 days after the effective date of the franchisor's registration statement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Content. The reports required by <cite path="02|02|08|.14|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The number of franchises sold in Maryland under the registration statement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The selling price of each franchise sold in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Graphic representations of exclusive areas, if any, sold to Maryland franchisees; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner directs with respect to a particular franchisor, current financial statements of the franchisor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|08|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Franchisor Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Records to Be Maintained. A franchisor offering or selling a franchise in the State shall maintain complete and accurate records of offers and sales of franchises, including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Offering circulars;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advertising;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Correspondence with franchisees and prospective franchisees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Past and present operations manuals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Training records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Training manuals; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Copies of executed agreements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Records. The records may be maintained on photographic or electronic media, but shall be printed if the Commissioner so orders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Retention Schedule. The records described in <cite path="02|02|08|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be maintained at an office readily accessible to the franchisor for 5 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Inspection of Records. The Commissioner or the Commissioner's designated representatives shall have access to the records described in <cite path="02|02|08|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> at any time, upon reasonable request during business hours, in order to conduct such examinations as the Commissioner considers necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of prospective franchisees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Other Investigative Powers. Nothing in this regulation is intended to limit the investigative powers of the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Fraudulent and Prohibited Practices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Antifraud Provisions. Unless otherwise indicated, the antifraud provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-229">Business Regulation Article, §14-229, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this regulation apply to any offer to sell or sale of a franchise in the State regardless of whether the franchise offering is exempt from registration under the Maryland Franchise Law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fraudulent Representations and Deceptive Statements. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise commits a "misrepresentation to, deceit of, or fraud on the buyer" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and engages in an "act, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit on another person" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-229">Business Regulation Article, §14-229(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if that person makes, or causes to be made, oral or written statements that do not comply with §§C—H of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Representations Concerning Nature of Franchise. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise may not make, or cause to be made, oral or written statements concerning the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exclusivity of the franchise rights granted to the franchisee without disclosing the exact nature of the exclusivity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nature and number of locations or sites appropriate for the franchisee's enterprise, whether or not to be obtained by the franchisor, without disclosing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By whom each site is to be secured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The manner in which the procurement of any site is to be financed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The source and terms for financing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The relationship, if any, between site procurement and the execution of a franchise agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The identity of anyone with whom the franchisor has a binding obligation for the procurement of any site;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Whether use of a site by a franchisee will entitle the franchisee to become affiliated with any existing enterprise; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Whether the use of a site by a franchisee will create an obligation on the part of the franchisor or franchisee to any third party;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Interest or readiness of other persons to enter into a franchise agreement substantially similar to that being offered or sold without disclosing the source of this information and the identities, including names and addresses, of those persons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Total number of franchises substantially similar to the franchise being offered or sold that have been established or are planned to be established in a geographical area without disclosing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Graphically, the area represented; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether the subject franchises are operating or have conducted business within the meaning of Item 20 of the MFOC; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Endorsement or approval of the franchise or its business by any person or entity without disclosing the nature of the endorsement or approval and any compensation by the franchisor or the franchisees to the person or entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Representations Concerning Income, Earnings, and Net Worth. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made, an offer or sale of a franchise may not make, or cause to be made, oral or written statements concerning:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Industry-wide total income or the income applicable to the prospective franchisee, whether actual or projected, for a product or service marketed by the franchisor, without disclosing the relationship, if any, of these representations to the franchisor's and its franchisees' actual income experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The actual income experience of the franchisor unless the person discloses the availability of certified audited financial statements and how they may be obtained;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Potential earnings from operation of the franchise if these earnings claims have not been included in the MFOC or other offering circular required to be filed with the Commissioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The net worth of the franchisor and its affiliates unless the person discloses whether financial statements of the franchisor are available and how they may be obtained; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The amount or value of revenue, sales, income, contracts, or business intended to be provided to a franchisee within a specified period of time, without disclosing the actual revenue, sales, income, contract, or business experience of existing franchisees purchasing similarly described franchises, and the period of time in which those franchisees achieved and maintained that revenue, sales, income, contracts, or business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Representations Concerning the Operation of the Franchise. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise may not make, or cause to be made, oral or written statements concerning the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date by which a prospective franchisee's enterprise will be totally operational without disclosing the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Factual basis upon which that date has been determined or estimated; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Average elapsed time between the signing of a franchise contract and the beginning of conduct of business of the franchisor's other franchisees throughout the continental United States and Canada;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sources from which a franchisee is required to purchase its goods, services, equipment, inventory, or real estate pursuant to the franchise agreement without disclosing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An affiliation between these sources and the franchisor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The relationship between the price at which a franchisee will make the purchases and the prevailing market price, if any, for these goods, services, supplies, equipment, inventory, or real estate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Franchisor's affiliation with any person or business entity from whom the franchisee shall be required to purchase goods or services or with whom the franchisee shall otherwise be required to do business without disclosing the legal nature of the affiliation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Qualifications or experience that the franchisor or any affiliate requires or recommends be possessed by a potential franchisee without disclosing whether additional personnel will be required for operation of the franchisee's business if the potential franchisee does not possess the requisite qualifications or experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Representations Concerning the Franchise Agreement. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise may not make, or cause to be made, oral or written statements concerning:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The application for a franchise agreement without disclosing that an application is a preliminary document and not the agreement by which a franchise will be sold or the creation of a contractual relationship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A payment or consideration without disclosing its significance in the franchise sale transaction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The execution of any contract, release, or any negotiable or other written instrument in connection with the franchise agreement without disclosing the complete contents of the document and the significance of the execution of the document in the franchise sale transaction; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recovery of a portion or all of the franchise fee or other investment without disclosing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whether the franchise fee or other investment is secured or guaranteed and, if so, in what manner; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the franchise fee or other investment is not secured or guaranteed, over what period of time, based on the actual experience of other franchises of the franchisor, the franchisee might expect to recover the franchise fee or other investment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Representations Concerning Franchisor Support. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise may not make, or cause to be made, oral or written statements concerning the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advertising support to be provided by the franchisee and by the franchisor without disclosing the manner by which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The funds are to be raised and spent; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A franchisee may obtain an accounting of expenditures;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extent of any training, supervision, and technical assistance to be provided by the franchisor under the franchise agreement without disclosing the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Frequency with which the training, supervision, and technical assistance will be provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cost of the training, supervision, and technical assistance to the franchisee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Effect of any failure of the franchisee to participate in the same; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Aid or assistance that the franchisor will provide to the franchisee in training, obtaining locations for conducting business, or in marketing the product or service of the franchisor without disclosing, before the execution of the franchise agreement, whether the franchise agreement imposes these obligations on the franchisor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Representations Concerning Public Agencies. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise may not make, or cause to be made, any oral or written statement concerning:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approval or endorsement of a franchise or a franchisor by the Division of Securities, any other State agency, or any other public agency or the employees of any public agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A finding by any agency of any state, or of any public agency, or by its agents or employees that any contents of advertising are true and not misleading; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name of the state or any state agency or the name of any public agency or any agency agents or employees in connection with promoting, advertising, offering, or selling a franchise other than to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State that compliance with applicable laws has been accomplished; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Demonstrate compliance by a showing of copies of correspondence or official records.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Misrepresentations. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made, an offer or sale of a franchise commits a "misrepresentation to, deceit of, or fraud on the buyer" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law,  <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and engages in an "act, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit on another person" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-229">Business Regulation Article, §14-229(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if that person misrepresents:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That execution of any document in connection with the offer or sale of a franchise constitutes only an application for a franchise if execution of the document creates a contractual relationship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of franchises of the franchisor that are similar in type and which are conducting or have conducted business within the meaning of Item 20 of the MFOC, within a given area at any time;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the franchise agreement and all of its obligations are embodied in one or several documents presented to, made available to, or executed by a prospective franchisee when, in fact:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The execution of additional documents, or the giving by the franchisee of additional consideration, is required for the creation of a contractual relationship; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The execution of one or more of these documents is not related to or necessary for the sale of the franchise;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any element of a franchise agreement or of the business of the franchisor that is required to be disclosed by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-216">Business Regulation Article, §14-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>False, Fraudulent, and Deceptive Omissions. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise commits a "misrepresentation to, deceit of, or fraud on the buyer" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and engages in an "act, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit on another person" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-229">Business Regulation Article, §14-229(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if that persons fails to make the following disclosures:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a relationship exists between the franchisor and any other person or entity that has offered, is offering, or will offer a franchise program substantially similar to that being offered or sold, to disclose the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Nature of the relationship; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Similarity, if any, between the trademark or commercial symbol or the production and marketing plan of the other person or entity to that of the franchise being offered or sold;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a franchisee is required to purchase goods, services, equipment, inventory, real estate, or other items from designated sources, including the franchisor, to disclose:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the case of sources other than the franchisor, any affiliation of the franchisor with these sources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the source is affiliated with the franchisor, the cost to the seller of these goods, services, equipment, inventory, real estate, or other items;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The prevailing market price, if any, for the goods, services, equipment, inventory, real estate, or other items, and if none, an explanation as to the inability of the seller to determine and disclose same; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The manner, if any, in which the availability of the goods, services, equipment, inventory, real estate, or other items will be insured by the franchisor or its affiliates under the terms of the franchise agreement; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any representation required to be made by the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-216">Business Regulation Article, §14-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which is an element of the franchise being offered or sold.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Misapplication of Proceeds. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made an offer or sale of a franchise commits a "misrepresentation to, deceit of, or fraud on the buyer" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and engages in an "act, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit on another person" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-229">Business Regulation Article, §14-229(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if that person applies, authorizes, or causes any material part of the proceeds from the sale of franchises to be applied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In any material way contrary to the purpose specified in the offering circular, advertising, or oral representations used in connection with the offer or sale of the franchise; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a purpose not reasonably related to the business of the franchisor as described in the offering circular, advertising, oral representations, or any contract related to the offer or sale of the franchise.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Releases from Liability and Waivers. A person authorizing, aiding in, or causing to be made, an offer or sale of a franchise commits a "misrepresentation to, deceit of, or fraud on the buyer" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-221">Business Regulation Article, §14-221(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and engages in an "act, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit on another person" within the meaning of the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-229">Business Regulation Article, §14-229(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if that person requires a franchisee to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide a release from liability under the provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law as part of a franchise agreement or as a condition of the sale, renewal, or assignment of a franchise;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assent to a period of limitations for causes of action under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-226">Business Regulation Article, §14-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, other than the period of limitations set forth in that statute; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Waive the franchisee's right to file a lawsuit alleging a cause of action arising under the Maryland Franchise Law in any court of competent jurisdiction in this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Interpretive Opinions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Filing of Request. A request for an interpretive opinion or a no action position under the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-209">Business Regulation Article, §14-209, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be filed with the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form of Request. A request for an interpretive opinion or a no action position shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An original and one copy of the letter requesting the interpretive opinion or no action position; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two copies of any supporting documentation or materials.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Content of Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request shall state the names of any franchisor, individual, or entity involved. Requests concerning unnamed franchisors, individuals, or entities, or hypothetical situations are not acceptable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request shall indicate in a prominent manner the specific parts of the statute or regulation to which the request pertains.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A request shall be limited to a particular fact situation and shall contain a legal analysis indicating why the requesting party believes that it is appropriate, given the language, meaning, and intent of the pertinent statutes and regulations, and the interests of investor protection, that the Commissioner should take a particular position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A request shall contain the name of the individual to be contacted by the Division if additional information is required. The designated individual shall be fully versed in the facts and legal analysis underlying the request for the interpretive opinion or no action position.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Request for Confidential Treatment. If a person requesting an interpretive opinion or no action position seeks to keep all or part of the request confidential, the person shall submit, together with the request for an interpretive opinion or no action position, a separate letter that states why the person believes that confidential treatment is appropriate or necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Payment of Fee. A request for an interpretive opinion or a no action position shall be accompanied by the fee set forth in the Maryland Franchise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-209">Business Regulation Article, §14-209(b)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The filing fee is nonrefundable.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Internet Offers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any communication made through the Internet, the World Wide Web, or any other similar proprietary or common carrier electronic delivery system, of an offer to sell a franchise (Internet Offer) is exempt from the registration provisions of the Maryland Franchise Law if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Internet Offer indicates, directly or indirectly, that the franchise is not being offered to residents of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Internet Offer is not otherwise directed to any person in Maryland by or on behalf of the franchisor or anyone acting with the franchisor's knowledge; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No franchises are sold in Maryland by or on behalf of the franchisor until the offering has been registered and declared effective and the MFOC has been delivered to the offeree before the sale and in compliance with the Maryland Franchise Law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reliance on an exemption from registration under this regulation does not preclude a franchisor from relying on any other exemption provided under the Maryland Franchise Law or these regulations.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|14-206">Business Regulation Article, §14-206, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-02">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|08|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 2, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2005); emergency status extended at 5:8 Md. R. 587</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-05-05">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|08|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective May 5, 1978 (5:9 Md. R. 683) (Recodified from <cite path="|02.02.04">COMAR 02.02.04</cite> to <cite path="|02.02.10">02.02.10</cite>)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-19">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|08|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|08|.08">.08</cite> recodified to Regulations <cite path="|02|02|08|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|08|.12">.12</cite> and amended effective May 19, 1986 (13:10 Md. R. 1154)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2525)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2525)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended and .10B adopted effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2525)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2525)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-15"><cite path="|02|02|08|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective April 15, 1991 (18:7 Md. R. 770)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-01-17" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|08|.13">.13</cite> under <cite path="|02.02.10">COMAR 02.02.10</cite> repealed effective January 17, 1994 (21:1 Md. R. 27)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-01-17" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|02|02|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|02|02|08|.17">.17</cite> adopted effective January 17, 1994 (21:1 Md. R. 27)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-23"><cite path="|02|02|08|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective May 23, 1994 (21:10 Md. R. 840)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-23"><cite path="|02|02|08|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended and C adopted effective May 23, 1994 (21:10 Md. R. 840)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-23"><cite path="|02|02|08|.10|G.">Regulation .10G</cite> amended effective May 23, 1994 (21:10 Md. R. 840)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-18" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 18, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1960)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 992)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.08|F.">Regulation .08F</cite> amended effective June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 992)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 992)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite>, D, H amended effective June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 992)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 992)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-29"><cite path="|02|02|08|.18">Regulation .18</cite> adopted effective June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 992)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
