<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Federal Covered Securities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Federal covered security" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Investment company" has the meaning stated in §3 of the Investment Company Act of 1940, 15 U.S.C. §80a-3.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Registration statement" has the meaning stated in §2(a)(8) of the Securities Act of 1933, 15 U.S.C. §77b(a)(8).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Unit investment trust" has the meaning stated in §4(2) of the Investment Company Act of 1940, 15 U.S.C. §80a-4(2).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following documents are incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Documents Incorporated.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>15 U.S.C. §80a-3.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>15 U.S.C. §80a-4(2).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>15 U.S.C. §77b(a)(8).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|09|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Use of Uniform Forms.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Required Uniform Forms. To comply with the notice filing requirements of this chapter and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-503</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, an issuer may use the following forms:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Form NF (Uniform Investment Company Notice Filing);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Form U-2 (Uniform Consent to Service of Process);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>SEC Form D (Notice of Sale of Securities Pursuant to Regulation D, Section 4(6), and/or Uniform Limited Offering Exemption).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Effect on Maryland Law. An instruction, undertaking, or other matter appearing in the forms listed in <cite path="02|02|09|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> does not limit the application of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca">Corporations and Associations Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or this chapter.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Notice Filing—Investment Companies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice Filing. An issuer registered with the SEC under the Investment Company Act of 1940 that intends to offer or sell securities that are federal covered securities under §18(b)(2) of the Securities Act of 1933 shall, before an offer or sale in Maryland, submit a notice filing for those securities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Separate Classes or Series of Securities. An issuer that offers multiple classes or series of securities shall file a separate notice filing with the Commissioner and pay a separate fee for each class or series of securities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Initial Notice Filing. An initial notice filing shall consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Form NF (Uniform Investment Company Notice Filing) or a copy of the investment company's registration statement filed with the SEC;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Form U-2 (Uniform Consent to Service of Process) or, if this document has been previously filed with the Commissioner, a cross-reference to the Maryland file number of an effective notice filing with which the Form U-2 was filed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name and CRD number, if any, of at least one broker-dealer or issuer agent that will effect transactions in the securities in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The fee required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any documents filed with the SEC that the Commissioner may request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Response to Notice Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice to Issuer. Following receipt of a notice filing, the Division shall notify an issuer that its notice filing is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Effective;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Effective pending SEC effectiveness; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Incomplete.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Effectiveness. The Division shall notify an issuer that its notice filing is effective upon receipt in Maryland if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The notice filing is complete;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The issuer's registration statement has been declared effective by the SEC; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No stop order is in effect and no proceeding is pending under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice Filing Effective Pending SEC Effectiveness.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Division shall notify an issuer that its notice filing is effective pending SEC effectiveness if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The notice filing is complete;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The issuer's registration statement has not been declared effective by the SEC; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>No stop order is in effect and no proceeding is pending under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An issuer shall notify the Commissioner when its registration statement is declared effective by the SEC.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The notice filing in Maryland is effective in Maryland immediately upon SEC effectiveness.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Incomplete Notice Filing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice of Deficiency.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If a notice is incomplete, the Commissioner, before issuing a stop order under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall notify an issuer of the deficiencies in the notice filing that must be corrected in order to complete the notice filing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If an issuer cures the deficiencies in its notice filing, the Commissioner shall notify the issuer that its notice filing is effective or effective pending SEC effectiveness.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stop Order.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If an issuer fails to cure the deficiencies in its notice filing within 15 calendar days of notification of the deficiencies, the Commissioner may issue a stop order suspending the offer or sale of the securities in Maryland under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If, after the Commissioner issues a stop order, the issuer completes the notice filing, the Commissioner may vacate or otherwise modify the stop order and declare the filing effective.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Duration of Notice Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Investment Companies Other Than Unit Investment Trusts. An initial or renewal notice filing submitted for an issuer is effective until the last day of the issuer's fiscal year end, when it must be renewed under Regulation .06 or terminated under <cite path="|02|02|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unit Investment Trusts.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An initial or renewal notice filing submitted for an issuer is effective for a 1-year period from the date of effectiveness, and must be renewed under Regulation .06 or terminated under <cite path="|02|02|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Division will run the effective period of the issuer's notice filing concurrently with the SEC effective period for the notice filing if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The issuer's SEC filing is already effective at the time the notice filing is made with the Division; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The issuer requests that the Division set the Maryland effective period to run concurrently.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>SEC Termination. If, after an issuer's notice filing is declared effective in Maryland, the issuer's registration with the SEC terminates, the issuer shall terminate its notice filing under <cite path="|02|02|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Amendment of Notice Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Filing Requirement. An issuer shall file with the Commissioner an amendment to the notice filing for any material changes in the information contained in the filing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Material Changes. Events requiring an issuer to amend its notice filing include, but are not limited to, changes in the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fiscal year-end date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name of the issuer or of a portfolio, series, or class of securities of the issuer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Business form of the issuer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Change in Fiscal Year End—Investment Companies Other Than Unit Investment Trusts. If an issuer changes its fiscal year-end date, the issuer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a renewal notice filing at the end of its new fiscal year-end date in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|09|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay a fee in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|09|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Filing Deadline. An issuer shall file amendments required by this section within 15 days of the event giving rise to the need to amend the filing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Registration Requirement—Nonpayment of Fees. Until October 10, 1999, if a notice filing is incomplete for nonpayment or underpayment of any fees required under <cite path="|02|02|09|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> and the deficiency is not remedied within 15 calendar days after notification is sent to an issuer, the Commissioner may require the registration of the securities under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-503, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|09|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notice Filing Fee—Investment Companies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice Filing Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An issuer submitting a notice filing under Regulation .04 or .06 of this chapter shall pay an initial part of its fee at the time of the notice filing and the remaining part of its fee by the due date under <cite path="02|02|09|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, or upon termination under <cite path="|02|02|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial Part of Fee. As part of its notice filing, an issuer shall pay $500 as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-510">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-510</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Remaining Part of Fee. An issuer may pay the remaining part of its fee by either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Paying a flat fee of $1,300; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Filing with the Commissioner a year-end sales report on Form NF and paying a calculated fee computed as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If gross sales in Maryland are $500,000 or less, no additional fee is due,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If gross sales in Maryland are equal to or greater than $1,500,000, the remaining part of the fee is $1,000, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>If gross sales in Maryland are greater than $500,000 but less than $1,500,000, the remaining part of the fee is equal to 0.1 percent of gross sales in Maryland, minus $500.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Due Date for Remaining Part of Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Investment Companies Other Than Unit Investment Trusts. An issuer shall submit the remaining part of its fee within 60 days after its fiscal year-end date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unit Investment Trusts. An issuer shall submit the remaining part of its fee within 60 days after expiration of effectiveness under <cite path="|02|02|09|.04|E.|(2)">Regulation .04E(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Change in Fiscal Year End—Prorated Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewing Issuer. If, as a result of a change in fiscal year-end date, the effective period for an issuer's existing notice filing extends beyond 12 months, an issuer renewing its notice filing under Regulation .06 shall</text>
        <text>submit a prorated fee in accordance with <cite path="02|02|09|.05|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terminating Issuer. If, as a result of a change in fiscal year-end date, the effective period for an issuer's existing notice filing extends beyond 12 months, an issuer terminating its notice filing under <cite path="|02|02|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite> shall submit a prorated fee in accordance with <cite path="02|02|09|.05|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, minus $500.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prorated Fee—Tables.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Flat Fee Table.</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th>Months Between Last Effective<br/>Date and New Fiscal Year End</th>
                  <th>Total Payment Due-----Flat Fee</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,950</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,100</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,250</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,400</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">17</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,550</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,700</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">19</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,850</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3,000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">21</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3,150</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">22</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3,300</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">23</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3,450</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3,600</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Calculated Fee Table.</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th>Months<br/>Between <br/>Last <br/>Effective <br/>Date and <br/>New Fiscal <br/>Year End</th>
                  <th>Total<br/>Payment<br/>Due-----<br/>Minimum<br/>Fee</th>
                  <th>Total<br/>Payment<br/>Due----- <br/>Maximum <br/>Fee</th>
                  <th>Total <br/>Payment<br/>Due-1/10 of 1%<br/>of Gross Sales for<br/>Effective Period</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">13</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$542</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$1,625</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001083 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">14</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">583</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">1,750</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001167 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">15</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">625</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">1,875</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.00125 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">667</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,000</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001333 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">17</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">708</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,125</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001417 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">18</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">750</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,250</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.0015 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">19</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">792</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,375</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001583 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">833</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,500</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001667 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">21</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">875</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,625</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.00175 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">22</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">917</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,750</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001833 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">23</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">958</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">2,875</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.001917 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">1,000</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">3,000</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">0.002 x gross sales</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|09|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Renewal Notice Filing—Investment Companies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Renewal Notice Filing. An issuer shall renew its notice filing for a successive 1-year period by paying $500 as the initial part of its renewal fee and submitting to the Commissioner, within the due date under <cite path="02|02|09|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the remaining part of its fee required by <cite path="|02|02|09|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Due Date for Renewal Notice Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Investment Companies Other Than Unit Investment Trusts.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An issuer shall submit its renewal notice filing within 60 days after its fiscal year-end date.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an issuer changes its fiscal year-end date, its existing notice filing may not remain effective for more than 24 months.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unit Investment Trusts. An issuer shall submit its renewal notice filing within 60 days after expiration of effectiveness under <cite path="|02|02|09|.04|E.|(2)">Regulation .04E(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Termination of Offering—Investment Companies.</heading>
    <text>If an issuer terminates an offering in Maryland, it shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notify the Commissioner of the termination of the offering; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pay the fee and file any year-end sales report required by <cite path="|02|02|09|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Combinations and Reorganizations—Investment Companies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Surviving Issuer. Within 15 days after the combination or reorganization of two or more issuers:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A surviving issuer with an effective notice filing in Maryland shall amend its notice filing in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|09|.04|F.">Regulation .04F of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A surviving issuer without an effective notice filing in Maryland shall submit a notice filing in accordance with <cite path="|02|02|09|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terminating Issuers. Within 15 days after the combination or reorganization of two or more issuers, issuers terminating their offerings in Maryland shall make the filings required by <cite path="|02|02|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|09|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Notice Filing and Fee—SEC Rule 506 Offerings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. An issuer that intends to offer or sell federal covered securities under §18(b)(4)(D) of the Securities Act of 1933 shall, not later than 15 days after the first sale of securities in Maryland, submit a notice filing unless the securities or transactions would qualify for a self-executing exemption under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-601">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-601 </cite>or 11-602, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice Filing. A notice filing shall consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed copy of SEC Form D (Notice of Sale of Securities Pursuant to Regulation D, Section 4(6), and/or Uniform Limited Offering Exemption), as filed with the SEC, including Part E, manually signed, and the Maryland portion of the appendix to the form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Form U-2 (Uniform Consent to Service of Process);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date of the first sale of the securities in Maryland under this offering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name and CRD number, if any, of at least one broker-dealer or issuer agent that will effect transactions in the securities in Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The fee required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-506">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-506, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Response to Notice Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice to Issuer. Following receipt of a notice filing, the Division shall notify an issuer that its notice filing is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Effective; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Incomplete.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Effectiveness. A notice filing is effective in Maryland if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The notice filing is complete; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No stop order is in effect and no proceeding is pending under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Incomplete Notice Filing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice of Deficiency.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If a notice filing is incomplete, the Commissioner, before issuing a stop order under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall notify an issuer of the deficiencies in the notice filing that must be corrected in order to complete the notice filing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If an issuer cures the deficiencies in its notice filing, the Commissioner shall notify the issuer that the notice filing is effective.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stop Order.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If an issuer fails to cure the deficiencies in its notice filing within 15 calendar days of notification of the deficiencies, the Commissioner may issue a stop order suspending the offer or sale of the securities in Maryland under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If, after the Commissioner issues a stop order, the issuer completes the notice filing, the Commissioner may vacate or otherwise modify the stop order and declare the filing effective.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Registration Requirement—Nonpayment of Fees. Until October 10, 1999, if a notice filing is incomplete for nonpayment or underpayment of any fees required under <cite path="02|02|09|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> and the deficiency is not remedied within 15 calendar days after notification is sent to an issuer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may require the issuer to register the securities under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-503, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The issuer may establish an exemption for the securities under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-601">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-601 </cite>or 11-602, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="02|02|09|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Notice Filing and Fee—Federal Covered Securities under §18(b)(3) and (b)(4)(A)—(C) of the Securities Act of 1933.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An issuer that intends to offer or sell federal covered securities under §18(b)(3) or (b)(4)(A)—(C) of the Securities Act of 1933 shall submit a notice filing unless the securities or transactions would qualify for a self-executing exemption under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-601">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-601 </cite>or 11-602, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A notice filing shall be filed with the Commissioner:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At the same time an issuer submits its filing for securities with the SEC; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If no SEC filing is required, not later than 15 days after the first sale in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice Filing. A notice filing shall consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of each document filed, if any, with the SEC under the Securities Act of 1933 with respect to the offer or sale of federal covered securities under this regulation; (2) Form U-2 (Uniform Consent to Service of Process);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Form U-2 (uniform Consent to Service of Process);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date of the first sale of the securities in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name and CRD number, if any, of at least one broker-dealer or issuer agent that will effect transactions in the securities in Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The fee required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-506">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-506, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Response to Notice Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice to Issuer. Following receipt of a notice filing, the Division shall notify an issuer that its notice filing is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Effective; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Incomplete.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Effectiveness. A notice filing is effective in Maryland if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The notice filing is complete; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No stop order is in effect and no proceeding is pending under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Incomplete Notice Filing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice of Deficiency.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If a notice filing is incomplete, the Commissioner, before issuing a stop order under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall notify an issuer of the deficiencies in the notice filing that must be corrected in order to complete the notice filing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If an issuer cures the deficiencies in its notice filing, the Commissioner shall notify the issuer that the notice filing is effective.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stop Order.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If an issuer fails to cure the deficiencies in its notice filing within 15 calendar days of notification of the deficiencies, the Commissioner may issue a stop order suspending the offer or sale of the securities in Maryland under Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1 and 11-513, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If, after the Commissioner issues a stop order, the issuer completes the notice filing, the Commissioner may vacate or otherwise modify the stop order and declare the filing effective.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Registration Requirement—Nonpayment of Fees. Until October 10, 1999, if a notice filing is incomplete for nonpayment or underpayment of any fees required under <cite path="02|02|09|.10|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> and the deficiency is not remedied within 15 calendar days after notification is sent to an issuer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may require the issuer to register the securities under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-503, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The issuer may establish an exemption for the securities under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-601">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-601 </cite>or 11-602, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Registration of Agents.</heading>
    <text>A person engaged in sales activity relating to the offer or sale of federal covered securities under this chapter shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Register as a broker-dealer agent under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-401">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="02.02.02.04">COMAR 02.02.02.04</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Register as an issuer agent under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-401">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="02.02.03.11">COMAR 02.02.03.11</cite>; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Qualify for an exclusion under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-101">Corporations and Associations Article, §11-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or an exemption under another provision.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Corporations and Associations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-203">11-203</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-501">11-501</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gca|11-503">11-503</cite>.1, 11-506, 11-510.1, 11-513, and 11-802, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24">Effective date: August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1358)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28">Regulations .09, .10 adopted effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1918)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
